51 O
BURGENLAND B-LOC
JEWS O
MARRONED O
ON O
BREAKWATER O
IN O
DANUBE B-LOC
: O

35 O
REPATRIATED O
AND O
ARRESTED O
BY O
NAZI O
. O

15 O
STILL O
HIDING O
IN O
WOOD O
ON O
FRONTIER O
. O

Prague B-LOC
, O
Apr B-DATE
. I-DATE
20th I-DATE
. O

( O
Jewish B-ORG
Telegraphic I-ORG
agency I-ORG
) O
. O

Fifty O
- O
one O
Jews O
from O
Burgenland B-LOC
were O
rescued O
on O
Sunday O
night O
from O
a O
breakwater O
in O
the O
Danube B-LOC
after O
the O
inhabitants O
of O
the O
Czech B-LOC
town O
of O
Theben B-LOC
had O
been O
attracted O
by O
their O
cries O
of O
distress O
. O

The O
breakwater O
was O
about O
100 O
meters O
from O
the O
Czech B-LOC
side O
of O
the O
river O
. O

Czech B-LOC
frontier O
guards O
brought O
the O
marooned O
Jews O
to O
Theben B-LOC
. O

The O
Jews O
, O
who O
are O
from O
the O
Austrian B-LOC
frontier O
towns O
of O
Kittsee B-LOC
and O
Kroatisch B-LOC
- I-LOC
Jarendorf I-LOC
, O
declared O
that O
they O
had O
been O
arrested O
by O
Nazi B-ORG
stormtroopers I-ORG
who O
had O
confiscated O
their O
property O
, O
put O
them O
in O
a O
motor O
- O
boat O
and O
left O
them O
marooned O
on O
the O
breakwater O
. O

Among O
the O
Jews O
was O
the O
82-year O
- O
old O
Rabbi O
of O
Kittsee B-LOC
, O
Perls B-PERS
, O
im O
Originaltext O
fälschlich O
: O

Parls O
his O
sick O
wife O
, O
and O
many O
women O
and O
small O
children O
. O

The O
Theben B-LOC
innkeeper O
Sieber B-PERS
took O
pity O
on O
the O
Jews O
and O
put O
them O
up O
at O
his O
inn O
. O

They O
were O
later O
fetched O
by O
Czecho B-LOC
- I-LOC
Slovak I-LOC
police O
who O
took O
them O
to O
the O
police O
detention O
station O
in O
Bratislava B-LOC
. O

Only O
the O
wife B-PERS
of I-PERS
Rabbi I-PERS
Perls I-PERS
was O
permitted O
to O
stay O
in O
the O
Jewish O
hospital O
in O
Bratislava B-LOC
, O
the O
rest O
were O
taken O
across O
the O
Hungarian B-LOC
frontier O
. O

The O
Czecho B-LOC
- I-LOC
Slovak I-LOC
authorities O
declare O
that O
they O
cannot O
allow O
any O
Jewish O
refugees O
from O
Austria B-LOC
to O
stay O
in O
the O
country O
, O
because O
, O
if O
they O
do O
, O
the O
Nazis O
would O
deport O
all O
the O
Burgenland B-LOC
Jews O
to O
Czecho B-LOC
- I-LOC
Slovakia I-LOC
. O

The O
Hungarian B-LOC
authorities O
deported O
the O
51 O
Jews O
to O
Austria B-LOC
on O
Tuesday O
. O

35 O
of O
them O
crossed O
the O
border O
into O
Austria B-LOC
and O
were O
arrested O
by O
Nazi B-ORG
stormtroopers I-ORG
of O
Kittsee B-LOC
who O
imprisoned O
them O
in O
one O
of O
their O
barracks O
. O

The O
remaining O
15 O
refugees O
were O
yesterday O
still O
in O
the O
Pheasants O
’ O
Wood O
along O
the O
border O
of O
Austria B-LOC
. O

A O
Jewish O
delegation O
left O
Bratislava B-LOC
for O
Prague B-LOC
to O
ask O
the O
Czecho B-LOC
- I-LOC
Slovak I-LOC
Minister O
of O
the O
Interior O
, O
Dr. O
Czerny B-PERS
, O
to O
allow O
the O
Jewish O
refugees O
to O
stay O
in O
Czecho B-LOC
- I-LOC
Slovakia I-LOC
. O

Another O
delegation O
is O
to O
leave O
for O
London B-LOC
to O
lodge O
a O
formal O
protest O
with O
the O
British B-LOC
Government O
against O
such O
mass O
expulsions O
. O

Dear O
Sirs O
, O
I O
am O
here O
in O
England B-LOC
as O
the O
authorised O
representative O
of O
the O
Board O
of O
Deputies O
of O
the O
Jews O
of O
Burgenland B-LOC
and O
the O
Orthodox O
Rabbis O
of O
Austria B-LOC
. O

I O
have O
been O
here O
for O
10 O
days O
already O
, O
but O
have O
unfortunately O
accomplished O
very O
little O
. O

In O
the O
name O
of O
many O
thousands O
of O
suffering O
people O
, O
I O
beg O
of O
you O
most O
urgently O
and O
desperately O
to O
support O
the O
case O
of O
the O
privately O
instituted O
Aid B-ORG
Committee I-ORG
of I-ORG
the I-ORG
Orthodox I-ORG
Jewry I-ORG
in I-ORG
Vienna I-ORG
and O
especially O
the O
desperate O
need O
of O
the O
Jews O
of O
Burgenland B-LOC
. O

[ O
... O
] O
In O
addition O
to O
this O
, O
we O
have O
to O
face O
the O
tragic O
problem O
of O
The O
Burgenland B-LOC
Refugees O
, O
the O
full O
burden O
of O
which O
falls O
upon O
the O
Committee B-ORG
. O

The O
Jews O
of O
the O
Burgenland B-LOC
, O
mostly O
families O
settled O
there O
since O
centuries O
and O
distinguished O
by O
their O
conservative O
conduct O
, O
numbering O
about O
3,000 O
, O
were O
- O
as O
is O
sufficiently O
known O
- O
by O
means O
of O
tortures O
unheard O
of O
, O
compelled O
to O
charge O
themselves O
in O
a O
written O
statement O
with O
the O
commitment O
of O
different O
crimes O
. O

On O
the O
ground O
of O
these O
extorted O
protocols O
, O
their O
property O
was O
confiscated O
and O
they O
themselves O
driven O
out O
of O
the O
country O
. O

One O
part O
of O
these O
Jews O
was O
deprived O
of O
all O
means O
, O
and O
driven O
to O
different O
frontiers O
- O
Czecho B-LOC
- I-LOC
Slovakia I-LOC
, O
Hungary B-LOC
and O
Jugo B-LOC
- I-LOC
Slavia I-LOC
[ O
! O

] O
. O

Among O
them O
, O
hunted O
in O
herds O
, O
the O
oldest O
victim O
was O
83 O
years O
, O
the O
youngest O
3 O
weeks O
old O
. O

Among O
them O
were O
families O
who O
once O
possessed O
more O
than O
£ O
100.000 O
, O
and O
have O
to O
- O
day O
not O
a O
single O
penny O
left O
. O

In O
Czecho B-LOC
- I-LOC
Slovakia I-LOC
alone O
, O
there O
are O
more O
than O
fifty O
of O
these O
people O
driven O
out O
and O
now O
hidden O
in O
different O
families O
, O
as O
they O
are O
there O
illegally O
without O
knowledge O
of O
the O
Authorities O
. O

Should O
the O
Authorities O
be O
informed O
of O
this O
state O
of O
affairs O
, O
they O
will O
be O
brought O
back O
to O
the O
Austrian B-LOC
frontier O
and O
the O
tragedy O
of O
persecution O
will O
start O
again O
. O

Another O
part O
of O
these O
Jews O
are O
on O
the O
well O
- O
known O
French B-LOC
steamer O
in O
the O
Danube B-LOC
at O
Rajka B-LOC
. O

It O
is O
said O
that O
the O
English B-PERS
and O
American B-PERS
Consul O
in O
Prague B-LOC
have O
undertaken O
a O
guarantee O
for O
emigration O
on O
behalf O
of O
these O
Jews O
. O

One O
part O
of O
these O
exiled O
are O
still O
in O
the O
Burgenland B-LOC
. O

Their O
businesses O
have O
been O
confiscated O
ant O
they O
will O
have O
to O
go O
at O
short O
notice O
. O

The O
longest O
term O
, O
which O
has O
been O
fixed O
for O
exile O
, O
is O
the O
25th B-DATE
of I-DATE
May I-DATE
. O

The O
greatest O
part O
of O
the O
Jews O
of O
Burgenland B-LOC
is O
, O
however O
, O
in O
Vienna B-LOC
- O
having O
saved O
their O
bare O
existence O
[ O
... O
] O
. O

[ O
... O
] O
Yours O
sincerely O
, O
Michal O
Weissmandl O
, O
Rabbi O
, O
Nitra O
, O
Č.S.R. O
Translation O
COPY O
. O

Strictly O
Confidential O
. O

To O
Mrs. O
Schmolka B-PERS
, O
HICEM B-ORG
Dear O
Madam O
, O
In O
our O
great O
despair O
, O
we O
appeal O
to O
you O
[ O
... O
] O
to O
help O
and O
secure O
our O
release O
from O
our O
unbearable O
situation O
. O

We O
already O
suffer O
gladly O
in O
addition O
to O
rats O
every O
natural O
inconvenience O
, O
but O
what O
happened O
to O
us O
on O
Saturday O
, O
the O
16th B-DATE
of I-DATE
July I-DATE
, O
is O
not O
only O
terrible O
but O
unendurable O
. O

[ O
... O
] O
At O
7.30 O
in O
the O
evening O
, O
four O
men O
from O
German B-LOC
- I-LOC
Austria I-LOC
, O
so O
called O
Gestapo B-ORG
- I-ORG
men I-ORG
, O
who O
by O
kicks O
and O
blows O
drove O
us O
out O
of O
our O
own O
home O
, O
now O
rob O
us O
even O
of O
the O
little O
peace O
we O
now O
enjoy O
by O
coming O
on O
board O
and O
attacking O
us O
. O

For O
this O
reason O
, O
we O
appeal O
to O
you O
with O
bursting O
hearts O
to O
come O
to O
our O
rescue O
quickly O
. O

We O
cannot O
put O
on O
paper O
details O
of O
how O
these O
four O
men O
behaved O
but O
suffice O
it O
to O
say O
that O
we O
wait O
only O
to O
get O
away O
from O
here O
. O

We O
will O
all O
sign O
so O
that O
you O
will O
again O
see O
how O
many O
await O
their O
release O
. O

May O
we O
ask O
you O
to O
send O
us O
some O
consolation O
quickly O
as O
to O
what O
will O
happen O
to O
us O
in O
the O
near O
future O
. O

[ O
... O
] O
We O
remain O
, O
The O
interned O
Jews O
on O
board O
the O
tug O
Laortis O
. O

Tug O
Laortis O
near O
Rajka B-LOC
, O
July B-DATE
18 I-DATE
, I-DATE
1938 I-DATE
. O

15 O
Namen O
, O
in O
einem O
Fall O
mit O
Frau O
und O
Familie O
P.S. O
Taking O
into O
consideration O
possible O
reprisals O
and O
our O
exposed O
and O
tolerated O
position O
, O
we O
urgently O
ask O
you O
to O
refrain O
from O
any O
kind O
of O
publicity O
. O

The O
Hon O
. O

Viscount B-PERS
Samuel I-PERS
of I-PERS
Mount I-PERS
Carmel I-PERS
, O
Council B-ORG
for I-ORG
German I-ORG
Jewry I-ORG
, O
[ O
... O
] O
Sir O
, O
re O
the O
Interned O
Jews O
on O
board O
the O
Tug O
Laortis O
, O
near O
Rajka B-LOC
. O

We O
very O
much O
regret O
to O
hear O
the O
negative O
result O
of O
the O
Conference O
, O
as O
reported O
to O
our O
President O
, O
Mrs. O
Marie B-PERS
Schmolka I-PERS
, O
who O
has O
just O
returned O
from O
London B-LOC
. O

Mrs. O
Schmolka B-PERS
went O
to O
Paris B-LOC
and O
the O
whole O
matter O
was O
again O
reviewed O
by O
Hicem B-ORG
, O
who O
came O
to O
the O
conclusion O
that O
there O
is O
no O
other O
way O
to O
solve O
this O
question O
except O
by O
the O
plan O
proposed O
. O

The O
families O
with O
many O
children O
cannot O
be O
sent O
to O
Argentine B-LOC
as O
First O
Class O
Tourists O
as O
the O
expense O
would O
be O
ar O
too O
great O
, O
for O
each O
person O
11,500 O
Crowns O
, O
a O
family O
of O
six O
persons O
costing O
about O
Five O
hundred O
pounds O
sterling O
. O

The O
situation O
of O
the O
people O
on O
board O
the O
tug O
is O
worse O
than O
anyone O
can O
imagine O
, O
as O
can O
be O
seen O
from O
the O
enclosed O
copy O
of O
letter O
received O
by O
us O
and O
also O
from O
what O
Mrs. O
Schmolka B-PERS
saw O
when O
she O
visited O
them O
on O
board O
, O
and O
therefore O
, O
under O
the O
cirumstances O
, O
we O
feel O
that O
we O
cannot O
accept O
sole O
responsibility O
for O
these O
poor O
people O
but O
must O
pass O
some O
on O
to O
the O
shoulders O
of O
Jewry O
as O
a O
whole O
. O

Hoping O
to O
hear O
from O
you O
in O
the O
very O
near O
future O
that O
you O
have O
used O
your O
influence O
to O
favourably O
reconsider O
this O
matter O
. O

We O
remain O
, O
Yours O
truly O
. O

Dear O
Sir O
– O
The O
revolting O
fate O
of O
68 O
BURGENLAND B-LOC
Jews O
, O
driven O
from O
their O
home O
, O
received O
into O
no O
neighbouring O
country O
, O
nor O
allowed O
to O
return O
, O
has O
been O
commented O
upon O
troughout O
the O
international O
Press O
. O

Now O
we O
receive O
the O
report O
, O
which O
we O
enclose O
, O
of O
distress O
still O
encompassing O
the O
persecuted O
, O
our O
authority O
being O
Mrs. B-PERS
M. I-PERS
SCHMOLKA I-PERS
, O
director O
of O
the O
Hicem B-ORG
Prague B-LOC
. O

You O
are O
free O
to O
make O
such O
use O
of O
the O
report O
as O
you O
think O
fit O
. O

Mrs. B-PERS
SCHMOLKA I-PERS
, O
however O
, O
does O
not O
wish O
her O
name O
to O
be O
mentioned O
, O
nor O
, O
as O
usual O
, O
must O
we O
be O
named O
as O
your O
source O
. O

Yours O
faithfully O
, O
JEWISH B-ORG
CENTRAL I-ORG
INFORMATION I-ORG
OFFICE I-ORG
Public B-ORG
Service I-ORG
Institute I-ORG
THE O
BURGENLAND B-LOC
JEWS O
on O
the O
DANUBE O
TUG O
– O
BOAT O
An O
Eye O
Witness O
Report O
On O
April B-DATE
16 I-DATE
, I-DATE
1938 I-DATE
, O
the O
Jewish O
inhabitants O
of O
Kittsee B-LOC
and O
Pama B-LOC
, I-LOC
Burgenland I-LOC
, I-LOC
Austria I-LOC
, O
were O
ejected O
from O
their O
homes O
, O
robbed O
of O
what O
money O
and O
identity O
papers O
they O
had O
and O
, O
during O
the O
night O
, O
marooned O
on O
some O
small O
island O
in O
the O
Czech B-LOC
section O
of O
the O
Danube B-LOC
. O

On O
April B-DATE
17 I-DATE
, O
they O
were O
found O
by O
the O
Czech B-LOC
frontier O
guard O
and O
taken O
to O
Bratislava B-LOC
. O

That O
very O
same O
day O
they O
were O
expelled O
from O
Czecho B-LOC
- I-LOC
Slovakia I-LOC
and O
once O
again O
taken O
to O
the O
German B-LOC
border O
. O

On O
a O
narrow O
streak O
, O
“ O
No O
- O
man’s O
- O
land O
” O
, O
somewhere O
between O
the O
borders O
of O
Czecho B-LOC
- I-LOC
Slovakia I-LOC
, O
Hungaria B-LOC
and O
Austria B-LOC
, O
they O
spent O
three O
days O
and O
nights O
, O
in O
the O
bitter O
cold O
, O
half O
starved O
, O
and O
without O
a O
roof O
over O
their O
heads O
, O
between O
the O
fixed O
bayonets O
of O
the O
sentries O
of O
all O
3 O
countries O
which O
they O
were O
not O
allowed O
to O
enter O
. O

Some O
of O
them O
, O
17 O
in O
all O
, O
managed O
to O
get O
back O
to O
Kittsee B-LOC
, O
where O
the O
old O
men O
and O
children O
were O
locked O
up O
in O
a O
cellar O
, O
and O
the O
grown O
ups O
, O
men O
and O
women O
, O
were O
made O
do O
hard O
scrubbing O
work O
. O

Exhausted O
from O
3 O
days O
’ O
starving O
, O
the O
poor O
people O
’s O
strength O
threatened O
to O
fail O
, O
but O
ruthless O
beating O
put O
them O
to O
work O
again O
. O

During O
the O
night O
, O
after O
a O
30 O
miles O
walk O
, O
they O
were O
taken O
back O
to O
the O
Czech B-LOC
frontier O
. O

At O
long O
last O
the O
Jews O
of O
Bratislava B-LOC
found O
a O
temporary O
way O
- O
out O
. O

They O
hired O
a O
tug O
- O
boat O
, O
which O
landed O
on O
the O
Hungarian B-LOC
side O
of O
the O
Danube B-LOC
, O
near O
Royka B-LOC
, O
and O
received O
the O
people O
, O
68 O
altogether O
, O
agricultural O
workers O
and O
merchants O
, O
infants O
and O
80 O
years O
old O
men O
. O

No O
country O
along O
the O
Danube B-LOC
being O
prepared O
to O
grant O
the O
refugees O
leave O
on O
land O
, O
the O
Hungarian B-LOC
authorities O
extend O
the O
permit O
from O
week O
to O
week O
, O
hoping O
that O
the O
Jewish O
organisations O
will O
secure O
their O
emigration O
overseas O
. O

It O
is O
now O
three O
months O
that O
these O
people O
, O
smitten O
with O
despair O
, O
refused O
by O
every O
country O
, O
and O
even O
grudged O
the O
stay O
aboard O
the O
ship O
– O
it O
is O
now O
three O
months O
that O
they O
are O
thus O
kept O
in O
the O
vague O
hope O
of O
salvation O
. O

Efforts O
were O
made O
to O
induce O
various O
countries O
overseas O
to O
receive O
these O
unfortunates O
. O

Though O
some O
of O
the O
inmates O
of O
the O
boat O
managed O
to O
emigrate O
to O
the O
United B-LOC
States I-LOC
, O
the O
majority O
could O
not O
be O
emigrated O
, O
being O
unable O
to O
comply O
with O
the O
requirements O
set O
up O
by O
the O
countries O
overseas O
. O

It O
was O
in O
full O
realisation O
of O
this O
plight O
of O
theirs O
that O
we O
went O
to O
see O
the O
refugees O
on O
the O
boat O
, O
on O
July O
10 O
. O

We O
have O
seen O
their O
unspeakable O
mental O
distress O
, O
even O
increased O
by O
physical O
torture O
, O
as O
they O
either O
must O
stay O
in O
the O
narrow O
rooms O
downstairs O
which O
are O
infested O
with O
rats O
and O
vermin O
, O
or O
on O
the O
upper O
deck O
where O
they O
are O
left O
to O
the O
weather O
’s O
mood O
. O

There O
must O
be O
an O
end O
to O
this O
awful O
tragedy O
. O

It O
is O
not O
enough O
that O
Jewry O
must O
suffer O
all O
the O
humiliation O
that O
is O
being O
heaped O
upon O
it O
? O

Are O
we O
going O
to O
proclaim O
no O
, O
before O
the O
whole O
world O
, O
our O
utter O
helplessness O
, O
deliver O
up O
these O
poorest O
of O
the O
poor O
to O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
, O
and O
allow O
a O
mass O
suicide O
? O

We O
have O
taken O
down O
all O
particulars O
of O
every O
one O
of O
these O
unfortunates O
, O
and O
in O
addition O
, O
worked O
out O
a O
plan O
to O
lead O
this O
problem O
towards O
its O
solution O
, O
it O
being O
in O
the O
last O
resort O
nothing O
more O
than O
a O
question O
of O
finance O
: O

4.000 O
Pounds O
. O

Dear O
Mrs. O
Schmolka B-PERS
, O
I O
have O
received O
your O
letter O
of O
August B-DATE
2nd I-DATE
, O
written O
on O
behalf O
of O
the O
Hicem B-ORG
of O
Prague B-LOC
, O
and O
relating O
to O
the O
tragic O
position O
of O
the O
Jews O
from O
the O
Burgenland B-LOC
on O
board O
of O
the O
Laortis O
. O

The O
Committee O
of O
the O
Council B-ORG
for I-ORG
German I-ORG
Jewry I-ORG
carefully O
considered O
the O
matter O
, O
but O
could O
not O
accept O
the O
proposal O
made O
to O
them O
that O
they O
should O
contribute O
£ O
4,000 O
for O
the O
rescue O
of O
four O
families O
. O

This O
is O
far O
in O
excess O
of O
any O
grant O
that O
has O
been O
previously O
made O
, O
and O
we O
felt O
that O
we O
should O
not O
be O
justified O
, O
in O
view O
of O
the O
many O
other O
claims O
that O
we O
must O
endeavour O
to O
meet O
, O
to O
expend O
so O
large O
a O
sum O
for O
the O
benefit O
of O
such O
a O
small O
number O
of O
persons O
. O

I O
much O
regret O
that O
I O
do O
not O
feel O
able O
to O
ask O
the O
Committee O
to O
reconsider O
this O
decision O
. O

Yourse O
sincerely O
, O
SAMUEL B-PERS
. I-PERS
Burgenland B-LOC
Jews O
stranded O
on O
French B-LOC
Tug O
on O
the O
Danube B-LOC
to O
go O
to O
Palestine B-LOC
. O

Prague B-LOC
, O
Aug B-DATE
. I-DATE
12th I-DATE
( B-ORG
Jewish I-ORG
Telegraphic I-ORG
Agency I-ORG
) I-ORG
. O

The O
70 O
Jews O
from O
the O
Burgenland B-LOC
who O
were O
stranded O
on O
an O
old O
French B-LOC
tug O
in O
the O
Danube B-LOC
since O
April B-DATE
after O
being O
rescued O
from O
a O
breakwater O
where O
the O
Nazis O
had O
dumped O
them O
, O
are O
to O
receive O
the O
last O
Palestine B-LOC
immigration O
certificates O
allotted O
to O
Austrian B-LOC
refugees O
. O

The O
seventy O
Jewish O
refugees O
, O
among O
whom O
are O
many O
old O
people O
, O
are O
now O
to O
go O
to O
Palestine B-LOC
. O

“ O
I O
have O
the O
honor O
to O
report O
that O
considerable O
controversy O
has O
followed O
the O
introduction O
into O
Parliament B-ORG
of O
the O
new O
Jew O
Bill O
. O

The O
Jewish O
and O
the O
Gentile O
press O
came O
to O
grips O
over O
it O
. O

The O
former O
printed O
articles O
by O
prominent O
Gentile O
Hungarians O
, O
many O
of O
the O
aristocracy O
, O
advancing O
the O
argument O
that O
the O
Bill O
was O
contrary O
to O
the O
principles O
of O
Christianity O
, O
violated O
the O
Constitution O
, O
and O
was O
inhumane O
. O

The O
Gentile O
press O
stressed O
the O
inability O
of O
the O
Jews O
to O
assimilate O
, O
their O
practicing O
a O
doctrine O
of O
race O
defense O
, O
their O
inferior O
outlook O
on O
life O
, O
and O
their O
failure O
to O
accept O
the O
general O
principles O
of O
Christian O
morals O
, O
and O
it O
was O
predicted O
that O
the O
Jews O
would O
attempt O
sabotage O
to O
vitiate O
the O
effects O
of O
the O
Bill O
. O

Protests O
against O
the O
Bill O
were O
expressed O
in O
sermons O
delivered O
in O
the O
Budapest B-LOC
synagogues O
. O

[ O
... O
] O
Many O
see O
in O
the O
presenting O
of O
this O
drastic O
bill O
a O
clever O
move O
by O
Imrédy B-PERS
to O
steal O
the O
thunder O
of O
the O
Hungarian B-ORG
National I-ORG
Socialists I-ORG
, O
to O
produce O
per O
se O
a O
revulsion O
to O
anti O
- O
Semitic O
sentiment O
( O
because O
in O
wide O
circles O
it O
is O
considered O
un- O
Hungarian O
and O
unfair O
) O
, O
and O
to O
make O
Hungary B-LOC
unattractive O
to O
the O
Jews O
of O
neighboring O
countries O
who O
would O
flee O
to O
it O
as O
a O
haven O
from O
persecution O
. O

[ O
... O
] O
In O
the O
last O
analysis O
, O
many O
responsible O
Hungarians O
are O
wondering O
what O
will O
become O
of O
the O
Jews O
, O
especially O
the O
poorer O
ones O
, O
when O
they O
are O
deprived O
of O
their O
means O
of O
livelihood O
. O

They O
feel O
that O
the O
Government O
is O
making O
a O
huge O
problem O
for O
itself O
by O
accelerating O
this O
problem O
without O
sufficient O
preparation O
. O

The O
German O
Minister O
told O
me O
that O
he O
did O
not O
think O
it O
possible O
for O
the O
Hungarians O
to O
carry O
on O
an O
anti O
- O
Semitic O
policy O
as O
they O
conceived O
it O
because O
, O
unlike O
Germany O
, O
there O
were O
no O
skilled O
Gentiles O
to O
replace O
the O
Jews O
. O
” O
A O
revivication O
of O
the O
Iron O
Guard O
movement O
did O
not O
eventuate O
; O

rather O
, O
the O
legionary O
leaders O
have O
been O
shot O
and O
the O
movement O
’s O
strength O
, O
both O
actual O
and O
potential O
, O
is O
greatly O
diminished O
. O

But O
the O
Nazi O
shadow O
still O
looms O
large O
. O

Whether O
the O
German O
threat O
is O
a O
controlling O
or O
only O
a O
contributory O
factor O
, O
the O
fact O
is O
that O
the O
plight O
of O
the O
Jews O
in O
this O
country O
has O
grown O
worse O
and O
their O
fears O
are O
greatly O
increased O
. O

The O
Government O
can O
scarcely O
be O
called O
, O
as O
compared O
with O
the O
Goga B-PERS
Government O
a O
year O
ago O
, O
strongly O
anti O
- O
Semitic O
, O
but O
it O
‘ O
recognizes O
the O
existence O
of O
a O
Jewish O
problem O
’ O
and O
many O
are O
constrained O
to O
feel O
that O
although O
the O
Goga B-PERS
and O
Cuza B-PERS
program O
was O
openly O
and O
violently O
anti O
- O
Jewish O
the O
actual O
effect O
of O
the O
measures O
and O
methods O
employed O
by O
the O
present O
regime O
is O
more O
severe O
. O

It O
is O
true O
that O
there O
is O
no O
out O
- O
and O
- O
out O
pogrom O
and O
that O
Governmental O
regulation O
of O
the O
Jews O
is O
, O
on O
the O
surface O
, O
relatively O
slight O
, O
but O
pressure O
, O
obstacles O
, O
discriminations O
– O
all O
of O
these O
forms O
of O
persecution O
are O
becoming O
noticeably O
more O
numerous O
. O
[ O
... O
] O
The O
attitude O
of O
the O
Romanian B-ORG
Government I-ORG
is O
, O
then O
, O
that O
this O
surplus O
population O
of O
non O
- O
citizen O
Jews O
must O
go O
; O

there O
is O
to O
be O
no O
pogrom O
, O
no O
violence O
, O
no O
brutality O
, O
but O
they O
must O
go O
. O

Until O
a O
place O
is O
found O
for O
them O
and O
an O
arrangement O
is O
made O
for O
them O
to O
get O
there O
they O
will O
probably O
have O
a O
hard O
time O
. O

As O
to O
the O
others O
, O
the O
800,000 O
who O
have O
established O
their O
citizenship O
, O
the O
Government O
points O
to O
their O
citizenship O
as O
a O
guarantee O
of O
the O
same O
treatment O
as O
accorded O
to O
others O
, O
although O
admitting O
that O
Jews O
‘ O
will O
probably O
not O
be O
admitted O
to O
the O
higher O
positions O
’ O
. O
[ O
... O
] O
The O
Romanians O
are O
not O
, O
on O
the O
whole O
, O
a O
harsh O
or O
vindictive O
people O
; O

they O
are O
, O
rather O
, O
tolerant O
and O
easy O
- O
going O
. O

I O
feel O
, O
therefore O
, O
that O
although O
the O
program O
of O
getting O
rid O
of O
what O
are O
termed O
the O
‘ O
surplus O
’ O
Jews O
will O
probably O
in O
any O
case O
be O
retained O
, O
there O
is O
not O
much O
likelihood O
of O
such O
a O
degree O
of O
violence O
or O
severity O
being O
employed O
as O
would O
call O
down O
strong O
criticism O
or O
general O
protest O
from O
the O
outside O
world O
. O

I O
have O
the O
honor O
to O
refer O
to O
despatch O
No O
. O
866 O
, O
dated O
December B-DATE
27 I-DATE
, I-DATE
1938 I-DATE
, O
which O
in O
the O
last O
paragraph O
on O
page O
2 O
mentions O
the O
growing O
tendency O
among O
certain O
politicians O
to O
enact O
anti O
- O
Jewish O
legislation O
, O
and O
to O
report O
that O
this O
movement O
is O
gaining O
momentum O
. O

In O
fact O
, O
at O
the O
beginning O
of O
the O
present O
budget O
session O
of O
the O
Parliament B-ORG
early O
in O
December O
, O
Deputy O
Stoch B-PERS
informed O
the O
press O
that O
he O
had O
worked O
out O
a O
concrete O
proposal O
embodying O
anti O
- O
Jewish O
legislation O
which O
he O
wished O
to O
present O
. O
[ O
… O
] O
Deputy O
Stoch B-PERS
project O
is O
based O
not O
so O
much O
on O
racial O
but O
on O
religious O
principles O
and O
proposes O
the O
extension O
of O
only O
temporary O
citizenship O
[ O
sic O
] O
to O
all O
professed O
Jews O
, O
including O
even O
those O
who O
changed O
their O
religion O
as O
far O
back O
as O
1918 B-DATE
. O

Under O
his O
project O
these O
temporary O
citizens O
would O
lose O
: O

Their O
political O
rights O
, O
Employment O
in O
public O
service O
institutions O
and O
schools O
, O
with O
the O
exception O
of O
Jewish O
private O
schools O
, O
Title O
to O
military O
service O
, O
Right O
to O
handle O
public O
service O
supplies O
, O
Right O
to O
perform O
licensed O
professions O
, O
Right O
to O
publish O
and O
collaborate O
in O
Polish B-LOC
press O
organs O
, O
Right O
to O
own O
and O
operate O
advertising O
offices O
. O

Furthermore O
the O
bill O
provides O
that O
pensions O
and O
insurance O
fees O
paid O
up O
to O
date O
by O
these O
citizens O
would O
be O
returned O
to O
them O
. O

Full O
citizenship O
rights O
would O
be O
enjoyed O
only O
by O
Jews O
converted O
to O
Christianity O
before O
the O
restoration O
of O
Poland B-LOC
’s I-LOC
independence O
, O
as O
well O
as O
Jews O
having O
special O
merits O
because O
of O
their O
service O
during O
the O
war O
or O
because O
of O
their O
outstanding O
work O
for O
Poland B-LOC
. O

[ O
… O
] O
As O
was O
pointed O
out O
in O
my O
despatch O
No O
. O
560 O
of O
January B-DATE
24 I-DATE
, I-DATE
1938 I-DATE
( O
Anti O
- O
Jewish O
Legislation O
) O
, O
it O
is O
still O
true O
, O
as O
was O
then O
the O
case O
, O
that O
the O
Polish B-LOC
Government O
feels O
that O
the O
time O
is O
not O
ripe O
yet O
for O
the O
enactment O
of O
anti O
- O
Jewish O
legislation O
as O
such O
. O

However O
, O
the O
significant O
point O
in O
this O
report O
is O
that O
the O
tendency O
and O
trend O
of O
public O
opinion O
is O
in O
that O
direction O
. O

In O
the O
meantime O
the O
Government O
still O
endeavors O
to O
side O
- O
step O
the O
main O
issue O
, O
but O
working O
through O
OZON B-ORG
, O
continues O
its O
policy O
of O
guarded O
discrimination O
, O
limiting O
Jewish O
activity O
wherever O
possible O
without O
direct O
racial O
reference O
. O

Temporizing O
in O
this O
manner O
, O
the O
Government O
hopes O
to O
avoid O
hostile O
foreign O
censure O
, O
placate O
anti O
- O
Jewish O
circles O
here O
, O
and O
not O
to O
arouse O
Jewish O
apprehension O
or O
enmity O
. O

The O
Government O
is O
under O
no O
illusion O
, O
however O
, O
but O
that O
eventually O
this O
issue O
will O
have O
to O
be O
faced O
squarely O
. O

[ O
... O
] O
Indeed O
, O
it O
is O
characteristic O
of O
Bohemia B-LOC
, O
where O
nationality O
is O
a O
matter O
of O
language O
rather O
than O
of O
blood O
, O
that O
speech O
rather O
than O
origin O
is O
the O
distinguishing O
characteristic O
of O
friend O
or O
foe O
. O

Such O
resentment O
of O
the O
Jews O
as O
exists O
in O
Bohemia B-LOC
thus O
centers O
largely O
on O
the O
German O
- O
speaking O
Jews O
– O
particularly O
those O
who O
have O
come O
to O
Bohemia B-LOC
since O
the O
war O
. O

Among O
the O
Czechs B-LOC
themselves O
, O
there O
is O
comparatively O
little O
anti O
- O
semitism O
. O

Only O
the O
small O
Czech B-LOC
fascist O
groups O
and O
certain O
sections O
of O
the O
nationalist O
- O
conservative O
element O
are O
anti O
- O
semitic O
. O

This O
applies O
particularly O
to O
the O
younger O
element O
in O
the O
New B-ORG
National I-ORG
Unity I-ORG
Party I-ORG
, O
which O
is O
being O
organized O
as O
a O
government O
party O
. O

All O
these O
elements O
together O
, O
however O
, O
make O
up O
only O
a O
small O
minority O
of O
the O
Czech B-LOC
population O
. O

The O
mass O
of O
the O
people O
appear O
simply O
to O
have O
very O
little O
interest O
in O
anti O
- O
semitism O
. O

The O
present O
talk O
of O
anti O
- O
semitic O
measures O
and O
the O
general O
anxiety O
of O
the O
Jewish O
population O
is O
due O
principally O
to O
the O
pressure O
which O
is O
being O
brought O
to O
bear O
on O
the O
Czech B-LOC
Government O
by O
Berlin B-LOC
in O
the O
direction O
of O
an O
anti O
- O
Jewish O
policy O
. O

There O
is O
no O
doubt O
of O
the O
existence O
of O
this O
pressure O
. O
[ O
... O
] O
Very O
little O
has O
happened O
in O
Prague B-LOC
thus O
far O
to O
justify O
the O
panicky O
atmosphere O
which O
has O
prevailed O
in O
Jewish O
circles O
here O
since O
the O
Munich O
agreement O
. O

The O
vast O
majority O
of O
the O
Jews O
in O
Bohemia B-LOC
and O
Moravia B-LOC
have O
remained O
up O
to O
the O
present O
quite O
unmolested O
both O
in O
their O
private O
lives O
and O
their O
economic O
activities O
. O
[ O
... O
] O
In O
Slovakia B-LOC
, O
other O
conditions O
prevail O
. O

Here O
the O
percentage O
of O
Jews O
, O
in O
the O
first O
place O
, O
is O
higher O
than O
in O
Bohemia B-LOC
. O

The O
Slovak B-LOC
Jews O
are O
not O
only O
prominent O
in O
the O
cities O
but O
, O
in O
contrast O
to O
the O
situation O
prevailing O
in O
Bohemia B-LOC
, O
are O
scattered O
in O
large O
numbers O
throughout O
the O
countryside O
and O
play O
a O
conspicuous O
part O
in O
the O
economic O
life O
of O
the O
Slovak B-LOC
village O
. O

They O
are O
the O
object O
of O
widespread O
resentment O
on O
the O
part O
of O
the O
Slovak B-LOC
population O
. O

Many O
of O
them O
are O
of O
the O
poorer O
orthodox O
type O
. O

Their O
dress O
, O
their O
manners O
and O
their O
habits O
are O
conspicuous O
and O
– O
to O
many O
Slovaks B-LOC
– O
offensive O
. O

They O
are O
prominent O
in O
the O
villages O
as O
money O
- O
lenders O
, O
lawyers O
, O
saloon O
- O
keepers O
, O
druggists O
, O
merchants O
, O
etc. O
In O
the O
larger O
cities O
they O
form O
a O
wealthy O
class O
which O
makes O
up O
a O
good O
part O
of O
the O
intelligentsia O
and O
controls O
a O
very O
large O
proportion O
of O
the O
capital O
of O
the O
country O
. O

Many O
of O
the O
educated O
Jews O
are O
Hungarian B-LOC
-speaking O
and O
have O
always O
looked O
to O
Budapest B-LOC
for O
cultural O
inspiration O
. O

A O
smaller O
but O
by O
no O
means O
insignificant O
number O
have O
had O
a O
German B-LOC
cultural O
orientation O
. O

This O
doubtless O
explains O
to O
a O
large O
extent O
the O
feeling O
prevalent O
in O
many O
Slovak B-LOC
circles O
to O
the O
effect O
that O
the O
Jews O
have O
always O
sided O
with O
the O
oppressors O
of O
the O
Slovaks B-LOC
, O
against O
the O
native O
population O
. O

[ O
... O
] O
As O
will O
have O
been O
seen O
from O
the O
above O
discussion O
, O
the O
Jewish O
question O
in O
Czechoslovakia B-LOC
presents O
a O
highly O
confused O
picture O
. O

The O
Jews O
themselves O
fall O
into O
many O
different O
categories O
, O
varying O
from O
the O
highly O
cultured O
intellectuals O
of O
Prague B-LOC
to O
the O
pious O
and O
primitive O
orthodox O
Jews O
of O
the O
Slovak B-LOC
and O
Ruthenian O
villages O
. O

They O
are O
divided O
among O
various O
cultural O
tendencies O
: O

Yiddish O
, O
German B-LOC
, O
Hungarian B-LOC
, O
Polish B-LOC
and O
Czechoslovak B-LOC
. O

The O
attitude O
of O
the O
Aryan O
population O
toward O
them O
varies O
again O
, O
between O
city O
and O
country O
, O
between O
the O
various O
classes O
and O
professions O
, O
between O
the O
different O
provinces O
. O

In O
these O
circumstances O
, O
it O
is O
scarcely O
to O
be O
expected O
that O
any O
clear O
- O
cut O
policy O
or O
attitude O
on O
the O
part O
of O
the O
responsible O
authorities O
will O
emerge O
. O

It O
seems O
evident O
that O
if O
Czechoslovakia B-LOC
existed O
in O
a O
vacuum O
the O
Jews O
, O
despite O
their O
considerable O
number O
, O
would O
not O
present O
any O
problem O
which O
could O
not O
be O
solved O
with O
relatively O
humane O
and O
painless O
methods O
. O

The O
country O
does O
not O
contain O
in O
itself O
the O
basis O
for O
a O
really O
serious O
and O
widespread O
anti O
- O
semitic O
movement O
. O

“ O
I O
have O
the O
honor O
to O
refer O
to O
paragraph O
1 O
, O
section O
c O
, O
of O
my O
telegram O
No O
. O
39 O
, O
March B-DATE
29 I-DATE
, I-DATE
1938 I-DATE
, O
5 O
p.m O
. O
, O
regarding O
a O
proposed O
bill O
to O
limit O
ritual O
slaughter O
in O
Poland B-LOC
and O
to O
report O
that O
a O
new O
bill O
calling O
for O
a O
gradual O
diminution O
of O
ritual O
slaughter O
over O
the O
next O
three O
years O
has O
just O
passed O
the O
Committee O
of O
the O
Sejm B-ORG
and O
awaits O
presentation O
to O
that O
body O
as O
a O
whole O
. O
[ O
… O
] O
In O
discussing O
with O
the O
leaders O
of O
various O
Jewish O
groups O
their O
reactions O
, O
I O
gained O
the O
impression O
that O
it O
is O
mainly O
the O
orthodox O
, O
and O
even O
amongst O
their O
number O
the O
more O
strictly O
religious O
, O
who O
, O
from O
a O
religious O
angle O
are O
seriously O
concerned O
over O
the O
prospect O
of O
eventually O
doing O
away O
with O
ritual O
slaughter O
. O

Others O
, O
such O
as O
the O
Zionists O
, O
and O
the O
Zionist O
Revisionists O
, O
and O
particularly O
the O
youth O
thereof O
, O
are O
less O
concerned O
by O
the O
bill O
’s O
potential O
effect O
on O
ritual O
slaughter O
than O
by O
the O
prospect O
of O
the O
bill O
’s O
presaging O
further O
anti O
- O
Semitic O
measures O
. O

One O
prominent O
member O
of O
the O
Zionist O
Revisionist O
inner O
circles O
imparted O
his O
opinion O
that O
the O
bill O
was O
aimed O
mainly O
as O
propaganda O
to O
force O
the O
Jews O
of O
all O
categories O
in O
Poland B-LOC
to O
unite O
in O
support O
of O
the O
Government O
search O
for O
a O
solution O
of O
the O
Jewish O
problem O
, O
mainly O
in O
terms O
of O
emigration O
. O

[ O
… O
] O
My O
own O
observation O
led O
me O
to O
believe O
that O
contributing O
to O
the O
bill O
’s O
proposal O
there O
are O
the O
following O
military O
and O
social O
aspects O
: O

military O
, O
in O
that O
the O
Army O
’s O
long O
- O
range O
program O
envisages O
the O
eventual O
centralization O
of O
meat O
control O
and O
refrigeration O
to O
meet O
emergency O
periods O
; O

and O
socially O
, O
in O
that O
the O
racial O
Polish B-LOC
peasant O
wants O
to O
replace O
the O
Jew O
in O
the O
meat O
business O
. O

As O
to O
the O
prospects O
of O
the O
bill O
’s O
amendment O
, O
this O
, O
in O
my O
opinion O
, O
will O
depend O
largely O
upon O
the O
Government O
’s O
attitude O
in O
general O
towards O
the O
Jewish O
question O
. O

At O
the O
moment O
, O
I O
do O
not O
look O
for O
the O
bill O
to O
be O
rejected O
. O
” O
“ O
I O
have O
the O
honor O
to O
refer O
to O
paragraph O
1 O
, O
section O
c O
, O
of O
my O
telegram O
No O
. O
39 O
, O
March B-DATE
29 I-DATE
, I-DATE
1938 I-DATE
, O
5 O
p.m O
. O
, O
regarding O
a O
proposed O
bill O
to O
limit O
ritual O
slaughter O
in O
Poland B-LOC
and O
to O
report O
that O
a O
new O
bill O
calling O
for O
a O
gradual O
diminution O
of O
ritual O
slaughter O
over O
the O
next O
three O
years O
has O
just O
passed O
the O
Committee O
of O
the O
Sejm B-ORG
and O
awaits O
presentation O
to O
that O
body O
as O
a O
whole O
. O
[ O
… O
] O
In O
discussing O
with O
the O
leaders O
of O
various O
Jewish O
groups O
their O
reactions O
, O
I O
gained O
the O
impression O
that O
it O
is O
mainly O
the O
orthodox O
, O
and O
even O
amongst O
their O
number O
the O
more O
strictly O
religious O
, O
who O
, O
from O
a O
religious O
angle O
are O
seriously O
concerned O
over O
the O
prospect O
of O
eventually O
doing O
away O
with O
ritual O
slaughter O
. O

Others O
, O
such O
as O
the O
Zionists O
, O
and O
the O
Zionist O
Revisionists O
, O
and O
particularly O
the O
youth O
thereof O
, O
are O
less O
concerned O
by O
the O
bill O
’s O
potential O
effect O
on O
ritual O
slaughter O
than O
by O
the O
prospect O
of O
the O
bill O
’s O
presaging O
further O
anti O
- O
Semitic O
measures O
. O

One O
prominent O
member O
of O
the O
Zionist O
Revisionist O
inner O
circles O
imparted O
his O
opinion O
that O
the O
bill O
was O
aimed O
mainly O
as O
propaganda O
to O
force O
the O
Jews O
of O
all O
categories O
in O
Poland B-LOC
to O
unite O
in O
support O
of O
the O
Government O
search O
for O
a O
solution O
of O
the O
Jewish O
problem O
, O
mainly O
in O
terms O
of O
emigration O
. O

[ O
… O
] O
My O
own O
observation O
led O
me O
to O
believe O
that O
contributing O
to O
the O
bill O
’s O
proposal O
there O
are O
the O
following O
military O
and O
social O
aspects O
: O

military O
, O
in O
that O
the O
Army O
’s O
long O
- O
range O
program O
envisages O
the O
eventual O
centralization O
of O
meat O
control O
and O
refrigeration O
to O
meet O
emergency O
periods O
; O

and O
socially O
, O
in O
that O
the O
racial O
Polish B-LOC
peasant O
wants O
to O
replace O
the O
Jew O
in O
the O
meat O
business O
. O

As O
to O
the O
prospects O
of O
the O
bill O
’s O
amendment O
, O
this O
, O
in O
my O
opinion O
, O
will O
depend O
largely O
upon O
the O
Government O
’s O
attitude O
in O
general O
towards O
the O
Jewish O
question O
. O

At O
the O
moment O
, O
I O
do O
not O
look O
for O
the O
bill O
to O
be O
rejected O
. O
” O
[ O
... O
] O
There O
is O
no O
sympathy O
in O
Bulgaria B-LOC
for O
the O
anti O
- O
Jewish O
demonstrations O
of O
this O
organization O
‚ O
Workers B-ORG
of I-ORG
New I-ORG
Bulgaria I-ORG
‘ O
, O
especially O
as O
there O
is O
no O
Jewish O
problem O
here O
, O
the O
total O
number O
of O
Jews O
amounting O
to O
less O
than O
55,000 O
. O

The O
Jews O
are O
not O
active O
in O
political O
and O
public O
life O
; O

there O
are O
none O
among O
the O
army O
officers O
and O
almost O
none O
in O
civil O
service O
. O

Their O
sphere O
of O
activity O
is O
business O
, O
industry O
and O
small O
trades O
, O
and O
there O
are O
very O
few O
Jews O
in O
the O
liberal O
professions O
and O
arts O
. O

The O
anti O
- O
Jewish O
propaganda O
conducted O
by O
the O
‚ O
Workers B-ORG
of I-ORG
New I-ORG
Bulgaria I-ORG
‘ O
is O
of O
foreign O
origin O
and O
is O
, O
it O
is O
believed O
, O
directly O
encouraged O
from O
Germany B-LOC
. O
[ O
... O
] O
The O
Department O
will O
note O
that O
the O
law O
was O
modified O
substantially O
. O

Primarily O
, O
the O
class O
of O
Jews O
to O
be O
considered O
officially O
as O
Christians O
was O
enlarged O
but O
its O
economic O
restrictions O
were O
increased O
, O
thus O
creating O
a O
sort O
of O
second O
- O
class O
citizenship O
. O

This O
represents O
the O
real O
compromise O
made O
between O
the O
two O
houses B-ORG
of I-ORG
Parliament I-ORG
. O

Also O
, O
the O
idea O
of O
placing O
the O
Jews O
in O
a O
distinct O
category O
for O
political O
purposes O
was O
discarded O
. O

Instead O
, O
the O
Jews O
retain O
free O
active O
and O
passive O
suffrage O
, O
but O
the O
conditions O
of O
their O
enfranchisement O
were O
made O
much O
more O
severe O
. O

Agricultural O
property O
may O
be O
taken O
from O
the O
Jews O
, O
their O
right O
to O
acquire O
real O
estate O
is O
limited O
, O
and O
the O
restriction O
of O
their O
employment O
is O
greatly O
increased O
. O

Jewish O
journalists O
complain O
bitterly O
against O
the O
special O
press O
restriction O
by O
which O
the O
law O
was O
amended O
. O

It O
appears O
that O
, O
in O
practice O
, O
Jewish O
youth O
will O
suffer O
the O
most O
. O

A O
general O
removal O
of O
male O
Jews O
aged O
17 O
to O
70 O
was O
ordered O
from O
Mahrisch B-LOC
- I-LOC
Ostrau I-LOC
, I-LOC
Bohemia I-LOC
for O
October B-DATE
17 I-DATE
and O
is O
reported O
to O
have O
been O
carried O
out O
quite O
completely O
. O

The O
men O
were O
directed O
to O
report O
with O
limited O
luggage O
, O
food O
for O
several O
days O
and O
money O
up O
to O
3,000 O
crowns O
. O

Their O
destination O
has O
not O
been O
stated O
but O
the O
trains O
carrying O
them O
departed O
toward O
Poland B-LOC
. O

The O
Jewish O
women O
were O
also O
required O
to O
register O
on O
the O
same O
day O
and O
fear O
that O
they O
too O
will O
be O
sent O
away O
. O

Observers O
believe O
that O
this O
movement O
may O
be O
to O
labor O
camp O
in O
Poland B-LOC
for O
reconstruction O
work O
there O
. O

Further O
details O
are O
being O
sought O
and O
will O
be O
reported O
. O

It O
would O
seem O
, O
from O
all O
indications O
, O
that O
the O
intent O
is O
to O
obtain O
a O
large O
group O
of O
workers O
for O
use O
in O
Poland B-LOC
. O

What O
this O
use O
is O
seems O
to O
be O
problematical O
, O
but O
it O
may O
well O
be O
to O
prepare O
a O
place O
for O
the O
permanent O
settlement O
of O
the O
families O
, O
etc. O
, O
of O
these O
men O
. O

It O
would O
seem O
that O
this O
movement O
may O
well O
be O
part O
of O
a O
larger O
movement O
of O
populations O
which O
the O
German O
authorities O
are O
carrying O
out O
, O
including O
the O
bringing O
back O
of O
German O
families O
from O
the O
Baltic O
States O
, O
Russia B-LOC
, O
and O
those O
parts O
of O
Poland B-LOC
recently O
occupied O
by O
Russia B-LOC
. O

There O
are O
many O
rumors O
, O
but O
to O
date O
unverified O
, O
that O
the O
German O
authorities O
intend O
to O
bring O
into O
Bohemia O
and O
Moravia O
many O
of O
the O
Germans O
who O
are O
being O
evacuated O
from O
others O
sections O
of O
Europe B-LOC
, O
including O
some O
of O
those O
who O
are O
leaving O
the O
country O
near O
the O
German B-LOC
- O
Frenche B-LOC
French O
war O
zone O
. O

If O
these O
rumors O
are O
warranted O
, O
it O
may O
well O
be O
the O
plan O
to O
replace O
some O
of O
the O
Jewish O
populations O
in O
Bohemia B-LOC
and I-LOC
Moravia I-LOC
by O
German O
populations O
. O

Mr. O
Foreign B-ORG
Minister I-ORG
I O
have O
the O
honour O
of O
forwarding O
the O
3 O
copies O
of O
the O
confidential O
report O
received O
from O
the O
Royal O
. O

Consul O
General O
in O
Prague B-LOC
. O

Dated O
the O
3 O
rd O
. O

concerning O
- O
the O
Conditions O
of O
the O
Protectorate B-LOC
of I-LOC
Bohemia I-LOC
and I-LOC
Moravia I-LOC
. O

I O
have O
the O
honour O
to O
remain O
with O
the O
highest O
consideration O
Dear O
Chamberlain O
Zahle B-PERS
The O
situation O
has O
worsened O
considerably O
, O
since O
21 O
September O
of O
the O
same O
year O
, O
when O
I O
last O
reported O
about O
the O
conditions O
here O
. O

By O
the O
messages O
I O
have O
received O
I O
am O
under O
the O
impression O
that O
the O
State O
Protector O
and O
several O
of O
his O
officials O
sincerely O
wanted O
to O
establish O
a O
good O
relationship O
between O
Germans B-LOC
and O
Czechs B-LOC
. O

However O
, O
the O
party B-ORG
with O
the O
Sudeten B-LOC
German O
Secretary O
of O
State O
, O
Mr. O
Frank B-PERS
at O
the O
helm O
have O
completely O
lacked O
the O
tact O
needed O
or O
they O
may O
have O
thought O
that O
with O
hardness O
one O
should O
suppress O
any O
resistance O
from O
the O
Czechs B-LOC
. O

Now O
you O
can O
see O
a O
Germanization B-ORG
of O
the O
Protectorate B-LOC
in O
all O
areas O
. O

Many O
Czech O
estates O
, O
whose O
owners O
at O
the O
establishment O
of O
the O
Protectorate B-LOC
stayed O
abroad O
and O
did O
not O
return O
home O
, O
and O
estates O
which O
, O
at O
the O
demarcation O
, O
were O
located O
partly O
in O
the O
Protectorate B-LOC
and O
partly O
in O
the O
German B-LOC
Empire I-LOC
, O
are O
placed O
under O
German O
administration O
. O

It O
is O
expected O
, O
that O
similar O
extensions O
will O
take O
place O
in O
regard O
to O
German B-LOC
Colonization O
. O

Jewish O
businesses O
are O
mostly O
being O
handed O
over O
to O
Germans O
. O

In O
Banks O
and O
Industrial O
Enterprises O
, O
there O
is O
strong O
pressure O
from O
the O
German B-LOC
side O
for O
mergers O
and O
transactions O
, O
so O
that O
the O
main O
influence O
of O
the O
company O
in O
question O
can O
be O
transferred O
to O
rich O
German B-LOC
banks O
. O

Perhaps O
some O
of O
these O
transactions O
- O
as O
a O
bank O
director O
familiar O
with O
Czech O
transactions O
in O
the O
post O
- O
World O
Bank O
banking O
sector O
, O
has O
told O
me O
- O
are O
merely O
restitutions O
, O
but O
in O
my O
opinion O
, O
the O
German B-LOC
proceed O
with O
greater O
severity O
and O
consistency O
than O
the O
Czechs B-LOC
in O
this O
regard O
. O

Your O
honour O
Mr O
Chamberlain O
Herluf B-PERS
Zahle I-PERS
Royal O
envoy O
in O
Berlin B-LOC
Everywhere O
the O
German O
language O
is O
being O
preferred O
over O
the O
Czech O
language O
. O

Learning O
institutions O
and O
theatres O
are O
taken O
over O
by O
the O
German B-LOC
Reich I-LOC
and O
Germans O
are O
hired O
in O
all O
institutions O
and O
administration O
offices O
. O

For O
example O
, O
an O
order O
has O
been O
imposed O
on O
the O
Tram O
conductors O
to O
call O
out O
the O
stations O
, O
first O
in O
German O
and O
then O
secondly O
in O
Czech O
, O
has O
caused O
unnecessary O
commotion O
of O
the O
public O
. O

In O
Bohemia B-LOC
and I-LOC
Moravia I-LOC
, O
there O
were O
no O
food O
shortages O
and O
before O
the O
war O
broke O
out O
, O
there O
were O
large O
supplies O
and O
industrial O
goods O
of O
great O
quality O
. O

In O
a O
short O
period O
of O
time O
, O
the O
stocks O
have O
been O
emptied O
and O
a O
rationing O
system O
has O
been O
introduced O
. O

The O
rationing O
is O
not O
yet O
as O
widespread O
as O
in O
the O
German B-LOC
Reich I-LOC
but O
it O
is O
just O
a O
matter O
of O
time O
before O
this O
happens O
and O
then O
there O
will O
be O
a O
" O
Gleichschaltung O
" O
. O

In O
addition O
, O
Dualism O
in O
the O
Administration O
contributes O
to O
the O
fact O
that O
the O
demand O
for O
rationed O
consumer O
goods O
is O
hardly O
as O
well O
organized O
as O
in O
the O
German B-LOC
Empire I-LOC
. O

People O
often O
go O
to O
buy O
items O
, O
which O
according O
to O
the O
card O
system O
should O
be O
available O
just O
to O
find O
out O
that O
it O
is O
not O
. O

After O
the O
Munich O
Decree O
last O
year O
, O
the O
diminished O
territory O
of O
Czechoslovakia B-LOC
was O
established O
, O
and O
many O
Czechs B-LOC
believed O
that O
with O
a O
little O
goodwill O
they O
could O
establish O
great O
relations O
with O
the O
German O
Empire O
. O

After O
the O
creation O
of O
the O
Protectorate B-LOC
, O
a O
few O
people O
still O
hoped O
this O
was O
possible O
but O
now O
you O
won’t O
find O
a O
single O
Czech O
person O
that O
doesn’t O
feel O
resentment O
against O
Germany O
. O

I O
don’t O
think O
that O
these O
feelings O
will O
cause O
any O
outbreaks O
as O
long O
as O
the O
German O
discipline O
stands O
firm O
. O

The O
people O
are O
not O
armed O
and O
they O
know O
that O
the O
German B-ORG
troops I-ORG
and O
the O
German O
police O
will O
suppress O
any O
demonstration O
with O
extreme O
brutality O
. O

In O
the O
first O
period O
of O
the O
Protectorate B-LOC
there O
where O
arrests O
among O
the O
supporters O
of O
Beneš B-PERS
' I-PERS
, O
undesired O
politicians O
, O
legionaries O
, O
and O
others O
. O

However O
, O
many O
of O
the O
arrested O
have O
since O
been O
released O
and O
they O
believed O
that O
the O
main O
clash O
with O
Germans O
and O
people O
not O
well O
regarded O
by O
them O
had O
taken O
place O
. O

When O
the O
war O
broke O
out O
, O
Gestapo B-ORG
's I-ORG
activity O
increased O
and O
in O
addition O
to O
the O
before O
- O
mentioned O
, O
a O
large O
number O
of O
members O
of O
the O
Military O
were O
now O
also O
arrested O
, O
as O
well O
as O
people O
from O
the O
industries O
, O
clerics O
and O
many O
others O
. O

Ever O
since O
it O
looks O
like O
the O
arrests O
won’t O
stop O
and O
it O
is O
difficult O
to O
see O
a O
system O
in O
the O
actions O
of O
Gestapo B-ORG
, O
you O
might O
see O
this O
as O
taking O
hostages O
. O

A O
former O
Czech O
politician O
and O
diplomat O
, O
which O
has O
been O
retired O
for O
several O
years O
, O
told O
me O
about O
some O
of O
the O
arrests O
. O

He O
told O
about O
how O
certain O
people O
on O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
's I-ORG
list O
of O
arrests O
had O
remained O
in O
Freedom O
– O
at O
least O
until O
now O
– O
just O
because O
they O
were O
not O
at O
home O
when O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
came O
for O
them O
, O
so O
the O
police O
went O
on O
to O
the O
next O
one O
on O
the O
list O
. O

My O
informant O
told O
me O
that O
he O
changed O
his O
residence O
because O
he O
was O
afraid O
that O
he O
was O
going O
to O
be O
arrested O
. O

Many O
of O
the O
arrested O
people O
will O
be O
sent O
to O
the O
concentration B-CAMP
camp I-CAMP
Buchenwald I-CAMP
in O
Germany B-LOC
. O

A O
reliable O
source O
told O
me O
that O
the O
internees O
are O
treated O
just O
as O
it O
is O
described O
in O
the O
newly O
published O
English O
white O
paper O
about O
German O
concentration O
camps O
. O

The O
prominent O
Jews O
, O
the O
ones O
who O
lived O
there O
before O
the O
World O
War O
, O
are O
not O
as O
affected O
by O
the O
Jewish O
persecutions O
as O
others O
. O

I O
know O
of O
several O
examples O
of O
Jewish O
Bank O
Directors O
, O
although O
retired O
, O
that O
are O
working O
a O
couple O
of O
hours O
daily O
in O
the O
Bank O
to O
explain O
the O
conditions O
to O
the O
new O
Managers O
and O
live O
peacefully O
in O
their O
villas O
. O

However O
, O
they O
had O
to O
turn O
in O
their O
cars O
and O
radios O
. O

I O
have O
also O
heard O
of O
Jewish O
lawyers O
that O
work O
from O
home O
and O
then O
have O
their O
Aryan O
colleagues O
take O
the O
cases O
to O
court O
. O

Some O
Jewish O
doctors O
have O
been O
given O
temporary O
work O
in O
hospitals O
. O

Jews O
who O
can’t O
prove O
a O
permanent O
residence O
in O
the O
Protectorate B-LOC
seem O
to O
be O
facing O
very O
bad O
times O
. O

They O
will O
probably O
all O
be O
transferred O
to O
Poland B-LOC
, O
to O
the O
regions O
around O
Lemberg B-LOC
. O

From O
Mährisch B-LOC
Ostrau I-LOC
, O
many O
Hundreds O
of O
Jews O
have O
already O
been O
sent O
to O
this O
area O
to O
do O
Labour O
service O
in O
preparation O
for O
the O
great O
relocation O
. O

Under O
the O
conditions O
described O
above O
, O
the O
former O
Czechoslovakia O
National O
Day O
, O
on O
October O
28 O
, O
was O
met O
with O
great O
anxiety O
. O

When O
it O
was O
reported O
that O
the O
Czechs B-LOC
wanted O
to O
grieve O
that O
day O
, O
the O
Germans O
had O
planned O
a O
mourning O
ceremony O
for O
the O
fallen O
people O
in O
Poland O
. O

The O
Czechs B-LOC
then O
canceled O
their O
plans O
, O
and O
the O
Czech O
national O
unity O
party O
ordered O
its O
members O
to O
stay O
indoors O
and O
keep O
calm O
. O

The O
Germans O
also O
distanced O
themselves O
from O
holding O
the O
mourning O
ceremony O
. O

Despite O
the O
fact O
that O
it O
was O
Labour O
Day O
, O
the O
traffic O
in O
the O
main O
streets O
was O
very O
busy O
. O

In O
spite O
of O
the O
prohibition O
, O
many O
Czech O
people O
wore O
cockades O
with O
silk O
ribbons O
in O
the O
Czechoslovakia O
colours O
, O
and O
many O
male O
persons O
covered O
their O
heads O
with O
the O
same O
kind O
of O
cap O
of O
as O
the O
late O
President O
Masaryk B-PERS
usually O
wore O
. O

All O
the O
Czech B-ORG
Police I-ORG
was O
stationed O
in O
the O
Main O
Streets O
and O
the O
German B-ORG
Police I-ORG
and O
S.S. B-ORG
-members O
had O
taken O
up O
positions O
as O
a O
reserve O
in O
side O
streets O
and O
passages O
. O

The O
tensions O
erupted O
into O
fights O
as O
large O
sections O
the O
S.A. B-ORG
-members O
passed O
through O
the O
main O
streets O
with O
music O
, O
and O
various O
clashes O
between O
the O
Czech O
people O
's O
groups O
and O
the O
police O
took O
place O
. O

In O
some O
streets O
, O
the O
Communists O
demonstrated O
, O
and O
German O
police O
had O
to O
support O
the O
Czech O
police O
to O
get O
the O
streets O
cleared O
. O

During O
the O
clashes O
, O
a O
couple O
of O
persons O
( O
allegedly O
a O
dozen O
people O
) O
were O
killed O
and O
some O
of O
them O
were O
injured O
. O

A O
couple O
of O
young O
people O
were O
arrested O
. O

However O
, O
in O
view O
of O
the O
population O
’s O
agitated O
state O
of O
mind O
, O
the O
events O
must O
be O
considered O
less O
serious O
than O
one O
might O
have O
expected O
. O

This O
was O
also O
stated O
to O
me O
by O
a O
German O
Official O
from O
the O
Chancellor B-PERS
's I-PERS
Office O
. O

However O
, O
we O
cannot O
exclude O
that O
the O
incidents O
will O
give O
rise O
to O
new O
reprisals O
against O
the O
Czechs B-LOC
, O
and O
the O
resentment O
against O
the O
Germans O
will O
then O
be O
further O
increased O
. O

Yours O
sincerely O
Your O
devoted O
( O
sign O
. O
) O
Leth B-PERS
, I-PERS
Eigil I-PERS
. O

P.S. O
This O
Report O
was O
sent O
with O
a O
Swedish B-LOC
Courier O
to O
the O
Swedish O
Embassy O
in O
Berlin B-LOC
for O
its O
Further O
Action O
. O

From O
Consul O
Toyohara B-PERS
Yukio I-PERS
( O
Manchouli B-LOC
) O
To O
: O

Japanese O
Ambassador O
to O
Manchukuo B-LOC
Umetsu B-PERS
Yoshijirō I-PERS
Jews O
are O
being O
seriously O
persecuted O
by O
the O
Nazi O
regime O
. O

It O
is O
not O
an O
exaggeration O
to O
say O
that O
those O
fellow O
[ O
Jews O
] O
living O
in O
Germany B-LOC
are O
suffering O
from O
tremendous O
hardship O
. O

This O
time O
when O
they O
left O
Germany O
their O
properties O
were O
confiscated O
and O
they O
were O
not O
allowed O
to O
bring O
funds O
or O
clothing O
… O
. O

Bucharest B-LOC
, O
9 B-DATE
July I-DATE
1940 I-DATE
Confidential O
Political O
report O
no O
. O
187/40 O
[ O
… O
] O
When O
it O
comes O
to O
the O
content O
of O
the O
legal O
status O
of O
Jews O
in O
Romania B-LOC
, O
I O
would O
like O
to O
note O
, O
firstly O
, O
that O
after O
the O
abolition O
of O
the O
old O
anti O
- O
Jewish O
laws O
in O
year O
1919 O
there O
was O
no O
legal O
difference O
between O
a O
Jew O
and O
a O
non O
- O
Jew O
[ O
… O
] O
. O

Until O
recently O
, O
if O
a O
Jew O
had O
a O
Romanian B-LOC
nationality O
, O
facing O
the O
law O
he O
had O
the O
same O
rights O
as O
any O
other O
Romanian B-LOC
. O

It O
is O
crucial O
to O
note O
this O
fact O
, O
since O
it O
explains O
all O
the O
basis O
of O
this O
law O
. O

In O
general O
, O
it O
can O
be O
said O
that O
although O
everything O
depends O
on O
how O
the O
individual O
points O
of O
this O
law O
are O
going O
to O
be O
carried O
out O
in O
real O
life O
, O
right O
now O
it O
seems O
that O
it O
ended O
up O
quite O
benevolent O
for O
the O
Jews O
. O

This O
relative O
benevolence O
, O
however O
, O
does O
not O
mean O
that O
there O
was O
not O
enough O
will O
and O
determination O
at O
the O
relevant O
places O
to O
proceed O
more O
radically O
, O
rather O
I O
have O
a O
feeling O
that O
it O
’s O
the O
missing O
resources O
, O
since O
the O
Jews O
play O
a O
very O
important O
role O
in O
the O
economic O
life O
of O
Romania B-LOC
. O

If O
they O
were O
suddenly O
excluded O
from O
all O
of O
the O
activities O
, O
it O
could O
have O
unpleasant O
results O
on O
all O
of O
the O
economic O
life O
. O

So O
it O
seems O
that O
for O
these O
reasons O
the O
Jews O
had O
to O
be O
divided O
into O
3 O
categories O
and O
the O
second O
category O
, O
especially O
all O
the O
Jewish O
frontline O
soldiers O
, O
are O
keeping O
almost O
all O
the O
rights O
, O
with O
some O
exceptions O
existing O
. O

With O
the O
new O
status O
, O
the O
first O
and O
the O
third O
category O
have O
, O
however O
, O
fairly O
limited O
options O
when O
it O
comes O
to O
some O
employments O
although O
they O
are O
not O
“ O
expressis O
verbis O
” O
prohibited O
from O
doing O
business O
. O

Nevertheless O
, O
a O
Jew O
from O
these O
categories O
cannot O
be O
a O
member O
of O
any O
executive O
board O
anymore O
. O

A O
general O
ban O
is O
placed O
on O
all O
the O
categories O
when O
it O
comes O
to O
ownership O
of O
rural O
land O
. O

This O
is O
nothing O
new O
for O
the O
Romanian B-LOC
circumstances O
, O
since O
a O
similar O
ban O
was O
formally O
valid O
in O
the O
old O
kingdom O
area O
up O
until O
1919 O
, O
if O
I O
am O
not O
being O
mistaken O
, O
when O
it O
was O
removed O
by O
the O
liberal O
regime O
. O

I O
have O
to O
repeat O
myself O
by O
saying O
that O
at O
first O
glance O
the O
law O
seems O
to O
be O
quite O
benevolent O
for O
the O
local O
Jews O
and O
the O
information O
I O
am O
getting O
from O
the O
Romanian B-LOC
Christian O
bankers O
is O
that O
a O
weight O
was O
put O
off O
their O
hearts O
. O

The O
business O
in O
the O
banks O
has O
almost O
completely O
stopped O
due O
to O
the O
Jews O
fearing O
the O
upcoming O
law O
and O
now O
it O
is O
expected O
that O
the O
economic O
and O
financial O
life O
will O
come O
alive O
again O
, O
since O
the O
economic O
crisis O
is O
gone O
for O
now O
. O

It O
was O
a O
similar O
economic O
crisis O
to O
the O
one O
which O
forced O
the O
government O
of O
Goga B-PERS
– O
Cuza B-PERS
to O
capitulat O
. O

Their O
strong O
nationalist O
and O
anti O
- O
Jewish O
program O
caused O
Jews O
to O
freak O
out O
and O
to O
stop O
trading O
, O
which O
hurt O
all O
of O
the O
Romania B-LOC
. O

The O
legal O
status O
of O
the O
Jews O
in O
Romania B-LOC
is O
, O
thus O
, O
much O
less O
brutal O
than O
the O
one O
in O
Germany B-LOC
, O
for O
example O
, O
and O
it O
could O
be O
compared O
“ O
mutatis O
mutandis O
” O
to O
the O
Jewish O
laws O
in O
Hungary B-LOC
. O

However O
, O
it O
should O
not O
be O
forgotten O
that O
it O
is O
only O
the O
first O
of O
the O
legal O
steps O
and O
is O
being O
less O
severe O
out O
of O
caution O
. O

This O
step O
can O
be O
followed O
by O
others O
, O
if O
the O
situation O
asks O
for O
it O
, O
which O
could O
touch O
the O
lives O
of O
Jews O
much O
more O
and O
with O
severe O
impact O
, O
since O
the O
nationalists O
are O
most O
probably O
not O
going O
to O
be O
very O
happy O
about O
this O
law O
and O
are O
expected O
to O
ask O
for O
further O
steps O
in O
time O
. O

To O
the O
topic O
of O
the O
law O
against O
the O
mixed O
marriages O
I O
would O
like O
to O
note O
, O
that O
this O
law O
protecting O
the O
Romanian B-LOC
race O
is O
not O
of O
any O
major O
practical O
relevance O
, O
since O
based O
on O
my O
information O
, O
the O
mixed O
marriages O
have O
never O
threatened O
the O
Romanian B-LOC
race O
, O
although O
there O
were O
many O
of O
them O
, O
and O
[ O
... O
] O
the O
number O
of O
the O
mixed O
marriages O
has O
almost O
declined O
to O
almost O
zero O
percent O
during O
the O
past O
months O
. O

Made O
in O
6 O
copies O
, O
4 O
of O
them O
for O
the O
Ministry O
of O
Foreign O
Affairs O
, O
1 O
copy O
for O
the O
army O
attaché O
and O
1 O
copy O
to O
be O
stored O
within O
the O
records O
. O

Delegate B-PERS
The O
Government O
appears O
to O
be O
making O
every O
effort O
on O
the O
one O
hand O
to O
appease O
the O
Jews O
by O
restraining O
molestation O
of O
all O
kinds O
, O
while O
on O
the O
other O
hand O
proceeding O
with O
such O
discriminatory O
regulations O
as O
those O
just O
mentioned O
Law O
for O
the O
Organization O
of O
the O
College O
of O
Doctors O
, O
stipulates O
that O
only O
Rumanian O
citizens O
enjoying O
full O
civil O
rights O
can O
be O
members O
, O
therefore O
excluding O
Jews O
. O

Some O
are O
suspected O
of O
clandestinely O
encouraging O
attacks O
on O
the O
Jews O
because O
of O
their O
conviction O
that O
( O
a O
) O
this O
is O
the O
solution O
of O
the O
entire O
Rumanian B-LOC
problem O
and O
( O
b O
) O
it O
will O
curry O
favor O
with O
Germany O
. O

Rumanians O
in O
general O
seem O
to O
wish O
to O
wreak O
their O
wrath O
either O
actively O
or O
passively O
on O
the O
Jews O
for O
the O
events O
which O
have O
taken O
place O
in O
Bessarabia B-LOC
, O
particularly O
the O
many O
instances O
which O
are O
gradually O
becoming O
known O
in O
which O
the O
Jews O
, O
either O
aided O
or O
encouraged O
by O
communists O
and O
other O
members O
of O
the O
local O
populations O
, O
rose O
against O
the O
departing O
Rumanian B-LOC
officials O
at O
the O
time O
of O
the O
Russian B-LOC
entry O
. O

Continual O
reports O
of O
persecutions O
and O
killings O
of O
Jews O
in O
the O
provinces O
, O
particularly O
in O
Moldavian B-LOC
villages O
and O
towns O
along O
the O
new O
frontier O
, O
are O
drifting O
into O
Bucharest B-LOC
daily O
, O
but O
it O
is O
difficult O
to O
ascertain O
just O
what O
proportion O
of O
them O
may O
be O
true O
. O

I O
have O
the O
honor O
to O
report O
that O
Ambassador O
Stoica B-PERS
, O
formerly O
Ambassador O
at O
Ankara B-LOC
and O
now O
Under O
Secretary O
of O
Propaganda O
, O
told O
me O
the O
other O
evening O
at O
dinner O
at O
my O
house O
in O
honor O
of O
himself O
and O
the O
representatives O
of O
the O
American B-LOC
newspapers O
, O
that O
his O
Government B-ORG
was O
going O
to O
do O
everything O
within O
its O
power O
to O
prevent O
anti O
- O
Jewish O
outbreaks O
, O
but O
that O
it O
greatly O
feared O
such O
outbreaks O
on O
the O
part O
of O
the O
Army O
as O
the O
latter O
was O
so O
incensed O
at O
the O
treatment O
meted O
out O
to O
it O
by O
the O
Jews O
in O
Bessarabia B-LOC
when O
it O
was O
withdrawing O
. O

I O
observed O
that O
for O
once O
Rumania B-LOC
had O
a O
good O
press O
in O
the O
outside O
world O
, O
where O
there O
was O
great O
sympathy O
because O
it O
had O
been O
set O
upon O
by O
a O
powerful O
nation O
of O
180,000,000 O
people O
, O
and O
that O
I O
thought O
it O
would O
be O
a O
great O
pity O
to O
sacrifice O
this O
for O
the O
sake O
of O
a O
Pogrom O
or O
two O
. O

On O
another O
recent O
occasion O
I O
had O
an O
opportunity O
informally O
to O
emphasize O
to O
Prime O
Minister O
Gigurtu B-PERS
that O
any O
internal O
disturbance O
, O
especially O
Jewish O
persecution O
, O
might O
easily O
be O
seized O
upon O
by O
Russia B-LOC
as O
an O
excuse O
for O
further O
action O
. O
[ O
... O
] O
The O
Gigurtu B-PERS
group O
maintains O
that O
to O
pass O
rigid O
laws O
against O
Jews O
at O
the O
present O
critical O
moment O
would O
seriously O
affect O
the O
economic O
structure O
of O
the O
State O
, O
as O
well O
as O
create O
a O
most O
unfortunate O
impression O
among O
nations O
abroad O
, O
particularly O
the O
United B-LOC
States I-LOC
. O

Some O
observers O
take O
the O
view O
that O
should O
there O
be O
no O
further O
pressure O
from O
Hungary B-LOC
and O
Bulgaria B-LOC
for O
territorial O
cession O
at O
present O
the O
moderate O
group O
will O
win O
its O
point O
and O
there O
will O
be O
no O
strong O
anti O
- O
Semitic O
reaction O
in O
Rumania B-LOC
; O

if O
, O
however O
, O
the O
Government O
is O
forced O
to O
cede O
more O
territory O
immediately O
, O
a O
cession O
for O
which O
public O
opinion O
has O
not O
yet O
been O
adequately O
prepared O
, O
the O
Iron B-ORG
Guard I-ORG
thesis O
will O
be O
more O
likely O
to O
win O
because O
the O
Government O
will O
find O
it O
necessary O
to O
resort O
to O
anti O
- O
Semitic O
agitation O
as O
a O
cloak O
and O
counter O
- O
irritant O
. O

In O
recent O
days O
a O
few O
mild O
anti O
- O
Jewish O
measures O
have O
been O
announced O
but O
nothing O
to O
suggest O
a O
really O
vicious O
program O
. O
[ O
... O
] O
I O
accordingly O
feel O
that O
no O
really O
strong O
Jewish O
persecutions O
are O
apt O
to O
eventuate O
in O
the O
near O
future O
except O
as O
they O
may O
arise O
out O
of O
new O
circumstances O
created O
by O
the O
evolution O
of O
international O
events O
or O
further O
dissatisfaction O
in O
the O
Army O
. O

Confidential O
22 B-DATE
July I-DATE
1940 I-DATE
Political O
report O
no O
. O
167/40 O
Probably O
the O
most O
important O
issue O
of O
the O
internal O
politics O
of O
Mr. O
Gigurtu´s B-PERS
government O
is O
the O
adjustment O
of O
the O
Jewish O
Question O
. O

It O
is O
not O
only O
an O
important O
question O
of O
the O
internal O
politics O
, O
which O
would O
be O
no O
more O
than O
a O
logical O
resolution O
of O
the O
new O
orientation O
of O
the O
Romanian B-LOC
politics O
overall O
and O
which O
would O
adjust O
the O
situation O
of O
Jews O
in O
Romania B-LOC
towards O
the O
new O
order O
. O

It O
is O
a O
much O
more O
important O
problem O
, O
since O
it O
reaches O
maybe O
way O
too O
far O
into O
the O
overall O
economic O
structure O
of O
modern O
Romania B-LOC
. O

I O
have O
to O
point O
out O
right O
at O
the O
beginning O
that O
it O
is O
not O
only O
about O
the O
fact O
that O
one O
or O
the O
other O
of O
the O
important O
industrial O
or O
business O
company O
is O
owned O
by O
Jews O
and O
that O
a O
radical O
Aryanization O
is O
needed O
. O

All O
that O
would O
not O
be O
such O
a O
big O
problem O
and O
could O
be O
carried O
out O
under O
certain O
circumstances O
, O
following O
the O
example O
of O
Germany O
, O
radically O
but O
without O
any O
severe O
damages O
to O
the O
economy O
. O

The O
problem O
, O
however O
, O
is O
much O
more O
complicated O
due O
to O
the O
exceptional O
situation O
of O
Romania B-LOC
. O

In O
this O
wealthy O
country O
is O
the O
majority O
of O
the O
capital B-LOC
in O
the O
companies O
of O
non- O
Romanian B-LOC
origin O
. O

Mostly O
it O
is O
Jewish O
, O
but O
also O
British B-LOC
, O
French B-LOC
, O
from O
Belgium B-LOC
and O
from O
Netherlands B-LOC
. O

This O
side O
of O
the O
situation O
is O
the O
one O
which O
can O
bring O
major O
issues O
for O
the O
Romanian B-LOC
economy O
if O
not O
handled O
very O
carefully O
. O

Voices O
are O
growing O
louder O
, O
saying O
that O
the O
British B-LOC
capital O
has O
already O
been O
withdrawn O
, O
since O
Romania B-LOC
is O
seen O
as O
a O
country O
definitely O
in O
the O
interest O
area O
of O
the O
German O
Reich O
. O

As O
proof O
of O
this O
claim O
, O
it O
is O
reported O
that O
the O
British B-LOC
sold O
at O
the O
last O
moment O
participation O
in O
some O
of O
the O
most O
important O
oil O
companies O
to O
Russia B-LOC
, O
even O
below O
value O
, O
just O
to O
upset O
both O
Romania B-LOC
and O
Germany O
. O

[ O
… O
] O
Therefore O
, O
there O
is O
a O
possibility O
that O
the O
sources O
of O
foreign O
capital O
– O
the O
sources O
so O
much O
needed O
for O
a O
country O
as O
Romania B-LOC
which O
is O
weak O
on O
capital O
, O
since O
the O
Romanian O
population O
does O
not O
invest O
the O
money O
and O
the O
money O
is O
not O
within O
the O
estates O
and O
houses O
[ O
... O
] O
– O
will O
be O
suddenly O
cut O
off O
and O
thus O
a O
new O
and O
much O
stronger O
financial O
and O
economic O
crisis O
will O
occur O
. O

The O
local O
Jews O
, O
afraid O
, O
have O
already O
cut O
off O
any O
further O
businesses O
, O
theydo O
not O
dislodge O
goods O
that O
accumulate O
at O
customs O
, O
and O
they O
do O
not O
make O
any O
new O
trades O
or O
transaction O
. O

They O
are O
gathering O
money O
and O
investing O
it O
into O
volatile O
values O
, O
such O
as O
diamonds O
, O
dollar O
bills O
, O
etc. O
It O
seems O
to O
me O
that O
they O
are O
not O
even O
trying O
to O
sabotage O
anything O
; O

rather O
they O
are O
worried O
for O
the O
future O
of O
Jews O
in O
Romania B-LOC
, O
which O
will O
certainly O
to O
be O
very O
difficult O
. O

The O
crisis O
is O
definitely O
just O
around O
the O
corner O
, O
since O
the O
German O
capital O
cannot O
come O
into O
effect O
straight O
away O
and O
if O
Romania B-LOC
was O
under O
threat O
of O
losing O
another O
territory O
to O
Hungary B-LOC
and O
Bulgaria B-LOC
, O
after O
already O
losing O
Bessarabia B-LOC
and O
northern O
Bukovina B-LOC
, O
the O
extend O
of O
the O
crisis O
could O
be O
devastating O
. O

Current O
national O
budget O
of O
about O
130 O
billion O
is O
already O
a O
heavy O
load O
for O
this O
diminished O
territory O
and O
if O
there O
were O
to O
be O
other O
civil O
servants O
returning O
to O
Romania B-LOC
, O
those O
from O
the O
territories O
Romania B-LOC
could O
lose O
, O
the O
financial O
burden O
would O
be O
way O
too O
big O
for O
the O
rest O
of O
Romania B-LOC
. O

These O
are O
serious O
perspectives O
, O
it O
is O
not O
only O
a O
sheer O
Jewish O
misconception O
and O
propaganda O
to O
protect O
their O
positions O
, O
therefore O
the O
solutions O
the O
government O
is O
about O
to O
take O
when O
it O
comes O
to O
the O
Jewish O
Question O
are O
very O
intensely O
awaited O
at O
this O
moment O
. O

If O
the O
solution O
is O
rational O
time O
- O
wise O
and O
also O
prepared O
( O
and O
so O
far O
there O
are O
no O
causes O
, O
even O
among O
the O
smaller O
officers O
, O
already O
manifesting O
dissatisfaction O
of O
the O
anti- O
Jewish O
sentiment O
to O
expect O
the O
government O
to O
act O
hastily O
) O
, O
the O
chances O
that O
the O
solution O
of O
the O
Jewish O
Question O
will O
bring O
on O
a O
central O
crisis O
will O
be O
at O
least O
smaller O
. O

However O
, O
if O
the O
government O
does O
not O
proceed O
carefully O
, O
it O
could O
be O
facing O
such O
major O
failures O
as O
the O
nationalist O
government O
of O
the O
late O
Octavian B-PERS
Goga I-PERS
did O
. O

His O
government O
had O
to O
be O
removed O
after O
only O
two O
months O
of O
its O
existence O
; O

therefore O
Romania B-LOC
was O
threatened O
by O
a O
major O
economical O
and O
financial O
crisis O
. O

Very O
similar O
aspects O
are O
now O
reappearing O
, O
awaiting O
the O
solutions O
to O
the O
Jewish O
Question O
, O
therefore O
an O
objective O
observer O
needs O
to O
be O
thinking O
of O
this O
unpleasant O
precedent O
[ O
... O
] O
however O
, O
it O
cannot O
be O
forgotten O
that O
the O
government O
of O
Mr. O
Gigurtu B-PERS
has O
a O
very O
practical O
national O
economist O
and O
financial O
expert O
– O
the O
Prime O
Minister O
himself O
. O

He O
must O
be O
aware O
of O
the O
difficulties O
connected O
to O
this O
situation O
and O
therefore O
he O
will O
definitely O
proceed O
very O
rationally O
and O
as O
carefully O
as O
it O
is O
necessary O
, O
given O
the O
circumstances O
. O

Moreover O
, O
the O
Minister O
of O
the O
National O
Economy O
, O
who O
is O
at O
the O
same O
time O
a O
well O
- O
known O
national O
economist O
, O
oversees O
all O
the O
so O
called O
economical O
resorts O
, O
thus O
he O
has O
the O
necessary O
possibilities O
of O
a O
united O
progress O
and O
can O
avoid O
any O
conflicts O
in O
the O
competencies O
of O
resorts O
. O

Based O
on O
all O
the O
mentioned O
reasons O
I O
can O
express O
my O
hope O
that O
the O
government O
will O
solve O
the O
urgent O
and O
difficult O
problems O
without O
any O
major O
shakedowns O
, O
given O
they O
take O
reasonable O
approach O
. O

Made O
in O
6 O
copies O
, O
4 O
of O
them O
for O
the O
Ministry O
of O
Foreign O
Affairs O
, O
1 O
copy O
for O
the O
army O
attaché O
and O
1 O
copy O
to O
be O
stored O
within O
the O
records O
. O

Delegate B-PERS
The O
following O
information O
with O
regard O
to O
the O
deportation O
of O
Jews O
from O
Krakow B-LOC
was O
furnished O
in O
confidence O
by O
Jewish O
leaders O
at O
Warsaw B-LOC
. O

The O
Jewish O
population O
of O
Krakow B-LOC
now O
totals O
some O
67,000 O
including O
about O
11,000 O
deportees O
who O
have O
recently O
arrived O
from O
Polish B-LOC
regions O
annexed O
to O
Germany B-LOC
. O

The O
deportation O
held O
in O
May B-DATE
will O
immediately O
affect O
a O
total O
of O
80,000 O
Jews O
and O
it O
cannot O
be O
regarded O
otherwise O
than O
a O
major O
disaster O
to O
Polish O
Jewry O
. O

The O
break O
up O
of O
the O
ancient O
, O
rich O
and O
powerful O
Jewish O
community O
at O
Krakow B-LOC
can O
bring O
nothing O
but O
destitution O
to O
its O
members O
who O
will O
be O
forced O
on O
short O
notice O
to O
emigrate O
without O
resources O
to O
such O
localities O
in O
the O
General O
Government O
as O
are O
able O
and O
willing O
to O
receive O
them O
. O

Confidential O
August B-DATE
21st I-DATE
1940 I-DATE
Political O
report O
no O
. O
196/40 O
To O
the O
local O
report O
no O
. O
2767 O
of O
the O
political O
report O
no O
. O
187 O
from O
April B-DATE
8th I-DATE
1940 I-DATE
about O
the O
Jewish O
law O
I O
would O
like O
to O
announce O
that O
the O
Ministries O
and O
all O
the O
central O
offices O
issued O
a O
whole O
lot O
of O
the O
internal O
decrees O
to O
get O
the O
Jewish O
law O
carried O
out O
in O
their O
area O
of O
competence O
and O
to O
get O
the O
Jews O
working O
as O
civil O
servants O
immediately O
eliminated O
from O
their O
positions O
. O

The O
list O
of O
names O
of O
such O
Jews O
stripped O
of O
their O
positions O
was O
given O
to O
print O
. O

As O
an O
interesting O
fact O
I O
would O
like O
to O
also O
state O
, O
that O
also O
Jews O
who O
held O
their O
official O
functions O
at O
the O
withdrawn O
areas O
of O
Bessarabia B-LOC
and O
northern O
Bukovina B-LOC
were O
a O
part O
of O
this O
list O
. O

This O
brought O
a O
smile O
to O
the O
faces O
of O
critical O
people O
; O

however O
its O
purpose O
was O
to O
prevent O
these O
Jews O
– O
clerks O
from O
the O
areas O
of O
Bessarabia B-LOC
and O
northern O
Bukovina B-LOC
– O
from O
getting O
employed O
as O
civil O
servants O
back O
in O
Romania B-LOC
. O

The O
critical O
voices O
from O
the O
local O
diplomatic O
corps O
can O
be O
also O
heard O
, O
since O
according O
to O
them O
an O
issue O
with O
the O
Jews O
as O
civil O
servants O
was O
an O
easy O
one O
to O
solve O
because O
there O
were O
not O
many O
of O
them O
and O
none O
at O
the O
leading O
positions O
. O

In O
practice O
, O
the O
carrying O
out O
of O
the O
Jewish O
law O
faces O
some O
issues O
as O
well O
, O
coming O
from O
standards O
governing O
this O
issue O
. O

The O
legal O
decrees O
about O
the O
National O
party O
state O
that O
only O
a O
member O
of O
the O
Party O
can O
become O
a O
member O
of O
an O
executive O
board O
and O
vice O
- O
versa O
[ O
... O
] O
the O
law O
states O
that O
a O
Jew O
cannot O
become O
a O
member O
of O
the O
National O
party O
at O
all O
. O

This O
law O
, O
thus O
, O
does O
not O
give O
Jews O
a O
chance O
to O
remain O
members O
of O
the O
executive O
boards O
of O
companies O
. O

Nevertheless O
, O
the O
Jewish O
law O
( O
see O
the O
quoted O
report O
) O
prevents O
only O
the O
Jews O
of O
the O
first O
and O
the O
third O
category O
to O
become O
members O
of O
executive O
boards O
and O
does O
not O
create O
any O
obstacles O
for O
the O
Jews O
of O
the O
second O
category O
. O

From O
all O
of O
that O
a O
practical O
question O
arises O
in O
the O
companies O
, O
that O
is O
which O
of O
the O
two O
legal O
decrees O
is O
valid O
. O

It O
is O
only O
natural O
that O
the O
Jews O
are O
trying O
to O
hold O
on O
to O
the O
more O
convenient O
Jewish O
law O
with O
all O
the O
means O
possible O
, O
since O
based O
on O
the O
information O
I O
got O
it O
is O
not O
at O
all O
easy O
for O
Jews O
to O
prove O
their O
right O
to O
be O
in O
the O
second O
category O
, O
because O
the O
competent O
offices O
are O
making O
operative O
steps O
in O
this O
issue O
and O
are O
supposedly O
dismissing O
also O
those O
proofs O
which O
satisfy O
the O
formal O
requirements O
. O

I O
am O
not O
sure O
whether O
I O
am O
mistaken O
, O
but O
it O
seems O
that O
the O
differences O
between O
the O
legal O
decrees O
are O
not O
coincidental O
. O

It O
is O
hard O
to O
imagine O
such O
frivolousness O
, O
especially O
when O
it O
comes O
to O
such O
an O
important O
issue O
for O
Romanian B-LOC
economic O
life O
. O

Thus O
, O
it O
can O
be O
assumed O
that O
it O
is O
something O
intended O
for O
great O
deal O
of O
elasticity O
in O
this O
issue O
. O

The O
inconsistency O
in O
the O
execution O
of O
the O
decrees O
can O
be O
seen O
also O
within O
the O
army O
, O
where O
each O
of O
the O
divisions O
applies O
the O
decrees O
individually O
. O

I O
was O
informed O
about O
cases O
where O
regiments O
simply O
demobilized O
a O
Jewish O
rank O
and O
sent O
it O
home O
. O

The O
other O
regiment O
, O
however O
, O
sent O
a O
Jewish O
rank O
home O
in O
uniforms O
and O
told O
them O
to O
come O
back O
in O
their O
plain O
clothes O
to O
then O
decide O
their O
fate O
. O

Finally O
the O
third O
regiment O
demobilized O
its O
Jewish O
rank O
immediately O
, O
however O
they O
were O
told O
to O
come O
back O
every O
morning O
and O
every O
afternoon O
in O
their O
plain O
clothes O
to O
ask O
about O
any O
work O
that O
comes O
up O
. O

Similar O
inconsistent O
solutions O
are O
possible O
when O
it O
comes O
to O
the O
local O
administrative O
customs O
. O

The O
overall O
picture O
one O
gets O
from O
these O
individual O
events O
is O
that O
when O
it O
comes O
to O
the O
solution O
of O
the O
Jewish O
problem O
, O
the O
steps O
taken O
are O
going O
to O
depend O
on O
the O
given O
situation O
and O
will O
be O
opportunistic O
enough O
to O
bring O
the O
most O
for O
Romania B-LOC
and O
Romanian B-LOC
population O
. O

It O
is O
convenient O
exactly O
for O
these O
opportunistic O
possibilities O
that O
the O
basic O
decrees O
are O
so O
different O
and O
that O
, O
even O
more O
than O
with O
any O
other O
laws O
, O
in O
this O
case O
everything O
will O
depend O
on O
how O
the O
steps O
are O
being O
executed O
and O
on O
the O
administrative O
practice O
. O

Made O
in O
6 O
copies O
, O
4 O
of O
them O
for O
the O
Ministry O
of O
Foreign O
Affairs O
, O
1 O
copy O
for O
the O
army O
attaché O
and O
1 O
copy O
to O
be O
stored O
within O
the O
records O
. O

Delegate B-PERS
The O
compulsory O
labor O
law O
envisaged O
the O
employment O
of O
conscripts O
not O
liable O
to O
or O
desired O
for O
military O
service O
on O
work O
supplementary O
to O
the O
military O
effort O
. O

The O
virtually O
general O
mobilization O
has O
resulted O
in O
a O
large O
reservoir O
of O
such O
labor O
which O
is O
composed O
entirely O
or O
in O
large O
measure O
of O
Jews O
since O
their O
number O
permitted O
in O
military O
units O
is O
restricted O
to O
10 O
% O
of O
the O
complements O
, O
and O
includes O
persons O
high O
in O
commercial O
, O
industrial O
and O
professional O
life O
who O
previously O
had O
performed O
no O
manual O
labor O
as O
well O
as O
former O
army O
officers O
of O
Jewish O
extraction O
, O
many O
of O
high O
rank O
. O

They O
are O
organized O
in O
labor O
camps O
under O
strict O
military O
control O
, O
receive O
no O
pay O
or O
clothing O
and O
live O
in O
a O
condition O
bordering O
on O
servitude O
. O

Most O
of O
the O
labor O
presently O
performed O
by O
them O
appears O
to O
have O
no O
connection O
with O
defense O
measures O
. O
[ O
... O
] O
Unavailing O
protests O
by O
prominent O
persons O
have O
been O
made O
to O
the O
Prime O
Minister O
and O
it O
is O
generally O
considered O
that O
the O
persecution O
of O
the O
Jews O
will O
increase O
either O
at O
German O
instigation O
or O
in O
an O
effort O
to O
indicate O
Hungarian O
union O
with O
the O
Axis O
. O

Belgrade B-LOC
, O
October B-DATE
7th I-DATE
1940 I-DATE
Today O
I O
paid O
a O
visit O
to O
the O
chairman O
of O
the O
main O
union O
of O
peasant O
farmers O
’ O
cooperatives O
in O
Belgrade B-LOC
, O
the O
former O
Prime O
minister O
– O
{ O
{ O
Vojislav O
Djordjevič O
} O
} O
. O

[ O
… O
] O
I O
was O
asking O
the O
Minister O
about O
the O
current O
political O
situation O
in O
Yugoslavia B-LOC
and O
about O
the O
circumstances O
this O
situation O
depends O
on O
. O

I O
was O
very O
happy O
that O
Minister O
Djordjevič O
did O
not O
talk O
to O
me O
as O
to O
a O
diplomat O
, O
rather O
as O
to O
a O
friend O
and O
a O
person O
from O
a O
country B-LOC
he O
got O
to O
know O
and O
held O
dear O
to O
his O
heart O
. O

I O
would O
like O
to O
point O
out O
that O
Djordjevič O
used O
to O
be O
a O
part O
of O
the O
government O
of O
Dr. B-PERS
Milan I-PERS
Stojadinović I-PERS
; O

therefore O
, O
he O
has O
been O
having O
a O
positive O
attitude O
towards O
the O
German B-LOC
Reich I-LOC
. O

[ O
… O
] O
Yugoslavia B-LOC
is O
trying O
to O
keep O
the O
best O
possible O
relationship O
with O
Germany B-LOC
. O

The O
fact O
is O
that O
Germany B-LOC
does O
not O
want O
to O
break O
Yugoslavia B-LOC
. O

Because O
Yugoslavia B-LOC
's I-LOC
economic O
unit O
represents O
a O
better O
supply O
terrain O
for O
Germany B-LOC
than O
a O
splitted O
Yugoslavia B-LOC
. O

Furthermore O
, O
Germany B-LOC
regards O
Yugoslavia B-LOC
as O
its O
natural O
way O
to O
the O
Adriatic B-LOC
Sea I-LOC
. O

However O
, O
Germany B-LOC
is O
not O
satisfied O
with O
the O
current O
situation O
in O
Yugoslavia B-LOC
. O

It O
is O
not O
being O
appreciated O
that O
Yugoslavia B-LOC
is O
slow O
, O
or O
even O
hesitates O
, O
to O
adapt O
to O
the O
new O
ways O
represented O
by O
the O
German B-LOC
Reich I-LOC
. O

The O
current O
government O
is O
not O
sympathizing O
with O
Germany B-LOC
, O
since O
it O
was O
build O
upon O
the O
premises O
which O
are O
worthless O
nowadays O
, O
after O
the O
victory O
of O
the O
National O
Socialist O
ideology O
. O

To O
explain O
further O
, O
the O
government O
conciliated O
against O
the O
politics O
of O
Milan B-PERS
Stojadinović I-PERS
, O
who O
wanted O
to O
orientate O
the O
politics O
of O
Yugoslavia B-LOC
towards O
Berlin B-LOC
and O
tried O
to O
present O
the O
country O
with O
the O
totalitarian O
regime O
. O

Today´s O
government O
stemmed O
from O
a O
democratic O
, O
pro- O
English B-LOC
and O
pro- O
French B-LOC
ideology O
, O
thus O
the O
ideology O
which O
is O
anti O
- O
German O
. O

Therefore O
, O
it O
can O
be O
said O
that O
this O
government O
is O
in O
a O
latent O
crisis O
and O
therefore O
so O
much O
is O
said O
about O
its O
resignation O
. O

The O
government O
was O
to O
resign O
already O
last O
week O
. O

It O
was O
because O
of O
the O
Jewish O
laws O
. O

Minister O
Korošec B-PERS
, O
who O
totally O
agrees O
with O
the O
politics O
of O
the O
German B-LOC
Reich I-LOC
, O
prepared O
the O
Jewish O
laws O
. O

These O
laws O
were O
, O
however O
, O
refused O
to O
be O
enacted O
by O
some O
of O
the O
government O
members O
. O

Dr. O
Korošec B-PERS
, O
therefore O
, O
stood O
in O
the O
government O
against O
Cvetkovic B-PERS
and O
Maček B-PERS
. O

The O
dispute O
ratchet O
up O
so O
that O
Dr. O
Korošec B-PERS
and O
the O
members O
of O
the O
cabinet O
who O
are O
standing O
in O
favour O
of O
a O
new O
direction O
of O
internal O
and O
foreign O
policy O
of O
Yugoslavia B-LOC
, O
i.e O
. O
Minister O
Vulović B-PERS
, O
Pantić B-PERS
, O
Bešlić B-PERS
and O
Krek B-PERS
, O
threatened O
a O
formal O
resignation O
. O

Only O
under O
the O
threat O
of O
the O
resignation O
, O
the O
laws O
were O
approved O
. O

These O
involved O
the O
Jewish O
Quotas O
and O
the O
prohibition O
of O
the O
Jewish O
trade O
in O
life O
needs O
in O
Yugoslavia B-LOC
. O

The O
laws O
were O
published O
, O
however O
, O
it O
is O
said O
behind O
the O
scenes O
that O
they O
are O
to O
be O
enacted O
very O
liberally O
. O

This O
is O
where O
the O
current O
government´s O
politics O
proves O
to O
be O
two O
- O
faced O
. O

It O
seems O
that O
Yugoslavia B-LOC
is O
facing O
huge O
political O
and O
personal O
changes O
. O

Minister O
Djordjevič O
indicated O
that O
it O
might O
go O
as O
far O
as O
it O
did O
in O
Romania B-LOC
. O

Prince B-PERS
Regent I-PERS
Pavel I-PERS
is O
a O
devoted O
anglophile O
and O
represents O
a O
regime O
which O
is O
intolerable O
to O
German B-LOC
politics O
. O

It O
is O
therefore O
expected O
that O
he O
will O
be O
forced O
to O
resign O
and O
the O
reign O
will O
be O
given O
to O
King B-PERS
Peter I-PERS
II I-PERS
, O
who O
is O
to O
be O
18 O
years O
old O
only O
the O
upcoming O
year O
. O

There O
is O
a O
possibility O
that O
Korošec B-PERS
will O
become O
the O
Prime O
Minister O
. O

[ O
… O
] O
Na O
stráž O
! O

Chargé O
d´affaires O
: O

The O
establishment O
of O
a O
Jewish O
ghetto O
in O
Warsaw B-LOC
has O
not O
been O
unexpected O
as O
reports O
of O
some O
such O
impending O
action O
have O
been O
current O
in O
that O
city O
, O
particularly O
among O
Jewish O
circles O
, O
from O
the O
early O
days O
of O
the O
occupation O
. O

At O
the O
same O
time O
active O
preparations O
, O
which O
could O
be O
interpreted O
in O
no O
other O
way O
than O
as O
tending O
towards O
a O
complete O
segregation O
of O
the O
Jewish O
population O
, O
have O
been O
in O
course O
for O
some O
months O
. O
[ O
... O
] O
A O
strange O
commentary O
on O
life O
in O
German O
- O
occupied O
Warsaw B-LOC
is O
presented O
by O
the O
fact O
that O
many O
a O
nationalist O
Pole O
has O
endeavored O
to O
take O
on O
the O
‘ O
protective O
coloration O
’ O
of O
the O
Jew O
in O
order O
to O
escape O
from O
the O
German B-ORG
police I-ORG
or O
to O
avoid O
compulsory O
labor O
. O

These O
‘ O
refugees O
’ O
have O
adopted O
Jewish O
insignia O
and O
taken O
up O
residence O
in O
the O
ghetto O
; O

many O
stories O
are O
current O
in O
Warsaw B-LOC
of O
Jews O
tearing O
off O
their O
racial O
badges O
and O
passing O
them O
over O
in O
the O
streets O
to O
fleeing O
Poles O
. O

It O
is O
noteworthy O
that O
during O
the O
period O
of O
anti O
- O
Jewish O
disturbances O
in O
Poland B-LOC
prior O
to O
German O
occupation O
the O
600,000 O
people O
in O
the O
Jewish O
district O
, O
almost O
evenly O
divided O
between O
Poles O
and O
Jews O
, O
managed O
to O
get O
along O
together O
peacefully O
and O
lived O
in O
a O
community O
spirit O
which O
was O
not O
noticeable O
in O
the O
other O
parts O
of O
the O
city O
. O

The O
pending O
segregation O
of O
the O
Jews O
in O
an O
official O
ghetto O
affects O
an O
equal O
number O
of O
Poles O
and O
the O
move O
may O
in O
the O
long O
run O
bring O
greater O
discomfort O
to O
the O
latter O
than O
to O
the O
majority O
of O
the O
Jewish O
population O
. O

At O
any O
rate O
the O
Jews O
may O
well O
be O
in O
a O
better O
position O
to O
maintain O
a O
united O
front O
towards O
the O
occupying O
authorities O
and O
to O
find O
in O
community O
life O
a O
solace O
and O
protection O
until O
the O
time O
comes O
when O
a O
life O
of O
freedom O
and O
tolerance O
can O
at O
last O
be O
the O
lot O
of O
the O
unhappy O
thousands O
now O
to O
be O
concentrated O
in O
the O
greatest O
of O
Eastern B-LOC
Europe I-LOC
’s I-LOC
many O
Jewries O
by O
an O
alien O
conqueror O
and O
a O
ruthless O
race O
enemy O
. O

In O
adverting O
to O
reports O
from O
this O
Mission O
with O
respect O
to O
anti O
- O
Semitic O
measures O
in O
German O
- O
occupied O
countries O
, O
I O
have O
the O
honor O
to O
submit O
hereunder O
in O
summary O
form O
a O
description O
of O
measures O
recently O
announced O
in O
the O
German O
press O
directed O
against O
the O
Jewish O
population O
of O
occupied O
France B-LOC
, O
the O
Netherlands B-LOC
, O
Belgium B-LOC
and O
Northern O
France O
, O
Alsace B-LOC
, O
the O
General B-ORG
Government I-ORG
( O
of O
Poland B-LOC
) O
, O
and O
Slovakia B-LOC
. O

[ O
… O
] O
General B-ORG
Government I-ORG
( O
of O
Poland B-LOC
): O
In O
view O
of O
the O
heavy O
migration O
of O
population O
into O
the O
new O
Jewish O
ghetto O
in O
Warsaw B-LOC
, O
the O
period O
for O
the O
completion O
of O
voluntary O
establishment O
there O
by O
Jewish O
families O
from O
other O
quarters O
of O
the O
city O
has O
been O
extended O
through O
November B-DATE
15 I-DATE
. O

At O
the O
same O
time O
the O
limits O
of O
the O
ghetto O
have O
been O
enlarged O
to O
take O
in O
certain O
additional O
blocks O
and O
it O
is O
feared O
that O
this O
enlargement O
may O
mean O
the O
moving O
into O
the O
ghetto O
of O
Jews O
not O
as O
yet O
resident O
in O
Warsaw B-LOC
. O

It O
has O
also O
been O
decided O
to O
force O
the O
transfer O
of O
Jewish O
owned O
and O
operated O
industrial O
plants O
into O
the O
ghetto O
and O
the O
removal O
from O
the O
ghetto O
of O
many O
such O
enterprises O
carried O
on O
therein O
by O
non O
- O
Jews O
. O

There O
are O
taking O
place O
conversations O
between O
the O
owners O
of O
such O
plants O
as O
to O
whether O
an O
exchange O
of O
ownership O
cannot O
be O
effected O
in O
a O
manner O
acceptable O
to O
both O
the O
Jews O
and O
non O
- O
Jews O
. O

The O
authorities O
express O
the O
hope O
that O
this O
extension O
of O
the O
ghetto O
idea O
to O
include O
industrial O
enterprises O
may O
be O
carried O
out O
without O
undue O
delay O
. O

Slovakia B-LOC
: O

A O
decree O
is O
reported O
to O
be O
under O
preparation O
by O
the O
Slovakian B-ORG
Government I-ORG
which O
will O
block O
Jewish O
accounts O
in O
banking O
establishments O
and O
will O
make O
obligatory O
the O
deposit O
of O
all O
securities O
belonging O
to O
Jewish O
persons O
or O
enterprises O
. O

Payments O
to O
Jews O
will O
only O
be O
possible O
through O
such O
blocked O
accounts O
and O
Jews O
will O
only O
be O
allowed O
to O
withdraw O
up O
to O
a O
maximum O
of O
5,000 O
crowns O
per O
week O
on O
the O
basis O
of O
a O
special O
and O
individual O
permit O
from O
their O
blocked O
accounts O
. O

The O
above O
developments O
indicate O
that O
German O
anti O
- O
Semitic O
measures O
are O
rapidly O
being O
put O
into O
effect O
in O
the O
occupied O
territories O
. O

At O
the O
same O
time O
the O
German O
press O
publishes O
articles O
reporting O
somewhat O
similar O
measures O
in O
Rumania B-LOC
, O
Jugoslavia B-LOC
, O
Bulgaria B-LOC
and O
unoccupied O
France O
. O

There O
appears O
, O
consequently O
, O
to O
be O
a O
definite O
program O
of O
carrying O
German O
anti O
- O
Semitism O
beyond O
the O
German O
borders O
into O
such O
countries O
as O
come O
into O
the O
German O
sphere O
of O
influence O
. O

But O
, O
as O
earlier O
despatches O
have O
already O
suggested O
, O
the O
lot O
of O
the O
Jews O
in O
Rumania B-LOC
has O
definitely O
worsened O
since O
the O
inauguration O
of O
the O
present B-ORG
regime I-ORG
three O
months O
ago O
. O

In O
the O
first O
place O
, O
the O
green O
- O
shirted O
Iron O
Guard O
is O
in O
power O
, O
and O
the O
Iron O
Guard O
is O
notoriously O
and O
avowedly O
an O
essentially O
anti O
- O
Semitic O
organization O
. O

In O
the O
second O
place O
, O
Rumania B-LOC
not O
only O
has O
come O
under O
the O
direct O
‘ O
influence O
’ O
of O
Nazi O
Germany O
but O
is O
now O
actually O
a O
member O
of O
the O
Axis O
and O
an O
adherent O
to O
the O
Tripartite O
Pact O
. O

And O
, O
thirdly O
, O
the O
country O
requires O
scape O
- O
goats O
for O
all O
the O
evils O
and O
misfortunes O
of O
the O
day O
, O
and O
finds O
that O
the O
Jews O
, O
along O
with O
former O
King B-PERS
Carol I-PERS
and O
the O
old O
politicians O
, O
serve O
admirably O
in O
this O
unhappy O
role O
. O

These O
considerations O
, O
plus O
an O
underlying O
sentiment O
of O
genuine O
anti O
- O
Semitism O
generally O
, O
provide O
sufficient O
reason O
and O
background O
for O
Jewish O
fears O
and O
sufferings O
in O
Rumania B-LOC
today O
. O
[ O
... O
] O
In O
recent O
weeks O
the O
Jewish O
plaint O
has O
not O
been O
one O
of O
lost O
positions O
, O
special O
taxes O
or O
discriminatory O
restrictions O
– O
that O
is O
an O
old O
story O
. O

Rather O
it O
has O
been O
one O
of O
deaths O
, O
torture O
, O
beatings O
, O
abductions O
, O
confiscation O
, O
robbery O
and O
violence O
in O
all O
forms O
. O

It O
is O
not O
an O
exaggeration O
to O
say O
that O
here O
today O
one O
sees O
the O
Jews O
with O
tears O
, O
hollow O
eyes O
and O
wringing O
hands O
. O

Many O
of O
them O
never O
go O
out O
; O

they O
keep O
to O
their O
homes O
for O
fear O
of O
meeting O
violence O
in O
the O
street O
. O

A O
few O
, O
who O
have O
reasons O
to O
fear O
they O
may O
be O
sought O
out O
, O
creep O
from O
friend O
to O
friend O
or O
house O
to O
house O
afraid O
to O
go O
to O
their O
own O
homes O
to O
sleep O
. O

Those O
of O
means O
endeavor O
frantically O
to O
dispose O
of O
their O
property O
, O
secure O
funds O
abroad O
and O
find O
a O
way O
to O
leave O
the O
country O
. O

The O
text O
of O
the O
anti O
- O
Jewish O
law O
‚ O
Law O
on O
the O
Defense O
of O
the O
Nation O
‘ O
passed O
in O
its O
entirety O
on O
December B-DATE
26 I-DATE
has O
not O
been O
published O
. O

With O
only O
49000 O
Jews O
here O
of O
a O
good O
class O
and O
holding O
no O
important O
government O
positions O
there O
was O
no O
Jewish O
problem O
. O

The O
law O
is O
said O
to O
be O
drastic O
in O
its O
terms O
but O
a O
loophole O
in O
its O
strict O
enforcement O
may O
be O
the O
fact O
that O
rules O
and O
regulations O
for O
the O
laws O
application O
drawn O
up O
by O
the O
Minister O
of O
the O
Interior O
must O
be O
approved O
by O
the O
Council B-ORG
of I-ORG
Ministers I-ORG
. O

I O
find O
the O
Bulgarian O
people O
as O
a O
whole O
apathetic O
about O
it O
and O
a O
little O
ashamed O
. O

Contents O
This O
trip O
to O
Warsaw B-LOC
is O
the O
fourth O
one O
I O
undertook O
after O
the O
outbreak O
of O
the O
German O
- O
Polish O
War O
( O
December B-DATE
1939 I-DATE
, O
March B-DATE
and O
August B-DATE
1940 I-DATE
) O
. O

I O
must O
say O
that O
my O
impression O
of O
the O
German B-LOC
rule O
becomes O
more O
pessimistic O
each O
time O
. O

Namely O
, O
the O
public O
sentiment O
in O
the O
German O
- O
occupied O
areas O
, O
under O
the O
General O
Government O
, O
deteriorates O
more O
and O
more O
. O

The O
high O
- O
handed O
policies O
of O
the O
German O
authorities O
, O
coupled O
with O
the O
complex O
economic O
situation O
particular O
to O
this O
area O
, O
are O
fanning O
anti O
- O
German O
sentiment O
among O
the O
local O
population O
. O

On O
the O
other O
hand O
, O
the O
progress O
of O
the O
so O
- O
called O
rebuilding O
program O
is O
producing O
expected O
results O
thanks O
to O
the O
earnest O
efforts O
of O
the O
authorities O
. O

However O
, O
on O
the O
whole O
, O
its O
pace O
is O
extremely O
slow O
, O
and O
there O
is O
nothing O
really O
impressive O
. O

1a O
Transportation O
Except O
for O
the O
Jews O
, O
travel O
within O
the O
General O
Government O
is O
allowed O
. O

However O
, O
a O
special O
permit O
is O
required O
to O
travel O
between O
Germany O
proper O
and O
the O
General O
Government O
area O
by O
those O
other O
than O
government O
or O
military O
personnel O
on O
official O
business O
. O

Poles O
in O
principles O
are O
forbidden O
to O
travel O
outside O
the O
General O
Government O
area O
. O

1b O
. O

Post O
… O
re O
- O
organization O
of O
personnel O
( O
Poles O
are O
replaced O
by O
Germans O
) O
, O
confiscation O
of O
radio O
sets O
( O
Germans O
, O
Ukrainians O
, O
Belarussians O
, O
and O
White O
Russians O
are O
exempted O
from O
this O
) O
. O

1c O
. O

Monopoly O
1d O
. O

Currency O
1e O
. O

Mining O
and O
Industry O
1f O
. O

Labor O
Coupon O
1 O
g. O
Agriculture O
and O
Forestry O
1h O
. O

Judicial O
Matters O
1i O
. O

Public O
health O
1j O
. O
Press O
and O
Publication O
… O
. O

Among O
the O
newspapers O
listed O
above O
, O
Gazeta O
Judoska O
published O
its O
first O
issue O
in O
mid B-DATE
- I-DATE
July I-DATE
1940 I-DATE
. O

It O
is O
the O
Polish O
- O
language O
newspaper O
for O
Jews O
under O
the O
General O
Government O
( O
hence O
there O
is O
no O
newspaper O
in O
Hebrew O
) O
. O

Its O
content O
is O
roughly O
the O
same O
as O
other O
Polish O
- O
language O
newspapers O
, O
and O
mainly O
consists O
of O
articles O
relating O
to O
the O
Jews O
. O

While O
it O
publishes O
articles O
pertaining O
to O
General O
Government O
’s O
policies O
concerning O
Jews O
, O
there O
are O
also O
sections O
on O
literature O
and O
children O
. O

In O
the O
Politics O
sections O
, O
it O
prints O
German O
reports O
without O
adding O
any O
commentary O
. O

To O
name O
something O
of O
interest O
to O
us O
, O
the O
second O
issue O
of O
this O
newspaper O
published O
on O
July B-DATE
22 I-DATE
, I-DATE
1940 I-DATE
printed O
an O
item O
with O
considerable O
details O
under O
Necessary O
Procedures O
for O
Emigrating O
to O
Shanghai O
. O

1k O
. O

Radio O
Based O
on O
Regulations O
Concerning O
Confiscation O
and O
Returning O
of O
Radio O
Sets O
of O
December B-DATE
15 I-DATE
, I-DATE
1939 I-DATE
, O
Jews O
and O
Poles O
are O
ordered O
to O
turn O
in O
all O
radio O
sets O
by O
January B-DATE
15 I-DATE
, I-DATE
1940 I-DATE
. O

Those O
in O
violation O
will O
be O
tried O
under O
special O
courts O
and O
may O
be O
fined O
or O
subject O
to O
long O
- O
term O
corporeal O
punishment O
. O

Germans O
, O
Ukrainians O
, O
Belarussians O
, O
and O
White O
Russians O
may O
possess O
radios O
. O

1l O
. O

Cinema O
and O
Theater O
1 O
m. O
Education O
of O
Germans O
1n O
. O

Other O
In O
Warsaw B-LOC
the O
water O
supply O
and O
sewage O
are O
only O
partially O
restored O
. O

The O
same O
is O
with O
the O
telephone O
; O

although O
it O
is O
being O
partially O
restored O
, O
the O
number O
of O
its O
users O
has O
fallen O
to O
1/20 O
of O
the O
prewar O
level O
. O

The O
streets O
are O
still O
full O
of O
collapsed O
houses O
from O
artillery O
attacks O
by O
the O
German O
army O
and O
chaotic O
. O

Moreover O
, O
as O
many O
human O
and O
animal O
corpses O
are O
buried O
under O
the O
rubbles O
, O
the O
city O
shrouded O
in O
a O
certain O
stench O
. O

In O
March B-DATE
1940 I-DATE
I O
saw O
dead O
horses O
in O
the O
middle O
of O
the O
street O
; O

now O
they O
are O
gone O
. O

Immediately O
after O
the O
war O
in O
1939 B-DATE
plans O
were O
drawn O
up O
to O
move O
Jews O
to O
the O
east O
and O
to O
rebuild O
urban O
Warsaw B-LOC
. O

Concerning O
the O
former O
, O
no O
further O
concrete O
decisions O
have O
been O
revealed O
and O
the O
plan O
has O
been O
shelved O
; O

as O
for O
the O
latter O
, O
except O
the O
opening O
of O
a O
few O
news O
streets O
, O
it O
appears O
the O
plan O
has O
been O
grounded O
. O

It O
can O
be O
imagined O
rebuilding O
has O
many O
difficulties O
ahead O
. O

Lublin B-LOC
and O
its O
vicinity O
were O
designated O
as O
area O
of O
Jewish O
residence O
. O

However O
, O
subsequently O
no O
movement O
of O
Jews O
from O
Warsaw B-LOC
and O
the O
Krakow B-LOC
region O
have O
taken O
place O
. O

This O
plan O
seems O
to O
have O
been O
abolished O
. O

There O
has O
been O
no O
rebuilding O
or O
restoration O
in O
Lublin B-LOC
. O

Water O
supply O
and O
sewage O
are O
being O
restored O
in O
Krakow B-LOC
, O
where O
rebuilding O
effort O
has O
developed O
the O
furthest O
. O

1o O
. O
Summary O
While O
the O
rebuilding O
efforts O
have O
just O
started O
under O
the O
General O
Government O
as O
stated O
above O
, O
given O
the O
abundant O
labor O
force O
and O
the O
superior O
organizational O
capacity O
of O
the O
authorities O
, O
the O
efforts O
should O
bear O
fruit O
. O

At O
the O
party O
congress O
held O
in O
Krakow B-LOC
at O
the O
beginning O
of O
1941 B-DATE
Governor B-PERS
General I-PERS
Dr. I-PERS
Frank I-PERS
outlined O
major O
rebuilding O
projects O
for O
1941 B-DATE
and O
underscored O
their O
importance O
. O

This O
plan O
includes O
the O
dredging O
of O
the O
Vistula B-LOC
River I-LOC
, O
re O
- O
organization O
of O
industries O
, O
and O
building O
of O
housing O
and O
roads O
. O

2a O
. O

Administration O
2b O
. O

Policies O
The O
policy O
of O
the O
German O
authorities O
toward O
Poles O
in O
areas O
under O
the O
General O
Government O
has O
always O
been O
total O
oppression O
. O

Its O
ultimate O
political O
objective O
appears O
to O
be O
erasing O
Polishness O
from O
Eastern B-LOC
Europe I-LOC
, O
or O
at O
least O
preventing O
Poles O
from O
becoming O
a O
political O
force O
in O
the O
future O
. O

This O
is O
done O
through O
depriving O
them O
of O
ethnic O
identity O
by O
destroying O
their O
cultural O
roots O
so O
that O
they O
are O
reduced O
to O
a O
mere O
geographical O
existence O
. O

2c O
. O

Compulsory O
Labor O
2d O
. O

Destruction O
of O
Human O
Culture O
by O
means O
other O
than O
Compulsory O
Labor O
2e O
. O

Restrictions O
on O
Education O
2f O
. O
