LIST O
OF O
PERSONS B-TER
DIED O
IN O
KAMENSK-URAL B-LOC
, I-LOC
U.S.S.R. I-LOC
, O
ORIGINALLY O
DEPORTED B-TER
TO O
NISKO B-LOC
FROM O
VIENNA B-LOC
. O

FEDRIDT B-PER
Rudolf I-PER
, O
born O
in O
Trebitsch B-LOC
, O
died O
in O
summer O
1942 O
. O

FREUDMANN B-PER
Josef I-PER
, O
born O
18.5.1897 O
in O
Vienna B-LOC
, O
died O
6.9.1942 O
. O

HOLZER B-PER
David I-PER
, O
born O
in O
February O
1886 O
in O
Rechnitz B-LOC
, I-LOC
Burgenland I-LOC
, O
died O
12.2.1942 O
. O

KATZER B-PER
Berthold I-PER
, O
born O
25.12.1885 O
in O
Vienna B-LOC
, O
died O
7.6.1943 O
. O

KLAUSNER B-PER
Berthold I-PER
, O
born O
1883 O
in O
Vienna B-LOC
, O
died O
20.2.1944 O
. O

LICHTBLAU B-PER
Adolf I-PER
, O
born O
in O
Vienna B-LOC
, O
died O
1942 O
. O

LOEWY B-PER
Jakob I-PER
, O
born O
1889 O
in O
Vienna B-LOC
, O
died O
1943 O
. O

WURMFELD B-PER
Adalbert I-PER
, O
born O
8.12.1866 O
in O
Gross B-LOC
Hirm I-LOC
, I-LOC
Burgenland I-LOC
, O
died O
summer O
1942 O
. O

