It O
would O
seem O
, O
from O
all O
indications O
, O
that O
the O
intent O
is O
to O
obtain O
a O
large O
group O
of O
workers O
for O
use O
in O
Poland B-LOC
. O

What O
this O
use O
is O
seems O
to O
be O
problematical O
, O
but O
it O
may O
well O
be O
to O
prepare O
a O
place O
for O
the O
permanent O
settlement O
of O
the O
families O
, O
etc O
. O

, O
of O
these O
men O
. O

It O
would O
seem O
that O
this O
movement O
may O
well O
be O
part O
of O
a O
larger O
movement O
of O
populations O
which O
the O
German O
authorities O
are O
carrying O
out O
, O
including O
the O
bringing O
back O
of O
German O
families O
from O
the O
Baltic O
States O
, O
Russia B-LOC
, O
and O
those O
parts O
of O
Poland B-LOC
recently O
occupied O
by O
Russia B-LOC
. O

There O
are O
many O
rumors O
, O
but O
to O
date O
unverified O
, O
that O
the O
German O
authorities O
intend O
to O
bring O
into O
Bohemia O
and O
Moravia O
many O
of O
the O
Germans O
who O
are O
being O
evacuated O
from O
others O
sections O
of O
Europe B-LOC
, O
including O
some O
of O
those O
who O
are O
leaving O
the O
country O
near O
the O
German B-LOC
- O
Frenche B-LOC
French O
war O
zone O
. O

If O
these O
rumors O
are O
warranted O
, O
it O
may O
well O
be O
the O
plan O
to O
replace O
some O
of O
the O
Jewish O
populations O
in O
Bohemia B-LOC
and I-LOC
Moravia I-LOC
by O
German O
populations O
. O

In O
response O
to O
your O
letter O
of O
22 O
December O
, O
in O
which O
you O
request O
the O
Consulate O
General O
to O
search O
for O
your O
sister O
, O
Miss O
Anna B-PERS
Wimmer I-PERS
, O
assuming O
that O
you O
are O
a O
Danish B-LOC
citizen O
, O
we O
hereby O
inform O
you O
that O
it O
is O
true O
that O
Miss O
Wimmer O
left O
for O
Poland B-LOC
together O
with O
a O
Family B-PERS
Stark I-PERS
in O
October B-DATE
of I-DATE
1941 I-DATE
. O

At O
the O
Israeli B-ORG
Cultural I-ORG
Commemoration I-ORG
Centre I-ORG
, O
Vienna B-LOC
, O
I. O
, O
Seitenstettengasse O
2/4 O
, O
the O
Consulate O
General O
has O
learned O
that O
you O
can O
contact O
' O
An O
den O
Aeltesten O
der O
Juden O
, O
Lizmannstadt B-GHETTO
, I-GHETTO
Ghetto I-GHETTO
, O
Polen O
’ O
, O
which O
then O
probably O
through O
the O
Jewish O
organizations O
in O
question O
will O
be O
able O
to O
provide O
information O
about O
your O
sister O
's O
present O
address O
. O

The O
Consulate O
General O
shall O
add O
that O
no O
further O
action O
can O
be O
taken O
in O
this O
matter O
, O
unless O
special O
instructions O
are O
received O
from O
the O
Royal O
Commission O
. O

Ministry O
of O
Foreign O
Affairs O
in O
Copenhagen O
. O

P. O
G. O
V. O
Vice O
Consul O
, O
signed O
V.V. B-PERS
Broch I-PERS
Addressed O
to O
R. O
Ministry B-ORG
of I-ORG
Foreign I-ORG
Affairs I-ORG
, O
Rome B-LOC
M O
Mussolini B-PERS
Zagreb O
, O
12th B-DATE
May I-DATE
1942 I-DATE
, O
Year O
XX O
Re O
: O
The O
Jewish O
problem O
in O
Croatia B-LOC
A O
year O
after O
the O
start O
of O
the O
anti O
- O
Jewish O
campaign O
undertaken O
by O
the O
Ustashe O
Regime O
when O
they O
came O
to O
power O
, O
and O
now O
that O
the O
Croatian B-LOC
racial O
policy O
has O
been O
normalized O
within O
a O
framework O
of O
strict O
legality O
, O
assessing O
the O
situation O
may O
be O
of O
some O
interest O
. O

Croatian O
racism O
is O
based O
on O
and O
finds O
its O
justification O
in O
paragraph O
XI O
of O
the O
Ustashe O
Principles O
of O
1933 O
that O
for O
the O
first O
time O
mentions O
Croatian O
blood O
. O

From O
this O
source O
derives O
the O
law O
- O
decree O
of O
30th B-DATE
April I-DATE
1941 I-DATE
on O
the O
Aryan O
race O
, O
the O
fundamental O
text O
of O
Croatian B-LOC
racism O
. O

According O
to O
that O
law O
, O
all O
persons O
are O
considered O
Jewish O
: O
l O
) O
if O
they O
have O
at O
least O
three O
ancestors O
in O
the O
second O
degree O
who O
belong O
to O
the O
Jewish O
race O
; O
2 O
) O
if O
they O
have O
two O
ancestors O
of O
the O
Jewish O
race O
, O
namely O
in O
the O
following O
instances O
: O
a O
) O
if O
on O
the O
date O
of O
the O
10th B-DATE
April I-DATE
1941 I-DATE
they O
belonged O
to O
the O
Jewish O
religion O
or O
if O
they O
later O
converted O
to O
that O
religion O
, O
b O
) O
if O
they O
have O
a O
spouse O
who O
is O
considered O
Jewish O
, O
c O
) O
if O
after O
the O
present O
decree O
has O
come O
into O
force O
they O
have O
entered O
into O
matrimony O
with O
a O
person O
having O
two O
or O
more O
ancestors O
in O
the O
second O
degree O
belonging O
to O
the O
Jewish O
race O
, O
also O
the O
children O
issued O
from O
such O
a O
marriage O
, O
d O
) O
if O
they O
are O
the O
illegitimate O
children O
of O
a O
Jew O
, O
3 O
) O
if O
they O
were O
born O
outside O
the O
territory O
of O
the O
Independent O
State O
of O
Croatia B-LOC
from O
parents O
who O
do O
not O
trace O
their O
origins O
to O
the O
Independent O
State O
of O
Croatia B-LOC
, O
if O
at O
the O
date O
of O
10th B-DATE
April I-DATE
1941 I-DATE
they O
belonged O
to O
the O
Jewish O
religion O
or O
if O
they O
have O
at O
least O
two O
ancestors O
in O
the O
second O
degree O
belonging O
to O
the O
Jewish O
race O
, O
or O
if O
they O
are O
considered O
Jews O
by O
the O
law O
of O
the O
country O
from O
where O
they O
originate O
. O

4 O
) O
if O
after O
the O
present O
decree O
came O
into O
force O
they O
enter O
into O
matrimony O
with O
a O
non O
- O
Aryan O
person O
. O

5 O
) O
if O
they O
are O
the O
illegitimate O
children O
of O
a O
Jewish O
woman O
. O

Persons O
belonging O
to O
the O
Jewish O
race O
do O
not O
enjoy O
citizenship O
rights O
and O
are O
therefore O
banned O
from O
taking O
part O
in O
economic O
, O
social O
, O
youth O
, O
sports O
and O
cultural O
activities O
and O
organizations O
of O
the O
Croatian O
People O
in O
general O
, O
and O
more O
particularly O
in O
literature O
, O
journalism O
, O
sculpture O
, O
music O
, O
theatre O
and O
cinema O
. O

The O
law O
- O
decree O
of O
30th B-DATE
April I-DATE
1941 I-DATE
must O
be O
considered O
together O
with O
the O
other O
decree O
instituting O
the O
Political O
Commission O
on O
Race O
, O
which O
delivers O
opinions O
and O
offers O
suggestions O
on O
all O
cases O
in O
which O
the O
racial O
status O
is O
in O
doubt O
, O
and O
with O
the O
other O
, O
On O
the O
Protection O
of O
Aryan O
Blood O
and O
the O
Honour O
of O
the O
Croatian O
People O
, O
which O
absolutely O
forbids O
marriage O
between O
Jews O
or O
persons O
not O
belonging O
to O
the O
Aryan O
race O
and O
persons O
of O
the O
Aryan O
race O
and O
punishes O
with O
great O
severity O
extramarital O
relations O
between O
the O
Jew O
or O
a O
person O
not O
of O
Aryan O
blood O
and O
female O
persons O
of O
Aryan O
origin O
. O

In O
addition O
to O
these O
legislative O
measures O
there O
is O
also O
a O
body O
of O
police O
regulations O
concerning O
Jews O
, O
the O
main O
being O
: O
Jews O
are O
banned O
from O
living O
in O
certain O
parts O
of O
town O
their O
personal O
property O
is O
confiscated O
without O
compensation O
they O
are O
forbidden O
to O
keep O
radios O
and O
telephones O
male O
Jews O
aged O
from O
16 O
to O
60 O
must O
have O
themselves O
entered O
in O
special O
registers O
they O
must O
all O
, O
irrespective O
of O
age O
and O
gender O
, O
wear O
a O
special O
badge O
on O
the O
chest O
and O
on O
the O
back O
they O
must O
observe O
a O
special O
curfew O
they O
are O
forbidden O
to O
loiter O
in O
the O
streets O
in O
the O
city O
centre O
, O
and O
may O
only O
pass O
through O
they O
are O
banned O
from O
entering O
public O
establishments O
, O
etc O
. O

Having O
thus O
determined O
the O
legal O
status O
of O
persons O
belonging O
to O
the O
Jewish O
race O
, O
it O
became O
necessary O
to O
settle O
all O
attendant O
economic O
matters O
. O

A O
first O
step O
was O
therefore O
to O
declare O
null O
and O
void O
all O
contracts O
entered O
into O
between O
Jews O
and O
between O
Jews O
and O
others O
in O
the O
60 O
days O
preceding O
the O
declaration O
of O
the O
Independent O
State O
of O
Croatia B-LOC
, O
if O
the O
value O
of O
the O
contract O
was O
over O
100,000 O
Dinars O
and O
if O
it O
had O
not O
been O
subsequently O
approved O
by O
the O
Ministry O
of O
Justice O
. O

Almost O
at O
the O
same O
time O
a O
law O
- O
decree O
was O
issued O
whereby O
all O
businesses O
that O
were O
entirely O
or O
partially O
owned O
by O
Jews O
as O
well O
as O
those O
in O
which O
one O
or O
more O
Jews O
were O
sitting O
on O
the O
Board O
of O
Directors O
or O
had O
managerial O
posts O
were O
considered O
Jewish O
. O

That O
same O
decree O
ordered O
Jews O
, O
persons O
of O
Aryan O
origin O
joined O
in O
matrimony O
with O
Jews O
, O
foreign O
Jews O
who O
were O
on O
Croatian O
territory O
as O
of O
5th B-DATE
June I-DATE
1941 I-DATE
and O
Jewish O
businesses O
to O
report O
their O
assets O
as O
well O
as O
all O
changes O
of O
ownership O
that O
had O
occurred O
after O
10th B-DATE
February I-DATE
1941 I-DATE
. O

With O
this O
decree O
any O
alienation O
of O
Jewish O
property O
, O
as O
well O
as O
the O
transfer O
of O
Jewish O
businesses O
, O
of O
stocks O
, O
of O
shares O
in O
consortia O
and O
other O
property O
rights O
was O
made O
impossible O
, O
since O
any O
contract O
of O
whatever O
kind O
required O
the O
approval O
of O
the O
Ministry B-ORG
of I-ORG
National I-ORG
Economy I-ORG
. O

Jewish O
businesses O
thus O
confiscated O
by O
the O
State O
might O
be O
managed O
by O
the O
State O
itself O
, O
or O
be O
either O
leased O
, O
sold O
or O
liquidated O
in O
favour O
of O
the O
Treasury O
. O

The O
final O
decision O
in O
all O
these O
cases O
lies O
with O
the O
Ministry B-ORG
of I-ORG
National I-ORG
Economy I-ORG
. O

Lastly O
, O
with O
the O
Decree O
of O
10th B-DATE
October I-DATE
1941 I-DATE
, O
the O
authority O
on O
all O
matters O
concerning O
the O
estates O
of O
individual O
Jews O
or O
of O
Jewish O
businesses O
has O
been O
assigned O
to O
the O
State O
Department O
for O
Reconstruction O
which O
may O
, O
with O
a O
discretionary O
decision O
that O
admits O
no O
recourse O
, O
nationalize O
the O
assets O
of O
any O
Jew O
as O
well O
as O
of O
any O
Jewish O
business O
and O
determine O
what O
compensation O
, O
if O
any O
, O
shall O
be O
paid O
and O
how O
. O

The O
estates O
thus O
acquired O
can O
be O
assigned O
to O
the O
Independent O
State O
of O
Croatia O
or O
to O
the O
State O
Department O
for O
Reconstruction O
. O

Recently O
this O
Department O
, O
as O
well O
as O
the O
Political O
Commission O
on O
Race O
, O
have O
been O
eliminated O
and O
all O
authority O
in O
matters O
concerning O
Jewish O
economic O
questions O
and O
the O
assessment O
of O
race O
has O
been O
transferred O
to O
the O
Ministry B-ORG
of I-ORG
Finance I-ORG
, O
Office O
for O
Nationalized O
Assets O
, O
and O
the O
Ministry O
of O
Interior O
Affairs O
respectively O
. O

The O
implementation O
of O
all O
these O
measures O
has O
not O
, O
in O
truth O
, O
been O
very O
easy O
. O

Croatian O
public O
opinion O
, O
being O
insufficiently O
prepared O
for O
a O
racial O
campaign O
and O
still O
wary O
of O
the O
new O
Regime O
, O
but O
most O
of O
all O
shaken O
by O
a O
string O
of O
illegal O
acts O
carried O
out O
by O
unscrupulous O
Ustashe O
officials O
, O
had O
a O
rather O
negative O
reaction O
against O
these O
anti O
- O
Jewish O
measures O
and O
watched O
the O
course O
of O
events O
with O
great O
scepticism O
. O

From O
a O
technical O
point O
of O
view O
, O
moreover O
, O
the O
State O
Department O
for O
Reconstruction O
, O
which O
ought O
to O
have O
been O
the O
buttress O
of O
the O
entire O
system O
, O
and O
whose O
task O
it O
was O
basically O
to O
centralize O
and O
draw O
up O
an O
inventory O
of O
all O
Jewish O
property O
, O
proved O
decidedly O
inferior O
to O
the O
task O
they O
had O
been O
entrusted O
with O
, O
both O
because O
their O
offices O
were O
disorganized O
and O
because O
its O
officials O
had O
absolutely O
no O
experience O
in O
such O
matters O
. O

This O
state O
of O
affairs O
was O
taken O
advantage O
of O
by O
elements O
of O
the O
German O
ethnic O
group O
in O
Croatia B-LOC
who O
, O
through O
their O
financial O
organizations O
, O
were O
able O
to O
acquire O
legally O
the O
main O
formerly O
Jewish O
businesses O
. O

Lastly O
, O
as O
to O
the O
present O
situation O
of O
Croats O
who O
own O
formerly O
Jewish O
property O
, O
it O
must O
be O
pointed O
out O
that O
they O
have O
acquired O
it O
in O
many O
different O
ways O
but O
mainly O
through O
a O
system O
of O
fictitious O
sales O
carried O
out O
for O
the O
benefit O
of O
persons O
appointed O
by O
the O
State O
to O
the O
task O
of O
managing O
said O
property O
. O

Of O
the O
40,000 O
Jews O
who O
, O
it O
has O
been O
estimated O
, O
were O
living O
in O
Croatian O
territory O
, O
only O
approx O
. O

6,000 O
are O
left O
, O
almost O
all O
interned O
in O
concentration O
camps O
or O
assigned O
to O
farm O
work O
or O
to O
land O
reclamation O
. O

Of O
the O
rest O
, O
some O
have O
managed O
to O
emigrate O
and O
some O
must O
be O
considered O
missing O
. O

The O
Jewish O
problem O
can O
therefore O
be O
considered O
virtually O
solved O
in O
the O
Independent O
State O
of O
Croatia O
; O
a O
few O
issues O
still O
remain O
pending O
, O
such O
for O
instance O
as O
mixed O
marriages O
, O
but O
they O
too O
will O
soon O
be O
dealt O
with O
and O
settled O
. O

Giustiniani B-PERS
Jewish O
Religious O
Community O
Karlovy B-LOC
Vary I-LOC
Karlovy B-LOC
Vary I-LOC
, O
December B-DATE
17th I-DATE
, I-DATE
1945 I-DATE
428/45 O
Tit O
. O

To O
the O
Council O
of O
Jewish O
Communities O
, O
Prague B-LOC
V. O
Maislova B-LOC
18 O
We O
are O
sending O
you O
an O
appendix O
that O
contains O
a O
carbon O
copy O
of O
a O
record O
that O
we O
have O
sent O
to O
the O
National O
Security O
Directorate O
and O
to O
the O
Investigative O
Commission O
. O

Kindly O
make O
note O
of O
it O
. O

1 O
. O

Appendix O
With O
all O
due O
respect O
Karlovy B-LOC
Vary I-LOC
, O
on O
13 B-DATE
. I-DATE
XII I-DATE
. O

Record O
Today O
, O
Mrs O
. O

Edita B-PERS
Stützová I-PERS
, O
née O
Lewinsohnová B-PERS
, O
born O
12 B-DATE
. I-DATE
II I-DATE
. I-DATE
1911 I-DATE
in O
Karlovy B-LOC
Vary I-LOC
, O
residing O
in O
Karlovy B-LOC
Vary I-LOC
, O
Lesní O
no O
. O

6 O
, O
stopped O
by O
our O
office O
and O
made O
the O
following O
statement O
: O
On O
November B-DATE
10th I-DATE
, I-DATE
1938 I-DATE
, O
at O
2 O
o’clock O
in O
the O
afternoon O
, O
the O
removal O
of O
all O
the O
Jews O
from O
Karlovy B-LOC
Vary I-LOC
began O
. O

Members O
of O
the O
former O
SDP B-ORG
organization O
, O
relying O
on O
apartment O
lists O
, O
barged O
into O
all O
of O
the O
apartments O
in O
which O
Jews O
lived O
and O
broke O
into O
the O
Jewish O
old O
people O
's O
home O
. O

The O
Jews O
were O
violently O
dragged O
from O
the O
old O
people O
's O
home O
and O
from O
their O
apartments O
and O
taken O
to O
the O
Střelnice O
hotel O
. O

After O
an O
hour O
- O
long O
wait O
, O
the O
Jews O
were O
loaded O
into O
vehicles O
and O
driven O
to O
the O
synagogue O
on O
Sadová B-LOC
Street I-LOC
, O
and O
were O
present O
when O
it O
was O
set O
on O
fire O
. O

After O
it O
burned O
down O
, O
the O
Jews O
were O
taken O
to O
the O
headquarters O
of O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
and O
then O
to O
the O
Regional O
Court O
, O
where O
they O
remained O
for O
6 O
weeks O
. O

They O
were O
then O
brought O
to O
the O
concentration O
camp O
in O
Olšová B-LOC
Vrata B-LOC
. O

After O
6 O
weeks O
, O
I O
was O
released O
from O
custody O
in O
the O
Regional O
Court O
in O
Karlovy B-LOC
Vary I-LOC
, O
where O
I O
was O
held O
because O
I O
lived O
in O
a O
mixed O
marriage O
. O

However O
, O
my O
father O
Vítězslav B-PERS
Lewinsohn I-PERS
and O
all O
of O
my O
relatives O
were O
taken O
to O
the O
previously O
mentioned O
concentration O
camp O
. O

Since O
I O
went O
to O
see O
my O
father O
at O
the O
camp O
every O
day O
and O
brought O
him O
food O
, O
the O
conditions O
there O
were O
well O
known O
to O
me O
. O

The O
following O
was O
taken O
away O
from O
the O
Jews O
: O
all O
of O
their O
money O
, O
jewelry O
, O
and O
bankbooks O
. O

The O
executive O
body O
in O
charge O
was O
: O
A O
German B-LOC
, O
Rödelbach B-PERS
, O
a O
tailor O
residing O
in O
Karlovy B-LOC
Vary I-LOC
on O
Londýnská B-LOC
Street I-LOC
in O
the O
Augarten O
house O
, O
which O
is O
currently O
located O
in O
the O
scrapyard O
in O
Nová B-LOC
Role B-LOC
. O

When O
the O
Jews O
were O
dragged O
away O
from O
the O
old O
people O
's O
home O
, O
they O
weren’t O
allowed O
to O
take O
anything O
with O
them O
, O
not O
even O
a O
coat O
, O
and O
they O
left O
behind O
all O
of O
their O
possessions O
. O

After O
they O
left O
, O
led O
by O
the O
above O
- O
mentioned O
Rödelbach B-PERS
, O
the O
old O
people O
's O
home O
was O
looted O
and O
everything O
in O
it O
was O
destroyed O
or O
stolen O
. O

The O
identity O
of O
the O
other O
perpetrators O
who O
took O
part O
in O
this O
looting O
is O
not O
known O
to O
me O
. O

I O
only O
know O
that O
the O
administrator O
of O
the O
concentration O
camp O
in O
Olšová B-LOC
Vrata B-LOC
was O
a O
German B-LOC
woman O
named O
Lüftnerová B-PERS
, O
who O
still O
lives O
in O
Karlovy B-LOC
Vary I-LOC
and O
could O
certainly O
provide O
more O
information O
about O
the O
conditions O
in O
the O
camp O
. O

I O
hereby O
swear O
that O
everything O
in O
this O
statement O
is O
true O
and O
I O
am O
willing O
to O
provide O
more O
details O
if O
need O
be O
to O
the O
best O
of O
my O
knowledge O
. O

Signature O
: O
Edita B-PERS
Stützová I-PERS
m. O
p. O
Present O
during O
the O
writing O
of O
this O
statement O
: O
Glattstein B-PERS
Ludvík I-PERS
, O
JRC O
clerk O
Klaubr B-PERS
Valtr I-PERS
, O
board O
member O
of O
the O
JRC O
On O
behalf O
of O
the O
Documentation O
Campaign O
: O
Dr O
. O

Weinberger B-PERS
On O
behalf O
of O
the O
archive O
: O
Tressler B-PERS
Transcription O
: O
R. B-PERS
Brammerová I-PERS
Prague B-LOC
, O
1 B-DATE
. I-DATE
II I-DATE
. I-DATE
1946 I-DATE
„ O
Reports O
received O
from O
Sofia B-LOC
on O
November B-DATE
13 I-DATE
, I-DATE
1942 I-DATE
, O
indicate O
that O
this O
law O
is O
being O
rigorously O
enforced O
. O

Previous O
reports O
that O
there O
was O
some O
lenity O
in O
the O
enforcement O
of O
the O
law O
applied O
only O
to O
a O
small O
number O
of O
Christian O
Jews O
with O
regard O
to O
wearing O
the O
Star O
of O
David O
. O

Also O
some O
postponement O
was O
found O
necessary O
due O
to O
the O
physical O
impossibility O
of O
moving O
so O
many O
Jews O
into O
the O
ghetto O
or O
deporting O
them O
at O
one O
time O
. O

A O
prominent O
Jewish O
surgeon O
arrived O
in O
Istanbul B-LOC
from O
Sofia B-LOC
on O
November B-DATE
12 I-DATE
after O
having O
been O
deprived O
of O
his O
right O
to O
practice O
his O
profession O
. O

He O
owned O
and O
operated O
a O
hospital O
and O
clinic O
, O
which O
is O
forbidden O
to O
Jews O
in O
accordance O
with O
Article O
33 O
of O
the O
Law O
. O

All O
his O
property O
was O
taken O
away O
from O
him O
. O

Actually O
this O
man O
is O
a O
Catholic O
and O
has O
been O
such O
for O
thirty O
- O
five O
years O
. O

He O
declared O
that O
the O
reason O
for O
his O
severe O
treatment O
is O
the O
jealousy O
of O
Bulgarian O
surgeons O
and O
doctors O
who O
take O
this O
means O
of O
ridding O
themselves O
of O
competition O
. O

As O
has O
already O
been O
mentioned O
several O
thousand O
Jews O
are O
now O
in O
the O
process O
of O
being O
deported O
from O
Sofia B-LOC
. O

Where O
they O
will O
be O
sent O
is O
not O
known O
. O

They O
are O
supposed O
to O
be O
deported O
to O
towns O
and O
villages O
in O
Bulgaria B-LOC
but O
some O
high O
placed O
persons O
believe O
many O
of O
them O
will O
be O
deported O
to O
Poland B-LOC
. O

Some O
think O
they O
will O
be O
put O
in O
concentration O
camps O
inside O
of O
Bulgaria B-LOC
where O
many O
will O
eventually O
die O
of O
disease O
and O
starvation O
. O

Others O
, O
including O
the O
surgeon O
referred O
to O
above O
, O
think O
that O
a O
large O
proportion O
of O
them O
will O
be O
shot O
, O
as O
they O
have O
been O
in O
Belgrade B-LOC
and O
other O
cities O
. O

In O
any O
case O
, O
the O
content O
of O
the O
law O
, O
together O
with O
the O
severity O
with O
which O
it O
is O
being O
enforced O
show O
that O
its O
purpose O
is O
the O
complete O
destruction O
of O
the O
Jewish O
community O
in O
Sofia B-LOC
. O

“ O
From O
: O
Consul O
Toyohara B-PERS
Yukio I-PERS
( O
Manzhouli B-LOC
) O
To O
: O
Ambassador O
Umezu B-PERS
Yoshijirō I-PERS
( O
Shinkyō B-LOC
) O
CC O
: O
MOFA O
Tokyo O
Re O
: O
Situation O
of O
Persecution O
of O
Jews O
in O
Germany B-LOC
Information O
gathered O
by O
the O
Foreign O
Affairs O
Section O
here O
for O
your O
reference O
. O

Due O
to O
the O
outbreak O
of O
second O
great O
war O
in O
Europe O
the O
persecution O
of O
Jews O
in O
Germany B-LOC
has O
become O
intensified O
recently O
. O

At O
last O
the O
Jews O
feel O
their O
living O
to O
be O
under O
threat O
and O
have O
no O
choice O
but O
to O
seek O
refuge O
abroad O
. O

Main O
testimonies O
are O
as O
follows O
( O
told O
by O
a O
German O
named O
Peistein O
bound O
for O
Tokyo B-LOC
) O
At O
the O
personal O
level O
, O
the O
persecution O
is O
even O
more O
severe O
. O

Association O
with O
Germans O
is O
strictly O
forbidden O
, O
and O
even O
kids O
are O
not O
allowed O
to O
play O
with O
German O
kids O
. O

Although O
in O
legal O
terms O
we O
are O
not O
expelled O
from O
the O
country O
, O
the O
method O
used O
goes O
against O
humanity O
and O
arouses O
( O
uncontrollable O
) O
anger O
. O

( O
told O
by O
a O
Jewish O
merchant O
named O
Frinkle B-PERS
bound O
for O
Shanghai B-LOC
) O
Given O
the O
situation O
described O
above O
, O
there O
is O
a O
need O
to O
closely O
monitor O
the O
movement O
of O
Jews O
in O
transit O
through O
our O
city O
. O

Statement O
written O
with O
Valerie B-PERS
Straussová I-PERS
, O
née O
Kantorová B-PERS
, O
born O
25 B-DATE
. I-DATE
6 I-DATE
. I-DATE
1907 I-DATE
, O
former O
prisoner O
of O
the O
Theresienstadt B-GHETTO
, O
Auschwitz B-CAMP
, O
Schlesiersee B-CAMP
concentration O
camps O
, O
currently O
residing O
in O
Prague B-LOC
XII O
. O

, O
on O
Horní B-LOC
stromka I-LOC
5 I-LOC
. O

I O
, O
the O
undersigned O
Valerie B-PERS
Straussová I-PERS
, I-PERS
née O
Kantorová B-PERS
, O
born O
25 B-DATE
. I-DATE
6 I-DATE
. I-DATE
1907 I-DATE
in O
Vienna B-LOC
, O
daughter O
of O
Evžen B-PERS
and O
Emilie B-PERS
Kantorovi I-PERS
, O
citizen O
of O
Czechoslovakia B-LOC
, O
residing O
in O
Prague B-LOC
XII O
, O
on O
Horní B-LOC
stromka I-LOC
5 I-LOC
, O
am O
giving O
, O
after O
my O
return O
on O
July B-DATE
13th I-DATE
, I-DATE
1945 I-DATE
, O
from O
various O
concentration O
camps O
, O
this O
true O
and O
faithful O
account O
of O
my O
experiences O
. O

I O
swear O
on O
my O
honor O
that O
I O
have O
neither O
invented O
nor O
exaggerated O
the O
statement O
that O
I O
am O
about O
to O
give O
. O

On O
February B-DATE
12th I-DATE
, I-DATE
1942 I-DATE
, O
I O
was O
transported O
to O
the O
ghetto O
in O
Theresienstadt B-GHETTO
, O
where O
I O
remained O
until O
October B-DATE
4th I-DATE
, I-DATE
1944 I-DATE
. O

In O
Theresienstadt B-GHETTO
, O
I O
worked O
in O
a O
haberdasher O
's O
workshop O
, O
as O
a O
cleaning O
lady O
in O
the O
SS O
command O
, O
as O
a O
typist O
in O
the O
hospital O
, O
and O
I O
spent O
two O
months O
doing O
forest O
work O
in O
Křivoklát B-LOC
. O

My O
husband O
worked O
in O
Theresienstadt B-GHETTO
as O
a O
musician O
in O
a O
coffeehouse O
. O

On O
September B-DATE
28th I-DATE
, I-DATE
1944 I-DATE
, O
he O
left O
Theresienstadt B-GHETTO
on O
a O
transport O
. O

We O
were O
told O
that O
the O
men O
were O
going O
one O
hour O
away O
from O
Theresienstadt B-GHETTO
to O
work O
in O
Germany B-LOC
. O

A O
week O
later O
, O
as O
his O
wife O
, O
I O
was O
placed O
on O
a O
transport O
and O
I O
left O
thinking O
that O
I O
would O
be O
reunited O
with O
him O
. O

All O
of O
the O
women O
pushed O
their O
way O
onto O
the O
train O
and O
each O
of O
us O
was O
happy O
to O
have O
been O
selected O
. O

Many O
children O
also O
went O
with O
us O
. O

When O
we O
approached O
Dresden B-LOC
, O
we O
prepared O
to O
disembark O
. O

How O
great O
was O
our O
disappointment O
when O
we O
rode O
through O
Dresden B-LOC
without O
stopping O
and O
saw O
that O
we O
were O
going O
east O
. O

Instead O
of O
riding O
for O
an O
hour O
, O
we O
rode O
for O
twenty O
- O
four O
until O
we O
reached O
the O
Auschwitz B-CAMP
train O
station O
. O

Here O
, O
we O
had O
to O
get O
off O
the O
train O
without O
our O
luggage O
and O
the O
selection O
process O
took O
place O
right O
in O
front O
of O
the O
train O
: O
women O
with O
children O
and O
the O
elderly O
on O
the O
right O
, O
us O
childless O
women O
on O
the O
left O
. O

At O
the O
time O
, O
we O
still O
didn’t O
know O
what O
being O
sent O
to O
the O
right O
meant O
( O
the O
gas O
chamber O
) O
. O

We O
were O
taken O
to O
the O
washrooms O
, O
where O
everything O
we O
had O
on O
was O
taken O
away O
, O
our O
heads O
were O
shaved O
, O
we O
were O
led O
to O
the O
showers O
, O
and O
clothed O
in O
old O
rags O
. O

And O
then O
the O
familiar O
, O
nerve O
- O
wrenching O
life O
in O
the O
concentration O
camp O
began O
. O

After O
5 O
days O
, O
we O
went O
through O
another O
selection O
and O
were O
taken O
to O
the O
train O
. O

We O
were O
given O
better O
clothing O
and O
sent O
to O
work O
in O
Germany B-LOC
. O

We O
rode O
until O
we O
reached O
the O
Schlesiersee B-LOC
train O
station O
in O
northeast O
Silesia B-LOC
, O
not O
far O
from O
the O
Polish B-LOC
border O
. O

From O
the O
station O
we O
walked O
for O
about O
2 O
hours O
. O

They O
put O
us O
up O
in O
two O
farms O
, O
1,000 O
women O
in O
each O
building O
. O

They O
housed O
us O
in O
two O
large O
barns O
for O
storing O
hay O
. O

The O
next O
morning O
, O
we O
were O
given O
shovels O
and O
spades O
and O
we O
dug O
3 O
½ O
meters O
deep O
anti O
- O
tank O
trenches O
. O

It O
was O
extremely O
hard O
work O
for O
us O
women O
and O
there O
was O
very O
little O
food O
, O
and O
so O
we O
quickly O
lost O
a O
lot O
of O
weight O
. O

At O
the O
end O
of O
October B-DATE
, O
one O
of O
the O
girls O
bumped O
into O
my O
leg O
with O
a O
wheelbarrow O
. O

I O
had O
a O
small O
scrape O
that O
I O
didn’t O
think O
was O
serious O
. O

Several O
days O
later O
, O
my O
leg O
started O
hurting O
, O
swelled O
up O
, O
and O
developed O
a O
small O
phlegmon O
. O

It O
gradually O
got O
worse O
and O
the O
doctor O
had O
to O
operate O
on O
me O
in O
the O
barn O
. O

After O
the O
incision O
, O
my O
high O
fever O
came O
down O
, O
but O
I O
couldn’t O
stand O
on O
my O
leg O
, O
and O
so O
for O
three O
weeks O
I O
crawled O
around O
on O
all O
fours O
. O

As O
soon O
as O
I O
got O
better O
, O
I O
was O
sent O
to O
perform O
domestic O
labor O
. O

I O
peeled O
potatoes O
. O

I O
would O
get O
up O
at O
4 O
in O
the O
morning O
and O
peeled O
potatoes O
until O
the O
evening O
. O

Two O
days O
later O
, O
I O
developed O
a O
fever O
of O
40 O
degrees O
, O
shooting O
pain O
on O
the O
right O
side O
of O
my O
chest O
, O
and O
I O
started O
coughing O
. O

The O
doctor O
diagnosed O
me O
with O
pneumonia O
. O

Since O
wrapping O
my O
chest O
would O
have O
been O
impossible O
in O
the O
cold O
barn O
and O
there O
was O
no O
medicine O
in O
the O
camp O
, O
I O
was O
left O
to O
my O
own O
fate O
. O

I O
was O
not O
allowed O
to O
lie O
down O
, O
and O
so O
I O
sat O
, O
leaning O
against O
the O
icy O
wall O
of O
the O
stable O
wearing O
only O
my O
clothes O
( O
coats O
and O
shoes O
were O
taken O
away O
from O
the O
sick O
and O
given O
to O
the O
healthy O
) O
. O

I O
was O
covered O
with O
a O
camp O
- O
issued O
blanket O
. O

Ten O
days O
later O
, O
my O
pneumonia O
disappeared O
as O
if O
by O
a O
miracle O
, O
but O
the O
injury O
on O
my O
leg O
got O
worse O
and O
started O
to O
fester O
. O

Around O
January B-DATE
10th I-DATE
, O
the O
sick O
were O
moved O
into O
quickly O
built O
wooden O
barracks O
. O

Before O
we O
moved O
, O
we O
had O
to O
hand O
over O
everything O
we O
wore O
and O
wash O
ourselves O
so O
that O
we O
wouldn’t O
bring O
lice O
, O
which O
we O
were O
completely O
infested O
with O
, O
into O
the O
new O
building O
. O

We O
entered O
the O
building O
completely O
naked O
and O
they O
promised O
to O
disinfect O
our O
clothes O
and O
give O
them O
back O
to O
us O
. O

Washing O
, O
however O
, O
didn’t O
rid O
us O
of O
lice O
. O

Our O
situation O
was O
much O
improved O
in O
the O
barracks O
. O

We O
slept O
in O
bunk O
beds O
on O
straw O
mattresses O
, O
two O
to O
a O
bed O
and O
covered O
by O
a O
single O
blanket O
. O

We O
were O
so O
cold O
. O

On O
January B-DATE
22nd I-DATE
, O
we O
heard O
that O
the O
battlefront O
was O
only O
20 O
km O
away O
from O
us O
. O

There O
were O
rumors O
that O
we O
would O
be O
evacuated O
. O

Sick O
women O
were O
to O
remain O
in O
the O
camp O
. O

We O
were O
happy O
and O
hoped O
that O
the O
Russians B-LOC
would O
liberate O
us O
soon O
. O

But O
we O
rejoiced O
too O
soon O
. O

At O
about O
7 O
o’clock O
in O
the O
evening O
, O
a O
German B-LOC
commander O
entered O
and O
ordered O
everyone O
to O
evacuate O
, O
including O
the O
seriously O
ill O
. O

The O
situation O
was O
desperate O
, O
because O
all O
of O
us O
were O
lying O
in O
bed O
completely O
naked O
. O

We O
started O
to O
panic O
and O
each O
of O
us O
tried O
to O
find O
something O
to O
wear O
. O

I O
begged O
our O
superior O
for O
some O
clothes O
, O
but O
it O
was O
all O
in O
vain O
. O

At O
the O
last O
minute O
, O
one O
of O
the O
nurses O
gave O
me O
a O
summer O
dress O
that O
I O
threw O
over O
my O
naked O
body O
. O

I O
wound O
strips O
ripped O
from O
a O
blanket O
around O
my O
legs O
, O
even O
though O
this O
was O
sabotage O
, O
and O
I O
managed O
to O
snag O
2 O
blankets O
. O

I O
tied O
one O
around O
my O
waist O
like O
a O
skirt O
, O
and O
wrapped O
the O
other O
around O
my O
shoulders O
. O

I O
was O
given O
a O
pair O
of O
clogs O
. O

Many O
women O
were O
barefoot O
and O
their O
feet O
became O
frostbitten O
. O

When O
we O
walked O
out O
into O
the O
courtyard O
we O
could O
barely O
stand O
up O
. O

It O
was O
freezing O
and O
there O
was O
a O
lot O
of O
snow O
. O

For O
our O
journey O
, O
they O
gave O
us O
a O
loaf O
of O
bread O
that O
was O
supposed O
to O
last O
us O
three O
days O
. O

Then O
they O
filled O
us O
into O
lines O
of O
5 O
and O
the O
march O
began O
. O

I O
wasn’t O
able O
to O
walk O
because O
I O
had O
been O
sick O
in O
bed O
for O
almost O
10 O
weeks O
, O
but O
the O
Schupo B-ORG
kept O
forcing O
me O
and O
threatening O
to O
shoot O
me O
. O

And O
so O
we O
marched O
all O
night O
until O
the O
afternoon O
of O
the O
next O
day O
. O

On O
the O
way O
, O
many O
of O
us O
died O
or O
froze O
to O
death O
. O

At O
3 O
o’clock O
the O
next O
day O
we O
came O
to O
a O
forest O
that O
was O
about O
4 O
km O
before O
Ostweide B-LOC
. O

The O
commander O
ordered O
all O
of O
the O
sick O
to O
sit O
down O
. O

A O
vehicle O
would O
be O
coming O
from O
Ostweide B-LOC
to O
pick O
them O
up O
soon O
. O

The O
healthy O
continued O
marching O
. O

I O
sat O
down O
on O
the O
edge O
of O
the O
forest O
by O
a O
ditch O
and O
was O
happy O
that O
I O
didn’t O
have O
to O
keep O
going O
. O

I O
believed O
that O
the O
vehicle O
would O
arrive O
, O
although O
others O
claimed O
that O
something O
else O
would O
happen O
. O

There O
were O
about O
40 O
of O
us O
here O
, O
in O
addition O
to O
the O
doctor O
, O
who O
took O
down O
our O
names O
. O

There O
were O
also O
2 O
corpses O
. O

About O
60 O
m O
from O
the O
edge O
of O
the O
forest O
, O
the O
Schupo B-ORG
were O
digging O
a O
hole O
. O

I O
thought O
that O
it O
was O
for O
our O
2 O
corpses O
. O

When O
it O
got O
dark O
and O
we O
had O
given O
up O
all O
hope O
that O
the O
vehicle O
would O
come O
, O
2 O
Schupo B-ORG
came O
up O
to O
us O
, O
grabbed O
about O
six O
women O
and O
forced O
them O
toward O
the O
hole O
, O
shouting O
arbeiten O
– O
arbeiten O
. O

The O
women O
screamed O
and O
wanted O
to O
escape O
, O
but O
then O
we O
heard O
shots O
and O
then O
silence O
. O

Now O
we O
knew O
for O
sure O
that O
there O
was O
no O
vehicle O
and O
what O
truly O
awaited O
us O
. O

After O
a O
while O
, O
the O
Schupo B-ORG
came O
for O
the O
next O
6 O
victims O
. O

I O
was O
part O
of O
the O
3rd O
group O
. O

I O
was O
reconciled O
with O
my O
fate O
and O
was O
absolutely O
calm O
. O

A O
Schupo B-ORG
came O
up O
to O
me O
, O
grabbed O
me O
by O
the O
shoulder O
, O
and O
shouted O
: O
Komm O
. O

I O
said O
to O
him O
: O
Just O
a O
moment O
, O
I’ll O
just O
give O
my O
bread O
and O
blanket O
to O
the O
doctor O
to O
hand O
out O
to O
the O
others O
since O
I O
won’t O
be O
needing O
them O
anymore O
. O

He O
answered O
, O
seeing O
that O
I O
was O
totally O
calm O
: O
You O
may O
. O

And O
so O
I O
went O
up O
to O
the O
doctor O
and O
thanked O
her O
for O
her O
work O
and O
for O
treating O
me O
and O
gave O
her O
the O
rest O
of O
my O
bread O
and O
the O
blanket O
. O

I O
then O
walked O
peacefully O
with O
my O
murderer O
up O
to O
the O
hole O
. O

About O
13 O
corpses O
lay O
in O
it O
. O

He O
made O
several O
women O
sit O
down O
on O
the O
mound O
of O
earth O
dug O
from O
the O
hole O
, O
and O
ordered O
me O
and O
two O
other O
women O
to O
turn O
our O
backs O
to O
him O
. O

First O
, O
he O
shot O
the O
women O
by O
the O
hole O
and O
then O
it O
was O
our O
turn O
. O

I O
stood O
in O
the O
middle O
. O

It O
was O
a O
beautiful O
moonlit O
night O
. O

I O
gazed O
up O
at O
the O
moon O
and O
thought O
to O
myself O
: O
what O
a O
pity O
that O
I O
have O
to O
die O
and O
nobody O
will O
ever O
know O
what O
happened O
here O
. O

It O
was O
at O
this O
moment O
that O
I O
finally O
understood O
how O
beautiful O
it O
is O
to O
be O
alive O
, O
even O
after O
all O
that O
we’d O
been O
through O
. O

And O
then O
a O
shot O
rang O
out O
and O
the O
woman O
to O
my O
right O
fell O
to O
the O
ground O
. O

And O
then O
a O
second O
shot O
and O
I O
felt O
a O
sharp O
pain O
on O
the O
left O
side O
of O
my O
neck O
. O

I O
collapsed O
onto O
the O
ground O
, O
but O
never O
lost O
consciousness O
. O

It O
felt O
strange O
to O
not O
be O
dead O
yet O
, O
but O
waiting O
for O
death O
. O

I O
soon O
realized O
that O
the O
shot O
had O
not O
been O
fatal O
. O

I O
felt O
the O
blood O
flowing O
from O
my O
wound O
and O
I O
quickly O
placed O
a O
hand O
on O
my O
neck O
. O

It O
all O
happened O
within O
an O
instant O
. O

In O
the O
meantime O
, O
the O
woman O
on O
my O
left O
side O
was O
shot O
. O

I O
began O
to O
be O
afraid O
that O
I O
would O
be O
buried O
alive O
. O

I O
heard O
the O
conversation O
between O
two O
of O
the O
Schupo B-ORG
who O
had O
shot O
us O
and O
were O
now O
standing O
right O
behind O
me O
. O

They O
had O
a O
very O
interesting O
conversation O
. O

One O
wanted O
to O
throw O
us O
into O
the O
hole O
right O
away O
, O
and O
the O
second O
said O
that O
they O
needed O
to O
wait O
until O
all O
of O
us O
were O
dead O
, O
and O
then O
the O
doctor O
would O
strip O
us O
and O
throw O
us O
into O
the O
hole O
. O

The O
seriously O
ill O
ones O
, O
who O
were O
brought O
here O
on O
wheelbarrows O
, O
those O
we’ll O
beat O
to O
death O
with O
our O
rifle O
butts O
, O
said O
one O
of O
the O
Schupo B-ORG
. O

When O
their O
conversation O
was O
over O
, O
they O
walked O
away O
from O
the O
hole O
to O
bring O
more O
victims O
from O
the O
edge O
of O
the O
forest O
. O

Without O
thinking O
, O
I O
turned O
over O
and O
crawled O
away O
into O
the O
forest O
on O
all O
fours O
. O

I O
thought O
to O
myself O
that O
it O
’s O
better O
if O
they O
shoot O
me O
again O
if O
they O
find O
me O
than O
to O
be O
buried O
alive O
. O

The O
night O
was O
clear O
and O
we O
were O
in O
a O
forest O
with O
tall O
trees O
, O
and O
so O
there O
was O
nowhere O
for O
me O
to O
hide O
. O

I O
crawled O
a O
couple O
meters O
away O
from O
the O
hole O
and O
hid O
behind O
a O
tree O
. O

Now O
, O
I O
began O
to O
be O
upset O
. O

I O
saw O
the O
Schupo B-ORG
force O
more O
women O
toward O
the O
hole O
. O

I O
heard O
shots O
and O
realized O
that O
they O
didn’t O
know O
I O
was O
missing O
and O
weren’t O
even O
looking O
for O
me O
. O

I O
heard O
them O
finish O
their O
task O
, O
strip O
the O
women O
, O
throw O
them O
into O
the O
hole O
, O
and O
fill O
up O
the O
hole O
. O

I O
don’t O
know O
what O
happened O
to O
the O
doctor O
. O

Then O
I O
must O
have O
fallen O
asleep O
, O
because O
I O
didn’t O
see O
them O
walk O
away O
from O
the O
hole O
. O

I O
woke O
up O
and O
saw O
from O
a O
distance O
the O
Schupo B-ORG
walking O
down O
the O
road O
with O
a O
wheelbarrow O
likely O
loaded O
with O
clothes O
taken O
from O
the O
people O
who O
were O
shot O
. O

I O
knew O
that O
I O
was O
saved O
. O

I O
started O
walking O
away O
. O

I O
went O
around O
the O
hole O
and O
crossed O
the O
main O
road O
that O
goes O
from O
Schlesiersee B-LOC
to O
Ostweide B-LOC
. O

In O
the O
afternoon O
, O
I O
observed O
German B-LOC
tanks O
riding O
away O
from O
the O
forest O
on O
the O
other O
side O
of O
the O
road O
. O

I O
thought O
that O
the O
frontline O
must O
be O
there O
and O
that O
I O
would O
meet O
up O
with O
the O
Russians B-LOC
any O
minute O
. O

And O
so O
I O
headed O
out O
on O
this O
road O
. O

After O
walking O
for O
about O
10 O
minutes O
, O
I O
saw O
a O
large O
haystack O
on O
the O
side O
of O
the O
road O
. O

I O
crawled O
inside O
of O
it O
and O
soon O
fell O
asleep O
. O

I O
was O
exhausted O
. O

We O
had O
marched O
the O
whole O
previous O
night O
, O
my O
leg O
was O
badly O
hurting O
, O
and O
to O
top O
it O
off O
my O
new O
neck O
wound O
, O
which O
hurt O
a O
little O
the O
first O
day O
. O

I O
slept O
until O
the O
morning O
and O
then O
headed O
out O
again O
. O

I O
walked O
through O
beautiful O
forests O
, O
along O
tank O
tracks O
, O
and O
didn’t O
meet O
a O
soul O
. O

I O
was O
terribly O
tired O
, O
but O
I O
was O
afraid O
to O
sit O
down O
in O
the O
snow O
. O

I O
didn’t O
want O
to O
fall O
asleep O
and O
freeze O
to O
death O
. O

As O
the O
evening O
approached O
, O
I O
chanced O
upon O
a O
crumbling O
barn O
for O
hay O
, O
where O
I O
spent O
the O
night O
. O

In O
the O
morning O
, O
I O
walked O
on O
and O
around O
noon O
I O
finally O
entered O
a O
small O
village O
, O
utterly O
exhausted O
. O

I O
went O
into O
the O
first O
house O
and O
asked O
if O
they O
would O
allow O
me O
to O
rest O
here O
. O

I O
was O
delighted O
to O
hear O
that O
I O
was O
in O
Poland B-LOC
. O

They O
gave O
me O
food O
and O
the O
next O
day O
the O
mayor O
took O
care O
of O
me O
. O

We O
burned O
my O
clothes O
, O
which O
were O
soaked O
with O
blood O
, O
and O
they O
gave O
me O
warm O
clothing O
, O
a O
dress O
, O
and O
blankets O
. O

I O
was O
given O
a O
room O
in O
a O
house O
that O
the O
Germans B-LOC
had O
abandoned O
. O

Polish B-LOC
girls O
lit O
the O
fire O
in O
my O
room O
and O
brought O
me O
food O
. O

The O
village O
didn’t O
have O
a O
doctor O
. O

Every O
day O
, O
a O
nurse O
came O
to O
check O
up O
on O
me O
and O
changed O
the O
bandages O
on O
my O
leg O
and O
neck O
. O

I O
was O
in O
great O
pain O
and O
couldn’t O
sleep O
at O
night O
. O

Five O
days O
after O
my O
arrival O
in O
the O
village O
, O
i.e O
. O

a O
week O
after O
I O
was O
injured O
, O
the O
Russians B-LOC
came O
to O
the O
village O
and O
I O
was O
finally O
truly O
liberated O
. O

A O
week O
later O
, O
a O
Polish B-LOC
nurse O
took O
me O
to O
the O
hospital O
in O
Wolstein B-LOC
. O

Fourteen O
days O
after O
I O
was O
shot O
was O
the O
first O
time O
I O
received O
medical O
assistance O
. O

I O
felt O
much O
better O
in O
the O
hospital O
, O
I O
quickly O
recuperated O
, O
and O
my O
wounds O
healed O
up O
. O

On O
March B-DATE
18th I-DATE
, O
the O
Russians B-LOC
picked O
me O
up O
from O
the O
hospital O
and O
took O
me O
to O
Schwiebus B-LOC
, O
where O
I O
helped O
out O
in O
the O
hospital O
. O

I O
remained O
in O
the O
service O
of O
a O
Russian B-LOC
unit O
that O
rode O
out O
to O
assist O
the O
Russian B-ORG
Army B-ORG
in O
combat O
. O

After O
my O
military O
service O
, O
I O
was O
discharged O
from O
duty O
and O
taken O
to O
the O
repatriation O
committee O
in O
Prague B-LOC
in O
July B-DATE
. O

Once O
in O
Prague B-LOC
, O
I O
found O
out O
that O
neither O
my O
husband O
, O
nor O
my O
parents O
, O
and O
neither O
my O
sister O
nor O
her O
husband O
, O
had O
returned O
. O

Only O
my O
brother O
came O
back O
. O

Before O
I O
left O
for O
Theresienstadt B-GHETTO
, O
I O
worked O
in O
an O
insurance O
office O
, O
and O
I O
plan O
on O
working O
there O
again O
. O

I O
know O
the O
exact O
location O
where O
the O
40 O
women O
were O
executed O
, O
and O
I O
am O
willing O
to O
show O
it O
to O
the O
relevant O
authorities O
. O

Valerie B-PERS
Straussová I-PERS
In O
Prague B-LOC
on O
July B-DATE
23rd I-DATE
, I-DATE
1945 I-DATE
Statement O
accepted O
by O
: O
Berta B-PERS
Gerzonová I-PERS
Signature O
of O
witnesses O
: O
Marta B-PERS
Fischerová I-PERS
Dita B-PERS
Saxlová I-PERS
On O
behalf O
of O
the O
Documentation O
campaign O
: O
Scheck B-PERS
On O
behalf O
of O
the O
archive O
: O
Tresssler B-PERS
Re O
: O
Treatment O
of O
Jews O
As O
this O
Royal O
Legation O
reported O
in O
the O
telegram O
mentioned O
above O
, O
the O
transfer O
to O
Poland B-LOC
of O
the O
Jewish O
survivors O
left O
in O
Croatia B-LOC
is O
currently O
under O
way O
. O

The O
transfer O
is O
carried O
out O
with O
special O
trains O
provided O
by O
Croatian B-LOC
authorities O
, O
who O
, O
besides O
equipping O
the O
people O
who O
are O
leaving O
, O
are O
also O
required O
to O
pay O
the O
Government O
of O
the O
Reich O
30 O
Mark O
per O
person O
. O

( O
Initially O
the O
Reich O
had O
requested O
500 O
Mark O
) O
. O

The O
said O
measures O
have O
led O
to O
a O
démarche O
– O
as O
the O
Poglavnik B-PERS
himself O
has O
confirmed O
– O
by O
the O
Apostolic O
Delegate O
here O
, O
which O
brought O
no O
conclusive O
results O
. O

It O
seems O
, O
however O
, O
that O
the O
category O
formed O
by O
Aryans O
joined O
in O
matrimony O
to O
Jews O
will O
be O
left O
alone O
. O

The O
Minister O
of O
Germany O
here O
, O
in O
a O
conversation O
he O
had O
with O
the O
R. O
Minister O
about O
various O
issues O
, O
hinted O
at O
the O
advisability O
of O
starting O
to O
remove O
also O
the O
Jews O
who O
have O
sought O
shelter O
in O
the O
2nd O
zone O
occupied O
by O
Italian B-LOC
troops O
and O
asked O
how O
many O
there O
might O
be O
. O

He O
added O
that O
the O
larger O
groups O
, O
as O
far O
as O
he O
is O
was O
aware O
, O
ought O
to O
be O
in O
Mostar B-LOC
, O
in O
Ragusa B-LOC
[ I-LOC
Dubrovnik I-LOC
] I-LOC
and O
in O
Cirquenizza B-LOC
[ I-LOC
Crikvenica I-LOC
] I-LOC
. O

Lastly O
, O
he O
hinted O
at O
an O
official O
step O
that O
the O
Government O
of O
the O
Reich O
is O
about O
to O
make O
in O
order O
to O
request O
that O
these O
Jews O
, O
like O
the O
others O
in O
Croatia B-LOC
, O
be O
also O
sent O
to O
Poland B-LOC
. O

Giustiniani B-PERS
I O
have O
the O
honor O
to O
report O
that O
Ambassador O
Stoica B-PERS
, O
formerly O
Ambassador O
at O
Ankara B-LOC
and O
now O
Under O
Secretary O
of O
Propaganda O
, O
told O
me O
the O
other O
evening O
at O
dinner O
at O
my O
house O
in O
honor O
of O
himself O
and O
the O
representatives O
of O
the O
American B-LOC
newspapers O
, O
that O
his O
Government B-ORG
was O
going O
to O
do O
everything O
within O
its O
power O
to O
prevent O
anti O
- O
Jewish O
outbreaks O
, O
but O
that O
it O
greatly O
feared O
such O
outbreaks O
on O
the O
part O
of O
the O
Army O
as O
the O
latter O
was O
so O
incensed O
at O
the O
treatment O
meted O
out O
to O
it O
by O
the O
Jews O
in O
Bessarabia B-LOC
when O
it O
was O
withdrawing O
. O

I O
observed O
that O
for O
once O
Rumania B-LOC
had O
a O
good O
press O
in O
the O
outside O
world O
, O
where O
there O
was O
great O
sympathy O
because O
it O
had O
been O
set O
upon O
by O
a O
powerful O
nation O
of O
180,000,000 O
people O
, O
and O
that O
I O
thought O
it O
would O
be O
a O
great O
pity O
to O
sacrifice O
this O
for O
the O
sake O
of O
a O
Pogrom O
or O
two O
. O

On O
another O
recent O
occasion O
I O
had O
an O
opportunity O
informally O
to O
emphasize O
to O
Prime O
Minister O
Gigurtu B-PERS
that O
any O
internal O
disturbance O
, O
especially O
Jewish O
persecution O
, O
might O
easily O
be O
seized O
upon O
by O
Russia B-LOC
as O
an O
excuse O
for O
further O
action O
. O

[ O
... O
] O
The O
Gigurtu B-PERS
group O
maintains O
that O
to O
pass O
rigid O
laws O
against O
Jews O
at O
the O
present O
critical O
moment O
would O
seriously O
affect O
the O
economic O
structure O
of O
the O
State O
, O
as O
well O
as O
create O
a O
most O
unfortunate O
impression O
among O
nations O
abroad O
, O
particularly O
the O
United B-LOC
States I-LOC
. O

Some O
observers O
take O
the O
view O
that O
should O
there O
be O
no O
further O
pressure O
from O
Hungary B-LOC
and O
Bulgaria B-LOC
for O
territorial O
cession O
at O
present O
the O
moderate O
group O
will O
win O
its O
point O
and O
there O
will O
be O
no O
strong O
anti O
- O
Semitic O
reaction O
in O
Rumania B-LOC
; O
if O
, O
however O
, O
the O
Government O
is O
forced O
to O
cede O
more O
territory O
immediately O
, O
a O
cession O
for O
which O
public O
opinion O
has O
not O
yet O
been O
adequately O
prepared O
, O
the O
Iron B-ORG
Guard I-ORG
thesis O
will O
be O
more O
likely O
to O
win O
because O
the O
Government O
will O
find O
it O
necessary O
to O
resort O
to O
anti O
- O
Semitic O
agitation O
as O
a O
cloak O
and O
counter O
- O
irritant O
. O

In O
recent O
days O
a O
few O
mild O
anti O
- O
Jewish O
measures O
have O
been O
announced O
but O
nothing O
to O
suggest O
a O
really O
vicious O
program O
. O

[ O
... O
] O
I O
accordingly O
feel O
that O
no O
really O
strong O
Jewish O
persecutions O
are O
apt O
to O
eventuate O
in O
the O
near O
future O
except O
as O
they O
may O
arise O
out O
of O
new O
circumstances O
created O
by O
the O
evolution O
of O
international O
events O
or O
further O
dissatisfaction O
in O
the O
Army O
. O

But O
, O
as O
earlier O
despatches O
have O
already O
suggested O
, O
the O
lot O
of O
the O
Jews O
in O
Rumania B-LOC
has O
definitely O
worsened O
since O
the O
inauguration O
of O
the O
present B-ORG
regime I-ORG
three O
months O
ago O
. O

In O
the O
first O
place O
, O
the O
green O
- O
shirted O
Iron O
Guard O
is O
in O
power O
, O
and O
the O
Iron O
Guard O
is O
notoriously O
and O
avowedly O
an O
essentially O
anti O
- O
Semitic O
organization O
. O

In O
the O
second O
place O
, O
Rumania B-LOC
not O
only O
has O
come O
under O
the O
direct O
‘ O
influence O
’ O
of O
Nazi O
Germany O
but O
is O
now O
actually O
a O
member O
of O
the O
Axis O
and O
an O
adherent O
to O
the O
Tripartite O
Pact O
. O

And O
, O
thirdly O
, O
the O
country O
requires O
scape O
- O
goats O
for O
all O
the O
evils O
and O
misfortunes O
of O
the O
day O
, O
and O
finds O
that O
the O
Jews O
, O
along O
with O
former O
King B-PERS
Carol I-PERS
and O
the O
old O
politicians O
, O
serve O
admirably O
in O
this O
unhappy O
role O
. O

These O
considerations O
, O
plus O
an O
underlying O
sentiment O
of O
genuine O
anti O
- O
Semitism O
generally O
, O
provide O
sufficient O
reason O
and O
background O
for O
Jewish O
fears O
and O
sufferings O
in O
Rumania B-LOC
today O
. O

[ O
... O
] O
In O
recent O
weeks O
the O
Jewish O
plaint O
has O
not O
been O
one O
of O
lost O
positions O
, O
special O
taxes O
or O
discriminatory O
restrictions O
– O
that O
is O
an O
old O
story O
. O

Rather O
it O
has O
been O
one O
of O
deaths O
, O
torture O
, O
beatings O
, O
abductions O
, O
confiscation O
, O
robbery O
and O
violence O
in O
all O
forms O
. O

It O
is O
not O
an O
exaggeration O
to O
say O
that O
here O
today O
one O
sees O
the O
Jews O
with O
tears O
, O
hollow O
eyes O
and O
wringing O
hands O
. O

Many O
of O
them O
never O
go O
out O
; O
they O
keep O
to O
their O
homes O
for O
fear O
of O
meeting O
violence O
in O
the O
street O
. O

A O
few O
, O
who O
have O
reasons O
to O
fear O
they O
may O
be O
sought O
out O
, O
creep O
from O
friend O
to O
friend O
or O
house O
to O
house O
afraid O
to O
go O
to O
their O
own O
homes O
to O
sleep O
. O

Those O
of O
means O
endeavor O
frantically O
to O
dispose O
of O
their O
property O
, O
secure O
funds O
abroad O
and O
find O
a O
way O
to O
leave O
the O
country O
. O

Addressed O
to O
Royal O
Ministry B-ORG
of I-ORG
Foreign I-ORG
Affairs I-ORG
, O
Rome O
. O

Bratislava O
, O
9th O
April O
1942 O
, O
Year O
XX O
Re O
: O
Jewish O
question O
The O
coldness O
with O
which O
the O
Slovakian B-LOC
Catholic O
press O
has O
greeted O
the O
anti O
- O
Jewish O
action O
of O
Minister O
of O
Interior O
Mach B-PERS
is O
an O
indication O
of O
the O
mood O
of O
the O
Slovakian B-LOC
Catholic O
population O
which O
, O
particularly O
in O
the O
provinces O
, O
feels O
no O
ill O
will O
towards O
Jews O
and O
because O
of O
their O
meekness O
and O
religious O
upbringing O
disagrees O
with O
the O
violent O
methods O
used O
by O
the O
men O
carrying O
out O
the O
expulsion O
decrees O
. O

There O
have O
even O
been O
instances O
in O
which O
local O
authorities O
have O
not O
carried O
out O
or O
carried O
out O
only O
partially O
the O
ministerial O
orders O
. O

As O
many O
as O
three O
prefects O
have O
been O
deposed O
or O
recalled O
and O
subjected O
to O
an O
enquiry O
. O

Church O
authorities O
have O
also O
objected O
to O
the O
methods O
employed O
. O

It O
has O
been O
reported O
that O
the O
Minister O
of O
Slovakia B-LOC
to O
the O
Vatican B-LOC
has O
been O
here O
, O
and O
there O
have O
been O
rumours O
about O
a O
note O
from O
the O
Secretariat O
of O
State O
to O
the O
Slovakian B-LOC
Legation O
. O

There O
has O
indeed O
been O
such O
a O
step O
and O
the O
Chargé O
d’Affaires O
of O
the O
Holy O
See O
here O
has O
repeatedly O
seen O
the O
Prime B-PERS
Minister I-PERS
and O
Minister O
for O
Foreign O
Affairs O
on O
this O
issue O
. O

Also O
, O
there O
have O
been O
critical O
voices O
against O
Mach B-PERS
within O
the O
Government O
itself O
, O
coming O
from O
his O
colleagues O
of O
the O
Slovakian B-ORG
people I-ORG
’s I-ORG
party I-ORG
Nonetheless O
, O
the O
forced O
exodus O
of O
Jews O
has O
continued O
and O
continues O
still O
. O

It O
is O
illegal O
, O
as O
no O
law O
authorizing O
it O
exists O
. O

There O
is O
– O
for O
now O
– O
only O
a O
bill O
approved O
a O
few O
days O
ago O
by O
the O
Council O
of O
Minister O
which O
has O
still O
to O
be O
submitted O
to O
Parliament O
. O

The O
full O
powers O
granted O
by O
Parliament O
to O
the O
Government O
in O
1940 O
to O
proceed O
against O
Jews O
cannot O
possibly O
apply O
to O
the O
issue O
of O
the O
exodus O
. O

As O
I O
have O
learned O
from O
Minister O
Mach B-PERS
himself O
, O
of O
the O
90,000 O
Jews O
who O
were O
in O
Slovakia B-LOC
on O
25th O
March O
last O
( O
in O
1939 O
there O
were O
120,000 O
, O
30,000 O
of O
whom O
have O
voluntarily O
left O
the O
country O
after O
the O
establishment O
of O
the O
independent O
Slovak O
State O
) O
, O
13,000 O
have O
been O
deported O
these O
past O
weeks O
to O
the O
Katowice B-LOC
area O
and O
to O
the O
General B-LOC
Governorate I-LOC
and O
those O
remaining O
will O
follow O
in O
the O
course O
of O
the O
next O
6 O
months O
. O

Mach B-PERS
told O
me O
“ O
The O
Jews O
were O
dominating O
our O
economy O
” O
, O
and O
ended O
by O
saying O
that O
to O
remedy O
such O
a O
state O
of O
affairs O
, O
the O
time O
for O
half O
measures O
is O
over O
. O

When O
he O
was O
accused O
of O
having O
acted O
because O
forced O
to O
do O
so O
by O
the O
Germans O
, O
the O
Minister B-PERS
of I-PERS
Interior I-PERS
declared O
to O
the O
press O
, O
as O
reported O
with O
Cable O
no O
. O

1095/245 O
from O
27th B-DATE
March I-DATE
, O
that O
the O
expulsion O
of O
Jews O
had O
been O
decided O
“ O
spontaneously O
and O
with O
full O
persuasion O
” O
. O

I O
have O
been O
told O
by O
the O
German O
Minister O
here O
that O
his O
Government O
had O
not O
used O
any O
pressure O
but O
had O
simply O
made O
a O
suggestion O
that O
had O
been O
accepted O
. O

As O
far O
as O
I O
know O
, O
the O
President B-PERS
of I-PERS
the I-PERS
Republic I-PERS
has O
done O
his O
utmost O
to O
mitigate O
the O
harshness O
of O
the O
methods O
employed O
for O
the O
exodus O
and O
made O
use O
, O
despite O
a O
strong O
opposition O
from O
the O
Prime B-PERS
Minister I-PERS
himself O
, O
of O
the O
right O
to O
discriminate O
granted O
him O
by O
the O
“ O
Jewish O
Code O
” O
in O
order O
to O
save O
a O
great O
many O
persons O
from O
expulsion O
. O

Clearly O
, O
if O
President B-PERS
Tiso I-PERS
has O
not O
done O
more O
and O
has O
even O
prevented O
a O
press O
controversy O
on O
the O
Jewish O
question O
from O
breaking O
out O
( O
all O
that O
appeared O
in O
the O
press O
, O
belatedly O
, O
were O
two O
critical O
articles O
in O
the O
Catholic O
newspapers O
Slovak O
and O
Slovenska O
Pravda O
) O
, O
this O
is O
due O
to O
the O
fact O
that O
he O
finds O
himself O
unable O
to O
oppose O
the O
will O
of O
the O
Reich O
, O
which O
has O
in O
Tuka B-PERS
and O
in O
Mach B-PERS
, O
particularly O
in O
regard O
to O
the O
Jewish O
question O
, O
willing O
and O
convinced O
executors O
. O

It O
is O
also O
likely O
that O
Monsignor O
Tiso B-PERS
judges O
that O
under O
any O
circumstances O
he O
can O
be O
more O
useful O
to O
his O
people O
in O
the O
presidential O
chair O
than O
elsewhere O
. O

Cortese B-PERS
Youth B-ORG
Social I-ORG
welfare I-ORG
1941 B-DATE
- O
1944 B-DATE
Origin O
and O
development O
: O
Beginnings O
Children O
arrived O
in O
Theresienstadt B-GHETTO
with O
the O
first O
transports O
from O
Brno B-LOC
and O
Prague B-LOC
in O
1941 B-DATE
. O

They O
were O
originally O
housed O
in O
the O
barracks O
with O
their O
parents O
, O
girls O
and O
boys O
up O
to O
age O
12 O
with O
their O
mothers O
, O
older O
boys O
with O
their O
fathers O
. O

In O
all O
of O
the O
men O
’s O
barracks O
, O
a O
special O
room O
for O
boys O
up O
to O
age O
16 O
was O
arranged O
immediately O
, O
and O
later O
rooms O
for O
children O
of O
both O
sexes O
were O
set O
up O
in O
the O
Podmokly B-LOC
barracks I-LOC
( I-LOC
Bodenbacher I-LOC
Kaserne I-LOC
) I-LOC
. O

First O
Houses O
In O
February B-DATE
, O
the O
first O
home O
for O
girls O
was O
established O
in O
the O
Hamburg B-LOC
( I-LOC
Hamburger I-LOC
Kaserne I-LOC
) I-LOC
and O
Dresden B-LOC
barracks I-LOC
( I-LOC
Dresdner I-LOC
Kaserne I-LOC
) I-LOC
. O

Children O
were O
separated O
into O
rooms O
in O
groups O
according O
to O
age O
. O

These O
rooms O
then O
became O
the O
youth O
homes O
, O
which O
were O
placed O
in O
special O
buildings O
after O
the O
ghetto O
was O
opened O
in O
the O
summer O
of O
1942 B-DATE
, O
and O
thanks O
to O
the O
energetic O
representation O
of O
the O
children O
’ O
s O
interest O
, O
took O
up O
the O
best O
houses O
in O
Theresienstadt B-GHETTO
( O
former O
school O
, O
former O
command O
of O
the O
division O
etc O
. O

) O
. O

Educaters O
The O
staff O
consisted O
of O
a O
team O
of O
volunteers O
that O
was O
put O
together O
by O
Gonda B-PERS
Redlich I-PERS
and O
Fredy B-PERS
Hirsch I-PERS
, O
the O
first O
head O
of O
the O
Youth B-ORG
Social B-ORG
Welfare I-ORG
division I-ORG
. O

Both O
had O
come O
to O
Theresienstadt B-GHETTO
voluntarily O
with O
the O
first O
to O
be O
evacuated O
. O

There O
weren’t O
many O
experts O
among O
them O
, O
most O
were O
young O
people O
. O

Their O
experience O
consisted O
mostly O
of O
organizing O
summer O
camps O
and O
taking O
part O
in O
youth O
movements O
. O

Life O
in O
the O
houses O
Over O
time O
, O
a O
special O
rhythm O
of O
life O
developed O
in O
the O
houses O
. O

In O
accordance O
to O
the O
principles O
of O
collective O
education O
, O
the O
individual O
rooms O
became O
like O
separate O
houses O
that O
managed O
their O
own O
daily O
schedule O
. O

Besides O
their O
lessons O
, O
the O
children O
did O
house O
chores O
and O
organized O
frequent O
evenings O
programs O
. O

The O
caretakers O
lived O
with O
the O
children O
and O
thus O
could O
significantly O
influence O
their O
whole O
lives O
. O

The O
status O
of O
children O
in O
ghetto O
After O
the O
ghetto O
was O
opened O
, O
the O
children O
were O
allowed O
to O
move O
around O
freely O
, O
exercise O
, O
and O
play O
on O
a O
specially O
reserved O
part O
of O
the O
fortress O
. O

One O
must O
keep O
in O
mind O
that O
the O
Jewish O
Council O
wanted O
to O
help O
as O
many O
children O
as O
possible O
, O
even O
if O
it O
was O
at O
the O
expense O
of O
the O
old O
. O

Being O
out O
in O
the O
fresh O
air O
was O
an O
unattainable O
pleasure O
for O
an O
old O
person O
. O

The O
space O
set O
aside O
for O
the O
children O
was O
about O
2x O
larger O
than O
that O
for O
adults O
. O

The O
children O
received O
various O
food O
rations O
from O
the O
very O
beginning O
( O
food O
was O
also O
cooked O
in O
a O
special O
kitchen O
for O
the O
children O
) O
. O

Nevertheless O
, O
an O
average O
of O
20 O
- O
30 O
children O
( O
but O
also O
as O
high O
as O
120 O
) O
lived O
in O
one O
room O
without O
a O
bed O
or O
any O
other O
furniture O
. O

Diseases O
They O
were O
wholly O
insufficiently O
nourished O
, O
and O
very O
soon O
various O
diseases O
and O
epidemic O
infections O
broke O
out O
( O
scarlet O
fever O
, O
inf O
. O

hepatitis O
, O
and O
later O
typhus O
, O
childhood O
polio O
, O
and O
encephalitis O
) O
, O
avitaminosis O
, O
lung O
diseases O
and O
, O
despite O
our O
best O
efforts O
to O
maintain O
good O
hygiene O
, O
skin O
diseases O
( O
impetigo O
, O
phlegmons O
, O
etc O
. O

) O
Organization O
After O
the O
ghetto O
was O
opened O
, O
youth O
organization O
and O
social B-ORG
welfare I-ORG
deepened O
and O
expanded O
. O

Closed O
welfare O
For O
children O
4 O
to O
18 O
years O
in O
houses O
that O
were O
gradually O
made O
ready O
by O
January B-DATE
1943 I-DATE
. O

Nationality O
- O
Czech O
; O
sex O
- O
boys O
; O
age O
10 O
- O
14 O
; O
former O
building O
- O
school O
; O
current O
building O
- O
L B-LOC
417 I-LOC
condition O
at O
the O
time O
largest O
number O
of O
children O
during O
summer O
1943 B-DATE
- O
350 O
Nationality O
- O
Czech O
; O
sex O
- O
girls O
; O
age O
10 O
- O
16 O
; O
former O
building O
- O
mil O
headquarters O
; O
current O
building O
- O
L B-LOC
410 I-LOC
; O
condition O
at O
the O
time O
largest O
number O
of O
children O
during O
summer O
1943 B-DATE
- O
450 O
Nationality O
- O
German O
; O
sex O
- O
children O
; O
age O
10 O
- O
14 O
; O
former O
building O
- O
mil O
. O

headquarters O
; O
current O
building O
- O
L B-LOC
414 I-LOC
/II O
; O
condition O
at O
the O
time O
largest O
number O
of O
children O
during O
summer O
1943 B-DATE
- O
350 O
Nationality O
- O
Czech O
, O
German O
; O
sex O
- O
children O
; O
age O
4 O
- O
10 O
; O
former O
building O
sick O
room O
; O
current O
building O
- O
L B-LOC
318 I-LOC
; O
condition O
at O
the O
time O
largest O
number O
of O
children O
during O
summer O
1943 B-DATE
- O
300 O
Nationality O
- O
Czech O
, O
German O
; O
sex O
- O
children O
; O
age O
4 O
- O
12 O
; O
former O
building O
- O
in O
rooms O
; O
current O
building O
- O
C B-LOC
III I-LOC
; O
condition O
at O
the O
time O
largest O
number O
of O
children O
during O
summer O
1943 B-DATE
- O
100 O
Nationality O
- O
Czech O
, O
German O
; O
sex O
- O
boys O
; O
age O
14 O
- O
18 O
; O
former O
building O
- O
apprentice O
house O
; O
current O
building O
- O
Q B-LOC
710 I-LOC
, O
L B-LOC
218 I-LOC
, O
Q B-LOC
706 I-LOC
, O
Q B-LOC
708 I-LOC
; O
condition O
at O
the O
time O
largest O
number O
of O
children O
during O
summer O
1943 B-DATE
- O
500 O
Nationality O
- O
Czech O
, O
German O
; O
sex O
- O
children O
; O
age O
4 O
-12 O
; O
current O
building O
- O
Q B-LOC
609 I-LOC
; O
condition O
at O
the O
time O
largest O
number O
of O
children O
during O
summer O
1943 B-DATE
- O
250 O
Health B-ORG
care I-ORG
staff O
took O
care O
of O
children O
up O
to O
age O
4 O
, O
who O
were O
placed O
in O
a O
house O
for O
infants O
, O
and O
a O
house O
for O
toddlers O
, O
and O
lived O
together O
with O
their O
mothers O
and O
the O
staff O
. O

A O
children O
’ O
s O
hospital O
was O
established O
with O
a O
special O
section O
for O
children O
with O
tuberculosis O
, O
who O
were O
all O
sent O
to O
the O
gas O
chambers O
in O
the O
fall O
of O
1944 B-DATE
( O
about O
100 O
children O
) O
. O

After O
a O
large O
typhoid O
epidemic O
that O
claimed O
many O
children O
as O
victims O
, O
a O
house O
for O
people O
convalescing O
after O
surviving O
typhus O
was O
established O
in O
January B-DATE
1943 I-DATE
, O
L B-LOC
216 I-LOC
. O

Internal O
organization O
of O
houses O
In O
the O
summer O
of O
1943 B-DATE
when O
the O
population O
of O
children O
was O
at O
its O
highest O
, O
i.e O
. O

in O
the O
summer O
of O
1943 B-DATE
when O
there O
were O
about O
5,000 O
children O
in O
Theresienstadt B-GHETTO
, O
the O
internal O
youth B-ORG
welfare I-ORG
staff O
had O
about O
2,500 O
houses O
under O
their O
care O
. O

Besides O
their O
educational O
staff O
( O
caretakers O
, O
house O
leaders O
) O
, O
each O
of O
these O
institutions O
had O
a O
social B-ORG
welfare I-ORG
staff O
that O
oversaw O
repair O
shops O
, O
smaller O
tailor O
's O
workshops O
, O
a O
clothing O
issue O
counter O
, O
the O
collection O
of O
dirty O
laundry O
etc O
. O

A O
social O
welfare O
nurse O
took O
care O
of O
weaker O
children O
, O
for O
whom O
extra O
dinners O
were O
prepared O
in O
the O
kitchens O
. O

( O
A O
normal O
dinner O
was O
black O
coffee O
or O
watery O
soup O
) O
. O

In O
each O
house O
there O
were O
sick O
rooms O
with O
a O
doctor O
and O
nursing O
staff O
. O

Public O
care O
Children O
weren’t O
forced O
to O
move O
into O
the O
homes O
. O

Children O
who O
didn’t O
live O
in O
the O
homes O
were O
taken O
care O
of O
by O
the O
public O
youth B-ORG
welfare I-ORG
. O

The O
institute O
of O
public O
welfare O
consisted O
of O
homes O
for O
mothers O
and O
children O
( O
housing O
in O
various O
homes O
where O
only O
mothers O
with O
children O
up O
to O
6 O
years O
of O
age O
lived O
with O
no O
staff O
) O
, O
and O
a O
Czech B-LOC
Kindergarten O
. O

When O
the O
number O
of O
children O
in O
the O
camp O
was O
at O
its O
highest O
, O
about O
300 O
children O
from O
the O
Hebrew B-LOC
school O
and O
about O
70 O
- O
100 O
other O
children O
attended O
it O
. O

Public O
welfare O
was O
ensured O
by O
social O
welfare O
nurses O
, O
who O
regularly O
visited O
the O
children O
, O
ascertained O
their O
health O
condition O
, O
and O
arranged O
everything O
for O
them O
as O
much O
as O
the O
situation O
allowed O
. O

In O
the O
Youth B-ORG
Social I-ORG
Welfare I-ORG
Center O
, O
an O
orphan O
ledger O
was O
maintained O
and O
the O
office B-ORG
worked O
on O
an O
agenda O
for O
the O
youth B-ORG
( O
foster O
care O
etc O
. O

) O
. O

Training O
and O
employment O
The O
Training O
and O
employment O
of O
children O
in O
Theresienstadt B-GHETTO
was O
very O
complicated O
due O
to O
external O
circumstances O
. O

Training O
was O
forbidden O
, O
but O
the O
ban O
was O
ignored O
. O

Children O
were O
trained O
for O
daily O
work O
according O
to O
the O
tenets O
of O
public O
schools O
. O

The O
results O
were O
positive O
given O
the O
classes O
’ O
irregularity O
and O
illegality O
. O

Kindergartens O
Younger O
children O
up O
to O
age O
7 O
received O
a O
basic O
education O
in O
kindergartens O
. O

Teaching O
in O
the O
houses O
Older O
children O
that O
lived O
in O
the O
houses O
received O
3 O
- O
4 O
hours O
of O
school O
subjects O
alongside O
their O
day O
job O
, O
which O
officially O
only O
consisted O
of O
singing O
, O
manual O
labor O
, O
and O
drawing O
. O

The O
most O
basic O
teaching O
aids O
were O
lacking O
. O

There O
also O
weren’t O
enough O
experts O
in O
education O
and O
work O
was O
interrupted O
by O
such O
outside O
influences O
as O
transports O
and O
checks O
. O

Daytime O
children O
’s O
homes O
Children O
up O
to O
age O
14 O
who O
lived O
with O
their O
parents O
went O
to O
the O
shelters O
every O
day O
, O
where O
they O
attended O
lessons O
in O
the O
most O
difficult O
circumstances O
. O

Youths O
over O
14 O
years O
of O
age O
Young O
people O
over O
age O
14 O
who O
lived O
either O
with O
their O
parents O
or O
in O
homes O
were O
forced O
to O
work O
. O

They O
were O
assigned O
jobs O
mostly O
as O
needed O
and O
usually O
in O
agriculture O
and O
wartime O
production O
, O
some O
worked O
in O
the O
ghetto O
and O
only O
a O
small O
number O
received O
qualified O
handcraft O
work O
. O

Night O
courses O
that O
were O
designed O
to O
give O
them O
theoretical O
as O
well O
as O
practical O
schooling O
in O
the O
particular O
craft O
. O

These O
young O
people O
were O
also O
taken O
care O
of O
by O
a O
special O
apprenticeship O
commission O
that O
also O
administered O
exams O
once O
their O
training O
was O
completed O
. O

Educative O
activities O
A O
children O
’s O
library B-ORG
for O
children O
up O
to O
age O
13 O
and O
a O
young O
people O
's O
library B-ORG
for O
older O
children O
were O
established O
. O

Youths O
could O
also O
attend O
regular O
lectures O
on O
various O
topics O
( O
the O
national O
economy O
and O
various O
specialized O
subjects O
) O
. O

Educational O
goal O
Besides O
the O
ethical O
and O
practical O
educational O
goals O
and O
collective O
child O
rearing O
, O
we O
tried O
to O
encourage O
the O
children O
’s O
awareness O
. O

By O
teaching O
them O
about O
their O
lives O
and O
future O
jobs O
we O
wanted O
to O
help O
them O
rise O
above O
their O
sad O
and O
hopeless O
situation O
. O

Transports O
Around O
15,000 O
children O
passed O
through O
Theresienstadt B-GHETTO
. O

The O
main O
effort O
of O
the O
youth B-ORG
welfare I-ORG
, O
especially O
in O
the O
homes O
, O
was O
to O
create O
for O
the O
children O
the O
atmosphere O
of O
a O
free O
space O
safe O
from O
the O
physical O
and O
moral O
failings O
of O
their O
surroundings O
. O

This O
effort O
was O
unfortunately O
interrupted O
by O
transports O
that O
left O
in O
intervals O
of O
1 O
week O
to O
6 O
months O
. O

The O
transports O
not O
only O
interrupted O
daily O
schedules O
and O
the O
normal O
rhythm O
of O
life O
, O
but O
put O
an O
end O
to O
the O
care B-ORG
of I-ORG
the I-ORG
child I-ORG
placed O
on O
the O
transport O
. O

Being O
transported O
was O
a O
death O
sentence O
for O
the O
child O
and O
the O
sword O
of O
Damocles O
hung O
over O
the O
children O
that O
remained O
. O

In O
the O
beginning O
, O
it O
was O
possible O
to O
protect O
children O
younger O
than O
12 O
. O

But O
this O
age O
limit O
was O
gradually O
lowered O
, O
and O
in O
October B-DATE
1944 I-DATE
even O
babies O
were O
transported O
. O

Beautification O
In O
February B-DATE
1944 I-DATE
, O
the O
so O
- O
called O
Verschönerung O
began O
, O
i.e O
. O

the O
preparation O
of O
the O
ghetto O
for O
the O
arrival O
of O
the O
international O
committee O
. O

During O
this O
process O
, O
all O
homes O
were O
adapted O
, O
the O
school O
building O
in O
which O
classes O
were O
never O
taught O
was O
established O
, O
a O
children O
’s O
sanatorium O
and O
a O
children O
’s O
pavilion O
were O
established O
, O
children O
’s O
food O
rations O
were O
raised O
, O
the O
harshest O
regulations O
were O
repealed O
. O

To O
make O
sure O
that O
the O
town O
wouldn’t O
be O
overcrowded O
, O
right O
before O
the O
committee O
arrived O
7,500 O
people O
were O
sent O
to O
Auschwitz B-CAMP
to O
the O
gas O
chambers O
. O

Based O
on O
a O
special O
order O
, O
almost O
all O
were O
orphans O
. O

The O
remaining O
orphans O
above O
5 O
years O
of O
age O
left O
in O
October B-DATE
1944 I-DATE
together O
with O
the O
leaders O
and O
most O
of O
the O
staff O
. O

Conclusion O
Out O
of O
the O
15,000 O
children O
that O
spent O
time O
in O
Theresienstadt B-GHETTO
, O
1,086 O
children O
remained O
in O
the O
winter O
of O
1944 B-DATE
- O
1945 B-DATE
after O
the O
last O
transport O
departed O
. O

After O
the O
end O
of O
the O
war O
, O
no O
more O
than O
100 O
children O
over O
age O
14 O
returned O
from O
concentration O
camps O
. O

All O
of O
the O
efforts O
and O
work O
, O
all O
of O
the O
mental O
and O
physical O
care O
, O
all O
of O
the O
individual O
and O
collective O
education O
led O
nowhere O
. O

They O
could O
only O
make O
the O
children O
’ O
s O
stay O
in O
the O
ghetto B-GHETTO
a O
little O
easier O
. O

They O
couldn’t O
avert O
their O
terrible O
fate O
. O

It O
is O
learned O
that O
the O
some O
1200 O
Jews O
removed O
from O
Stettlin B-LOC
have O
been O
settled O
in O
three O
small O
towns O
in O
the O
neighborhood O
of O
Lublin B-LOC
where O
they O
are O
said O
to O
be O
now O
living O
under O
conditions O
of O
considerable O
hardship O
and O
poverty O
. O

According O
to O
reliable O
information O
the O
order O
for O
the O
deportation O
of O
the O
Jews O
from O
Schneidemuhl B-LOC
was O
issued O
by O
the O
same O
local O
authority O
who O
was O
responsible O
for O
the O
action O
taken O
in O
Stettin B-LOC
. O

An O
arrangement O
has O
been O
tentatively O
concluded O
whereby O
the O
Schneidemuhl B-LOC
Jews O
will O
not O
be O
sent O
to O
Eastern O
Poland B-LOC
as O
has O
been O
the O
case O
with O
those O
from O
Stettin B-LOC
but O
will O
be O
transferred O
to O
other O
parts O
of O
the O
Reich O
. O

What O
has O
been O
reported O
in O
the O
press O
of O
neutral O
countries O
, O
namely O
that O
the O
Bulgarian B-ORG
Government I-ORG
is O
said O
to O
be O
negotiating O
at O
the O
same O
time O
with O
Germany O
and O
with O
Great B-LOC
Britain I-LOC
concerning O
the O
removal O
from O
Bulgaria B-LOC
of O
significant O
groups O
of O
press O
of O
Israelites O
, O
is O
true O
. O

Germany O
has O
offered O
to O
transfer O
the O
Bulgarian O
Jewish O
groups O
to O
the O
ghettoes O
in O
Poland B-LOC
and O
has O
asked O
the O
Bulgarian B-ORG
government I-ORG
to O
pay O
the O
sum O
of O
five O
- O
hundred O
marks O
per O
person O
for O
transport O
costs O
and O
in O
exchange O
for O
property O
seized O
locally O
. O

Bulgarians O
have O
resisted O
this O
request O
and O
for O
the O
time O
being O
nothing O
has O
been O
decided O
as O
yet O
on O
the O
financial O
question O
. O

However O
, O
the O
departures O
of O
Jews O
for O
Poland B-LOC
have O
already O
begun O
, O
albeit O
limited O
to O
the O
Jewish O
groups O
living O
in O
the O
new O
Bulgarian B-LOC
territories O
, O
Thrace B-LOC
and O
Macedonia B-LOC
, O
where O
there O
are O
Jewish O
communities O
that O
have O
been O
estimated O
at O
approx O
. O

twenty O
- O
thousand O
individuals O
. O

As O
for O
the O
Jews O
in O
the O
ancient O
Bulgarian B-LOC
territory O
nothing O
definite O
has O
been O
decided O
, O
because O
reportedly O
the O
Bulgarian B-ORG
government I-ORG
is O
opposing O
a O
marked O
resistance O
. O

With O
Great B-LOC
Britain I-LOC
there O
have O
been O
negotiations O
through O
the O
Swiss B-ORG
Government I-ORG
about O
dispatching O
to O
Palestine B-LOC
four O
- O
thousand O
adult O
Bulgarian O
Jews O
and O
four O
- O
thousand O
Jewish O
children O
. O

But O
the O
Reich O
has O
stepped O
in O
and O
in O
a O
certain O
sense O
has O
“ O
vetoed O
” O
this O
departure O
, O
judging O
, O
as O
usual O
, O
that O
it O
is O
dangerous O
to O
transfer O
to O
an O
enemy O
territory O
such O
decidedly O
anti O
- O
German O
elements O
. O

In O
the O
end O
, O
apparently O
, O
the O
Bulgarian B-ORG
Government I-ORG
has O
resumed O
these O
negotiations O
despite O
that O
“ O
veto O
” O
, O
limiting O
them O
to O
the O
four O
- O
thousand O
children O
who O
would O
be O
accompanied O
by O
no O
more O
than O
five O
- O
hundred O
adults O
. O

This O
negotiation O
as O
well O
, O
however O
, O
seems O
to O
encounter O
problems O
of O
a O
financial O
nature O
. O

Magistrati B-PERS
Arnold B-PERS
Zadikov I-PERS
On O
March B-DATE
27 I-DATE
, I-DATE
1884 I-DATE
, O
the O
jud O
. O

cantor O
Isidor B-PERS
H. I-PERS
Zadikow I-PERS
's I-PERS
third O
child O
, O
a O
son O
, O
was O
born O
. O

In O
Kolberg B-LOC
, O
on O
the O
Baltic B-LOC
Sea I-LOC
beach O
, O
Arnold B-PERS
grew O
up O
, O
a O
boy O
more O
intelligent O
than O
average O
. O

His O
character O
contains O
great O
contrasts O
. O

Strength O
and O
tenderness O
, O
irascibility O
and O
goodness O
. O

The O
boy O
, O
who O
never O
misses O
a O
rascally O
prank O
with O
a O
wry O
look O
, O
is O
skipping O
school O
, O
pensively O
lying O
on O
the O
sea O
beach O
and O
immersing O
himself O
deeply O
in O
the O
ancient O
classics O
. O

He O
needed O
his O
strong O
personal O
courage O
early O
on O
. O

His O
fine O
sense O
of O
honour O
forces O
him O
to O
vigorously O
oppose O
any O
negatively O
intended O
allusion O
to O
his O
denomination O
- O
the O
little O
Jew O
boy O
has O
a O
fight O
with O
2 O
or O
3 O
heroes O
from O
time O
to O
time O
. O

At O
the O
age O
of O
twelve O
he O
left O
home O
to O
attend O
high O
school O
in O
Poznań B-LOC
. O

Childhood O
is O
over O
. O

He O
eats O
kosher O
- O
but O
badly O
and O
insufficiently O
; O
he O
always O
thought O
he O
would O
have O
grown O
taller O
if O
his O
years O
of O
physical O
development O
had O
been O
easier O
. O

It O
is O
a O
performance O
for O
the O
cantor O
of O
a O
small O
Jewish O
community O
to O
give O
4 O
children O
a O
good O
education O
! O
After O
graduating O
from O
lower O
secondary O
school O
, O
the O
father O
wishes O
Arnold B-PERS
to O
take O
up O
banking O
. O

That O
’s O
about O
the O
worst O
thing O
that O
can O
happen O
to O
Arnold B-PERS
. O

Things O
get O
tough O
between O
father O
and O
son O
. O

Yesterday O
still O
a O
student O
, O
Arnold B-PERS
stands O
with O
the O
masonry O
trowel O
in O
his O
hand O
as O
a O
masonry O
apprentice O
at O
the O
construction O
site O
. O

He O
later O
graduated O
from O
the O
building O
school O
in O
Poznań B-LOC
. O

At O
the O
age O
of O
18 O
he O
was O
a O
site O
manager O
in O
Berlin B-LOC
. O

The O
healthy O
boy O
from O
the O
provinces O
experiences O
the O
wonders O
of O
the O
big O
city O
- O
the O
musical O
sensitivity O
inherited O
from O
his O
father O
, O
his O
beautiful O
baritone O
voice O
prompts O
him O
to O
sing O
in O
the O
choir O
at O
oratorios O
- O
he O
experiences O
unforgettable O
Reinhardt O
performances O
. O

It O
is O
characteristic O
of O
his O
temperament O
that O
in O
the O
garden O
scene O
of O
Twelfth O
Night O
he O
actually O
falls O
off O
his O
chair O
laughing O
. O

The O
collections O
make O
the O
deepest O
impression O
on O
him O
. O

Looking O
at O
art O
is O
almost O
a O
religion O
for O
him O
, O
he O
begins O
to O
draw O
. O

Profound O
is O
everything O
unconscious O
- O
part O
of O
the O
creative O
thought O
- O
as O
with O
every O
beginner O
, O
his O
first O
works O
are O
also O
self O
- O
portraits O
. O

The O
bustling O
metropolis O
increases O
his O
diligence O
; O
after O
work O
he O
draws O
, O
he O
spends O
Sundays O
outdoors O
with O
or O
without O
a O
girl O
. O

He O
is O
now O
financially O
well O
off O
. O

But O
destiny O
wants O
something O
to O
happen O
every O
time O
he O
reaches O
a O
high O
point O
. O

Something O
good O
this O
time O
– O
Max B-PERS
Liebermann I-PERS
comments O
favourably O
on O
the O
drawings O
presented O
to O
him O
; O
Paul B-PERS
Nathan I-PERS
and O
James B-PERS
Simon I-PERS
, O
well O
- O
known O
Jewish O
patrons O
of O
the O
arts O
, O
guarantee O
a O
small O
grant O
– O
Arnold B-PERS
gives O
up O
the O
building O
trade O
, O
rents O
a O
small O
studio O
in O
Friedenau B-LOC
and O
becomes O
a O
sculptor O
. O

During O
this O
wonderful O
, O
strenuous O
period O
of O
study O
he O
is O
really O
happy O
for O
the O
first O
time O
. O

Begun O
late O
, O
the O
apprenticeship O
is O
surprisingly O
short O
. O

Although O
the O
technique O
of O
his O
earliest O
works O
is O
immature O
, O
they O
are O
charged O
with O
such O
emotional O
content O
that O
they O
have O
the O
allure O
of O
the O
primitive O
. O

In O
addition O
to O
study O
heads O
and O
figurative O
compositions O
, O
he O
designed O
Jewish O
tombstones O
. O

He O
wins O
second O
prize O
in O
an O
international O
competition O
. O

It O
was O
a O
design O
for O
a O
world O
telegraph O
monument O
in O
Bern B-LOC
. O

The O
young O
northerner O
goes O
south O
for O
the O
first O
time O
, O
in O
street O
shoes O
he O
makes O
the O
first O
of O
his O
beloved O
mountain O
tours O
, O
on O
the O
Jungfrau B-LOC
. O

His O
development O
curve O
rises O
very O
quickly O
. O

In O
1910 B-DATE
he O
left O
Berlin B-LOC
and O
went O
to O
Munich B-LOC
to O
study O
. O

As O
a O
master O
student O
and O
in O
his O
own O
modest O
studio O
, O
he O
can O
actualise O
himself O
uninhibitedly O
. O

He O
begins O
to O
be O
known O
beyond O
Jewish O
circles O
. O

In O
1913 B-DATE
he O
was O
awarded O
the O
Prussian O
Academy O
's O
Michael O
Bauer O
Prize O
, O
which O
meant O
a O
grant O
for O
a O
free O
stay O
of O
one O
year O
in O
Rome B-LOC
, O
his O
spiritual O
home O
. O

He O
carefully O
prepares O
his O
journey O
- O
once O
again O
a O
high O
point O
has O
been O
reached O
- O
the O
world O
war O
breaks O
out O
. O

Precisely O
because O
he O
is O
Jewish O
, O
he O
immediately O
volunteers O
for O
the O
field O
. O

After O
a O
short O
training O
in O
the O
Munich B-LOC
I. O
Bayr B-LOC
. O

Field O
Artillery O
Regiment O
, O
he O
goes O
to O
the O
front O
in O
France B-LOC
as O
a O
gunner O
, O
All O
Quiet O
on O
the O
Western O
Front O
. O

In O
1917 B-DATE
he O
was O
badly O
wounded O
in O
the O
shoulder O
near O
Arras B-LOC
and O
was O
taken O
prisoner O
by O
the O
British B-LOC
at O
Brocton B-LOC
Camp O
. O

Forced O
by O
circumstances O
to O
work O
on O
a O
small O
scale O
, O
he O
procured O
slates O
, O
made O
his O
own O
tools O
and O
began O
to O
cut O
masterful O
plaques O
in O
negative O
into O
slate O
. O

This O
imprisonment O
lasts O
an O
agonizingly O
long O
time O
– O
he O
can O
only O
return O
home O
a O
year O
after O
the O
conclusion O
of O
peace O
, O
in O
order O
to O
end O
up O
in O
a O
less O
agonizing O
imprisonment O
there O
. O

He O
marries O
his O
longtime O
girlfriend O
, O
a O
Jewish O
painter O
. O

Although O
there O
are O
always O
financial O
difficulties O
, O
the O
marriage O
is O
extremely O
happy O
. O

Love O
and O
understanding O
are O
great O
on O
both O
sides O
and O
stay O
that O
way O
– O
which O
is O
a O
problem O
. O

Fruitful O
years O
of O
creativity O
follow O
. O

The O
1916 B-DATE
plaque O
Die O
Heimatlose O
( O
The O
Homeland O
- O
less O
) O
created O
on O
a O
short O
home O
leave O
follows O
3 O
versions O
of O
David O
, O
a O
wonderful O
life O
- O
size O
group O
of O
Untersberger O
marble O
Motherhood O
, O
many O
portraits O
and O
reliefs O
; O
The O
Samson O
problem O
is O
particularly O
close O
to O
his O
heart O
, O
and O
he O
is O
constantly O
giving O
new O
expression O
to O
it O
. O

There O
is O
a O
strong O
upward O
trend O
and O
– O
as O
always O
in O
his O
life O
– O
the O
setback O
is O
near O
; O
Nazism O
begins O
to O
taint O
the O
sensitive O
, O
honourable O
and O
brave O
man O
' O
s O
life O
. O

Passive O
tolerance O
is O
not O
his O
thing O
. O

He O
plans O
to O
blow O
up O
the O
Circus O
Krone O
where O
the O
speeches O
are O
held O
. O

Family O
and O
religious O
community O
breathe O
a O
sigh O
of O
relief O
when O
he O
embarks O
on O
a O
study O
trip O
to O
Rome B-LOC
instead O
. O

Far O
away O
from O
politics O
and O
inflation O
, O
he O
finds O
his O
spiritual O
balance O
again O
. O

With O
great O
intensity O
he O
devotes O
himself O
to O
the O
study O
of O
ancient O
works O
of O
art O
and O
begins O
to O
master O
marble O
. O

He O
still O
can’t O
enjoy O
his O
state O
prize O
, O
the O
Villa O
Massimo O
/home O
of O
the O
scholarship O
holders/ O
is O
not O
yet O
vacant O
. O

It O
was O
not O
until O
1928 B-DATE
that O
he O
began O
this O
long O
- O
awaited O
stay O
. O

A O
life O
- O
size O
marble O
figure O
David O
, O
a O
self O
- O
portrait O
/philolexicon/ O
, O
a O
wonderfully O
pure O
figure O
of O
a O
girl O
reworked O
from O
poetry O
, O
etc O
. O

are O
the O
fruit O
of O
this O
most O
beautiful O
year O
. O

At O
home O
, O
the O
political O
sky O
is O
getting O
darker O
and O
darker O
. O

Home O
is O
the O
island O
surrounded O
by O
storms O
, O
on O
which O
alone O
creation O
is O
still O
possible O
. O

Personally O
threatened O
, O
he O
decides O
to O
go O
to O
Paris B-LOC
in O
1933 B-DATE
, O
where O
he O
lives O
under O
miserable O
circumstances O
as O
an O
emigrant O
until O
1936 B-DATE
. O

Nevertheless O
, O
a O
few O
busts O
, O
portraits O
of O
women O
of O
wonderful O
charm O
, O
are O
created O
. O

Now O
he O
has O
all O
the O
means O
of O
expression O
in O
his O
hands O
– O
now O
the O
most O
fruitful O
creative O
period O
of O
his O
life O
could O
and O
should O
begin O
. O

It O
was O
destined O
differently O
for O
him O
. O

He O
receives O
a O
call O
to O
Karlsbad B-LOC
to O
artistically O
manage O
the O
well O
- O
known O
glass O
factory O
Moser B-PERS
/státní O
sklárny/ O
for O
2 O
months O
. O

It O
turns O
out O
to O
be O
two O
years O
. O

A O
white O
crystal O
goblet O
with O
the O
portrait O
of O
President O
T. B-PERS
G. I-PERS
Masaryk I-PERS
is O
created O
- O
vases O
and O
bowls O
of O
wonderful O
cut O
and O
noblest O
shape O
, O
large O
spherical O
vases O
with O
engraved O
figures O
, O
during O
the O
production O
of O
which O
he O
monitors O
every O
millimeter O
- O
above O
all O
things O
a O
glass O
service O
Chopin O
- O
on O
each O
cup O
three O
dancing O
figures O
- O
of O
Pompeian B-LOC
charm O
, O
at O
the O
same O
time O
modern O
, O
rhythmic O
, O
even O
a O
bit O
harsh O
in O
detail O
, O
high O
art O
far O
beyond O
the O
framework O
of O
the O
decorative O
. O

The O
individual O
pieces O
are O
very O
expensive O
, O
are O
bought O
like O
hot O
cakes O
, O
he O
is O
offered O
a O
permanent O
position O
under O
very O
favourable O
conditions O
, O
one O
goal O
has O
been O
achieved O
- O
the O
Nazi O
occupation O
of O
the O
Sudeten B-LOC
region O
follows O
. O

He O
was O
the O
last O
to O
leave O
Karlsbad B-LOC
on O
the O
last O
train O
of O
refugees O
. O

Living O
with O
his O
family O
in O
Prague B-LOC
, O
he O
continued O
to O
work O
tirelessly O
– O
until O
he O
was O
deported O
to O
Theresienstadt B-GHETTO
in O
1942 B-DATE
. O

Even O
there O
his O
work O
and O
achievements O
can O
be O
of O
use O
- O
he O
digs O
clay O
for O
pottery O
, O
builds O
a O
kiln O
and O
sets O
up O
a O
pottery O
workshop O
. O

At O
night O
he O
makes O
portraits O
and O
compositions O
. O

Living O
in O
distress O
and O
constant O
danger O
, O
he O
creates O
out O
of O
wood O
( O
no O
other O
material O
is O
available O
to O
him O
) O
ritual O
objects O
, O
Sabbath O
candlesticks O
and O
a O
huge O
, O
very O
peculiar O
Menorah O
. O

Colleagues O
and O
acquaintances O
flock O
to O
his O
strong O
personality O
. O

He O
is O
popular O
with O
young O
and O
old O
, O
his O
sense O
of O
humour O
and O
his O
philosophy O
allow O
him O
to O
find O
a O
kind O
word O
for O
everyone O
. O

A O
few O
days O
before O
his O
59th O
birthday O
, O
a O
serious O
acute O
illness O
occurs O
- O
he O
has O
to O
be O
operated O
on O
. O

Bureaucratic O
formalities O
and O
other O
unfortunate O
circumstances O
delay O
the O
intervention O
. O

It O
was O
already O
too O
late O
. O

Three O
days O
later O
, O
on O
March B-DATE
8 I-DATE
, I-DATE
1943 I-DATE
, O
he O
left O
us O
, O
deliriously O
ranting O
of O
Sicily B-LOC
. O

He O
was O
no O
longer O
allowed O
to O
experience O
a O
solo O
funeral O
– O
on O
March B-DATE
10th I-DATE
– O
nor O
was O
he O
allowed O
to O
experience O
spring O
and O
the O
faintly O
burgeoning O
hope O
of O
liberation O
. O

Chief O
Rabbi O
Dr O
. O

Baeck B-PERS
spoke O
unforgettable O
words O
of O
wisdom O
and O
depth O
at O
his O
coffin O
- O
about O
the O
artist O
in O
general O
, O
about O
Arnold B-PERS
Zadikow I-PERS
in O
particular O
. O

His O
ashes O
have O
not O
been O
allowed O
to O
rest O
. O

The O
number O
of O
dead O
must O
be O
concealed O
from O
a O
commission O
, O
the O
crematorium O
is O
emptied O
; O
the O
cardboard O
boxes O
containing O
the O
ashes O
have O
to O
be O
passed O
by O
long O
lines O
of O
women O
. O

Through O
the O
hands O
of O
his O
wife O
his O
ashes O
went O
into O
the O
Eger B-LOC
. O

He O
who O
created O
so O
many O
glorious O
grave O
memorials O
has O
no O
grave O
. O

As O
it O
corresponded O
to O
his O
elemental O
nature O
, O
as O
he O
expressed O
it O
lyrically O
in O
his O
thought O
- O
deep O
, O
nature O
- O
oriented O
poems O
- O
he O
was O
absorbed O
in O
the O
element O
. O

Hilda B-PERS
Zadikow I-PERS
Prague B-LOC
, O
January B-DATE
1946 I-DATE
Doc O
. O

archives O
30./I. B-DATE
46 I-DATE
Dear O
Sir O
– O
The O
revolting O
fate O
of O
68 O
BURGENLAND B-LOC
Jews O
, O
driven O
from O
their O
home O
, O
received O
into O
no O
neighbouring O
country O
, O
nor O
allowed O
to O
return O
, O
has O
been O
commented O
upon O
troughout O
the O
international O
Press O
. O

Now O
we O
receive O
the O
report O
, O
which O
we O
enclose O
, O
of O
distress O
still O
encompassing O
the O
persecuted O
, O
our O
authority O
being O
Mrs B-PERS
. I-PERS

M. I-PERS
SCHMOLKA I-PERS
, O
director O
of O
the O
Hicem B-ORG
Prague B-LOC
. O

You O
are O
free O
to O
make O
such O
use O
of O
the O
report O
as O
you O
think O
fit O
. O

Mrs B-PERS
. I-PERS

SCHMOLKA I-PERS
, O
however O
, O
does O
not O
wish O
her O
name O
to O
be O
mentioned O
, O
nor O
, O
as O
usual O
, O
must O
we O
be O
named O
as O
your O
source O
. O

Yours O
faithfully O
, O
JEWISH B-ORG
CENTRAL I-ORG
INFORMATION I-ORG
OFFICE I-ORG
Public B-ORG
Service I-ORG
Institute I-ORG
THE O
BURGENLAND B-LOC
JEWS O
on O
the O
DANUBE O
TUG O
– O
BOAT O
An O
Eye O
Witness O
Report O
On O
April B-DATE
16 I-DATE
, I-DATE
1938 I-DATE
, O
the O
Jewish O
inhabitants O
of O
Kittsee B-LOC
and O
Pama B-LOC
, I-LOC
Burgenland I-LOC
, I-LOC
Austria I-LOC
, O
were O
ejected O
from O
their O
homes O
, O
robbed O
of O
what O
money O
and O
identity O
papers O
they O
had O
and O
, O
during O
the O
night O
, O
marooned O
on O
some O
small O
island O
in O
the O
Czech B-LOC
section O
of O
the O
Danube B-LOC
. O

On O
April B-DATE
17 I-DATE
, O
they O
were O
found O
by O
the O
Czech B-LOC
frontier O
guard O
and O
taken O
to O
Bratislava B-LOC
. O

That O
very O
same O
day O
they O
were O
expelled O
from O
Czecho B-LOC
- I-LOC
Slovakia I-LOC
and O
once O
again O
taken O
to O
the O
German B-LOC
border O
. O

On O
a O
narrow O
streak O
, O
“ O
No O
- O
man’s O
- O
land O
” O
, O
somewhere O
between O
the O
borders O
of O
Czecho B-LOC
- I-LOC
Slovakia I-LOC
, O
Hungaria B-LOC
and O
Austria B-LOC
, O
they O
spent O
three O
days O
and O
nights O
, O
in O
the O
bitter O
cold O
, O
half O
starved O
, O
and O
without O
a O
roof O
over O
their O
heads O
, O
between O
the O
fixed O
bayonets O
of O
the O
sentries O
of O
all O
3 O
countries O
which O
they O
were O
not O
allowed O
to O
enter O
. O

Some O
of O
them O
, O
17 O
in O
all O
, O
managed O
to O
get O
back O
to O
Kittsee B-LOC
, O
where O
the O
old O
men O
and O
children O
were O
locked O
up O
in O
a O
cellar O
, O
and O
the O
grown O
ups O
, O
men O
and O
women O
, O
were O
made O
do O
hard O
scrubbing O
work O
. O

Exhausted O
from O
3 O
days O
’ O
starving O
, O
the O
poor O
people O
’s O
strength O
threatened O
to O
fail O
, O
but O
ruthless O
beating O
put O
them O
to O
work O
again O
. O

During O
the O
night O
, O
after O
a O
30 O
miles O
walk O
, O
they O
were O
taken O
back O
to O
the O
Czech B-LOC
frontier O
. O

At O
long O
last O
the O
Jews O
of O
Bratislava B-LOC
found O
a O
temporary O
way O
- O
out O
. O

They O
hired O
a O
tug O
- O
boat O
, O
which O
landed O
on O
the O
Hungarian B-LOC
side O
of O
the O
Danube B-LOC
, O
near O
Royka B-LOC
, O
and O
received O
the O
people O
, O
68 O
altogether O
, O
agricultural O
workers O
and O
merchants O
, O
infants O
and O
80 O
years O
old O
men O
. O

No O
country O
along O
the O
Danube B-LOC
being O
prepared O
to O
grant O
the O
refugees O
leave O
on O
land O
, O
the O
Hungarian B-LOC
authorities O
extend O
the O
permit O
from O
week O
to O
week O
, O
hoping O
that O
the O
Jewish O
organisations O
will O
secure O
their O
emigration O
overseas O
. O

It O
is O
now O
three O
months O
that O
these O
people O
, O
smitten O
with O
despair O
, O
refused O
by O
every O
country O
, O
and O
even O
grudged O
the O
stay O
aboard O
the O
ship O
– O
it O
is O
now O
three O
months O
that O
they O
are O
thus O
kept O
in O
the O
vague O
hope O
of O
salvation O
. O

Efforts O
were O
made O
to O
induce O
various O
countries O
overseas O
to O
receive O
these O
unfortunates O
. O

Though O
some O
of O
the O
inmates O
of O
the O
boat O
managed O
to O
emigrate O
to O
the O
United B-LOC
States I-LOC
, O
the O
majority O
could O
not O
be O
emigrated O
, O
being O
unable O
to O
comply O
with O
the O
requirements O
set O
up O
by O
the O
countries O
overseas O
. O

It O
was O
in O
full O
realisation O
of O
this O
plight O
of O
theirs O
that O
we O
went O
to O
see O
the O
refugees O
on O
the O
boat O
, O
on O
July O
10 O
. O

We O
have O
seen O
their O
unspeakable O
mental O
distress O
, O
even O
increased O
by O
physical O
torture O
, O
as O
they O
either O
must O
stay O
in O
the O
narrow O
rooms O
downstairs O
which O
are O
infested O
with O
rats O
and O
vermin O
, O
or O
on O
the O
upper O
deck O
where O
they O
are O
left O
to O
the O
weather O
’s O
mood O
. O

There O
must O
be O
an O
end O
to O
this O
awful O
tragedy O
. O

It O
is O
not O
enough O
that O
Jewry O
must O
suffer O
all O
the O
humiliation O
that O
is O
being O
heaped O
upon O
it O
? O
Are O
we O
going O
to O
proclaim O
no O
, O
before O
the O
whole O
world O
, O
our O
utter O
helplessness O
, O
deliver O
up O
these O
poorest O
of O
the O
poor O
to O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
, O
and O
allow O
a O
mass O
suicide O
? O
We O
have O
taken O
down O
all O
particulars O
of O
every O
one O
of O
these O
unfortunates O
, O
and O
in O
addition O
, O
worked O
out O
a O
plan O
to O
lead O
this O
problem O
towards O
its O
solution O
, O
it O
being O
in O
the O
last O
resort O
nothing O
more O
than O
a O
question O
of O
finance O
: O
4.000 O
Pounds O
. O

To O
His O
Excellency O
Count O
Galeazzo O
Ciano B-PERS
di I-PERS
Cortellazzo I-PERS
Minister B-ORG
of I-ORG
Foreign I-ORG
Affairs I-ORG
, O
Rome B-LOC
Budapest B-LOC
, O
8th B-DATE
May I-DATE
1942 I-DATE
, O
XX O
Re O
: O
Semitism O
and O
anti O
- O
Semitism O
in O
Hungary B-LOC
. O

Sir O
, O
The O
program O
of O
anti O
- O
Jewish O
policy O
outlined O
by O
President O
Kállay B-PERS
in O
his O
speeches O
to O
the O
Lower O
Chamber O
and O
to O
the O
Party O
’s O
National O
Council O
( O
20th B-DATE
March I-DATE
and O
20th B-DATE
April I-DATE
last O
) O
and O
the O
measures O
that O
followed O
represent O
the O
start O
of O
a O
new O
stage O
in O
Hungary B-LOC
’ O
s O
official O
anti O
- O
Semitism O
. O

This O
R. O
Legation O
has O
repeatedly O
reported O
on O
the O
various O
developments O
and O
on O
individual O
aspects O
of O
the O
Jewish O
problem O
in O
this O
Country O
, O
highlighting O
along O
the O
way O
the O
various O
obstacles O
that O
have O
hindered O
the O
implementation O
of O
radical O
measures O
, O
the O
conflicting O
opinions O
within O
the O
Country O
, O
the O
Clergy O
and O
Parliament O
on O
the O
issue O
of O
anti O
- O
Jewish O
legislation O
, O
and O
on O
the O
frequent O
compromises O
ensuing O
from O
the O
doubts O
of O
a O
public O
opinion O
at O
times O
unconvinced O
that O
a O
drastic O
action O
is O
wise O
. O

However O
, O
the O
general O
situation O
in O
which O
the O
Jewish O
problem O
now O
again O
surfaces O
on O
the O
Hungarian B-LOC
political O
scene O
has O
changed O
deeply O
since O
the O
day O
when O
Hungary B-LOC
, O
linking O
its O
destiny O
to O
that O
of O
the O
Axis O
Powers O
, O
necessarily O
had O
to O
do O
away O
, O
even O
in O
its O
interior O
politics O
, O
with O
many O
hesitations O
and O
many O
formal O
shackles O
. O

Herein O
lies O
precisely O
the O
interest O
that O
the O
Jewish O
problem O
continues O
to O
attract O
after O
the O
emphatic O
and O
formally O
definitive O
official O
stance O
taken O
by O
the O
present O
Government O
. O

We O
will O
not O
desist O
from O
the O
struggle O
– O
said O
Kállay O
– O
until O
with O
a O
systematic O
and O
ever O
increasing O
pace O
we O
have O
taken O
away O
from O
the O
Jews O
every O
sector O
of O
national O
life O
and O
we O
have O
at O
last O
entirely O
removed O
them O
from O
our O
Country O
. O

In O
order O
to O
appreciate O
the O
significance O
of O
these O
words O
and O
to O
understand O
the O
complexity O
of O
the O
situation O
to O
which O
they O
refer O
it O
might O
be O
worthwhile O
to O
briefly O
reconsider O
the O
fundamental O
aspects O
of O
the O
Jewish O
problem O
in O
Hungary B-LOC
. O

Among O
the O
other O
misfortunes O
which O
befell O
this O
Country O
at O
the O
time O
of O
the O
Turkish B-LOC
invasion O
there O
was O
also O
the O
influx O
of O
many O
Jews O
who O
found O
a O
favourable O
situation O
under O
the O
Crescent O
. O

The O
expulsion O
of O
the O
Turks O
caused O
most O
of O
them O
to O
leave O
. O

Later O
, O
the O
severe O
decrees O
of O
the O
Habsburgs O
, O
particularly O
Charles B-PERS
III I-PERS
and O
Maria B-PERS
Theresa I-PERS
, O
helped O
to O
keep O
the O
Jews O
away O
from O
Hungary B-LOC
. O

Between O
1820 B-DATE
and O
1830 B-DATE
, O
however O
, O
there O
began O
that O
exodus O
of O
Jews O
from O
Galicia B-LOC
to O
the O
Hungarian B-LOC
territory O
which O
would O
continue O
uninterrupted O
into O
our O
own O
times O
, O
encouraged O
by O
the O
rise O
of O
capitalism O
and O
by O
the O
policies O
of O
the O
liberal O
governments O
that O
enabled O
the O
Jews O
to O
acquire O
predominance O
particularly O
in O
culture O
and O
in O
the O
economy O
. O

The O
census O
of O
1930 B-DATE
registered O
444,565 O
Jews O
then O
present O
in O
Hungary B-LOC
, O
to O
whom O
one O
must O
add O
78,190 O
in O
Upper O
Hungary O
( O
First O
Vienna O
Award O
) O
, O
103,000 O
in O
Subcarpathia O
and O
148,288 O
in O
Transylvania B-LOC
( O
Second O
Vienna O
Award O
) O
. O

Today O
there O
are O
approx O
. O

800,000 O
Jews O
living O
in O
Hungary B-LOC
, O
that O
is O
about O
6.2 O
% O
of O
the O
Hungarian B-LOC
population O
( O
13,500,000 O
) O
, O
a O
percentage O
that O
within O
Europe O
is O
exceeded O
only O
by O
Poland B-LOC
, O
by O
Lithuania B-LOC
and O
perhaps O
by O
Romania B-LOC
. O

In O
the O
capital B-LOC
only O
( O
1,110,000 O
) O
the O
Jews O
are O
over O
200,000 O
and O
have O
attained O
preeminent O
positions O
in O
banking O
, O
in O
manufacturing O
, O
in O
commerce O
, O
in O
journalism O
and O
in O
the O
arts O
. O

Even O
the O
Hungarian O
aristocracy O
, O
which O
together O
with O
the O
great O
landowning O
middle O
classes O
has O
for O
centuries O
held O
the O
leadership O
of O
the O
Country O
and O
has O
controlled O
it O
politically O
, O
has O
been O
unable O
or O
unwilling O
to O
oppose O
this O
invasion O
and O
in O
the O
end O
even O
acquiesced O
to O
it O
through O
a O
great O
many O
marriages O
that O
proved O
eminently O
useful O
to O
the O
Jews O
for O
strengthening O
their O
position O
in O
political O
life O
. O

The O
numerous O
Liberal- O
Masonic O
associations O
which O
emerged O
in O
Hungary B-LOC
in O
the O
second O
half O
of O
the O
past O
century O
and O
the O
Democratic O
Party O
, O
which O
immediately O
became O
the O
only O
workers O
’ O
party O
with O
a O
western O
- O
style O
organization O
, O
formed O
the O
framework O
which O
protected O
Jewish O
activity O
and O
the O
breeding O
ground O
both O
of O
the O
democratic O
revolution O
of O
October B-DATE
1918 I-DATE
and O
of O
the O
Communist O
revolution O
of O
March B-DATE
1919 I-DATE
. O

Statistics O
show O
better O
than O
any O
discourse O
the O
extent O
of O
the O
Jewish O
invasion O
into O
Hungarian B-LOC
life O
. O

If O
we O
limit O
our O
analysis O
to O
Budapest B-LOC
, O
which O
sums O
up O
the O
general O
situation O
, O
we O
will O
find O
the O
following O
percentages O
in O
1935 B-DATE
: O
bankers O
80 O
% O
; O
transport O
70 O
% O
; O
stockbrokers O
76 O
% O
; O
jewellers O
74 O
% O
; O
typographers O
73 O
% O
; O
owners O
of O
public O
establishments O
57 O
% O
; O
lawyers O
52 O
% O
; O
doctors O
40 O
% O
; O
journalists O
35 O
% O
. O

In O
the O
country O
, O
only O
10 O
% O
of O
the O
great O
landowners O
( O
over O
100 O
Jugers O
) O
are O
Jews O
, O
but O
among O
the O
tenants O
of O
great O
properties O
the O
Jews O
number O
42 O
% O
. O

As O
for O
the O
manufacturing O
sector O
, O
the O
presence O
of O
Jews O
is O
shown O
by O
the O
following O
numbers O
: O
iron O
and O
steel O
50 O
% O
, O
machinery O
43 O
% O
, O
timber O
53 O
% O
, O
leather O
68 O
% O
, O
textiles O
66 O
% O
, O
clothing O
73 O
% O
, O
paper O
58 O
% O
, O
chemistry O
54 O
% O
, O
etc O
. O

After O
the O
fall O
of O
the O
Bethlen B-PERS
Cabinet O
( O
1932 B-DATE
) O
, O
whose O
policy O
had O
greatly O
facilitated O
Jewish O
intrusiveness O
, O
the O
Gömbös B-PERS
Government O
marked O
the O
beginning O
of O
a O
resistance O
movement O
, O
solicited O
and O
demanded O
by O
the O
emergent O
far O
right O
organizations O
that O
were O
increasingly O
exerting O
their O
influence O
on O
the O
Daranyi B-PERS
, O
Imredi B-PERS
etc O
. O

governments O
that O
came O
later O
. O

The O
first O
anti O
- O
Jewish O
law O
dates O
from O
April B-DATE
1938 I-DATE
. O

The O
text O
avoided O
the O
word O
“ O
Jews O
” O
and O
granted O
such O
ample O
discrimination O
as O
to O
leave O
almost O
unaltered O
the O
average O
presence O
of O
Jews O
in O
the O
different O
sectors O
of O
Hungarian B-LOC
life O
. O

The O
pressure O
exerted O
by O
the O
rightist O
parties O
and O
the O
repercussions O
from O
the O
international O
situation O
prompted O
the O
second O
Jewish O
law O
in O
December B-DATE
1938 I-DATE
, O
whose O
fundamental O
principles O
are O
derived O
from O
the O
Italian B-LOC
anti O
- O
Jewish O
law O
of O
10th B-DATE
November I-DATE
1939 I-DATE
[ O
sic O
! O
, O
actually O
1938 O
] O
and O
which O
, O
in O
determining O
the O
definition O
of O
Jew O
according O
to O
fundamentally O
racial O
criteria O
, O
contains O
– O
numerous O
exceptions O
notwithstanding O
– O
severe O
measures O
. O
