Maria B-PER
Landwirt I-PER
Testimony O
( O
doc O
. O

301/1538 O
) O
Original O
, O
manuscript O
, O
2 O
pages O
, O
210 O
x O
295 O
mm O
, O
Polish O
language O
Oświęcim B-LOC
[ I-LOC
Auschwitz I-LOC
] I-LOC
, O
Bergen B-LOC
- I-LOC
Belsen I-LOC
, O
Aschersleben B-LOC
Maria B-PER
Landwirt I-PER
born O
7.3.1927 O
in O
Antwerp B-LOC
. O

Raised O
in O
Poland B-LOC
. O

The O
war B-TER
found O
her O
in O
Cracow B-LOC
. O

On O
March O
20 O
, O
she O
found O
herself O
[ O
in O
] O
the O
ghetto B-TER
; O
she O
was O
deported B-TER
; O
on O
March O
12 O
, O
1943 O
, O
she O
got O
into O
the O
Płaszów B-LOC
camp B-TER
. O

She O
was O
told O
about O
the O
hanging B-TER
of O
two O
20 O
- O
year O
old O
girls B-TER
for O
leaving O
the O
camp B-TER
and O
going O
to O
the O
city O
without O
permits O
, O
which O
made O
a O
strong O
impression O
on O
her O
. O

Besides O
, O
nothing O
bad O
happened O
to O
her O
personally O
there O
. O

On O
August O
6 O
, O
1944 O
she O
was O
sent O
to O
Oświęcim B-LOC
. O

135 O
people O
rode O
in O
a O
cattle B-TER
car I-TER
with O
her O
; O
at O
the O
station O
the O
children B-TER
and O
the O
elderly O
were O
segregated O
. O

Then O
they O
were O
all O
taken O
in O
front O
of O
the O
baths O
and O
there O
, O
in O
the O
presence O
of O
KP B-TER
- I-TER
men I-TER
, O
KP O
- O
men O
, O
kapomen O
– O
a O
kapo O
( O
an O
inmate O
functionary O
) O
all O
women B-TER
had O
to O
strip O
naked O
; O
then O
they O
were O
all O
taken O
to O
a O
shed O
, O
where O
they O
waited O
for O
a O
bath O
all O
night O
, O
naked O
, O
without O
food B-TER
. O

For O
the O
slightest O
movement O
they O
were O
beaten O
with O
crops O
at O
random O
by O
the O
kapomen B-TER
. O

At O
daybreak O
they O
went O
to O
the O
baths O
in O
groups O
; O
they O
were O
deprived O
of O
all O
their O
belongings O
; O
they O
were O
shaved O
, O
their O
heads O
, O
armpits O
and O
nether O
regions O
. O

They O
were O
shaved O
by O
men O
and O
women O
. O

Wet O
after O
the O
bath O
, O
they O
were O
chucked O
out O
into O
a O
room O
( O
most O
women O
had O
been O
deprived O
of O
their O
shoes B-TER
) O
, O
where O
were O
thrown O
some O
rags B-TER
which O
they O
put O
on O
wet O
bodies O
. O

They O
were O
convinced O
they O
were O
going O
to O
a O
crematory B-TER
, O
but O
they O
were O
taken O
to O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

During O
her O
stay O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
it O
once O
happened O
that O
a O
certain O
Hungarian B-TER
woman B-TER
overslept O
and O
did O
n’t O
report O
for O
roll B-TER
call I-TER
. O

A O
search O
began O
and O
when O
they O
found O
her O
the O
Lagerführer O
laid O
her O
on O
the O
ground O
and O
kept O
kicking O
and O
beating O
her O
, O
in O
full O
view O
of O
everybody O
, O
until O
she O
expired O
. O

The O
most O
horrible O
thing O
were O
selections O
. O

That O
’s O
when O
the O
German B-TER
doctor B-TER
Mengele B-PER
In O
the O
text O
: O
Mengerle O
appeared O
. O

He O
arranged O
all O
the O
women B-TER
, O
stripped O
naked O
, O
into O
rows O
and O
removed O
those O
he O
did O
n’t O
like O
from O
the O
rows O
. O

Those O
women B-TER
were O
then O
closed O
for O
24 O
hours O
in O
small O
rooms O
, O
duty O
rooms O
, O
without O
food B-TER
, O
and O
after O
that O
a O
truck O
came O
and O
took O
them O
to O
the O
crematory B-TER
in O
Brzezinka B-LOC
In O
the O
text O
: O
in O
Brzezinki O
b. O
There O
were O
usually O
about O
100 O
of O
such O
victims O
. O

We O
lived O
in O
the O
constant O
fear O
of O
death B-TER
. O

On O
October O
31 O
, O
1944 O
, O
3000 O
women B-TER
were O
sent B-TER
from O
Oświęcim B-LOC
to O
Bergen B-LOC
- I-LOC
Belsen I-LOC
. O

We O
stood O
outdoors O
throughout O
the O
night O
in O
our O
camp B-TER
rags B-TER
, O
waiting O
for O
a O
bath O
. O

After O
the O
bath O
there O
was O
another O
selection B-TER
. O

The O
elderly O
, O
slim O
or O
pregnant O
women B-TER
, O
as O
well O
as O
children B-TER
were O
destined O
for O
death B-TER
and O
immediately O
separated O
. O

The O
rest O
was O
given O
better O
clothes B-TER
for O
the O
transport B-TER
. O

There O
rode O
65 O
women B-TER
in O
each O
cattle B-TER
car I-TER
. O

They O
were O
given O
sufficient O
food B-TER
for O
the O
journey O
for O
it O
consisted O
of O
one O
loaf O
of O
bread B-TER
, O
10 O
dkg O
of O
margarine B-TER
and O
15 O
dkg O
of O
sausage B-TER
per O
head O
for O
the O
three O
days O
. O

They O
relieved O
nature O
in O
the O
closed O
car O
. O

After O
three O
days O
they O
arrived O
in O
Bergen B-LOC
- I-LOC
Belsen I-LOC
. O

They O
reported O
for O
roll B-TER
call I-TER
, O
where O
they O
were O
kept O
for O
5 O
hours O
, O
after O
which O
they O
were O
taken O
to O
tents B-TER
, O
where O
there O
was O
a O
bit O
of O
damp O
straw O
and O
2 O
thin O
blankets O
per O
each O
. O

They O
washed O
outdoors O
in O
December O
, O
at O
water O
taps O
, O
usually O
at O
dawn O
. O

One O
day O
the O
tents B-TER
were O
torn O
away O
by O
a O
storm O
, O
so O
the O
prisoners B-TER
were O
moved O
to O
the O
camp B-TER
kitchen O
, O
where O
those O
1500 O
women B-TER
stayed O
squeezed O
for O
4 O
days O
. O

Then O
they O
were O
moved O
to O
the O
barracks B-TER
left O
by O
American B-TER
citizens O
, O
where O
it O
was O
more O
bearable O
while O
in O
terms O
of O
food B-TER
, O
it O
was O
disastrous O
as O
they O
were O
sometimes O
given O
nothing O
for O
24 O
hours O
. O

That O
depended O
on O
the O
Sturmmann O
’s O
SS O
- O
Sturmmann O
– O
a O
military O
rank O
in O
the O
SS O
( O
the O
equivalent O
of O
Corporal O
) O
2 O
disposition O
. O

After O
3 O
pm O
it O
was O
dark O
, O
so O
they O
usually O
went O
to O
sleep O
. O

There O
was O
no O
work O
and O
they O
were O
afflicted O
by O
idleness O
and O
hunger B-TER
. O

After O
three O
months O
they O
took O
us O
to O
Aschersleben B-LOC
( O
near O
Magdeburg B-LOC
) O
. O

Our O
work B-TER
consisted O
in O
testing O
pipes O
for O
airplanes O
. O

We O
sabotaged B-TER
that O
work O
with O
the O
knowledge O
of O
the O
German B-TER
foreman O
Otto B-PER
Riesener I-PER
. O

There O
it O
was O
bearable O
, O
but O
on O
April O
12 O
we O
were O
sent O
towards O
Dachau B-LOC
. O

It O
turned O
out O
, O
however O
, O
that O
the O
road O
we O
were O
supposed O
to O
take O
was O
occupied O
. O

In O
Zörbig B-LOC
, O
In O
the O
text O
: O
Zerbig O
it O
turned O
out O
that O
the O
Americans B-TER
were O
30 O
km O
away O
from O
Leipzig B-LOC
, O
so O
part O
of O
SS B-TER
men I-TER
fled O
and O
the O
rest O
rode O
with O
the O
prisoners B-TER
on O
carts O
. O

Part O
of O
the O
women B-TER
fled B-TER
to O
the O
forest O
and O
that O
’s O
where O
they O
waited O
until O
the O
American B-TER
army B-TER
came O
on O
April O
15 O
, O
1945 O
. O

Cracow B-LOC
, O
August O
27 O
, O
1945 O
Margoth B-PER
Landwirth I-PER
Written O
down O
by O
Dr B-PER
Laura I-PER
Eichhornowa I-PER
