The O
person O
in O
question O
has O
given O
us O
the O
following O
information O
: O
At O
the O
beginning O
of O
October O
, O
1944 O
, O
I O
worked O
for O
Department B-ORG
A I-ORG
, O
that O
is O
, O
for O
children B-TER
’s O
department O
of O
the O
International B-ORG
Red I-ORG
Cross I-ORG
with O
its O
head O
office O
in O
4 B-LOC
Mérleg I-LOC
Street I-LOC
. O

My O
job O
was O
to O
administer O
less O
and O
more O
dangerous O
projects O
. O

As O
during O
this O
period O
call B-TER
- I-TER
up I-TER
placards I-TER
were O
placed O
practically O
every O
hour O
on O
the O
walls O
of O
the O
houses O
of O
Budapest B-LOC
and O
because O
( O
understandably O
) O
basically O
no O
one O
felt O
like O
being O
called B-TER
up I-TER
it O
was O
a O
part O
of O
our O
activity O
to O
produce O
forged B-TER
documents I-TER
including O
different O
kinds O
of O
baptismal O
certificates O
, O
exemption O
letters O
given O
by O
ammunition O
plants O
and O
by O
other O
organisations O
, O
etc O
. O

In O
practice O
we O
were O
manufacturing B-TER
these O
documents O
on O
a O
large O
scale O
and O
distributed B-TER
them O
to O
people O
of O
all O
social O
layers O
, O
ranks O
and O
religions O
. O

From O
the O
office O
we O
went O
to O
brick B-TER
factories I-TER
and O
to O
other O
places O
where O
the O
Arrow B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
concentrated B-TER
masses O
of O
Jews O
. O

Several O
times O
also O
György B-PER
Aczél I-PER
participated O
in O
these O
rescue B-TER
actions O
( O
he O
is O
now O
the O
local O
leader O
of O
the O
Communist B-TER
Party I-TER
in O
the O
5th B-LOC
district I-LOC
) O
, O
and O
in O
several O
cases O
we O
managed O
to O
free B-TER
the O
unfortunate O
Jews O
, O
especially O
women B-TER
staying O
in O
the O
brick B-TER
factory I-TER
. O

Later O
, O
4 B-LOC
Mérleg I-LOC
Street I-LOC
became O
a O
temporary O
asylum B-TER
especially O
for O
the O
part O
of O
enormous O
masses O
of O
children B-TER
who O
were O
brought O
to O
the O
office O
or O
were O
often O
just O
dropped O
in O
front O
of O
the O
gate O
. O

People O
, O
Christians O
also O
kept O
on O
notifying O
us O
about O
children B-TER
whose O
relatives O
had O
been O
taken O
away O
by O
the O
Arrow B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
and O
now O
stayed O
in O
abandoned O
flats O
lacking O
any O
supervision O
. O

Most O
of O
our O
energies O
were O
spent O
on O
collecting O
these O
Jewish O
orphans B-TER
from O
the O
furthest O
points O
of O
the O
city O
, O
from O
the O
suburbs O
, O
from O
Angyalföld B-LOC
, O
etc O
. O

I O
remember O
a O
case O
when O
in O
Bulcsu B-LOC
Street I-LOC
we O
collected O
a O
large O
number O
of O
abandoned O
children B-TER
and O
brought O
them O
to O
the O
office O
by O
car O
. O

We O
had O
so O
much O
work O
to O
do O
that O
we O
could O
hardly O
cope O
with O
it O
. O

We O
collected O
the O
children B-TER
with O
the O
escort O
of O
the O
police B-TER
. O

Soon O
we O
had O
to O
provide O
their O
accommodation B-TER
. O

We O
established O
a O
gathering O
and O
selecting O
office O
in O
4 B-LOC
Perczel I-LOC
Mór I-LOC
Street I-LOC
where O
we O
took O
the O
children B-TER
escorted O
by O
the O
police B-TER
to O
distributed O
them O
among O
the O
different O
orphanages B-TER
that O
we O
set O
up O
in O
the O
meantime O
. O

We O
were O
bringing O
and O
carrying O
children B-TER
with O
no O
end O
. O

Later O
, O
we O
received O
the O
building O
in O
16 B-LOC
Teleki I-LOC
Pál I-LOC
Street I-LOC
, O
where O
we O
gathered O
around O
1,000 O
children B-TER
. O

There O
were O
other O
orphanages B-TER
in O
76 B-LOC
Szondy I-LOC
Street I-LOC
, O
5 B-LOC
- I-LOC
7 I-LOC
and I-LOC
25 I-LOC
Munkácsy I-LOC
Mihály I-LOC
Street I-LOC
, O
and O
at O
different O
points O
of O
the O
city B-LOC
in O
a O
lot O
of O
places O
. O

When O
the O
surviving O
Jews O
of O
Budapest B-LOC
were O
put O
into O
the O
ghetto B-TER
our O
rescue B-TER
actions O
became O
even O
more O
frequent O
. O

The O
building O
in O
Mérleg B-LOC
Street I-LOC
was O
practically O
attacked O
by O
fugitives O
. O

Reports O
about O
abandoned O
children B-TER
got O
more O
frequent O
. O

As O
it O
is O
well O
known O
, O
they O
published O
a O
decree O
that O
all O
Jews O
– O
including O
the O
children B-TER
of O
orphanages B-TER
– O
had O
to O
go O
into O
the O
ghetto B-TER
. O

Delegate B-ORG
Weyermann B-PER
managed O
to O
get O
a O
six- O
day O
- O
postponement O
regarding O
the O
transport O
of O
the O
orphanages B-TER
, O
and O
added O
to O
it O
another O
6 O
days O
, O
finally O
further O
12 O
days O
. O

Orphanages B-TER
functioned O
relatively O
well O
despite O
adverse O
circumstances O
. O

Naturally O
, O
food B-TER
was O
supplied O
by O
the O
International B-ORG
Red I-ORG
Cross I-ORG
. O

In O
the O
days O
before O
Christmas O
, O
we O
had O
to O
take O
children B-TER
often O
for O
walks O
with O
the O
escort O
of O
the O
police B-TER
since O
the O
Arrow B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
appeared O
more O
and O
more O
frequently O
in O
one O
orphanage B-TER
or O
another O
and O
demanded O
we O
transported B-TER
the O
children B-TER
into O
the O
ghetto B-TER
immediately O
. O

Also O
on O
a O
sad O
day O
, O
just O
a O
few O
days O
before O
Christmas O
, O
they O
appeared O
in O
the O
orphanage B-TER
of O
5 B-LOC
- I-LOC
7 I-LOC
Munkácsy I-LOC
Mihály I-LOC
Street I-LOC
. O

Party O
men O
of O
the O
Arrow B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
with O
signs O
of O
Árpád O
’s O
stripes O
closed O
the O
street O
and O
surrounded O
the O
whole O
building O
. O

The O
building O
had O
military B-TER
guards I-TER
, O
a O
squad O
of O
Auxiliary O
Force O
Unit O
. O

Invading O
Arrow B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
men O
shot O
among O
the O
children B-TER
killing B-TER
around O
10 O
- O
15 O
children B-TER
and O
some O
adults O
. O

They O
justified O
their O
act O
claiming O
that O
children B-TER
defended O
themselves O
. O

The O
leader O
of O
the O
orphanage B-TER
was O
Lajos B-PER
Kraszner I-PER
, O
who O
was O
later O
put O
into O
the O
ghetto B-TER
. O

When O
we O
returned O
to O
the O
orphanage B-TER
with O
delegate B-ORG
Weyermann B-PER
we O
found O
a O
horrifying O
scene O
. O

For O
example O
, O
in O
one O
of O
the O
armchairs O
two O
children B-TER
were O
sitting O
embracing O
each O
other O
also O
in O
death B-TER
. O

We O
found O
a O
walled O
up O
door O
barricaded O
with O
all O
kinds O
of O
furniture O
. O

We O
managed O
to O
save O
the O
people O
who O
survived O
uninjured O
in O
the O
room O
behind O
. O

In O
another O
case O
, O
before O
this O
attack O
happened O
, O
the O
Arrow B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
took O
children B-TER
away O
, O
claiming O
they O
were O
going O
to O
take O
them O
into O
Síp B-LOC
Street I-LOC
, O
but O
instead O
, O
they O
took O
them O
into O
an O
abandoned O
ruined O
house O
in O
Szív B-LOC
Street I-LOC
- O
as O
they O
claimed O
- O
out O
of O
mistake O
. O

When O
we O
were O
informed O
we O
rushed O
there O
and O
demanded O
the O
children B-TER
from O
the O
janitor O
. O

We O
managed O
to O
get O
back O
around O
200 O
children B-TER
and O
smuggle B-TER
them O
back O
into O
Munkácsy B-LOC
Street I-LOC
. O

Once O
, O
Arrow B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
gangsters O
appeared O
also O
in O
the O
orphanage B-TER
of O
112 B-LOC
Róna I-LOC
Street I-LOC
. O

They O
killed B-TER
around O
50 O
- O
60 O
children B-TER
who O
were O
kept O
there O
, O
the O
rest O
could O
run O
away O
. O

Also O
the O
officers O
of O
the O
institute O
, O
including O
its O
head O
Pál B-PER
Vidor I-PER
, O
lost O
their O
lives O
during O
this O
attack B-TER
. O

International B-ORG
Red I-ORG
Cross I-ORG
had O
a O
so O
- O
called O
T O
( O
transport B-TER
) O
department O
. O

We O
went O
into O
the O
ghetto B-TER
with O
this O
department O
and O
smuggled B-TER
people O
out O
into O
places O
that O
had O
been O
arranged O
beforehand O
. O

This O
way O
we O
managed O
to O
free B-TER
around O
20 O
people O
from O
the O
ghetto B-TER
helped O
by O
the O
police B-TER
inside O
. O

It O
was O
anyway O
thanks O
to O
the O
policemen B-TER
that O
we O
could O
freely O
enter O
and O
leave O
the O
ghetto B-TER
and O
bring O
children B-TER
out O
into O
the O
orphanages B-TER
. O

Children B-TER
in O
the O
ghetto B-TER
lived O
in O
terrible O
squalor O
. O

We O
tried O
to O
smuggle B-TER
out O
as O
many O
as O
possible O
but O
also O
those O
who O
remained O
depended O
on O
our O
food B-TER
provisions O
. O

I O
was O
the O
link O
between O
delegate B-ORG
Weyermann B-PER
and O
the O
leader O
of O
Zionists B-TER
Ottó B-PER
Komoly I-PER
. O

January O
the O
first O
, O
we O
were O
sitting O
together O
in O
the O
lobby O
of O
Ritz B-LOC
, O
when O
four O
men O
with O
signs B-ORG
of I-ORG
Árpád I-ORG
’s I-ORG
stripes I-ORG
came O
to O
us O
and O
grabbed O
Ottó B-PER
Komoly I-PER
giving O
their O
word O
of O
honour O
that O
it O
was O
only O
about O
an O
inquiry O
and O
that O
they O
were O
going O
to O
bring O
him O
back O
in O
half O
an O
hour O
. O

Ottó B-PER
Komoly I-PER
has O
gone O
missing O
since O
then O
. O

When O
the O
international O
ghetto B-TER
was O
established O
the O
current O
ministerial O
secretary O
Dr B-PER
György I-PER
Gergely I-PER
initiated O
to O
transform O
two O
buildings O
( O
16 B-LOC
and I-LOC
23 I-LOC
Pozsonyi I-LOC
Road I-LOC
) O
into O
protected B-TER
houses I-TER
of O
the O
International B-ORG
Red I-ORG
Cross I-ORG
using O
forged O
documents O
. O

We O
came O
up O
with O
the O
idea O
that O
the O
International B-ORG
Red I-ORG
Cross I-ORG
was O
also O
a O
diplomatic B-TER
institution O
, O
and O
as O
such O
we O
could O
protect B-TER
the O
inhabitants O
of O
these O
houses O
like O
the O
Swiss B-ORG
, O
the O
Swedish B-LOC
, O
the O
Portuguese B-LOC
, O
the O
Spanish B-LOC
, O
or O
the O
papal B-LOC
legate B-TER
protected O
others O
. O

There O
were O
around O
1,500 O
men B-TER
and O
women B-TER
put O
up O
in O
these O
houses O
, O
who O
we O
gave O
excellent O
food B-TER
supplies O
. O

These O
protected O
people O
were O
not O
touched O
nor O
molested O
by O
the O
Arrow B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
, O
they O
had O
to O
go O
the O
ghetto B-TER
only O
the O
last O
week O
. O

