stamp O
on O
the O
left O
: O
Committee O
to O
Collect O
Material O
about O
the O
Destruction O
of O
Polish B-TER
Jewry O
1939 O
Blumberg B-PER
Leyb I-PER
Born O
in O
1915 O
, O
Warsaw B-LOC
Testimony O
number O
6 O
( O
recorded O
on O
16th O
November O
, O
1939 O
) O
I O
There O
are O
no O
personal O
pronouns O
and O
no O
auxiliary O
verbs O
in O
the O
record O
( O
probably O
in O
order O
to O
save O
time O
) O
, O
so O
it O
’s O
impossible O
to O
know O
if O
it O
is O
the O
1st O
or O
the O
3rd O
person O
. O

left O
Warsaw B-LOC
on O
14th O
October O
. O

Before O
, O
I O
had O
been O
hidden B-TER
all O
the O
time O
on O
Bonifraterska B-LOC
street I-LOC
4 I-LOC
. O

I O
did O
n’t O
see O
any O
scenes O
. O

The O
house O
was O
not O
damaged O
by O
bombings B-TER
. O

I O
reached O
Vilnius B-LOC
by O
the O
Małkinia B-LOC
– O
Białystok B-LOC
road O
. O

I O
went O
on O
foot O
, O
in O
the O
company O
of O
Christian B-TER
workers O
who O
were O
going O
to O
the O
Soviets B-TER
. O

There O
was O
also O
a O
prisoner B-TER
from O
the O
region O
of O
Vilnius B-LOC
. O

We O
got O
through O
safely O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
did O
not O
bother O
us O
. O

I O
heard O
a O
lot O
of O
stories O
, O
but O
do O
n’t O
remember O
any O
. O

The O
border O
was O
open O
, O
we O
reached O
Vilnius B-LOC
without O
difficulties O
. O

