Regional O
historical O
commission O
Białystok B-LOC
, O
July O
2 O
, O
1945 O
[ O
? O
] O
number O
35 O
My O
experiences O
during O
the O
German B-TER
occupation I-TER
Told O
by O
Żółtak B-PER
Etke I-PER
, O
17 O
years O
old O
, O
who O
was O
born O
and O
lived O
until O
the O
liquidation B-TER
of I-TER
the I-TER
ghetto I-TER
in O
Czyżew B-LOC
, O
Wysokie B-LOC
Mazowieckie I-LOC
county O
, O
voivodeship O
of O
Białystok B-LOC
. O

In O
hiding B-TER
since O
the O
1st O
of O
November O
, O
1942 O
in O
the O
same O
area O
. O

Lived O
in O
Białystok B-LOC
for O
a O
certain O
time O
after O
the O
liberation B-TER
. O

She O
wrote O
the O
protocol O
herself O
. O

When O
I O
heard O
the O
shots O
on O
the O
night O
of O
the O
1st O
of O
November O
, O
I O
understood O
that O
the O
Germans B-TER
would O
definitely O
deport B-TER
the O
Jews O
again O
. O

I O
decided O
to O
run B-TER
away I-TER
. O

I O
quickly O
got O
hold O
of O
an O
axe O
, O
cut O
through O
the O
wires O
and O
was O
out O
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
noticed O
me O
and O
started O
to O
shoot O
at O
me O
but O
I O
ran O
away O
not O
paying O
attention O
to O
the O
bullets O
. O

I O
went O
to O
a O
village O
, O
which O
was O
located O
9 O
kilometers O
away O
from O
the O
town O
, O
to O
[ O
H]elenowo B-LOC
, O
in O
the O
municipality O
of O
Szulborze B-LOC
- I-LOC
Koty I-LOC
, O
Wysokie B-LOC
Mazowieckie I-LOC
county O
, O
voivodeship O
of O
Białystok B-LOC
. O

I O
came O
to O
a O
peasant O
I O
knew O
, O
Szwiantkewic B-PER
[ I-PER
Świątkiewicz I-PER
] I-PER
Franciszek I-PER
, O
and O
asked O
him O
to O
hide B-TER
me O
for O
a O
few O
days O
. O

In O
the O
beginning O
he O
was O
not O
willing O
, O
because O
he O
was O
afraid O
, O
but O
I O
told O
him O
that O
no O
one O
saw O
me O
coming O
and O
he O
then O
answered O
that O
he O
would O
keep O
me O
until O
the O
12th O
of O
November O
. O

It O
made O
me O
very O
happy O
. O

I O
was O
not O
thinking O
about O
later O
. O

I O
entered O
into O
a O
cellar O
and O
spent O
all O
those O
days O
there O
. O

During O
night O
time O
I O
would O
go O
out O
for O
a O
short O
time O
in O
the O
street O
to O
get O
some O
fresh O
air O
, O
because O
there O
was O
no O
window O
in O
the O
cellar O
and O
during O
the O
day O
the O
entrance O
to O
the O
cellar O
was O
covered O
with O
hay O
. O

I O
would O
only O
eat O
at O
4 O
in O
the O
morning O
and O
at O
1[0 O
? O
] O
in O
the O
evening O
, O
when O
no O
strangers O
were O
around O
. O

On O
the O
12th O
of O
November O
1942 O
the O
peasant O
told O
me O
to O
go O
. O

As O
I O
was O
afraid O
of O
the O
Germans B-TER
, O
I O
went O
to O
the O
home O
of O
another O
peasant O
in O
the O
same O
village O
, O
Bogucki B-PER
Jan I-PER
. O

I O
knew O
that O
she O
[= O
Bogucki B-PER
’ I-PER
s O
wife B-TER
] O
has O
a O
room O
, O
closed O
with O
a O
double O
wall O
. O

I O
asked O
her O
to O
let O
me O
stay O
in O
their O
place O
. O

I O
told O
her O
that O
if O
she O
wanted O
, O
I O
would O
knit O
her O
from O
wool O
anything O
she O
liked O
. O

Then O
it O
was O
agreed O
I O
would O
spend O
a O
month O
with O
her O
. O

On O
the O
22nd O
of O
November O
, O
as O
I O
was O
sitting O
in O
my O
hiding B-TER
place I-TER
, O
Bogucka B-PER
ran O
in O
to O
tell O
me O
that O
there O
were O
police B-TER
in O
the O
village O
and O
they O
were O
making O
searches O
. O

I O
quickly O
left O
my O
hiding B-TER
place I-TER
and O
ran O
for O
the O
woods O
. O

In O
the O
forest O
, O
I O
hid B-TER
in O
a O
hole B-TER
in I-TER
the I-TER
ground I-TER
and O
waited O
until O
the O
night O
came O
and O
I O
could O
go O
back O
to O
the O
village O
, O
to O
my O
hiding B-TER
place I-TER
. O

At O
night O
, O
when O
I O
came O
back O
from O
the O
forest O
, O
Bogucki B-PER
told O
me O
I O
could O
not O
stay O
in O
his O
house O
anymore O
, O
because O
the O
Germans B-TER
had O
found O
out O
about O
the O
hiding B-TER
place I-TER
and O
he O
was O
afraid O
they O
would O
come O
unannounced O
. O

I O
left O
. O

I O
started O
to O
wander O
around O
the O
villages O
, O
and O
having O
no O
place O
to O
stay O
, O
decided O
to O
go O
to O
Warsaw B-LOC
to O
get O
Polish B-TER
documents B-TER
. O

On O
the O
25th O
of O
December O
1942 O
I O
went O
to O
Warsaw B-LOC
. O

Immediately O
upon O
my O
arrival O
, O
I O
entered O
a O
church O
on O
Chłodna B-LOC
street I-LOC
, O
because O
I O
wanted O
to O
obtain O
a O
birth B-TER
certificate I-TER
from O
a O
priest B-TER
. O

When O
I O
entered O
the O
church O
, O
I O
approached O
a O
priest B-TER
and O
asked O
for O
a O
birth B-TER
certificate I-TER
. O

He O
started O
to O
look O
for O
my O
name O
and O
surname O
in O
the O
registers O
. O

He O
told O
me O
I O
was O
not O
registered O
. O

He O
promised O
to O
issue O
me O
a O
birth B-TER
certificate I-TER
if O
I O
brought O
witnesses O
or O
a O
godmother O
. O

I O
agreed O
. O

I O
went O
out O
in O
the O
street O
to O
look O
for O
some O
woman B-TER
who O
could O
testify O
to O
the O
priest B-TER
. O

While O
searching O
, O
I O
met O
a O
woman B-TER
whom O
I O
asked O
to O
go O
to O
church O
with O
me O
. O

When O
she O
asked O
me O
, O
for O
what O
reason O
, O
I O
told O
her O
I O
would O
tell O
her O
in O
the O
church O
. O

She O
asked O
me O
again O
where O
I O
was O
taking O
her O
, O
and O
then O
I O
told O
her O
I O
wanted O
her O
to O
testify O
to O
the O
priest B-TER
that O
I O
had O
been O
baptized B-TER
in O
the O
church O
. O

In O
the O
beginning O
she O
refused O
, O
but O
when O
I O
gave O
her O
half O
a O
kilo O
butter O
, O
she O
agreed O
to O
go O
with O
me O
. O

The O
priest B-TER
, O
seeing O
that O
I O
brought O
a O
godmother O
, O
issued O
me O
a O
birth B-TER
certificate I-TER
explaining O
that O
I O
was O
registered O
, O
but O
the O
register O
book O
had O
been O
lost O
. O

With O
the O
certificate B-TER
I O
went O
back O
to O
Czyżew B-LOC
. O

I O
looked O
for O
work O
in O
a O
manor O
, O
telling O
that O
I O
came O
from O
Warsaw B-LOC
, O
because O
people O
starve O
there O
. O

The O
German B-TER
, O
not O
suspecting O
anything O
, O
gave O
me O
a O
job O
. O

The O
farm O
where O
I O
worked O
was O
not O
far O
away O
from O
Czyżew B-LOC
. O

On O
the O
10th O
of O
April O
police B-TER
came O
to O
the O
farm O
looking O
for O
a O
Jewish O
girl O
with O
long O
braids O
. O

It O
was O
me O
. O

When O
I O
heard O
about O
it O
, O
I O
wanted O
to O
run O
away O
, O
but O
the O
farm O
had O
already O
been O
surrounded O
by O
lots O
of O
police B-TER
. O

They O
started O
to O
look O
in O
all O
the O
buildings O
and O
could O
not O
find O
anyone O
in O
the O
beginning O
. O

The O
policeman B-TER
Kowalski B-PER
Stefan I-PER
from O
[ O
H]elenowo B-LOC
, O
municipality O
of O
Szulborze B-LOC
- I-LOC
Koty I-LOC
, O
was O
also O
with O
them O
and O
he O
recognized O
me O
and O
gave O
me O
in O
, O
because O
he O
noticed O
me O
working O
in O
the O
manor O
. O

When O
he O
saw O
me O
, O
he O
called O
all O
the O
policemen B-TER
to O
come O
. O

He O
showed O
me O
, O
telling O
them O
that O
I O
was O
a O
Jewish O
girl O
. O

He O
even O
pronounced O
my O
name O
. O

Then O
they O
made O
me O
stand O
against O
a O
wall O
and O
started O
to O
interrogate B-TER
me O
to O
see O
if O
I O
was O
the O
person O
the O
policeman B-TER
claimed O
I O
was O
. O

I O
said O
no O
, O
I O
came O
from O
Warsaw B-LOC
because O
I O
was O
starving O
there O
. O

The O
policeman B-TER
who O
recognized O
me O
told O
me O
I O
was O
telling O
a O
lie O
. O

Then O
they O
started O
asking O
me O
all O
kinds O
of O
questions O
about O
Warsaw B-LOC
and O
made O
me O
recite O
Christian B-TER
prayers O
, O
thinking O
that O
I O
could O
not O
answer O
correctly O
if O
I O
was O
Jewish O
. O

But O
I O
had O
already O
learnt O
everything O
and O
recited O
it O
by O
heart O
as O
a O
Polish B-TER
woman B-TER
would O
. O

After O
long O
hours O
, O
seeing O
that O
I O
do O
not O
speak O
confusedly O
and O
that O
they O
can O
not O
get O
anything O
out O
of O
me O
, O
they O
beat O
the O
policeman B-TER
Kowalski B-PER
and O
let O
me O
go O
free O
, O
thinking O
that O
I O
was O
Polish B-TER
. O

But O
they O
ordered O
me O
to O
come O
to O
Czyżew B-LOC
, O
because O
they O
wanted O
to O
make O
a O
phone O
call O
to O
my O
parents B-TER
in O
Warsaw B-LOC
. O

When O
they O
left O
, O
I O
wanted O
to O
run B-TER
away I-TER
, O
but O
then O
decided O
to O
stay O
. O

On O
the O
11th O
of O
April O
, O
I O
came O
at O
the O
appointed O
time O
. O

I O
told O
them O
an O
invented O
address O
and O
they O
started O
telephoning O
to O
Warsaw B-LOC
. O

When O
they O
received O
an O
answer O
that O
such O
family B-TER
was O
not O
to O
be O
found O
, O
they O
wanted O
to O
shoot B-TER
me O
for O
deceiving O
them O
. O

But O
I O
had O
one O
more O
idea O
: O
I O
asked O
them O
to O
telephone O
to O
the O
magistrate O
, O
explaining O
than O
it O
was O
possible O
that O
my O
mother B-TER
had O
moved O
to O
another O
apartment O
. O

They O
did O
what O
I O
said O
, O
telephoned O
, O
found O
out O
that O
I O
was O
not O
Jewish O
and O
let O
me O
go O
. O

They O
drove O
me O
back O
home O
. O

When O
the O
German B-TER
saw O
me O
, O
he O
told O
me O
I O
was O
alive O
because O
I O
had O
remained O
cold O
- O
blooded O
and O
calm O
. O

From O
then O
on O
, O
he O
would O
not O
allow O
me O
to O
work O
in O
the O
fields O
, O
I O
was O
a O
handmaid O
in O
his O
house O
. O

Etke B-PER
Żółtak I-PER
, O
witness O
Protocol O
written O
by O
[ O
signature O
of O
Etke B-PER
Żółtak I-PER
] O
Chairman O
of O
the O
historical O
commission O
of O
the O
voivodeship O
[ O
signature O
] O
Turek B-PER
