Passage O
from O
a O
letter B-TER
to O
Mr. O
Hugo B-PER
Glaser I-PER
, O
Prague B-LOC
XII O
. O

, O
Zelená B-LOC
7 I-LOC
, O
from O
Mr. O
Berthold B-PER
Burg I-PER
, O
prisoner B-TER
of O
the O
concentration B-TER
camps I-TER
in O
Lodz B-LOC
, O
Poznan B-LOC
, O
Auschwitz B-LOC
and O
Fürstengrube B-LOC
, O
current O
profession O
interpreter O
with O
Co. O
C O
823 O
T.D.Bn O
. O

A.P.O. O
339 O
, O
U.S.Army B-ORG
c O
/ O
o O
Postmaster O
N.Y. O
Dear O
Glasers B-PER
, O
I O
have O
just O
received O
a O
letter B-TER
from O
Napoleon O
and O
I O
am O
as O
happy O
as O
a O
child O
to O
hear O
that O
you O
are O
healthy O
and O
home O
once O
again O
. O

In O
October O
last O
year O
, O
I O
learned O
that O
you O
were O
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
and O
that O
you O
were O
doing O
well O
, O
that O
little O
Hugo B-PER
was O
working O
in O
a O
bakery O
, O
and O
that O
after O
9 O
years O
– O
instead O
of O
after O
9 O
months O
– O
you O
had O
a O
boy B-TER
. O

Where O
, O
pray O
, O
is O
this O
child B-TER
? O
My O
mother O
was O
gassed B-TER
. O

I O
have O
some O
sad O
news O
for O
you O
, O
but O
you O
have O
seen O
so O
much O
that O
we O
need O
not O
hesitate O
, O
especially O
when O
it O
concerns O
our O
dearest O
loved O
ones O
. O

This O
is O
what O
happened O
: O
on O
December O
18th O
, O
1943 O
, O
when O
we O
were O
in O
the O
Fürstengrube B-LOC
camp B-TER
near O
Auschwitz B-LOC
, O
around O
midnight O
, O
the O
afternoon O
shift O
returned O
to O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

I O
was O
in O
KB B-TER
at O
the O
time O
. O

After O
being O
injured O
in O
the O
mine O
, O
I O
had O
a O
bad O
hemorrhage O
in O
my O
ankle O
and O
whatnot O
. O

Max B-PER
was O
a O
Vorarbeiter O
on O
the O
afternoon O
shift O
. O

Two O
days O
earlier O
, O
zugangi O
arrived O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
– O
Galicians B-LOC
– O
Jews O
from O
Galicia B-LOC
. O

Some O
lived O
nearby O
, O
on O
the O
border O
of O
Upper O
Silesia B-LOC
and O
Galicia B-LOC
. O

One O
of O
them O
escaped B-TER
at O
the O
start O
of O
his O
shift O
. O

The O
SS B-TER
was O
celebrating O
Julfest O
that O
day O
. O

When O
the O
shift O
returned O
to O
the O
camp B-TER
, O
Lagerführer B-TER
- O
Hauptscharführer B-TER
Moll B-PER
( O
I O
remember O
his O
name O
, O
he O
’s O
one O
of O
the O
biggest O
murderers O
in O
all O
of O
Auschwitz B-LOC
, O
Birkenau B-LOC
and O
their O
surroundings O
) O
was O
drunk O
when O
he O
let O
them O
in O
. O

He O
interrogated B-TER
the O
capo B-TER
and O
then O
Vorarbeiter O
Häftling B-TER
to O
find O
out O
who O
had O
escaped B-TER
, O
and O
, O
unfortunately O
, O
that O
Vorarbeiter O
was O
Max B-PER
. O

Max B-PER
thought O
that O
he O
could O
explain O
everything O
to O
the O
Lagerführer B-TER
and O
calm O
him O
down O
, O
but O
he O
miscalculated O
. O

The O
Lagerführer B-TER
shot B-TER
him O
and O
5 O
or O
6 O
other O
Häftlings B-TER
. O

He O
would O
have O
shot O
more O
if O
Max B-PER
Schmidt I-PER
, O
his O
deputy O
at O
the O
time O
, O
had O
n’t O
stopped O
him O
. O

Later O
, O
Max B-PER
Schmidt I-PER
became O
our O
Lagerführer B-TER
. O

I O
became O
a O
Rapportschreiber O
in O
December O
1944 O
, O
and O
I O
discovered O
a O
statement O
with O
the O
following O
contents O
: O
On O
8 O
. O

12 O
. O

1944 O
the O
afternoon O
shift O
returned O
to O
the O
camp B-TER
at O
the O
usual O
hour O
during O
an O
air O
raid O
siren O
. O

Häftling B-TER
Max B-PER
Glaser I-PER
, O
a O
Czech B-TER
Jew O
, O
suddenly O
attacked O
an O
SS B-TER
- I-TER
man I-TER
, O
using O
the O
cover O
of O
a O
total O
blackout B-TER
, O
and O
tried O
to O
grab O
his O
service O
pistol O
. O

But O
the O
SS B-TER
- I-TER
man I-TER
managed O
to O
defend O
himself O
, O
discharged O
his O
weapon O
, O
and O
killed B-TER
him O
. O

Several O
häftlings B-TER
used O
the O
confusion O
to O
attempt O
a O
mass O
escape B-TER
– O
Massenausbruch B-TER
. O

The O
guards O
immediately O
opened O
fire O
on O
them O
, O
and O
shot B-TER
another O
5 O
or O
6 O
; O
one O
escaped B-TER
. O

This O
was O
followed O
by O
signatures O
. O

Maybe O
you O
have O
heard O
about O
this O
already O
. O

These O
are O
the O
facts O
I O
’ve O
received O
from O
eyewitnesses O
. O

Documentary B-TER
campaign I-TER
: O
Alex B-PER
. I-PER

Schmiedt I-PER
12.9.1945 O
Scheck B-PER
