Written O
with O
Mrs. O
Heda O
Grabová O
, O
born O
6 O
. O

VIII O
. O

1899 O
, O
residing O
in O
Prague B-LOC
I. I-LOC
, O
Plátnéřská B-LOC
7 I-LOC
. I-LOC

, O
Czech B-TER
nationality O
, O
profession O
opera B-TER
singer B-TER
, O
former O
prisoner B-TER
in O
the O
Theresienstadt O
– O
ghetto O
concentration O
camp O
. O

When O
I O
arrived O
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
on O
17 O
. O

12 O
. O

1941 O
as O
an O
N- O
transport B-TER
, O
we O
had O
no O
idea O
that O
it O
would O
be O
possible O
to O
sing B-TER
or O
put O
on O
a O
theater B-TER
performance O
during O
our O
imprisonment O
. O

We O
were O
simply O
ready O
for O
a O
life O
of O
working B-TER
in O
factories O
etc O
. O

, O
as O
we O
had O
been O
told O
. O

However O
, O
it O
’s O
well O
known O
that O
things O
looked O
and O
ended O
up O
differently O
. O

It O
can O
be O
said O
that O
in O
the O
beginning O
all O
we O
had O
was O
our O
fear O
of O
more O
transports B-TER
to O
Poland B-LOC
. O

We O
peeled O
potatoes O
a O
little O
and O
were O
terrified O
of O
the O
executions B-TER
that O
were O
taking O
place O
at O
the O
time O
. O

But O
in O
two O
months O
, O
when O
some O
work O
was O
organized O
under O
Edelstein B-PER
’s I-PER
leadership O
and O
when O
newer O
and O
newer O
transports B-TER
continued O
to O
arrive O
, O
a O
need O
arose O
to O
give O
people O
some O
spiritual O
nourishment O
along O
with O
their O
bad O
food O
and O
, O
one O
day O
, O
in O
the O
Hamburg B-LOC
barracks I-LOC
, O
where O
3,000 O
women B-TER
were O
housed B-TER
, O
Fredy B-PER
Hirsch I-PER
and O
Rabbi B-TER
Weiner B-PER
appeared O
and O
charged O
me O
, O
since O
I O
was O
known O
to O
them O
as O
an O
old O
singer B-TER
and O
actress B-TER
, O
with O
the O
task O
of O
creating O
something O
that O
was O
given O
the O
name O
Freizeitgestaltung O
in O
the O
Dienstelle O
. O

In O
short O
, O
I O
was O
to O
put O
together O
fun O
and O
educational O
programs B-TER
, O
and O
organize O
language O
courses B-TER
and O
lectures B-TER
. O

If O
possible O
, O
also O
a O
library O
out O
of O
the O
books O
that O
individuals O
had O
brought O
with O
them O
to O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
. O

Thus O
my O
work O
began O
. O

I O
procured O
a O
room O
, O
a O
hall O
that O
had O
not O
yet O
been O
inhabited O
, O
I O
had O
benches O
brought O
in O
and O
carried O
some O
in O
myself O
, O
I O
looked O
for O
a O
musical B-TER
instrument O
, O
at O
least O
a O
harmonica B-TER
, O
which O
could O
only O
be O
played O
in O
secret O
, O
however O
, O
because O
it O
was O
strictly O
forbidden O
to O
have O
musical B-TER
instruments O
in O
the O
ghetto B-LOC
. O

We O
held O
a O
so O
- O
called O
audition O
of O
everyone O
who O
had O
engaged O
in O
recitation B-TER
, O
singing B-TER
and O
dancing B-TER
, O
and O
I O
put O
together O
the O
first O
vibrant O
program B-TER
. O

On O
March O
21st O
, O
1942 O
, O
the O
so O
- O
called O
staff O
and O
Judenältester B-TER
Edelstein B-PER
came O
into O
the O
women B-TER
’s I-TER
barracks B-TER
, O
which O
was O
a O
small O
miracle O
since O
men B-TER
were O
n’t O
allowed O
in O
the O
women B-TER
’s I-TER
barracks B-TER
and O
vice O
versa O
. O

The O
so O
- O
called O
first O
cultural B-TER
evening O
took O
place O
, O
but O
it O
started O
at O
3 O
o’clock O
in O
the O
afternoon O
. O

I O
made O
sure O
that O
the O
program B-TER
was O
stylish O
as O
well O
as O
educational O
. O

I O
sang B-TER
, O
a O
group O
of O
6 O
young O
girls B-TER
danced O
the O
Czech O
polka O
, O
and O
the O
Adler B-PER
sisters O
, O
the O
daughters O
of O
Friedrich B-PER
Adler I-PER
, O
recited O
and O
sang B-TER
several O
short O
operetta B-TER
soubrettes O
from O
days O
of O
yore O
. O

I O
welcomed O
the O
audience O
myself O
and O
performed B-TER
, O
and O
the O
whole O
event O
was O
so O
successful O
that O
not O
only O
did O
we O
repeat O
the O
same O
program B-TER
several O
times O
to O
allow O
as O
many O
women B-TER
as O
possible O
to O
be O
able O
to O
attend O
it O
, O
but O
we O
received O
permission O
for O
the O
whole O
group O
to O
visit O
other O
barracks B-TER
( O
men B-TER
’s I-TER
) O
, O
where O
we O
performed O
this O
show B-TER
. O

This O
is O
how O
we O
began O
to O
share O
our O
art O
with O
the O
poor O
souls O
so O
that O
they O
could O
forget O
about O
the O
dire O
poverty O
in O
which O
they O
were O
living O
if O
only O
for O
a O
moment O
. O

We O
also O
went O
to O
hospitals B-TER
and O
sang B-TER
and O
recited B-TER
between O
the O
beds O
, O
generally O
with O
no O
musical B-TER
accompaniment O
, O
which O
was O
very O
difficult O
for O
the O
male O
singer B-TER
or O
female O
singer B-TER
, O
who O
was O
used O
to O
standing O
on O
a O
stage O
and O
singing B-TER
accompanied O
by O
an O
orchestra O
. O

But O
we O
were O
happy O
to O
do O
it O
, O
because O
we O
brought O
the O
poor O
souls O
a O
little O
something O
from O
a O
better O
world O
. O

This O
was O
how O
it O
all O
began O
. O

In O
time O
, O
more O
and O
more O
former O
singers B-TER
, O
musicians B-TER
, O
and O
composers B-TER
arrived O
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
, O
and O
the O
administration O
came O
to O
see O
the O
theater O
in O
a O
different O
light O
. O

It O
gave O
us O
a O
space O
and O
got O
the O
kommandantur B-TER
to O
approve O
musical O
instruments O
, O
and O
so O
it O
happened O
that O
in O
the O
concentration O
camp O
, O
under O
the O
leadership O
of O
the O
deceased B-TER
bandleader B-TER
Rafael B-PER
Schächter I-PER
, O
we O
rehearsed O
and O
performed O
an O
entire O
opera B-TER
: O
The O
Bartered O
Bride O
by O
Bedřich B-PER
Smetana I-PER
. O

At O
night O
, O
in O
the O
Sudeten B-LOC
barracks I-LOC
where O
he O
lived B-TER
, O
Schächter B-PER
began O
to O
study O
Jewish O
choir B-TER
pieces O
with O
the O
help O
of O
a O
single O
tuning O
fork O
that O
I O
had O
lent O
him O
. O

He O
got O
the O
idea O
to O
study O
the O
choruses B-TER
from O
The O
Bartered O
Bride O
and O
I O
put O
together O
a O
group O
of O
girls B-TER
from O
our O
barracks B-TER
. O

He O
practiced O
with O
the O
men B-TER
in O
the O
Sudeten B-LOC
barracks I-LOC
and O
gradually O
, O
when O
the O
right O
soloists O
were O
found O
, O
we O
got O
the O
idea O
to O
do O
the O
whole O
opera B-TER
as O
a O
concert O
. O

Somewhere O
in O
the O
Sokol B-LOC
gymnasium I-LOC
was O
an O
old O
, O
battered O
piano O
without O
legs O
and O
he O
managed O
to O
find O
a O
half O
- O
broken O
harmonium O
, O
and O
, O
somewhere O
in O
the O
cellar O
, O
a O
tiny O
room O
where O
he O
could O
regularly O
practice O
with O
his O
group O
. O

During O
the O
coldest O
part O
of O
the O
winter O
, O
bundled O
up O
to O
our O
ears O
, O
we O
rehearsed O
The O
Bartered O
Bride O
. O

We O
were O
finally O
ready O
and O
now O
needed O
to O
move O
the O
piano O
at O
night O
in O
secret O
into O
the O
ghetto B-LOC
, O
because O
the O
Sokol B-LOC
gymnasium I-LOC
could O
no O
longer O
be O
used O
. O

They O
let O
us O
use O
a O
gym O
in O
a O
boys B-TER
home I-TER
and O
we O
finally O
performed O
The O
Bartered O
Bride O
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
on O
November O
28th O
, O
1942 O
. O

It O
was O
an O
unforgettable O
experience O
. O

When O
the O
first O
measures O
of O
Proč O
bychom O
se O
netěšili O
sounded O
there O
was O
n’t O
a O
dry O
eye O
in O
the O
house O
. O

We O
performed O
The O
Bartered O
Bride O
around O
35 O
times O
. O

Then O
we O
started O
rehearsing O
something O
new O
, O
this O
time O
The B-TER
Marriage I-TER
of I-TER
Figaro I-TER
, O
and O
in O
the O
rest O
of O
the O
time O
we O
spent O
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
we O
gradually O
performed O
the O
operas B-TER
The B-TER
Bartered I-TER
Bride I-TER
, O
The B-TER
Kiss I-TER
, O
The B-TER
Marriage I-TER
of I-TER
Figaro I-TER
, O
The B-TER
Magic I-TER
Flute I-TER
, O
Rigoletto B-TER
, O
Tosca B-TER
, O
Carmen B-TER
, O
Bastien B-TER
and I-TER
Bastienne I-TER
, O
La B-TER
Serva I-TER
Padrona I-TER
, O
Verdi B-PER
’s O
Requiem B-TER
, O
Tvorstvo B-TER
, O
Elias B-TER
, O
and O
many O
choir O
concerts B-TER
, O
many O
German O
and O
Czech O
plays B-TER
, O
countless O
cabarets B-TER
, O
even O
a O
circus O
performance B-TER
in O
the O
courtyard O
of O
the O
Hamburg B-LOC
barracks I-LOC
and O
the O
Bauhof B-LOC
, O
a O
hundred O
individual O
piano O
, O
instrumental O
, O
and O
vocal B-TER
concerts B-TER
, O
in O
time O
even O
orchestral O
concerts O
conducted O
by O
the O
bandleader B-TER
Ančerle B-PER
, O
several O
operettas B-TER
, O
among O
them O
Die O
Fledermaus O
. O

In O
the O
year O
1943 O
- O
1944 O
, O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
’s O
cultural B-TER
and O
theatrical B-TER
life O
was O
so O
full O
that O
a O
mid O
- O
sized O
city O
in O
peacetime O
had O
n’t O
put O
on O
as O
many O
events O
as O
we O
had O
in O
our O
ghetto B-LOC
. O

The O
theater B-TER
halls O
were O
small O
and O
limited O
; O
the O
so O
- O
called O
Raumwirtschaft O
needed O
everything O
when O
the O
transports B-TER
arrived O
. O

And O
so O
we O
had O
to O
establish O
small O
stages O
in O
the O
attics O
of O
the O
barracks B-TER
and O
larger O
residential O
houses O
, O
where O
the O
acoustics O
were O
terrible O
, O
the O
heat O
in O
summer O
and O
the O
cold O
in O
winter O
was O
unbearable O
, O
that O
was O
for O
sure O
. O

But O
the O
audience O
’s O
enthusiasm O
and O
the O
performers O
’ O
joy O
made O
us O
forget O
these O
things O
. O

The O
performances O
were O
sold O
out O
even O
under O
these O
conditions O
. O

It O
seems O
strange O
that O
the O
SS B-TER
allowed O
Jews O
in O
the O
ghetto B-LOC
to O
cultivate O
music B-TER
, O
art B-TER
, O
lectures B-TER
etc O
. O

in O
such O
a O
way O
, O
but O
the O
gentlemen O
knew O
very O
well O
what O
they O
were O
doing O
. O

They O
wanted O
these O
things O
to O
help O
make O
Therezsienstadt B-LOC
a O
model O
to O
present O
to O
foreign O
countries O
, O
the O
so O
- O
called O
Musterghetto O
. O

They O
awaited O
the O
arrival O
of O
some O
sort O
of O
commission B-ORG
, O
and O
so O
they O
even O
let O
us O
use O
the O
Sokol B-LOC
gymnasium I-LOC
and O
ordered O
the O
operas B-TER
to O
be O
performed O
perfectly O
, O
in O
costume O
and O
with O
wigs O
, O
basically O
a O
real O
theater B-TER
performance O
. O

And O
so O
real O
theater B-TER
, O
beautifully O
theatrically B-TER
staged O
, O
was O
played O
at O
the O
beginning O
of O
May O
1944 O
, O
at O
the O
height O
of O
the O
so O
- O
called O
Verschönerung B-TER
of O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
. O

Architects O
Zelenka B-PER
, O
Prof. O
Lederer O
and O
other O
famous O
artists B-TER
worked O
non O
- O
stop O
to O
prepare O
the O
various O
stages O
. O

All O
of O
the O
lighting O
equipment O
and O
light O
bulbs O
necessary O
for O
the O
theater B-TER
had O
to O
be O
brought O
into O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
. O

A O
pavilion O
was O
erected O
in O
the O
square O
, O
where O
the O
town O
’s O
band O
, O
wonderful O
musicians B-TER
all O
of O
them O
and O
each O
individually O
a O
virtuoso O
, O
performed O
every O
day O
. O

The O
Trio O
played O
in O
the O
cafe O
and O
cabarets B-TER
( O
Hans B-PER
Hofer I-PER
) O
were O
held O
, O
and O
, O
in O
the O
summer O
, O
performances O
took O
place O
outside O
in O
the O
courtyards O
. O

In O
the O
summer O
of O
1944 O
, O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
seemed O
like O
an O
El O
Dorado O
in O
Europe O
, O
a O
place O
where O
there O
are O
no O
air B-TER
strikes I-TER
, O
no O
fronts O
, O
in O
short O
, O
no O
dangers O
threatened O
it O
. O

The O
famous O
commission B-ORG
arrived O
and O
apparently O
went O
around O
. O

An O
utter O
farce O
was O
performed O
, O
children B-TER
had O
to O
run O
behind O
the O
SS B-TER
- I-TER
komandant I-TER
, O
tug O
at O
his O
coat O
and O
cry O
: O
Uncle O
, O
come O
play O
with O
us O
, O
to O
which O
he O
replied O
: O
Today O
I O
can O
not O
, O
but O
tomorrow O
I O
shall O
. O

The O
famous O
film O
director O
Kurt B-PER
Geron I-PER
had O
to O
make O
a O
film B-TER
. O

Actors O
waited O
in O
the O
theaters B-TER
, O
ready O
to O
start O
playing O
at O
the O
moment O
when O
the O
commission B-ORG
set O
foot O
inside O
, O
as O
if O
the O
opera B-TER
or O
play B-TER
was O
already O
under O
way O
. O

After O
5 O
minutes O
, O
the O
commission B-ORG
moved O
on O
and O
the O
play B-TER
stopped O
. O

Everyone O
went O
home O
. O

The O
composers B-TER
Haas B-PER
, O
Krása B-PER
, O
Ullmann B-PER
, O
and O
Gideon B-PER
Klein I-PER
were O
also O
urged O
to O
compose O
operas B-TER
or O
songs B-TER
that O
then O
had O
to O
be O
played O
. O

The O
SS B-TER
itself O
ordered O
this O
. O

Two O
children B-TER
’s I-TER
operas B-TER
were O
also O
performed O
: O
Brundibár B-TER
, O
composed O
by O
Hans B-PER
Krása I-PER
, O
and O
Broučci B-TER
, O
a O
collection O
of O
Czech O
folk O
songs B-TER
, O
directed O
by O
Váva B-PER
Schönová I-PER
, O
the O
bandleader B-TER
Brok B-PER
, O
and O
the O
director O
Thein B-PER
. O

Children B-TER
up O
to O
age O
14 O
played O
and O
sang B-TER
. O

It O
seemed O
unimaginable O
that O
things O
could O
continue O
thus O
. O

And O
the O
ax O
did O
indeed O
come O
down O
. O

As O
soon O
as O
the O
commission B-ORG
left O
, O
the O
ghetto B-LOC
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
began O
to O
be O
liquidated O
. O

In O
just O
4 O
weeks O
, O
18,600 O
Jews O
were O
transported B-TER
to O
the O
so O
- O
called O
labor B-TER
camp I-TER
. O

In O
reality O
, O
they O
were O
taken O
to O
Auschwitz B-LOC
, O
where O
a O
large O
part O
went O
directly O
to O
the O
gas B-TER
chambers I-TER
and O
only O
a O
small O
number O
, O
when O
it O
passed O
through O
the O
selection B-TER
process I-TER
, O
was O
sent O
on O
to O
concentration B-TER
camps I-TER
. O

Almost O
all O
of O
the O
men B-TER
– O
artists B-TER
, O
actors B-TER
, O
composers B-TER
, O
singers B-TER
, O
bandleaders B-TER
, O
instrumentalists B-TER
– O
lost B-TER
their I-TER
lives I-TER
. O

Only O
seven O
women B-TER
out O
of O
the O
entire O
group O
remained O
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
. O

They O
were O
forgotten O
about O
and O
so O
they O
did O
n’t O
go O
to O
the O
same O
place O
as O
the O
other O
18,600 O
. O

When O
the O
last O
transport B-TER
left O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
for O
Auschwitz B-LOC
on O
October O
28th O
1944 O
, O
Judenältester B-TER
Murmelstein B-PER
had O
to O
hand O
over O
to O
Lagerhalter O
Rahm B-PER
the O
remaining O
people O
who O
were O
not O
parading O
before O
him O
, O
and O
it O
was O
discovered O
that O
7 O
women B-TER
– O
a O
singer B-TER
, O
a O
piano B-TER
player I-TER
, O
i.e. O
a O
piano B-TER
player I-TER
and O
actress B-TER
– O
were O
forgotten O
. O

When O
Murmelstein B-PER
asked O
whether O
they O
should O
be O
put O
on O
the O
last O
transport B-TER
, O
Rahm B-PER
, O
smiling O
condescendingly O
, O
said O
in O
his O
Viennese B-LOC
dialect O
: O
Aber O
was O
, O
lassenses O
da O
. O

Sollens O
dann O
wieder O
spielen O
und O
singen O
. O

This O
saved O
our O
lives O
. O

We O
immediately O
had O
to O
join O
the O
so O
- O
called O
Glimmerspalterei B-TER
, O
where O
we O
split O
mica B-TER
from O
5:30 O
in O
the O
morning O
until O
2:00 O
in O
the O
afternoon O
, O
but O
about O
3 O
days O
after O
the O
last O
transport B-TER
departed O
, O
I O
received O
an O
order O
to O
put O
together O
a O
new O
concert B-TER
program O
. O

And O
so O
we O
had O
to O
create O
an O
evening O
program O
to O
be O
held O
in O
the O
unheated O
space O
of O
the O
Sokol B-LOC
gymnasium I-LOC
and O
quickly O
rehearse O
the O
pieces O
, O
and O
once O
again O
sing B-TER
for O
those O
who O
remained O
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
. O

Four O
months O
went O
by O
, O
until O
March O
7th O
, O
1945 O
, O
when O
Mr. O
Rahm B-PER
took O
us O
off O
mica B-TER
duty O
and O
ordered O
us O
to O
quickly O
rehearse O
the O
children B-TER
’s I-TER
opera B-TER
Broučci B-TER
and O
the O
opera B-TER
The O
Tales O
of O
Hoffmann O
, O
because O
another O
commission O
was O
soon O
to O
arrive O
. O

Our O
days O
and O
nights O
were O
spent O
writing O
out O
the O
music O
, O
making O
sure O
the O
orchestra O
had O
the O
material O
it O
needed O
, O
rehearsing O
with O
the O
musicians B-TER
who O
had O
arrived B-TER
because O
they O
were O
married O
to O
an O
Aryan O
. O

And O
so O
we O
played O
again O
in O
the O
Sokol B-LOC
gymnasium I-LOC
in O
costume O
on O
a O
beautifully O
decorated O
stage O
. O

The O
commission O
arrived O
and O
everything O
went O
well O
, O
and O
life O
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
seemed O
to O
be O
as O
it O
had O
been O
before O
the O
thousands O
had O
departed B-TER
. O

Then O
, O
around O
April O
20th O
, O
the O
1st O
transport B-TER
of O
the O
so O
- O
called O
pajama O
wearers O
from O
Buchenwald B-LOC
arrived O
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
and O
our O
eyes O
were O
opened O
. O

We O
discovered O
the O
true O
reality O
and O
that O
day O
all O
of O
the O
singing B-TER
, O
playing B-TER
, O
and O
distracting O
ourselves O
stopped O
. O

We O
were O
in O
no O
mood O
to O
sing B-TER
. O

We O
were O
liberated B-TER
soon O
afterwards O
and O
our O
musical B-TER
artistic B-TER
career O
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
came O
to O
an O
end O
. O

I O
sang B-TER
almost O
every O
day O
, O
played O
in O
all O
of O
the O
operas B-TER
, O
and O
I O
can O
probably O
say O
that O
singing B-TER
and O
my O
art O
was O
the O
one O
thing O
that O
saved O
my O
life O
and O
spared O
me O
from O
the O
suffering O
that O
thousands O
of O
my O
brothers O
and O
sister O
must O
have O
experienced O
. O

I O
can O
say O
that O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
was O
the O
longest O
and O
worst O
- O
paid O
engagement O
in O
my O
entire O
musical B-TER
and O
theatrical B-TER
career O
. O

Signature O
: O
Heda B-PER
Grabová I-PER
Statement O
was O
accepted O
by O
: O
Berta B-PER
Gerzonová I-PER
Signatures O
of O
witnesses O
: O
Accepted O
on O
behalf O
of O
the O
Documentary B-TER
campaign I-TER
: O
Dita B-PER
Saxlová I-PER
Scheck B-PER
Helena B-PER
Schicková I-PER
Accepted O
on O
behalf O
of O
the O
archive O
: O
29 O
. O

IX O
. O

1945 O
Alex B-PER
. I-PER

Schmiedt I-PER
