JEWISH O
CENTRAL O
INFORMATION O
OFFICE O
19 B-LOC
Manchester I-LOC
Square I-LOC
, O
London B-LOC
, O
W. O
1 O
July O
, O
1945 O
Jewish O
Survivors O
Report O
Documents O
of O
Nazi O
Guilt O
No O
. O

3 O
Theresienstadt O
and O
From O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
to O
Auschwitz B-LOC
b O
y O
Max B-PER
E. I-PER
Mannheimer I-PER
This O
is O
the O
third O
of O
a O
series O
of O
personal O
reports O
received O
by O
the O
JEWISH O
CENTRAL O
INFORMATION O
OFFICE O
from O
eye O
- O
witnesses O
of O
the O
persecution B-TER
of I-TER
Jews I-TER
under O
Nazi B-TER
rule I-TER
. O

-1- O
I O
was O
living O
in O
Amsterdam B-LOC
when O
the O
Germans B-TER
occupied I-TER
Holland B-LOC
. O

My O
parents B-TER
are O
German B-TER
Jews O
who O
had O
settled O
in O
Holland B-LOC
many O
years O
before O
1933 O
. O

I O
attended O
a O
Dutch B-TER
school B-TER
, O
passed O
the O
Higher O
School O
Examination O
, O
and O
became O
a O
senior O
band O
clerk O
later O
. O

I O
am O
27 O
years O
of O
age O
and O
Stateless B-TER
. O

Till O
May O
1943 O
I O
was O
on O
the O
staff O
of O
the O
Joodsche B-TER
Raad I-TER
in O
Amsterdam B-LOC
as O
a O
voluntary O
social O
worker O
. O

Before O
the O
occupation B-TER
I O
had O
taken O
part O
in O
the O
welfare O
work O
of O
the O
Committee O
Voor B-ORG
Byzondere I-ORG
Joodsche I-ORG
Belangen I-ORG
. O

From O
Westerbork B-LOC
to O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
. O

In O
May O
1943 O
I O
was O
to O
be O
arrested B-TER
and O
had O
to O
go O
underground O
. O

I O
lived O
in O
the B-LOC
Hague I-LOC
till O
December O
1943 O
, O
when O
I O
was O
caught O
by O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
. O

A O
certain O
Kaptein O
, O
an O
SS B-TER
man I-TER
in O
mufti O
and O
a O
member O
of O
the O
Dutch B-TER
Gestapo B-ORG
, O
at O
Windekind O
, O
Hague B-LOC
, O
questioned O
me O
for O
three O
hours O
, O
beat O
and O
ill O
- O
treated O
me O
so O
severely O
that O
when O
transported B-TER
to O
the O
Dutch B-TER
camp B-TER
of O
Westerbork B-LOC
I O
had O
to O
be O
taken O
to O
the O
camp B-TER
hospital I-TER
. O

For O
seven O
weeks O
I O
was O
treated O
there O
for O
muscular O
inflammation O
, O
a O
consequence O
of O
the O
ill O
- O
treatment O
. O

Conditions B-TER
in O
Westerbork B-LOC
were O
known O
to O
me O
because O
I O
had O
often O
been O
sent O
there O
by O
the O
Joodsche B-ORG
Raad I-ORG
. O

I O
had O
seen O
many O
trains B-TER
loaded O
with O
deportees O
, O
dispatched O
for O
the O
East B-TER
. O

People O
generally O
left O
Westerbork B-LOC
calmly O
, O
sometimes O
even O
singing O
, O
because O
they O
were O
hoping O
to O
reach O
the O
place O
of O
their O
final O
settlement O
. O

Many O
preferred O
certainty O
about O
their O
future O
destination O
, O
which O
they O
hoped O
to O
find O
in O
the O
eastern O
camps O
, O
to O
the O
constant O
strain O
of O
suspense O
which O
hang O
Text O
blurred O
over O
them O
in O
Westerbork B-LOC
. O

Neither O
myself O
nor O
the O
1800 O
people O
who O
were O
detailed O
for O
transfer B-TER
to O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
on O
the O
25th O
Feb. O
1944 O
were O
frightened O
when O
we O
heard O
about O
the O
deportation B-TER
order O
. O

The O
name O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
, O
the O
model O
camp O
of O
the O
Nazis O
, O
did O
not O
imply O
horror O
. O

It O
was O
considered O
a O
special O
favour O
to O
be O
permitted O
to O
live O
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
. O

Ex B-TER
- I-TER
Servicemen I-TER
of O
the O
first O
World O
War B-TER
, O
with O
the O
Iron O
Cross O
, O
First O
Class O
, O
or O
the O
badge O
for O
wounded O
, O
descendants O
of O
mixed B-TER
marriages I-TER
, O
but O
of O
Jewish O
religion O
, O
baptised B-TER
Jews I-TER
, O
those O
whose O
names O
were O
on O
the O
so O
- O
called O
Barneveld O
List O
– O
some O
hundred O
Dutch B-TER
Jews O
sho O
had O
rendered O
special O
service O
to O
Holland B-LOC
– O
people O
who O
had O
made O
some O
outstanding O
contribution O
to O
German B-TER
life O
, O
and O
some O
persons O
whom O
the O
Nazi B-TER
authorities I-TER
or O
the O
Commandant O
in O
Westerbork B-LOC
selected O
, O
- O
these O
were O
the O
favoured O
classes O
who O
were O
allowed O
to O
go O
to O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
. O

We O
1800 O
, O
among O
us O
babies B-TER
and O
old O
people O
, O
were O
loaded O
into O
ordinary O
trains B-TER
not O
into O
goods O
trains B-TER
. O

We O
took O
this O
as O
a O
good O
sign O
, O
that O
the O
place O
of O
our O
destination O
was O
really O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
and O
not O
one O
of O
the O
ominous O
camps B-TER
. O

We O
were O
allowed O
to O
take O
our O
luggage O
with O
us O
, O
and O
received B-TER
jam B-TER
, O
margarine B-TER
and O
one O
loaf O
of O
bread B-TER
for B-TER
three I-TER
persons I-TER
. O

The O
compartments O
were O
locked O
. O

Members O
of O
the O
German O
Security O
Police O
( O
Gruene B-ORG
Polizei I-ORG
) O
accompanied O
the O
train O
which O
, O
after O
a O
journey B-TER
of O
three O
days O
and O
two O
nights O
, O
arrived O
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
. O

We O
were O
received O
by O
SS B-TER
officers I-TER
and O
Czech B-ORG
police I-ORG
– O
we O
did O
not O
see O
any O
SS B-ORG
privates O
– O
and O
taken O
to O
barracks O
where O
we O
had O
to O
register O
. O

The O
officials O
who O
took O
down O
our O
particulars O
were O
members O
of O
the O
Jewish B-TER
Self I-TER
- I-TER
Administration I-TER
. O

Doctors B-TER
belonging O
to O
the O
same O
body O
vaccinated O
us O
. O

We O
were O
searched O
by O
the O
police O
, O
our O
luggage O
was O
examined O
, O
whereupon O
the O
SS B-TER
officers I-TER
and O
the O
police B-TER
disappeared O
. O

We O
were O
left O
to O
ourselves O
, O
Jews O
amongst O
Jews O
, O
herded O
into O
a O
Ghetto B-TER
of O
which O
we O
had O
only O
known O
from O
history O
books O
, O
as O
an O
institution O
of O
bygone O
times O
. O

The O
Ghetto B-TER
Theresienstadt B-LOC
( O
Terezin B-LOC
) O
is O
an O
old O
fortress O
town O
lying O
on O
both O
sides O
of O
the O
River O
Eger B-LOC
, O
61 O
kms O
. O

from O
Prague B-LOC
, O
at O
the O
frontier O
of O
the O
former O
Protectorate O
and O
the O
Sudetenland B-LOC
. O

It O
had O
about O
7,000 O
inhabitants O
mostly O
Czechs B-TER
, O
when O
it O
was O
established O
as O
a O
ghetto B-TER
for O
the O
complete O
isolation B-TER
, O
first O
of O
the O
Czech B-TER
Jews O
, O
and O
later O
for O
other O
European O
Jews O
as O
well O
. O

-2- O
The O
7,000 O
non- O
Jewish O
inhabitants O
of O
the O
town O
had O
been O
evacuated B-TER
X. O
The O
barracks O
of O
the O
fortress O
formerly O
used O
for O
the O
Austrian B-ORG
Military I-ORG
and O
for O
Political O
prisoners B-TER
– O
among O
them O
Principe O
who O
assassinated O
the O
Archduke O
Franz B-PER
Ferdinand I-PER
of O
Austria B-LOC
in O
1914 O
and O
died B-TER
in O
the O
damp O
dungeons O
of O
Terezin B-LOC
– O
and O
the O
small O
houses O
of O
the O
town O
were O
all O
occupied O
by O
Jews O
; O
only O
the O
church B-TER
was O
excluded O
and O
was O
locked O
up O
. O

These O
barracks O
and O
houses O
were O
situated O
in O
the O
so O
- O
called O
Grosse O
Festung O
( O
Big O
Fortress O
) O
, O
the O
ghetto O
proper O
, O
a O
minor O
part O
of O
which O
was O
reserved O
for O
the O
SS B-TER
. O

There O
, O
in O
the O
Sudeten B-LOC
Kaserne I-LOC
, O
the O
SS B-TER
kept O
the O
files O
of O
their O
records O
. O

The O
big O
fortress O
is O
surrounded O
by O
walls O
, O
the O
gates O
of O
which O
were O
guarded O
by O
Czech B-ORG
police I-ORG
. O

Though O
it O
was O
not O
easy O
to O
escape B-TER
from O
that O
prison O
town O
it O
was O
not O
impossible O
, O
provided O
the O
people O
who O
dared O
the O
attempt O
spoke O
the O
vernacular O
. O

Some O
Czech B-TER
Jews O
while O
on O
work O
outside O
the O
ghetto B-TER
succeeded O
in O
fleeing B-TER
. O

As O
punishment O
for O
this O
escape B-TER
Jakob B-PER
Edelstein I-PER
, O
the O
first O
elder I-ORG
of I-ORG
the I-ORG
Jews I-ORG
( O
Judeneltester O
) O
was O
dismissed O
from O
his O
post O
and O
sent O
to O
Auschwitz B-LOC
. O

On O
the O
far O
side O
of O
the O
Eger B-LOC
lies O
the O
small O
fortress O
( O
Kleine B-LOC
Festung I-LOC
) O
, O
a O
concentration B-TER
camp I-TER
for O
people O
from O
Czecho B-LOC
- I-LOC
Slovakia I-LOC
and O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
. O

The O
women B-TER
of O
Lidice B-LOC
, O
for O
example O
, O
were O
held O
there O
. O

The O
accommodation B-TER
of O
the O
Grosse O
Festung O
was O
enlarged O
by O
some O
wooden O
huts O
, O
built O
by O
the O
Jewish O
inmates B-TER
. O

Men B-TER
and O
women B-TER
lived O
separated B-TER
from O
each O
other O
in O
the O
barracks O
. O

Some O
were O
men B-TER
's O
quarters O
, O
others O
women B-TER
's O
quarters O
. O

Family B-TER
life O
was O
impossible O
, O
but O
people O
could O
see O
each O
other O
after O
day O
's O
work B-TER
was O
done O
. O

The O
space O
allotted B-TER
to O
each O
person O
was O
not O
more O
than O
about O
4 O
ft O
. O

5 O
ins O
. O

just O
enough O
to O
lie O
down O
, O
but O
in O
this O
small O
space B-TER
one O
was O
supposed O
to O
eat O
, O
wash O
and O
sleep O
, O
and O
to O
live O
. O

Bedsteads O
, O
or O
rather O
wooden O
bunks O
, O
were O
placed O
in O
three O
tiers O
. O

People O
slept O
on O
straw O
- O
filled O
sacks O
, O
straw O
mattresses O
– O
rugs O
were O
not O
provided O
. O

Everybody O
had O
to O
provide O
a O
rug O
or O
cover O
for O
himself O
. O

All O
the O
barracks O
were O
bug O
- O
infested O
. O

In O
the O
small O
private O
houses O
, O
which O
might O
more O
correctly O
be O
called O
slum O
quarters O
, O
no O
furniture O
was O
left O
, O
and O
the O
same O
small O
space O
was O
detailed O
to O
the O
inmates B-TER
. O

We O
had O
dim O
electric O
light O
. O

Sanitation B-TER
was O
most O
primitive O
. O

For O
about O
5,000 O
people O
, O
the O
officials O
of O
the O
administration O
and O
some O
persons O
who O
, O
on O
German B-TER
orders I-TER
, O
had O
to O
receive O
preferential O
treatment O
, O
a O
little O
more O
space O
– O
about O
5 O
ft O
. O

X O
5 O
ft O
. O

– O
was O
allocated B-TER
. O

During O
the O
last O
month O
of O
my O
stay O
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
I O
shared O
a O
room O
of O
about O
12 O
ft O
. O

X O
12 O
ft O
. O

with O
four O
members O
of O
my O
family B-TER
, O
my O
wife B-TER
and O
my O
mother B-TER
amongst O
them O
. O

In O
Feb. O
1944 O
about O
38000 O
Jews O
were O
confined O
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
, O
the O
majority O
of O
them O
Czechs B-TER
, O
2,800 O
Dutch B-TER
, O
300 O
Danes B-TER
, O
the O
rest O
German B-TER
and O
Austrian B-TER
Jews O
; O
later O
a O
few O
French B-TER
Jews O
were O
brought O
to O
the O
ghetto B-TER
, O
amongst O
them O
Monsieur B-PER
Meyer I-PER
, O
the O
former O
Mayor O
of O
Le B-LOC
Havre I-LOC
. O

X O
Compare O
the O
ordinance O
published O
in O
the O
Verordnungsblatt O
des O
Reichsprotektors O
f. O
Boehmen O
und O
Maehren O
of O
the O
28th O
Feb. O
1942 O
, O
according O
to O
which O
all O
Jews O
in O
the O
Protectorate O
are O
to O
be O
concentrated B-TER
at O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
. O

According O
to O
this O
decree B-TER
the O
complete O
isolation B-TER
had O
been O
proved O
necessary O
in O
order O
to O
prevent O
whispering O
propaganda O
and O
subversive O
activities O
, O
chiefly O
emanating O
from O
Jews O
. O

XX O
The O
cattle O
of O
Lidice B-LOC
had O
been O
brought O
to O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
, O
and O
were O
looked O
after O
by O
the O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
Jews O
. O

Young O
Jews O
from O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
were O
taken O
to O
Lidice B-LOC
by O
the O
SS B-TER
to O
dig B-TER
the O
graves B-TER
for O
the O
murdered B-TER
Lidice B-LOC
population B-TER
. O

-3- O
Sixty O
- O
eight O
Thousand O
People O
Crowded O
into O
a O
Town O
Meant O
for O
Seven O
Thousand O
. O

At O
one O
time O
the O
ghetto B-TER
had O
to O
accommodate O
up O
to O
68,000 O
inhabitants O
. O

The O
number O
had O
decreased O
by O
deportation B-TER
and O
death B-TER
. O

About O
150,000 O
people O
were O
said O
to O
have O
passed O
through O
that O
show O
camp B-TER
of O
the O
Nazis O
. O

Jewish B-TER
Self I-TER
- I-TER
Administration I-TER
. O

The O
town O
was O
administered B-TER
entirely O
by O
Jews O
. O

At O
the O
head O
of O
the O
administration O
was O
Dr. O
Paul B-PER
Epstein I-PER
from O
Berlin B-LOC
, O
a O
former O
member O
of O
the O
Board O
of O
the O
Reichsvereinigung B-ORG
der I-ORG
Juden I-ORG
in I-ORG
Deutschland I-ORG
and O
a O
lecturer O
on O
economics O
in O
Mannheim B-LOC
. O

He O
was O
assisted O
by O
the O
Czech B-TER
civil O
engineers O
, O
Murmelstein B-PER
and O
Zucker B-PER
, O
the O
latter O
subsequently O
put O
to O
death B-TER
in O
Auschwitz B-LOC
. O

Dr. O
Epstein B-PER
was O
deported B-TER
later O
to O
the O
East O
and O
never O
heard O
of O
again O
. O

The O
administrators B-TER
were O
assisted O
by O
the O
so O
- O
called O
Aeltestenrat O
( O
Council B-ORG
of I-ORG
Elders I-ORG
) O
the O
most O
prominent O
member O
of O
which O
was O
Dr. B-PER
Leo I-PER
Baeck I-PER
, O
the O
venerated O
Rabbi B-TER
from O
Berlin B-LOC
, O
a O
personality O
of O
almost O
prophetic O
stature O
. O

Life B-TER
in I-TER
the I-TER
ghetto I-TER
was O
organised O
by O
the O
different O
departments O
of O
the O
administration B-TER
, O
the O
economic O
department O
– O
food B-TER
distribution B-TER
and O
production O
– O
the O
housing B-TER
department O
( O
Raumwirtschaft O
) O
and O
the O
health B-TER
department O
. O

The O
economic O
department O
was O
responsible O
for O
the O
distribution B-TER
of I-TER
food I-TER
which O
they O
got O
from O
SS B-ORG
Headquarters O
in O
Prague B-LOC
. O

The O
Jews O
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
were O
maintained O
by O
Jewish O
funds B-TER
i.e. O
by O
assets B-TER
confiscated I-TER
from O
Czech B-TER
Jews O
. O

The O
economic O
department O
had O
also O
to O
organise O
work B-TER
, O
which O
was O
obligatory O
for O
everyone O
except O
the O
very O
old O
and O
very O
sick O
, O
and O
the O
children B-TER
. O

People O
were O
employed B-TER
in O
the O
timber O
yard O
, O
the O
joinery O
and O
the O
plumbers O
shop O
, O
working O
for O
the O
maintenance O
of O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

There O
were O
also O
work B-TER
- I-TER
shops I-TER
with O
people O
engaged O
in O
the O
production O
of O
ink O
powder O
, O
the O
manufacture O
of O
leather O
goods O
, O
artistic O
handicraft O
( O
necklaces O
etc O
. O

) O
, O
mica O
and O
of O
uniforms O
and O
mackintoshes O
for O
the O
German B-TER
Wehrmacht B-ORG
. O

Before O
my O
arrival O
wooden O
cases O
were O
also O
manufactured O
. O

Young O
people O
had O
to O
do O
agricultural O
work O
outside O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
, O
either O
on O
farms O
or O
on O
estates B-TER
confiscated I-TER
by O
the O
German B-TER
authorities B-TER
. O

This O
kind O
of O
work O
was O
very O
popular O
among O
the O
younger O
inmates B-TER
of I-TER
the I-TER
camp I-TER
, O
because O
there O
they O
had O
a O
chance O
of O
getting O
some O
additional O
food B-TER
to O
their O
meagre O
diet O
. O

Repair O
shops O
for O
clothing B-TER
and O
shoes O
, O
and O
watch O
- O
makers O
’ O
shops O
supplemented O
this O
organisation O
of O
a O
Jewish O
autarchy O
. O

The O
economic O
department O
was O
supervised O
by O
Mr. O
Freiberger B-PER
, O
the O
central O
department O
which O
had O
to O
detail O
labour O
was O
led O
by O
Dr. O
Oestereicher B-PER
and O
Mr. O
Weinberger B-PER
, O
a O
Czech B-TER
civil O
engineer O
. O

The O
housing B-TER
department O
responsible O
for O
the O
distribution O
of O
living O
, O
or O
rather O
sleeping O
accommodation O
, O
was O
administered O
by O
Dr. O
Loewinger B-PER
, O
Dr. O
Braun B-PER
and O
Mr. O
Rindler B-PER
. O

Hospitals B-TER
. O

Nearly O
one O
quarter O
of O
the O
available O
space O
of O
the O
ghetto B-TER
was O
reserved O
for O
hospitals B-TER
or O
homes B-TER
for I-TER
aged I-TER
people I-TER
. O

As O
a O
matter O
of O
fact O
the O
Nazis O
had O
declared O
the O
town O
a O
Central O
Jewish O
Home O
for O
Aged O
People O
( O
Jeudisches O
Reichsaltersheim O
) O
, O
but O
with O
the O
growing O
transports B-TER
, O
people O
of O
different O
ages O
, O
even O
babies B-TER
, O
arrived O
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
. O

In O
the O
barracks O
converted O
to O
hospitals B-TER
there O
were O
real O
bedsteads O
. O

The O
doctors B-TER
, O
many O
of O
them O
from O
Czecho B-LOC
- I-LOC
Slovakia I-LOC
, O
had O
modern O
medical O
instruments O
at O
their O
disposal O
. O

Dentists O
, O
chemists O
, O
nurses O
and O
opticians O
were O
also O
on O
the O
staff O
of O
the O
health B-TER
department I-TER
, O
which O
was O
also O
in O
charge O
of O
the O
bath O
- O
house O
too O
, O
attached O
to O
one O
of O
the O
hospitals B-TER
. O

The O
work O
of O
the O
doctors B-TER
and O
their O
staff O
was O
beyond O
praise O
. O

They O
did O
everything O
in O
their O
power O
to O
alleviate O
the O
lot O
of O
their O
patients O
. O

The O
Jewish B-TER
self I-TER
- I-TER
administration I-TER
, O
with O
the O
help O
of O
the O
medical B-TER
staff I-TER
, O
even O
provided O
a O
diet O
kitchen O
and O
a O
special O
kitchen O
for O
children B-TER
, O
working O
independently O
of O
the O
five O
or O
six O
central O
kitchens O
in O
the O
barracks O
. O

-4- O
Mortality B-TER
Rate O
. O

Finally O
the O
crematorium B-TER
has O
to O
be O
mentioned O
, O
which O
had O
been O
built O
after O
the O
mortality B-TER
rate I-TER
had O
become O
very O
high O
. O

Before O
1944 O
, O
at O
the O
time O
when O
the O
place O
was O
inhabited O
by O
up O
to O
68,000 O
, O
about O
130 O
people O
died B-TER
daily O
. O

When O
I O
arrived O
in O
Feb. O
1944 O
the O
death B-TER
rate O
was O
about O
30 O
a O
day O
, O
and O
decreased O
later O
to O
10 O
. O

The O
reason O
was O
obvious O
. O

The O
old O
people O
had O
died B-TER
or O
had O
been O
deported B-TER
, O
the O
remaining O
ones O
had O
accustomed O
themselves O
to O
the O
meagre O
diet O
and O
were O
thus O
able O
to O
endure O
the O
hardships B-TER
. O

It O
can O
not O
be O
doubted O
that O
under O
- O
nourishment O
had O
been O
the O
chief O
cause O
of O
death B-TER
of O
the O
many O
old O
Jews O
who O
found O
their O
grave B-TER
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
. O

At O
the O
time O
when O
the O
settlement O
was O
started O
the O
dead B-TER
were O
buried B-TER
; O
afterwards O
they O
were O
cremated B-TER
and O
the O
urns O
kept O
in O
a O
more O
or O
less O
honoured O
place O
. O

Starvation B-TER
Diet O
. O

The O
diet O
was O
absolutely O
insufficient O
. O

The O
SS B-ORG
allocated B-TER
to O
the O
Jewish B-TER
self I-TER
- I-TER
administration I-TER
provisions O
calculated O
on O
the O
basis O
of O
an O
inadequate O
daily O
ration O
. O

But O
even O
so O
, O
the O
self B-TER
- I-TER
administration I-TER
had O
had O
to O
cut O
these O
meagre O
rations B-TER
in O
order O
to O
be O
able O
to O
give O
priority O
to O
heavy O
workers O
and O
a O
special O
diet O
to O
children B-TER
. O

It O
must O
be O
pointed O
out O
that O
the O
food B-TER
allocation I-TER
described O
below O
, O
though O
meagre O
enough O
, O
had O
been O
even O
worse O
before O
1944 O
. O

At O
that O
time O
many O
new O
inmates B-TER
died B-TER
not O
only O
from O
under O
- O
nourishment O
but O
from O
dysentery B-TER
or O
a O
similar O
disease B-TER
. O

The O
rations B-TER
available O
on O
food O
cards O
were O
: O
In O
the O
morning O
half O
a O
loaf O
of O
bread B-TER
for O
3 O
days O
, O
black O
bread B-TER
about O
750 O
grms O
. O

i.e. O
250 O
grms O
. O

daily O
. O

Heavy O
workers O
received O
a O
loaf O
of O
1,000 O
grms O
. O

for O
three O
days O
. O

– O
Coffee B-TER
substitute O
– O
70 O
grms O
. O

sugar B-TER
, O
60 O
grms O
. O

margarine B-TER
a O
week O
. O

Workers O
’ O
ration O
was O
– O
100 O
grms O
. O

sugar B-TER
and O
80 O
grms O
. O

margarine B-TER
. O

Lunch O
: O
Soup B-TER
consisting O
of O
water O
, O
salt O
and O
barely O
( O
0/30 O
liters O
) O
without O
any O
nourishment O
value O
– O
350 O
grms O
. O

potatoes B-TER
and O
0/25 O
litres O
of O
a O
sauce O
made O
from O
powder O
sometimes O
with O
a O
little O
meat B-TER
, O
or O
0.30 O
to O
0.40 O
litre O
vegetables B-TER
, O
mostly O
cabbage B-TER
. O

Instead O
of O
potatoes B-TER
occasionally O
dumplings B-TER
were O
served O
. O

Sometimes O
we O
had O
barley O
( O
0.40 O
litre O
) O
. O

Very O
seldom O
the O
kitchen O
received O
lettuce B-TER
. O

Supper O
: O
For O
supper O
we O
had O
a O
thick O
barley O
soup B-TER
four O
times O
a O
week O
, O
and O
twice O
a O
week O
a O
drink O
of O
coffee B-TER
substitute O
. O

Heavy O
Workers O
received O
50 O
% O
of O
the O
described O
diet O
in O
addition O
. O

The O
food B-TER
was O
well O
cooked O
and O
our O
cooks O
did O
everything O
to O
serve O
a O
tasty O
meal O
. O

Buchten B-TER
( O
yeast O
dumplings B-TER
) O
served O
once O
a O
week O
with O
coffee B-TER
and O
sugar B-TER
sauce O
were O
specially O
popular O
. O

Very O
occasionally O
the O
Red B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
supplied O
little O
cheeses B-TER
or O
liver B-TER
paste I-TER
. O

All O
in O
all O
, O
these O
rations B-TER
provided O
nothing O
but O
a O
starvation B-TER
diet O
. O

During O
the O
first O
three O
months O
of O
my O
stay O
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
I O
was O
hardly O
able O
to O
sleep O
at O
nights O
. O

I O
could O
think O
of O
nothing O
but O
food B-TER
, O
I O
even O
dreamt O
of O
food O
when O
I O
managed O
to O
fall O
asleep O
. O

At O
that O
time O
I O
was O
hungrier O
than O
later O
in O
Auschwitz B-LOC
, O
or O
in O
the O
Gleiwitz B-LOC
camp I-LOC
. O

When O
working O
in O
the O
office O
of O
the O
administration O
I O
could O
only O
concentrate O
my O
mind O
for O
the O
first O
two O
or O
three O
hours O
, O
and O
later O
failed O
to O
do O
sums O
. O

Naturally O
everybody O
lost O
weight O
rapidly O
. O

X O
A O
letter O
from O
a O
former O
member O
of O
a O
Jewish B-TER
Women I-TER
’s I-TER
Organisation I-TER
in O
Berlin B-LOC
, O
who O
was O
released O
from O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
in O
February O
1945 O
, O
states O
that O
the O
urns O
were O
removed O
by O
the O
SS B-ORG
one O
day O
. O

Nobody O
knows O
what O
happened O
to O
them O
. O

-5- O
Children B-TER
between O
4 O
and O
16 O
received B-TER
a O
better O
and O
more O
sufficient O
diet O
, O
extra O
milk B-TER
, O
skimmed O
cream B-TER
cheese I-TER
and O
some O
of O
the O
food B-TER
the O
Red B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
provided O
. O

Although O
babies B-TER
were O
given O
milk B-TER
, O
that O
milk B-TER
was O
skimmed O
and O
of O
low O
nutritive O
value O
. O

Fresh O
vegetables B-TER
, O
except O
cabbage B-TER
, O
and O
any O
kind O
of O
fruit O
were O
completely O
lacking O
, O
although O
the O
surrounding O
country O
was O
very O
rich O
in O
fruit O
, O
especially O
apples B-TER
. O

Those O
who O
received O
parcels O
from O
the O
Joint B-ORG
could O
consider O
themselves O
lucky O
, O
but O
many O
of O
the O
addressees O
were O
dead B-TER
or O
deported B-TER
at O
the O
time O
of O
the O
arrival O
of O
this O
help O
. O

The O
contents O
of O
the O
undeliverable O
parcels O
were O
given O
to O
relatives O
of O
the O
addressees O
, O
or O
to O
the O
hospitals B-TER
. O

Communal O
Life O
. O

Such O
were O
the O
basic O
conditions B-TER
on O
which O
the O
Jews O
had O
to O
build O
their O
communal O
life B-TER
in I-TER
the I-TER
ghetto I-TER
. O

There O
was O
no O
lack O
of O
intellectuals B-TER
who O
were O
able O
and O
willing O
to O
give O
lectures O
. O

I O
attended O
excellent O
lectures O
by O
Dr. B-PER
Baeck I-PER
and O
Prof. B-PER
Brahn I-PER
, O
the O
well O
- O
known O
philosopher O
, O
and O
Nietzsche B-PER
scholar O
, O
who O
, O
as O
I O
have O
been O
told O
, O
died B-TER
in O
Auschwitz B-LOC
after O
deportation B-TER
. O

I O
myself O
lectured O
on O
British B-LOC
education B-TER
in O
the O
so O
- O
called O
English B-LOC
Club O
, O
an O
unofficial O
gathering O
of O
people O
who O
tried O
to O
brush O
up O
their O
English O
. O

Musicians B-TER
. O

organised O
concerts O
, O
and O
even O
little O
opera O
performances B-TER
conducted O
by O
two O
Czech B-TER
Jews O
, O
Klein B-PER
and O
Schechter B-PER
( O
Dr. O
Kurt B-PER
Singer I-PER
, O
the O
Berlin B-LOC
conductor O
and O
leader O
of O
the O
Kulturbund O
der O
Juden O
in O
Deutschland O
, O
had O
died B-TER
just O
before O
my O
arrival O
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
) O
. O

There O
were O
also O
theatre B-TER
performances O
given O
by O
Czech B-TER
and O
German B-TER
actors B-TER
. O

Plays O
were O
produced O
in O
the O
little O
cinema O
of O
Terezin B-LOC
and O
in O
the O
barracks O
. O

The O
ghetto B-TER
cafe O
served O
lemonade B-TER
and O
coffee B-TER
substitute O
, O
but O
a O
piece O
of O
cake B-TER
or O
a O
bun B-TER
so O
much O
longed O
for O
was O
not O
available O
on O
the O
tariff O
of O
this O
show O
cafe O
. O

Dancing O
was O
officially O
not O
permitted O
, O
but O
some O
people O
nevertheless O
danced O
, O
Black O
i.e. O
, O
illegally O
. O

Neither O
was O
school O
education B-TER
allowed O
. O

We O
had O
many O
children B-TER
who O
were O
not O
able O
to O
read O
or O
write O
. O

Potemkin O
Village O
. O

But O
in O
a O
news O
reel O
which O
was O
made O
in O
order O
to O
bluff O
that O
part O
of O
the O
world O
on O
whose O
opinion O
the O
Nazis O
set O
great O
store O
you O
will O
find O
two O
school O
buildings O
. O

The O
news O
- O
reel O
was O
made O
when O
a O
Commission B-ORG
from O
Denmark B-LOC
arrived O
. O

Days O
in O
advance O
we O
had O
to O
clean O
the O
camp B-TER
and O
to O
paint O
the O
houses O
. O

The O
word O
School O
was O
put O
on O
two O
buildings O
, O
which O
were O
to O
represent O
the O
Girls O
’ O
School O
and O
the O
Boys O
’ O
School O
. O

During O
the O
week O
in O
which O
the O
Commission B-ORG
visited O
the O
model O
camp B-TER
, O
we O
received O
three O
times O
the O
ordinary O
rations O
. O

X O
X O
Mr. O
Ralph B-PER
Oppenheim I-PER
, O
who O
was O
one O
of O
the O
first O
Jews O
returned O
to O
Denmark B-LOC
after O
1½ O
years O
’ O
confinement O
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
, O
reports O
as O
follows O
in O
Berlinske O
Tidende O
about O
the O
visit O
of O
the O
Danish B-LOC
Commission B-ORG
: O
Some O
weeks O
before O
the O
Commission B-ORG
arrived O
we O
were O
ordered O
to O
paint O
the O
houses O
, O
and O
we O
got O
some O
Austrian B-TER
peasant O
furniture O
. O

Single O
beds O
were O
placed O
in O
the O
huts O
that O
were O
being O
shown O
. O

The O
day O
before O
the O
Commission B-ORG
arrived O
we O
were O
summoned O
before O
the O
Commandant O
, O
who O
gave O
us O
to O
understand O
that O
should O
we O
dare O
to O
tell O
the O
Commission B-ORG
about O
the O
real O
conditions B-TER
all O
the O
Danes B-TER
would O
be O
sent O
eastwards B-TER
, O
and O
at O
the O
same O
time O
the O
food B-TER
parcels O
from O
home O
would O
be O
taken O
away O
from O
us O
. O

And O
we O
knew O
that O
this O
would O
be O
equivalent O
to O
death B-TER
. O

All O
the O
sick B-TER
, O
the O
war O
invalids O
and O
old O
people O
were O
put O
into O
houses O
which O
would O
not O
be O
shown O
to O
the O
Commission B-ORG
. O

For O
the O
children B-TER
a O
kindergarten O
was O
arranged O
in O
a O
great O
hurry O
. O

The O
children B-TER
were O
instructed O
that O
when O
the O
Commandant O
entered O
with O
the O
Commission B-ORG
, O
they O
must O
run O
to O
meet O
him O
and O
shout O
Good O
- O
day O
Uncle O
Rahm O
, O
are O
you O
coming O
to O
play O
with O
us O
? O
and O
as O
the O
party O
left O
they O
were O
to O
say O
When O
are O
you O
coming O
to O
see O
us O
again O
, O
Uncle O
Rahm O
? O
The O
Commission B-ORG
was O
tricked O
. O

Everyone O
ought O
to O
have O
been O
able O
to O
scent O
that O
the O
painting O
was O
fresh O
, O
that O
the O
furniture O
in O
our O
huts O
had O
been O
lately O
put O
in O
and O
had O
not O
been O
used O
. O

And O
our O
eyes O
ought O
to O
have O
told O
them O
the O
rest O
– O
but O
instead O
they O
thought O
that O
we O
were O
in O
good O
spirits O
and O
full O
of O
hope O
. O

-6- O
The O
whole O
character O
of O
the O
town O
was O
changed O
by O
this O
embellishment O
by O
order O
. O

Recreation O
grounds O
were O
laid O
out O
with O
large O
flower O
- O
beds O
, O
a O
music B-TER
tent O
where O
the O
town O
band O
gave O
concert O
every O
afternoon O
was O
built O
, O
a O
kindergarten O
with O
cradles O
, O
a O
slide O
and O
a O
see O
- O
saw O
was O
established O
, O
as O
well O
as O
a O
laundry O
. O

Even O
a O
restaurant O
was O
opened O
where O
one O
could O
eat O
one O
's O
meals O
on O
one O
's O
ration B-TER
card O
. O

The O
benches O
erected O
in O
the O
improvised O
parks O
turned O
out O
to O
be O
a O
blessing O
for O
the O
inmates B-TER
who O
, O
from O
that O
time O
on O
, O
could O
sit O
down O
in O
the O
open O
. O

In O
a O
word O
, O
a O
Potemkin O
village O
was O
put O
before O
the O
eyes O
of O
the O
foreign O
visitors O
. O

Dr. O
Epstein B-PER
had O
to O
make O
an O
exaggerated O
report O
about O
the O
favourable O
conditions B-TER
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
to O
the O
delegation O
. O

He O
was O
sure O
, O
as O
he O
told O
us O
, O
that O
the O
members O
of O
the O
Commission B-ORG
would O
realise O
the O
bluff O
the O
Nazis O
were O
putting O
up O
, O
but O
apparently O
the O
Commission B-ORG
allowed O
themselves O
to O
be O
deceived O
. O

Reproduction O
Prohibited O
. O

Dr. O
Epstein B-PER
had O
to O
mention O
the O
high O
birth O
rate O
in O
the O
ghetto B-TER
, O
while O
in O
fact O
reproduction O
was O
prohibited B-TER
. O

Women B-TER
when O
entering O
the O
camp B-TER
were O
warned O
that O
they O
had O
to O
undergo O
abortion O
during O
the O
first O
four O
months O
of O
their O
pregnancy O
. O

Nevertheless O
there O
were O
about O
150 O
babies B-TER
born O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
, O
black O
babies O
as O
we O
used O
to O
call O
them O
, O
babies B-TER
born O
in O
spite O
of O
the O
prohibition B-TER
. O

Religious B-TER
Services I-TER
. O

Services O
were O
held O
by O
Dr. B-PER
Baeck I-PER
and O
other O
Rabbis B-TER
. O

I O
venture O
to O
say O
that O
, O
in O
spite O
of O
the O
hardships B-TER
we O
had O
to O
undergo O
in O
the O
ghetto B-TER
, O
and O
the O
even O
more O
severe O
conditions O
which O
we O
inmates B-TER
had O
experienced O
before O
, O
people O
had O
not O
become O
more O
deeply O
attached O
to O
religion B-TER
than O
they O
had O
generally O
been O
. O

Jewish O
Police B-TER
and O
Jewish O
Court B-TER
. O

Order O
was O
kept O
by O
the O
Community O
Guard B-TER
( O
Gemeindewache B-TER
) O
, O
formerly O
called O
Ghetto O
Wache O
, O
which O
, O
like O
every O
other O
institution B-TER
in O
the O
ghetto B-TER
, O
consisted O
of O
Jews O
. O

There O
was O
also O
a O
Jewish B-TER
Court I-TER
before O
which O
marriages B-TER
could O
be O
registered O
according O
to O
Jewish O
law O
. O

In O
addition O
the O
Court B-TER
acted O
in O
Penal O
cases O
e.g. O
thefts O
. O

It O
had O
to O
send O
its O
sentences O
to O
the O
SS B-ORG
for O
confirmation O
. O

Prison B-TER
sentences O
were O
executed O
in O
the O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
prison B-TER
. O

Only O
in O
one O
case O
did O
the O
SS B-ORG
demand O
heavier O
punishment O
than O
the O
Court B-TER
had O
pronounced O
. O

The O
SS B-ORG
. O

Sent O
the O
defendant O
who O
had O
committed O
theft O
of O
provisions O
to O
the O
concentration B-LOC
camp I-LOC
in I-LOC
the I-LOC
small I-LOC
fortress I-LOC
. I-LOC

Otherwise O
the O
SS B-ORG
. O

did O
not O
interfere O
with O
camp B-TER
life I-TER
, O
at O
least O
according O
to O
the O
experience O
of O
the O
ordinary O
inmate B-TER
. O

We O
did O
not O
see O
any O
SS B-ORG
men O
apart O
from O
the O
Commandant O
who O
occasionally O
rode O
on O
horseback O
through O
the O
ghetto B-TER
streets O
. O

The O
camp B-TER
administration I-TER
, O
however O
, O
had O
to O
work O
under O
the O
daily O
threat O
of O
their O
SS B-ORG
supervisors O
. O

Camp B-TER
Currency O
. O

The O
official O
currency O
of O
the O
ghetto B-TER
was O
the O
so O
- O
called O
Ghetto B-TER
Krone O
, O
a O
specially O
designed O
camp O
currency O
which O
the O
ghetto B-TER
bank O
circulated O
. O

Camp B-TER
workers O
earned O
up O
to O
100 O
Ghetto B-TER
Crowns O
a O
month O
. O

For O
this O
one O
could O
buy O
provisions O
such O
as O
mustard B-TER
, O
carraway B-TER
- I-TER
seeds I-TER
, O
a O
kind O
of O
Oxo O
, O
but O
also O
theatre B-TER
tickets O
and O
coupons O
on O
which O
the O
cafe O
sold O
lemonade B-TER
and O
coffee B-TER
. O

Old O
clothing B-TER
, O
shoes O
and O
travelling O
cases O
left O
by O
the O
deportees B-TER
or O
the O
deceased B-TER
, O
were O
also O
sold O
for O
Ghetto B-TER
Crowns O
provided O
one O
had O
the O
necessary O
points O
, O
which O
were O
issued O
. O

But O
things O
badly O
needed O
, O
such O
as O
additional O
food B-TER
or O
cigarettes O
, O
were O
not O
available O
for O
camp B-TER
money O
. O

For O
treasures O
like O
these O
one O
had O
to O
pay O
in O
Reichsmarks O
or O
Czech B-TER
Crowns O
. O

On O
the O
Black B-TER
Market I-TER
, O
which O
, O
owing O
to O
the O
starvation B-TER
diet O
and O
the O
complete O
lack O
of O
tobacco O
, O
had O
developed O
of O
necessity O
as O
in O
every O
prison B-TER
camp B-TER
, O
one O
could O
buy O
a O
loaf O
for O
15 O
Marks O
or O
a O
cigarette O
for O
4.50 O
Marks O
( O
5/- O
) O
. O

These O
cigarettes O
were O
smuggled O
into O
the O
camp B-TER
by O
people O
working O
outside O
the O
ghetto B-TER
walls O
, O
in O
some O
cases O
by O
SS B-ORG
men O
themselves O
, O
who O
made O
tremendous O
profits O
from O
this O
illegal O
traffic O
. O

On O
the O
other O
hand O
SS B-ORG
parties O
raided O
the O
camp B-TER
in O
order O
to O
find O
out O
people O
possessing O
currency O
i.e. O
Reichsmarks O
or O
Czech B-TER
Crowns O
, O
gold O
or O
jewellery O
. O

Anybody O
caught O
in O
possession O
of O
State O
currency O
was O
sent O
to O
the O
concentration B-LOC
camp I-LOC
in I-LOC
the I-LOC
small I-LOC
fortress I-LOC
from O
which O
nearly O
every O
week O
transports B-TER
went O
to O
the O
notorious O
Auschwitz B-LOC
camp I-LOC
. O

-7- O
Relations O
between O
the O
inmates B-TER
were O
better O
than O
in O
Westerbork B-LOC
nor O
in O
Auschwitz B-LOC
. O

People O
were O
not O
as O
nervous O
as O
they O
were O
in O
the O
more O
notorious O
camps B-TER
. O

In O
a O
concentration B-TER
camp I-TER
everyone O
considers O
his O
neighbour O
an O
enemy O
who O
might O
jeopardise O
one O
's O
own O
chance O
of O
survival B-TER
. O

In O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
your O
neighbour O
was O
not O
exactly O
your O
friend O
, O
but O
at O
least O
a O
neutral O
person O
. O

I O
have O
only O
noticed O
some O
tension O
and O
state O
of O
irritation O
arising O
in O
the O
relations O
of O
married O
couples O
owing O
to O
the O
separation O
. O

Humanity O
True O
to O
Nazi O
Pattern O
. O

Such O
was O
life O
in O
the O
show O
camp B-TER
the O
Nazis O
had O
deliberately O
organised O
to O
provide O
an O
alibi O
for O
themselves O
. O

Was O
it O
not O
an O
example O
of O
humanity O
to O
set O
up O
a O
kindergarten O
, O
to O
permit O
Jews O
to O
go O
to O
a O
cafe O
or O
to O
listen O
to O
a O
music B-TER
band O
? O
Humane O
indeed O
, O
if O
you O
call O
it O
humane O
to O
deprive O
decent O
, O
innocent O
people O
arbitrarily O
of O
their O
freedom O
, O
to O
strip O
them O
of O
everything O
but O
the O
clothes O
they O
had O
on O
, O
to O
feed O
them O
on O
a O
diet O
which O
enables O
only O
the O
strong O
to O
survive B-TER
, O
to O
isolate B-TER
ordinary O
people O
and O
some O
who O
had O
won O
world O
fame O
, O
completely O
from O
the O
outer O
world O
, O
behind O
guarded O
ghetto B-TER
walls O
, O
sealed O
off O
from O
life O
. O

All O
the O
time O
I O
could O
not O
help O
imagining O
that O
we O
were O
interred O
in O
a O
mass B-TER
grave I-TER
in O
which O
people O
were O
dancing O
. O

People O
danced O
, O
attended O
theatres B-TER
or O
concerts B-TER
in O
order O
to O
escape O
the O
constant O
nightmare O
haunting O
the O
minds O
of O
all O
of O
us O
: O
the O
threat O
of O
further O
deportation B-TER
to O
the O
East O
. O

Parents O
hoping O
to O
survive B-TER
the O
Nazi O
way O
against O
the O
Jews O
together O
with O
their O
children B-TER
were O
separated O
from O
each O
other O
. O

Old O
brothers O
and O
sisters O
who O
had O
been O
reunited O
in O
the O
ghetto B-TER
had O
had O
to O
part O
again O
. O

A O
sister O
who O
was O
only O
64 O
years O
of O
age O
had O
had O
to O
go O
first O
, O
leaving O
her O
brothers O
or O
sisters O
behind O
her O
, O
who O
were O
fortunate O
enough O
to O
be O
in O
their O
seventies O
. O

But O
even O
very O
old O
age O
was O
no O
protection O
against O
the O
fate O
of O
being O
selected B-TER
for O
the O
next O
transport B-TER
, O
for O
the O
train B-TER
, O
destination O
unknown O
. O

Thus O
was O
the O
humanity O
administered O
in O
the O
model O
camp B-TER
true O
to O
Nazi O
character O
. O

There O
was O
of O
course O
a O
difference O
between O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
and O
the O
Eastern O
camps B-TER
. O

In O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
those O
at O
least O
who O
were O
permitted O
to O
stay O
there O
, O
were O
allowed O
to O
die B-TER
slowly O
. O

In O
the O
East O
the O
death B-TER
sentence O
never O
expressly O
pronounced O
was O
carried O
out O
immediately O
on O
arrival O
. O

Transports B-TER
to O
the O
East O
. O

Work O
detachments O
had O
left O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
before O
my O
arrival O
and O
continued O
to O
leave O
the O
ghetto B-TER
from O
time O
to O
time O
. O

They O
did O
not O
go O
to O
the O
East O
, O
but O
were O
sent O
to O
Germany B-LOC
to O
build O
barracks O
and O
huts O
for O
the O
SS B-ORG
e.g. O
in O
Zossen B-LOC
. O

Only O
skilled O
workers O
, O
young O
men B-TER
in O
good O
health O
, O
were O
detailed O
for O
this O
kind O
of O
work B-TER
. O

They O
still O
belonged O
to O
the O
so O
- O
called O
ArbeitskommandoTheresienstadt O
( O
Work O
Detachment O
) O
, O
and O
were O
brought O
back O
to O
the O
ghetto B-TER
when O
sick B-TER
or O
disabled B-TER
. O

But O
on O
the O
11th O
May O
1944 O
a O
different O
kind O
of O
transport B-TER
was O
ordered O
. O

The O
Hamburger O
barracks O
were O
cleared O
and O
there O
the O
people O
selected B-TER
for O
this O
transport B-TER
had O
to O
assemble O
. O

The O
Jewish O
self B-TER
- I-TER
administration I-TER
had O
the O
heart O
- O
breaking O
task O
of O
choosing O
the O
victims O
according O
to O
general O
orders O
of O
the O
SS B-ORG
. O

Some O
deportees B-TER
were O
named O
by O
special O
instructions O
from O
the O
SS B-ORG
. O

On O
the O
18th O
May O
1944 O
7,000 O
men B-TER
, O
women B-TER
and O
children B-TER
left O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
for O
Auschwitz B-LOC
, O
transported B-TER
in O
good O
wagons B-TER
, O
and O
under O
the O
guard O
of O
SS B-ORG
and O
Security B-ORG
Police I-ORG
. O

Goods O
wagons B-TER
and O
SS B-ORG
........ O
these O
were O
evil O
forebodings O
. O

In O
September O
1944 O
I O
met O
one O
person O
, O
who O
had O
left O
with O
that O
transport B-TER
, O
in O
Auschwitz B-LOC
, O
just O
one O
........ O
In O
spite O
of O
the O
uncertainty O
, O
or O
rather O
the O
certainty O
of O
their O
future O
fate O
, O
men B-TER
, O
women B-TER
, O
children B-TER
and O
sick B-TER
people O
left O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
composedly O
. O

On O
the O
20th O
September O
1944 O
a O
second O
transport B-TER
was O
announced O
, O
this O
time O
a O
work B-TER
detachment O
for O
Germany B-LOC
. O

Neither O
sick B-TER
people O
nor O
women B-TER
were O
selected B-TER
, O
only O
able O
- O
bodied O
men B-TER
of O
military O
age O
. O

It O
first O
seemed O
as O
if O
there O
were O
some O
truth O
in O
the O
alleged O
purpose O
of O
that O
transport B-TER
, O
work O
in O
Germany B-LOC
. O

When O
I O
, O
who O
had O
to O
join O
this O
party O
of O
2,500 O
men B-TER
, O
saw O
goods O
wagons B-TER
I O
did O
not O
feel O
at O
ease O
. O

On O
the O
26th O
September O
1944 O
the O
train B-TER
left O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
. O

Near O
Dresden B-LOC
the O
SS B-ORG
guards O
asked O
us O
to O
write O
a O
p O
ost B-TER
card I-TER
to O
our O
wives B-TER
. O

We O
were O
to O
tell O
them O
that O
we O
had O
arrived O
at O
our O
destination O
, O
that O
food B-TER
and O
accommodation B-TER
were O
good O
and O
work O
was O
not O
too O
heavy O
. O

We O
were O
to O
invite O
our O
wives B-TER
to O
follow O
us O
as O
soon O
as O
possible O
. O

This O
-8- O
trick O
was O
obvious O
. O

By O
this O
bait O
the O
SS B-ORG
wanted O
to O
entice O
our O
wives B-TER
to O
join O
us O
without O
arousing O
any O
suspicion O
about O
the O
destination O
of O
the O
next O
women B-TER
’s I-TER
transport B-TER
. O

Although O
they O
had O
the O
power O
to O
force O
everybody O
into O
a O
death B-TER
train B-TER
they O
employed O
diabolical O
methods O
like O
these O
to O
deceive O
people O
about O
their O
fate O
in O
order O
to O
avoid O
irritation O
and O
disturbances O
in O
the O
model O
camp O
. O

Perhaps O
another O
commission B-TER
might O
arrive O
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
and O
notice O
the O
change O
in O
the O
mental O
atmosphere O
of O
the O
inmates B-TER
. O

The O
same O
method O
was O
employed O
on O
many O
occasions O
all O
over O
the O
eastern O
camps B-TER
. O

That O
accounts O
for O
the O
numerous O
messages O
relatives O
received O
describing O
favourable O
conditions O
in O
the O
east O
. O

The O
Hangman O
. O

After O
a O
journey O
of O
three O
days O
and O
two O
nights O
the O
train B-TER
arrived O
at O
a O
railway O
siding O
on O
29th O
September O
1944 O
. O

It O
was O
dark O
, O
about O
9 O
p.m. O
, O
but O
though O
we O
could O
not O
see O
the O
name O
of O
the O
station O
we O
guessed O
we O
were O
in O
the O
notorious O
Oswiecim B-LOC
( I-LOC
Auschwitz I-LOC
) I-LOC
camp I-LOC
. O

We O
were O
dragged O
out O
of O
the O
wagons B-TER
by O
prisoners B-TER
and O
not O
allowed O
to O
take O
our O
luggage O
with O
us O
. O

It O
was O
looted O
afterwards O
, O
and O
even O
the O
small O
rations O
we O
had O
were O
stolen O
by O
the O
old O
camp B-TER
inmates B-TER
. O

We O
were O
formed O
into O
files O
and O
had O
to O
pass O
an O
SS B-ORG
officer O
– O
most O
probably O
an O
SS B-ORG
doctor B-TER
. O

He O
sat O
on O
a O
chair O
, O
three O
yards O
away O
from O
us O
, O
with O
legs O
outstretched O
in O
a O
half O
? O
? O
Text O
unclear O
position O
, O
almost O
motionless O
. O

The O
only O
part O
of O
his O
body O
which O
he O
moved O
was O
the O
thumb B-TER
of O
his O
right O
hand O
. O

With O
this O
he O
pointed O
either O
to O
the O
left O
or O
to O
the O
right O
as O
a O
man O
stood O
in O
front O
of O
him O
. O

He O
did O
not O
utter O
a O
single O
word O
. O

We O
had O
been O
ordered O
to O
answer O
three O
questions O
: O
What O
age O
, O
what O
occupation O
, O
in O
what O
state O
of O
health O
. O

I O
answered O
: O
27 O
– O
metal O
worker O
– O
fit O
. O

The O
SS B-ORG
officer O
thumbed O
me O
to O
the O
right O
. O

After O
this O
sorting B-TER
of O
human O
beings O
1600 O
men B-TER
found O
themselves O
on O
the O
right O
, O
900 O
on O
the O
left O
. O

Not O
everybody O
had O
declared O
himself O
fit O
. O

Was O
this O
not O
after O
all O
a O
working B-TER
detachment O
? O
The O
very O
word O
seemed O
to O
indicate O
that O
there O
were O
different O
kinds O
of O
work B-TER
to O
do O
, O
heavy O
for O
younger O
people O
, O
and O
lighter O
work O
for O
elderly O
men B-TER
. O

Thus O
some O
of O
the O
parded O
men B-TER
may O
have O
explained O
that O
they O
were O
suffering O
from O
complaints O
preventing O
them O
from O
doing O
too O
heavy O
work B-TER
. O

Others O
gave O
themselves O
away O
by O
their O
grey O
hair O
, O
though O
the O
whole O
detachment O
consisted O
of O
men B-TER
of O
military B-TER
age O
. O

This O
latter O
fact O
explains O
why O
so O
few O
were O
directed O
to O
the O
left O
. O

As O
I O
heard O
afterwards O
the O
usual O
percentage O
of O
people O
selected B-TER
for O
annihilation B-TER
was O
85/90 O
% O
. O

While O
queuing O
in O
front O
of O
our O
hangman O
we O
saw O
flames O
arising O
from O
the O
chimneys O
of O
several O
buildings O
, O
and O
were O
told O
by O
the O
old O
timers O
that O
these O
housed O
the O
central O
heating O
plants O
of O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

During O
the O
whole O
night O
we O
had O
to O
stand O
in O
a O
stable O
. O

Then O
we O
had O
to O
strip O
and O
to O
give O
up O
everything O
, O
including O
our O
wedding O
rings O
, O
except O
our O
belts O
, O
spectacles O
and O
shoes O
. O

We O
were O
next O
led O
into O
a O
bath O
- O
house O
where O
our O
heads O
were O
shaved O
and O
we O
had O
to O
take O
a O
shower O
. O

We O
, O
i.e. O
the O
1600 O
fortunate O
ones O
. O

Extermination B-TER
. O

The O
other O
party O
, O
the O
900 O
doomed O
men B-TER
, O
had O
undergone O
the O
same O
procedure O
of O
waiting O
, O
stripping O
and O
giving O
up O
their O
belongings O
. O

They O
too O
were O
led O
into O
a O
bath O
- O
house O
, O
but O
instead O
of O
steam O
and O
water O
, O
poison O
gas B-TER
was O
infiltrated O
into O
that O
chamber B-TER
. O

All O
our O
900 O
comrades O
, O
with O
some O
of O
whom O
we O
had O
shared O
the O
times O
of O
anxiety O
and O
persecution B-TER
in O
Holland B-LOC
, O
and O
later O
the O
months O
of O
respite O
, O
hope O
and O
again O
anxiety O
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
, O
met O
their O
end O
in O
the O
death B-TER
chambers I-TER
of O
Auschwitz B-LOC
on O
the O
morning O
of O
the O
30th O
Sept. O
1944 O
. O

They O
had O
, O
as O
one O
of O
the O
Jewish B-TER
camp I-TER
doctors I-TER
told O
me O
later O
, O
not O
known O
up O
to O
the O
last O
moment O
, O
what O
was O
in O
store O
for O
them O
. O

Before O
they O
entered O
the O
gate O
of O
death B-TER
the O
fate O
of O
three O
of O
the O
doomed O
men O
changed O
at O
the O
very O
last O
moment O
. O

Some O
SS B-ORG
men B-TER
passing O
that O
batch O
of O
people O
being O
led O
to O
the O
gas B-TER
chambers I-TER
picked O
out O
three O
men B-TER
, O
maybe O
because O
they O
seemed O
still O
fit O
for O
work B-TER
. O

One O
of O
the O
three O
thus O
saved O
a O
few O
minutes O
before O
annihilation B-TER
was O
Spitz B-PER
, O
a O
civil O
engineer O
of O
about O
50 O
. O

His O
brother B-TER
, O
a O
Czech B-TER
Jew O
, O
who O
had O
been O
brought O
to O
Auschwitz B-LOC
at O
the O
same O
time O
, O
had O
to O
leave O
the O
camp B-TER
with O
-9- O
a O
work O
detachment O
on O
the O
1st O
October O
. O

He O
had O
seen O
his O
brother B-TER
, O
the O
engineer O
, O
go O
to O
the O
left O
, O
selected B-TER
as O
one O
of O
the O
900 O
, O
and O
left O
the O
camp B-TER
under O
the O
impression O
that O
his O
brother B-TER
had O
been O
asphyxiated O
with O
the O
others O
. O

But O
Spitz B-PER
, O
the O
engineer O
, O
was O
alive O
at O
least O
at O
the O
time O
of O
my O
leaving O
Auschwitz B-LOC
in O
the O
middle O
of O
October O
. O

Among O
the O
selected B-LOC
men B-TER
were O
Engineer O
Zucker B-PER
, O
one O
of O
Dr. O
Epstein B-PER
's O
colleagues O
in O
the O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
camp B-TER
administration I-TER
, O
an O
able O
and O
distinguished O
man O
, O
and O
the O
actors B-TER
Max B-PER
Ehrlich I-PER
and O
Willy B-PER
Rosen I-PER
, O
Ehrlich B-PER
conspicuous O
by O
his O
grey O
hair O
. O

X O
We O
stayed O
in O
Section O
E O
of O
Auschwitz B-LOC
, O
the O
so O
- O
called O
gypsy B-TER
camp B-TER
, O
a O
quarantine O
for O
new O
arrivals O
. O

Human O
Guinea O
- O
Pigs O
. O

There O
I O
heard O
from O
the O
Dutch B-TER
Jewish O
doctor B-TER
Sal B-PER
. I-PER

De I-PER
Jong I-PER
, O
that O
the O
SS B-PER
doctor I-PER
Moll I-PER
, O
and O
his O
SS B-ORG
colleagues O
, O
were O
experimenting B-TER
on O
camp B-TER
inmates I-TER
. O

I O
was O
told O
of O
experiments B-TER
made O
with O
twins O
and O
also O
of O
vivisection O
carried O
out O
on O
human O
beings O
. O

A O
girl B-TER
from O
the O
Auschwitz B-LOC
camp B-TER
who O
had O
hidden O
there O
when O
the O
Germans B-TER
evacuated B-TER
Auschwitz B-LOC
, O
and O
whom O
I O
met O
after O
my O
escape B-TER
, O
told O
me O
that O
these O
human O
guinea O
- O
pigs O
were O
all O
killed B-TER
before O
the O
evacuation B-TER
. O

At O
that O
time O
the O
gas B-TER
chambers I-TER
were O
no O
longer O
working O
, O
nor O
were O
the O
crematoria B-TER
which O
had O
been O
blown B-TER
up I-TER
. O

The O
victims B-TER
were O
therefore O
thrown O
into O
pits O
and O
unslaked O
lime O
was O
poured O
over O
them O
. O

Whether O
they O
had O
been O
shot O
before O
I O
do O
not O
know O
, O
but O
the O
Jewish B-TER
camp I-TER
doctor I-TER
, O
Epstein B-PER
from O
Prague B-LOC
, O
who O
has O
survived B-TER
, O
must O
be O
able O
to O
furnish O
further O
information O
. O

XX O
In O
Auschwitz B-LOC
everybody O
was O
more O
than O
keen O
on O
being O
transferred B-TER
to O
a O
camp B-TER
in O
which O
conditions B-TER
were O
supposed O
to O
be O
somewhat O
bearable O
. O

In O
the O
opinion O
of O
X O
Willy B-PER
Rosen I-PER
was O
well O
known O
as O
a O
writer O
and O
composer O
of O
popular O
airs O
, O
which O
were O
sung O
and O
whistled O
all O
over O
Germany B-LOC
. O

Max B-PER
Ehrlich I-PER
, O
a O
highly O
educated O
actor B-TER
and O
a O
book O
- O
collector O
Text O
blurred O
, O
was O
up O
to O
1933 O
one O
of O
the O
most O
popular O
comedians O
in O
Berlin B-LOC
, O
a O
star O
of O
the O
Admiralspalast O
shows O
. O

In O
1933 O
, O
when O
he O
was O
banned O
from O
appearing O
before O
German B-TER
audiences O
, O
he O
joined O
the O
Judische O
Kulturbund O
. O

His O
fine O
performances O
in O
comedies O
, O
and O
his O
cabaret B-TER
shows O
, O
were O
gratefully O
applauded O
by O
the O
Jewish O
public O
whose O
minds O
Ehrlich B-PER
distracted O
from O
the O
daily O
humiliations B-TER
. O

A O
few O
days O
after O
the O
November B-TER
pogrom I-TER
of I-TER
1938 I-TER
had O
been O
staged O
by O
the O
Nazis O
, O
thousands O
of O
Jewish O
men B-TER
imprisoned B-TER
and O
all O
the O
Jewish B-TER
organisation I-TER
s O
closed O
down O
by O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
, O
the O
Nazi O
supervisor O
of O
the O
Kulturbund O
, O
Hinkel B-PER
, O
ordered O
the O
re O
- O
opening O
of O
the O
Kulturbund O
and O
forced O
Ehrlich B-PER
to O
present O
a O
cabaret B-TER
show O
. O

The O
world O
reacting O
with O
disgust O
to O
the O
pogrom B-TER
was O
told O
by O
the O
Nazi B-TER
Press I-TER
that O
the O
Jews O
could O
even O
enjoy O
cabaret B-TER
shows O
, O
and O
the O
reports O
in O
the O
foreign O
press O
were O
nothing O
but O
atrocity O
stories O
. O

This O
November O
performance O
on O
Gestapo B-ORG
orders O
was O
to O
become O
a O
symbol O
of O
Ehrlich B-PER
's I-PER
future O
fate O
: O
a O
comedian O
who O
had O
to O
smile O
and O
make O
people O
laugh O
by O
the O
order O
of O
his O
mortal O
enemy O
. O

In O
1939 O
Ehrlich B-PER
emigrated B-TER
to O
Holland B-LOC
where O
he O
opened O
a O
cabaret B-TER
together O
with O
Camilla B-PER
Spira I-PER
and O
Kurt B-PER
Gerron I-PER
. O

After O
the O
occupation B-TER
of O
Holland B-LOC
Ehrlich B-PER
was O
taken O
to O
the O
Westerbork B-LOC
camp I-LOC
and O
again O
, O
on O
the O
Commandant O
’s O
order O
, O
had O
to O
cheer O
up O
the O
people O
in O
this O
vast O
waiting O
- O
room O
for O
the O
train B-TER
into O
limbo O
. O

( O
See O
no O
. O

2 O
. O

of O
our O
Series O
The O
Persecution O
of O
Jews O
in O
Holland O
) O
. O

In O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
, O
where O
he O
was O
taken O
from O
Westerbork B-LOC
, O
he O
could O
not O
continue O
this O
work O
, O
because O
he O
was O
only O
there O
for O
a O
fortnight O
. O

This O
true O
Pagliacci O
fate O
ended O
in O
the O
extermination B-TER
chambers I-TER
of O
Auschwitz B-LOC
. O

XX O
He O
has O
already O
given O
evidence O
to O
the O
Russian B-TER
Authorities O
. O

-10- O
the O
Auschwitz B-LOC
candidates O
for O
death B-TER
, O
Belsen B-LOC
, O
Buchenwald B-LOC
and O
Dachau B-LOC
were O
considered O
to O
be O
gute O
K.Z.s O
( O
good O
concentration B-TER
camps I-TER
) O
; O
dreaded O
camps B-TER
were O
, O
besides O
Auschwitz B-LOC
, O
Mauthausen B-LOC
and O
the O
forest O
camp B-TER
Bielce O
. O

Most O
of O
our O
rations B-TER
were O
embezzled O
by O
the O
Capos O
and O
block O
elders O
( O
overseers B-TER
and O
prisoners B-TER
themselves O
) O
who O
sold O
their O
loot O
in O
the O
Black B-TER
Market I-TER
. O

Black O
marketeering O
flourished O
in O
a O
camp B-TER
where O
, O
owing O
to O
the O
daily O
presence O
of O
death B-TER
– O
meanwhile O
we O
had O
learned O
the O
real O
meaning O
of O
the O
fires O
rising O
from O
the O
central O
heating O
plant O
– O
all O
normal O
moral O
restrictions O
had O
ceased O
. O

The O
Capos B-TER
, O
mostly O
non O
- O
Jewish O
criminals B-TER
, O
among O
them O
many O
homo B-TER
- I-TER
sexuals I-TER
and O
brutes O
, O
sold O
gold O
fillings O
extracted O
from O
the O
teeth O
of O
the O
gassed B-TER
victims B-TER
, O
and O
especially O
valuables O
or O
currency O
, O
looted O
from O
the O
luggage O
of O
the O
new O
arrivals O
. O

The O
members O
of O
the O
so O
- O
called O
Canada B-ORG
detachment I-ORG
employed O
in O
searching O
the O
luggage O
and O
clothing B-TER
of O
the O
newcomers O
, O
plundered O
them O
and O
enriched O
themselves O
grossly O
. O

A O
diamond O
brooch O
found O
in O
a O
jam O
jar O
, O
in O
which O
a O
deportee O
had O
tried O
to O
save O
his O
last O
treasure O
, O
fetched O
40,000 O
Marks O
. O

That O
sum O
enabled O
the O
black B-TER
marketeer I-TER
who O
sold O
it O
to O
buy O
food B-TER
and O
tobacco O
for O
just O
one O
month O
. O

Gleiwitz B-LOC
. O

Registration B-TER
only O
took O
place O
when O
prisoners B-TER
were O
detailed O
for O
work B-TER
. O

In O
exchange O
for O
their O
name O
they O
got O
a O
number O
which O
was O
tattooed O
on O
the O
arm O
. O

My O
number O
was O
B12749 O
. O

The O
registers B-TER
kept O
in O
the O
political B-TER
department I-TER
of O
Auschwitz B-LOC
were O
burned B-TER
when O
the O
Nazis O
retreated O
in O
Jan. O
1945 O
. O

I O
should O
like O
to O
point O
out O
that O
the O
deportees B-TER
who O
were O
gassed B-TER
immediately O
on O
arrival O
were B-TER
not I-TER
registered I-TER
at O
all O
. O

They O
were O
destroyed O
like O
vermin O
, O
nameless O
victims B-TER
, O
leaving O
no O
trace O
behind O
them O
. O

In O
the O
middle O
of O
Oct. O
1944 O
, O
after O
being O
clothed B-TER
in O
prisoner B-TER
's I-TER
garments O
and O
given O
wooden O
boots O
– O
usually O
leather O
shoes O
were O
stolen O
by O
the O
Capos B-TER
– O
I O
was O
transferred B-TER
to O
the O
work B-TER
camp I-TER
Gleiwitz B-LOC
III I-LOC
. O

It O
belonged O
to O
the O
Concentration B-LOC
Camp I-LOC
Auschwitz I-LOC
III I-LOC
. I-LOC

We O
were O
housed O
in O
the O
yard O
of O
a O
foundry O
, O
Oberhuette O
, O
Stahl O
& O
Presswerk O
, O
Gleiwitz B-TER
von I-TER
Krugstrasse I-TER
I. O
There O
we O
got O
our O
food B-TER
and O
were O
not O
allowed O
to O
leave O
the O
yard O
, O
converted O
into O
a O
small O
concentration B-TER
camp I-TER
and O
surrounded O
by O
electrified O
barbed O
wire O
. O

We O
, O
the O
new O
batch O
of O
150 O
men O
, O
found O
there O
450 O
old O
prisoners B-TER
. O

We O
were O
to O
assemble O
gun O
carriages O
, O
which O
should O
have O
been O
assembled O
at O
the O
rate O
of O
four O
a O
day O
, O
but O
owing O
to O
the O
lack O
of O
tools O
, O
skilled O
labour O
and O
sabotage B-TER
which O
we O
tried O
to O
do O
wherever O
we O
could O
, O
it O
took O
us O
six O
weeks O
to O
assemble O
the O
schemed O
production O
of O
two O
days O
. O

We O
worked O
under O
the O
supervision O
of O
a O
Polish B-TER
Chief O
Engineer O
, O
while O
the O
camp B-TER
itself O
was O
run O
by O
the O
Lagerfuehrer O
SS B-ORG
. O

Oberschar O
F. B-PER
Spicker I-PER
. O

In O
him O
I O
found O
for O
the O
first O
time O
in O
my O
numerous O
encounters O
with O
members O
of O
the O
SS B-ORG
. O

a O
man O
free O
from O
any O
sadistic O
traits O
. O

Maybe O
that O
the O
death B-TER
of O
his O
son B-TER
, O
who O
had O
been O
killed B-TER
in O
action O
shortly O
before O
our O
arrival O
, O
had O
made O
him O
realise O
the O
value O
of O
life O
. O

Anyway O
, O
none O
of O
the O
prisoners B-TER
in O
Gleiwitz B-LOC
III I-LOC
was O
ill O
- O
treated O
, O
and O
the O
twenty O
odd O
who O
died B-TER
there O
succumbed O
to O
under O
- O
nourishment O
or O
died B-TER
from O
accidents O
and O
lack O
of O
medical O
attention O
. O

When O
we O
were O
evacuated B-TER
on O
18 O
Jan. O
1945 O
Spicker B-PER
led O
our O
party O
for O
two O
days O
. O

We O
were O
marching O
from O
Gleiwitz B-LOC
to O
Cosel B-LOC
, O
but O
had O
to O
return O
to O
Gleiwitz B-LOC
for O
unknown O
reasons O
. O

We O
were O
guarded O
by O
newly O
formed O
SS B-ORG
detachments O
, O
conscripted O
from O
members O
of O
the O
Wehrmacht B-ORG
. O

Not O
a O
single O
man B-TER
was O
shot B-TER
whereas O
, O
as O
I O
learned O
later O
, O
hundreds O
of O
the O
prisoners B-TER
in O
the O
work B-TER
detachment O
Gleiwitz B-LOC
I I-LOC
and B-LOC
II I-LOC
were O
shot B-TER
down I-TER
and O
died B-TER
by O
the O
roadside O
like O
hunted O
animals O
. O

I O
stress O
this O
fact O
purposely O
because O
I O
want O
to O
emphasise O
that O
the O
whole O
responsibility O
for O
the O
murder B-TER
of O
my O
poor O
fellow- O
prisoners B-TER
lies O
with O
the O
Commanding O
SS B-ORG
Officers O
. O

Where O
no O
orders O
to O
massacre B-TER
were O
given O
, O
as O
in O
the O
case O
of O
Spicker B-PER
, O
no O
one O
was O
shot B-TER
. O

We O
were O
marched B-TER
back O
to O
Blechhammer B-LOC
on O
our O
way O
to O
Gleiwitz B-LOC
III I-LOC
. O

On O
the O
21 O
Jan. O
1945 O
I O
noticed O
that O
some O
of O
the O
SS B-ORG
Guards B-TER
of I-TER
the I-TER
camp I-TER
had O
left O
their O
posts O
, O
when O
I O
was O
pushed O
out O
of O
the O
gates O
by O
the O
crowd O
of O
fellow- O
prisoners B-TER
. O

Together O
with O
a O
fellow B-TER
- I-TER
prisoner I-TER
, O
Dr. O
Eduard B-PER
Zelderust I-PER
, O
I O
ran O
away O
. O

For O
some O
days O
and O
nights O
we O
remained O
in O
the O
forest O
near O
Blechhammer B-LOC
where O
we O
heard O
the O
roar O
of O
the O
approaching O
battle O
. O

We O
were O
happy O
. O

There O
were O
machine O
- O
gun O
bullets O
and O
shell O
- O
fire O
, O
but O
we O
did O
not O
feel O
frightened O
. O

Was O
this O
only O
due O
to O
our O
lack O
of O
fighting O
experience O
? O
In O
part O
it O
might O
have O
been O
so O
because O
we O
were O
surprised O
when O
we O
noticed O
that O
all O
civilians B-TER
around O
us O
had O
suddenly O
disappeared O
. O

-11- O
It O
took O
us O
some O
time O
to O
realise O
that O
these O
people B-TER
had O
simply O
thrown O
themselves O
down O
on O
the O
ground O
, O
in O
order O
to O
take O
cover O
, O
and O
we O
followed O
, O
of O
course O
, O
their O
example O
. O

But O
I O
think O
there O
was O
another O
reason O
for O
our O
standing O
upright O
while O
shells O
and O
bullets O
whistled O
around O
us O
. O

It O
was O
impersonal O
death B-TER
which O
we O
here O
encountered O
for O
the O
first O
time O
. O

The O
bullets O
and O
shells O
were O
not O
meant O
to O
end O
just O
our O
lives O
. O

Death B-TER
, O
which O
had O
been O
at O
our O
heels O
from O
the O
first O
day O
of O
our O
falling O
into O
the O
hands O
of O
the O
Nazis O
, O
death O
in O
Auschwitz B-LOC
, O
was O
quite O
a O
different O
companion O
. O

In O
Auschwitz B-LOC
we O
were O
singled O
out O
, O
we O
Jews B-TER
, O
defenseless O
, O
completely O
at O
the O
mercy O
of O
the O
merciless O
. O

Death B-TER
was O
lurking O
at O
every O
corner O
ready O
to O
force O
us O
into O
his O
suffocating O
grip O
. O

At O
times O
we O
even O
felt O
a O
desire O
to O
surrender O
to O
this O
greedy O
companion O
to O
escape B-TER
at O
least O
the O
daily O
, O
nay O
hourly O
, O
threat O
that O
he O
might O
strike O
us O
down O
. O

In O
Auschwitz B-LOC
we O
had O
to O
resist B-TER
the O
temptation O
to O
throw O
ourselves O
against O
the O
seductive O
electric O
wire O
and O
thus O
end O
our O
suspense O
. O

In O
the O
Blechhammer B-LOC
Forest O
, O
where O
only O
impersonal O
death B-TER
threatened O
, O
we O
shared O
a O
danger O
common O
to O
all O
and O
felt O
free O
and O
relieved O
even O
when O
we O
realised O
that O
the O
shells O
and O
bullets O
might O
end O
our O
escape B-TER
into O
life O
. O

Appendix O
. O

The O
Jewish B-ORG
Central I-ORG
Information I-ORG
Office I-ORG
has O
been O
informed O
by O
another O
eye O
- O
witness O
that O
, O
after O
Mr. O
Mannheimer B-PER
's O
deportation B-TER
, O
transports B-TER
to O
the O
East O
continued O
to O
leave O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
, O
and O
that O
about O
a O
total O
of O
18,000 O
people O
were O
removed B-TER
in O
the O
autumn O
of O
1944 O
. O

In O
the O
early O
months O
of O
1945 O
the O
Nazis O
deliberately O
brought O
into O
the O
camp B-TER
people O
from O
other O
concentration B-TER
camps I-TER
who O
were O
infected O
with O
typhus B-TER
; O
some O
days O
trains B-TER
arrived O
with O
up O
to O
150 O
bodies B-TER
of O
people O
who O
had O
died B-TER
from O
this O
disease B-TER
on O
the O
way O
. O

When O
the O
camp B-TER
was O
liberated B-TER
by O
the O
Russians B-ORG
there O
were O
some O
5,000 O
Jews O
from O
Germany B-LOC
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
, O
4,000 O
Jewish O
husbands B-TER
or O
wives B-TER
of O
mixed B-TER
marriages I-TER
who O
had O
been O
separated B-TER
from O
their O
non O
- O
Jewish O
partners O
. O

This O
eye O
- O
witness O
estimated O
that O
the O
death B-TER
rate I-TER
during O
the O
maximum O
occupation O
of O
the O
camp B-TER
, O
which O
he O
maintains O
was O
not O
more O
than O
40,000 O
, O
was O
150 O
a O
day O
. O

He O
is O
of O
opinion O
that O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
was O
never O
intended O
to O
be O
anything O
more O
than O
a O
transit B-TER
camp I-TER
, O
irrespective O
of O
the O
age O
of O
the O
people O
privileged O
to O
live O
in O
this O
Home O
for O
the O
Aged O
. O

