[ O
... O
] O
There O
is O
no O
sympathy O
in O
Bulgaria B-LOC
for O
the O
anti B-TER
- I-TER
Jewish I-TER
demonstrations I-TER
of O
this O
organization O
‚ O
Workers B-ORG
of I-ORG
New I-ORG
Bulgaria I-ORG
‘ O
, O
especially O
as O
there O
is O
no O
Jewish B-TER
problem O
here O
, O
the O
total O
number O
of O
Jews B-TER
amounting O
to O
less O
than O
55,000 O
. O

The O
Jews B-TER
are O
not O
active O
in O
political B-TER
and O
public O
life O
; O
there O
are O
none O
among O
the O
army B-TER
officers O
and O
almost O
none O
in O
civil O
service O
. O

Their O
sphere O
of O
activity O
is O
business B-TER
, O
industry B-TER
and O
small O
trades B-TER
, O
and O
there O
are O
very O
few O
Jews B-TER
in O
the O
liberal O
professions O
and O
arts B-TER
. O

The O
anti O
- O
Jewish O
propaganda B-TER
conducted O
by O
the O
‚ O
Workers B-ORG
of I-ORG
New I-ORG
Bulgaria I-ORG
‘ O
is O
of O
foreign O
origin O
and O
is O
, O
it O
is O
believed O
, O
directly O
encouraged O
from O
Germany B-LOC
. O

[ O
... O
] O
