From O
: O
Consul O
Yamaguchi B-PER
( O
Vienna B-LOC
) O
To O
: O
Foreign O
Minister O
Shigemitsu B-PER
Mamoru I-PER
( O
Tokyo B-LOC
) O
Since O
29 O
th O
of O
last O
month O
, O
the O
control O
of O
Jews B-TER
in O
Vienna B-LOC
has O
become O
even O
harsher O
. O

The O
following O
is O
what O
we O
learned O
in O
extreme O
confidentiality O
. O

Those O
who O
married B-TER
Jews I-TER
are O
confined O
to O
certain B-TER
houses I-TER
; O
Those O
with O
mixed B-TER
Jewish I-TER
blood I-TER
are O
not O
allowed O
to O
join O
the O
Arbeitsfront B-ORG
or O
are O
expelled B-TER
from O
it O
. O

