“ O
A O
prominent O
non B-TER
- I-TER
Jewish I-TER
Bulgarian B-TER
member O
of O
the O
Bulgarian B-ORG
Parliament I-ORG
has O
come O
to O
Istanbul B-LOC
especially O
to O
make O
strong O
personal O
representations O
upon O
humanitarian O
grounds O
in O
influential O
quarters O
regarding O
the O
condition O
of O
the O
Jews B-TER
in O
Bulgaria B-LOC
. O

[ O
... O
] O
This O
informant O
says O
that O
the O
entire O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
in O
Bulgaria B-LOC
is O
threatened B-TER
with O
immediate O
destruction B-TER
. O

Bulgarian B-LOC
Jews B-TER
are O
now O
in O
a O
much O
worse O
situation O
than O
those O
in O
Rumania B-LOC
and O
Hungary B-LOC
. O

Nothing O
can O
be O
done O
for O
the O
Jews B-TER
from O
Bulgarian B-TER
occupied O
Thrace B-LOC
and O
Macedonia B-LOC
, O
for O
all O
of O
them O
including O
men B-TER
, O
women B-TER
and O
children B-TER
will O
be O
deported B-TER
to O
Poland B-LOC
and O
their O
deportation B-TER
has O
already O
begun O
. O

He O
adds O
that O
the O
intention O
of O
the O
Bulgarian B-ORG
Government I-ORG
is O
to O
deport B-TER
to O
Poland B-LOC
all O
Jews B-TER
in O
Bulgaria B-LOC
and O
an O
order B-TER
for O
this O
purpose O
has O
been O
issued O
. O

Owing O
to O
popular B-TER
protests I-TER
led O
by O
prominent O
non B-TER
- I-TER
Jewish I-TER
Bulgarian B-LOC
citizens O
this O
order O
has O
been O
stayed O
temporarily O
but O
not O
rescinded O
. O

The O
policy B-TER
of O
extermination B-TER
he O
states O
is O
demanded O
by O
the O
Germans B-TER
and O
promoted O
by O
Gabrovski B-PER
. O

The O
lives O
of O
45,000 O
Jews B-TER
are O
at O
stake O
. O

The O
parliamentarian O
declares O
that O
in O
his O
opinion O
the O
most O
effective O
way O
to O
help B-TER
them O
is O
for O
the O
United B-ORG
States I-ORG
Government I-ORG
to O
make O
a O
vigorous O
protest B-TER
to O
the O
Bulgarian B-ORG
Government I-ORG
through O
the O
Swiss B-LOC
authorities O
declaring O
in O
the O
strongest O
terms O
its O
abhorrence O
of O
the O
policy B-TER
of O
the O
Bulgarian B-ORG
Government I-ORG
toward O
the O
Jews B-TER
. O

” O
