Wolf B-PER
Fajnsztadt I-PER
Testimony O
( O
doc O
. O

301/945 O
) O
Typescript O
, O
2 O
pages O
, O
210 O
x O
295 O
mm O
, O
Polish O
language O
Wolf B-PER
Fajnsztadt I-PER
In O
the O
later O
part O
of O
the O
text O
he O
is O
called O
Fajnstok O
. O

born O
on O
November O
15 O
, O
1919 O
, O
in O
Lublin B-LOC
. O

Father O
Mojżesz B-PER
, O
mother O
Chana B-PER
Mendelewicz I-PER
. O

Before O
the O
war O
he O
lived O
in O
Ostrowiec B-LOC
[ I-LOC
Świętokrzyski I-LOC
] I-LOC
. O

At O
present O
[ O
residing O
in O
] O
Będzin B-LOC
, O
9 B-LOC
Potockiego I-LOC
Street I-LOC
. O

Partisan B-TER
fighting O
I O
was O
a O
partisan B-TER
from O
July O
26 O
, O
[ O
1944 O
] O
, O
until O
January O
17 O
, O
1945 O
. O

Before O
my O
time O
as O
a O
partisan B-TER
I O
was O
in O
a O
camp B-TER
in O
Ostrowiec B-LOC
Świętokrzyski I-LOC
. O

In O
February O
1943 O
, O
still O
in O
the O
ghetto B-LOC
, O
boys O
had O
organised O
an O
attack O
on O
the O
commandant O
of O
the O
Jewish B-TER
militia I-TER
, O
and O
we O
took O
away O
from O
him O
40 O
Probably O
dollars O
. O

in O
gold O
, O
the O
sum O
which O
we O
spent O
on O
arms O
. O

We O
exchanged O
that O
currency O
for O
36 O
thousand O
zlotys O
, O
and O
bought O
12 O
revolvers O
with O
this O
money O
. O

For O
the O
time O
being O
, O
we O
were O
in O
the O
ghetto B-LOC
. O

Seventeen O
of O
our O
boys O
went O
to O
Kunów B-LOC
to O
hide B-TER
there O
on O
Aryan B-TER
papers I-TER
, O
but O
they O
were O
killed B-TER
by O
the O
AK B-ORG
men O
. O

Those O
men O
threw O
a O
grenade O
into O
the O
bunker B-TER
where O
our O
friends O
were O
hiding B-TER
, O
and O
all O
of O
them O
were O
killed B-TER
on O
that O
occasion O
. O

This O
delayed O
our O
action O
in O
the O
ghetto B-LOC
until O
March O
1944 O
. O

At O
the O
beginning O
there O
were O
47 O
of O
us O
, O
and O
only O
30 O
members O
remained O
alive O
. O

The O
leaders O
of O
our O
fighting O
unit O
were O
two O
Stein B-PER
brothers O
from O
Ostrowiec B-LOC
. I-LOC

. O

Both O
of O
them O
were O
killed B-TER
in O
June O
1944 O
during O
the O
talks O
with O
the O
boss O
of O
the O
workers O
’ O
party O
from O
Ostrowiec B-LOC
. O

His O
name O
was O
Rybowski B-PER
, O
alias O
Wujo O
[ O
Uncle O
] O
, O
and O
he O
was O
a O
Pole B-TER
. O

They O
met O
to O
discuss O
the O
question O
of O
an O
escape B-TER
attempt O
from O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

And O
then O
one O
Jew O
named O
Blumental B-PER
, O
a O
capo B-TER
from O
Ostrowiec B-LOC
, O
informed O
on O
them O
to O
the O
Germans B-TER
, O
who O
immediately O
apprehended O
them O
, O
and O
the O
Stein B-PER
brothers O
were O
executed B-TER
by O
a O
firing O
squad O
two O
days O
later O
. O

It O
took O
place O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
square O
in O
Ostrowiec B-LOC
. O

After O
that O
Dawid B-PER
Kepiński I-PER
from O
Konin B-LOC
took O
over O
the O
command O
. O

Led O
by O
him O
, O
we O
cut O
through O
the O
camp B-TER
wires O
and O
escaped B-TER
to O
the O
forest O
on O
July O
25 O
, O
1944 O
. O

There O
were O
29 O
of O
us O
. O

We O
had O
14 O
revolvers O
, O
2 O
short O
machine O
guns O
, O
and O
3 O
grenades O
. O

Thanks O
to O
Antek B-PER
Cukierman I-PER
we O
received O
money O
from O
a O
Jewish B-ORG
fighting I-ORG
organisation I-ORG
from O
Warsaw B-LOC
. O

That O
money O
was O
brought O
by O
Frania B-PER
Beatus I-PER
, O
a O
Jewish O
woman B-TER
from O
Konin B-LOC
. O

She O
brought O
25,000 O
zlotys O
and O
one O
grenade O
. O

She O
came O
to O
the O
camp B-TER
on O
Aryan B-TER
papers I-TER
. O

As O
one O
group O
of O
the O
Jews O
from O
the O
Ostrowiec B-LOC
camp B-TER
worked O
in O
the O
town O
on O
the O
Aryan B-TER
side O
, O
she O
joined O
that O
group O
of O
workers O
when O
they O
were O
coming O
back O
to O
the O
camp B-TER
, O
and O
in O
this O
way O
she O
also O
got O
into O
the O
camp B-TER
and O
established O
contact O
with O
us O
. O

On O
the O
following O
morning O
she O
returned O
with O
the O
same O
group O
to O
the O
town O
, O
but O
from O
there O
she O
went O
to O
Warsaw B-LOC
. O

But O
on O
the O
way O
some O
Germans B-TER
recognised O
she O
was O
Jewish O
and O
she O
was O
killed B-TER
. O

We O
stored O
the O
arms O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
- O
in O
crates O
, O
feather O
quilts O
, O
and O
so O
on O
. O

When O
we O
entered O
the O
forest O
, O
in O
Krzemionki B-LOC
near O
Ostrowiec B-LOC
, O
we O
joined O
a O
Russian B-TER
unit O
of O
nine O
. O

They O
had O
escaped B-TER
from O
German B-TER
captivity O
. O

They O
were O
well O
armed O
- O
they O
had O
eight O
machine O
guns O
. O

We O
contacted O
them O
through O
a O
Pole B-TER
named O
Sternik B-PER
from O
the O
workers O
’ O
party O
from O
Ostrowiec B-LOC
( O
he O
is O
at O
present O
a O
commandant O
of O
the O
militia O
in O
the O
Security O
Department O
in O
Bodzechów B-LOC
W O
tekście O
: O
Bodzanowie O
. O

near O
Ostrowiec B-LOC
) O
. O

We O
built O
three O
sheds O
because O
it O
was O
still O
summer O
, O
and O
in O
September O
we O
made O
up O
underground B-TER
bunkers I-TER
, O
the O
so O
- O
called O
dug O
- O
outs O
. O

There O
were O
four O
bunkers B-TER
for O
thirty O
- O
eight O
people O
. O

There O
were O
also O
girls B-TER
, O
about O
20 O
years O
old O
, O
among O
us O
. O

They O
cooked O
for O
us O
. O

We O
escaped B-TER
from O
the O
camp B-TER
because O
we O
were O
aware O
that O
it O
was O
going O
to O
be O
liquidated B-TER
. O

We O
were O
also O
planning O
to O
save O
our O
families B-TER
but O
, O
unfortunately O
, O
it O
was O
too O
late O
. O

On O
August O
2 O
, O
1944 O
, O
the O
camp B-TER
was O
evacuated O
to O
Auschwitz B-LOC
, O
because O
the O
front O
was O
drawing O
nearer O
. O

We O
obtained O
food B-TER
from O
well O
- O
off O
peasants O
and O
manors O
, O
and O
we O
paid O
for O
the O
products O
the O
pre O
- O
war O
prices O
. O

We O
went O
to O
get O
the O
food B-TER
at O
night O
, O
and O
we O
were O
armed O
. O

From O
time O
to O
time O
we O
met O
Germans B-TER
at O
those O
peasants O
’ O
homes O
, O
and O
then O
the O
shooting O
ensued O
. O

On O
one O
such O
occasion O
four O
our O
boys O
were O
killed B-TER
and O
two O
were O
wounded O
. O

But O
also O
two O
Germans B-TER
were O
killed B-TER
, O
and O
we O
took O
off O
their O
uniforms O
and O
got O
hold O
of O
their O
arms O
, O
and O
went O
back O
to O
the O
forest O
. O

One O
day O
we O
met O
a O
German B-TER
lorry O
which O
had O
a O
cargo O
of O
cigarettes O
and O
canned O
food B-TER
. O

We O
killed B-TER
two O
Germans B-TER
, O
seized O
the O
cargo O
, O
and O
burnt O
the O
lorry O
, O
having O
first O
poured O
petrol O
on O
it O
. O

On O
June O
29 O
, O
1944 O
, O
we O
derailed O
a O
German B-TER
train B-TER
which O
was O
carrying O
ammunition O
and O
explosives O
to O
the O
front O
. O

On O
October O
4 O
we O
blew O
up O
the O
whole O
building O
in O
the O
village O
of O
Sudół B-LOC
Górny I-LOC
, O
In O
the O
text O
: O
Sudogóra O
in O
which O
a O
German B-TER
Hauptmann O
Hauptmann O
( O
Ger O
. O

) O
– O
captain O
. O

was O
staying O
. O

That O
Hauptmann O
was O
killed B-TER
, O
and O
we O
managed O
to O
run O
away O
. O

In O
November O
there O
was O
an O
ambush O
organised O
by O
the O
Germans B-TER
, O
because O
we O
had O
been O
given O
away O
by O
one O
forester O
who O
told O
them O
where O
we O
were O
hiding B-TER
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
came O
to O
the O
bunker B-TER
and O
opened O
fire O
. O

Certainly O
, O
we O
fought O
back O
. O

Eight O
of O
our O
people O
were O
killed B-TER
at O
that O
time O
, O
including O
those O
two O
girls B-TER
and O
one O
Russian B-TER
. O

As O
there O
were O
sixty O
Germans B-TER
, O
we O
had O
to O
withdraw O
and O
we O
fled B-TER
to O
the O
forest O
in O
the O
village O
of O
Czarna B-LOC
Glinka I-LOC
In O
the O
text O
: O
Czarna O
Glina O
. O

near O
Ostrowiec B-LOC
. O

We O
built O
three O
new O
bunkers B-TER
there O
. O

The O
conditions B-TER
were O
harsh O
because O
we O
were O
persecuted O
by O
AK B-ORG
groups O
and O
the O
Germans B-TER
wherever O
we O
moved O
. O

Only O
armed O
individuals O
could O
go O
out O
to O
obtain O
food B-TER
. O

We O
had O
run O
out O
of O
money O
by O
that O
time O
, O
so O
we O
took O
the O
food B-TER
from O
peasants O
without O
paying O
. O

Towards O
the O
end O
of O
December O
we O
were O
surrounded O
by O
a O
Hungarian B-TER
detachment O
which O
was O
allied O
with O
the O
Germans B-TER
. O

Severe O
fighting O
followed O
again O
. O

A O
lot O
of O
our O
people O
were O
killed B-TER
. O

Only O
six O
of O
us O
survived O
: O
five O
Jews O
and O
a O
Russian B-TER
. O

We O
escaped B-TER
to O
the O
forest O
in O
Ruda B-LOC
Kościelna I-LOC
near O
Ostrowiec B-LOC
, O
where O
we O
hid O
in O
bunkers B-TER
for O
three O
weeks O
until O
the O
arrival O
of O
the O
Russians B-TER
. O

We O
belonged O
to O
the O
Armia B-ORG
Ludowa I-ORG
. O

We O
received O
newsletters O
and O
front O
news O
from O
the O
Main O
Partisan B-TER
Headquarters O
in O
Ostrowiec B-LOC
. O

We O
were O
given O
those O
papers O
by O
the O
liaison O
officer O
Sternik B-PER
. O

The O
names O
of O
the O
members O
of O
that O
partisan B-TER
unit O
: O
1 O
. O

Mojżesz B-PER
Wajzer I-PER
aged O
28 O
2 O
. O

Berek B-PER
Szerman I-PER
28 O
3 O
. O

Wolf B-PER
Szerman I-PER
52 O
4 O
. O

Matla B-PER
Waldman I-PER
20 O
5 O
. O

Szyfra B-PER
Weinberg I-PER
20 O
6 O
. O

Majer B-PER
Fleischmann I-PER
32 O
7 O
. O

Izrael B-PER
Fleischmann I-PER
24 O
8 O
. O

Tojwie B-PER
Fachler I-PER
31 O
9 O
. O

Jakub B-PER
Fachler I-PER
22 O
10 O
. O

Szmul B-PER
Fachler I-PER
29 O
11 O
. O

Mendel B-PER
Waserman I-PER
21 O
12 O
. O

Uszer B-PER
Rubinsztejn I-PER
18 O
13 O
. O

Josef B-PER
Wajnberg I-PER
22 O
All O
of O
them O
come O
from O
Ostrowiec B-LOC
. O

14 O
. O

Izrael B-PER
Słodki I-PER
22 O
15 O
. O

Szymon B-PER
Kempiński I-PER
28 O
16 O
. O

Fajwel B-PER
Kempiński I-PER
21 O
17 O
. O

Mojżesz B-PER
Zygielbaum I-PER
21 O
18 O
. O

Ajzyk B-PER
Zygielbaum I-PER
23 O
19 O
. O

Szlama B-PER
Szmilewicz I-PER
34 O
20 O
. O

Szmul B-PER
Alios I-PER
32 O
21 O
. O

Juda B-PER
Singer I-PER
22 O
22 O
. O

Hersz B-PER
Akerman I-PER
30 O
23 O
. O

Gecel B-PER
Akerman I-PER
26 O
24 O
. O

Dawid B-PER
Niskier I-PER
23 O
25 O
. O

Motek B-PER
Ajzman I-PER
31 O
26 O
. O

Wolf B-PER
Fajnstok I-PER
26 O
From O
all O
those O
mentioned O
above O
the O
survivors O
are O
: O
1 O
. O

Berek B-PER
Szerman I-PER
and O
his O
brother O
Wolf B-PER
2 O
. O

Szymon B-PER
Kempiński I-PER
3 O
. O

Mojżesz B-PER
Wajzer I-PER
4 O
. O

Motek B-PER
Ajzman I-PER
5 O
. O

Myself O
, O
Wolf B-PER
Fajnstok I-PER
The O
others O
perished B-TER
. O

Recorded O
by O
Chain B-PER
, O
Będzin B-LOC
. O

