Ela B-PER
Wowsi I-PER
Testimony O
( O
doc O
. O

301/81 O
) O
Original O
, O
manuscript O
, O
4 O
pages O
, O
210 O
x O
295 O
mm O
, O
Polish O
language O
The O
experiences O
of O
a O
Jewish O
woman B-TER
from O
Latvia B-LOC
in O
the O
camps B-TER
in O
Riga B-LOC
, O
Stutthof B-LOC
and O
Toruń B-LOC
Ela B-PER
Wowsi I-PER
, O
born O
in O
1898 O
in O
Subala O
in O
Latvia B-LOC
, O
lived O
in O
Dyneburg B-LOC
, O
pharmacist O
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
entered O
Dyneburg B-LOC
on O
June O
26 O
, O
1941 O
. O

On O
June O
29 O
, O
they O
already O
announced O
that O
all O
men B-TER
were O
to O
be O
taken O
. O

( O
The O
Jewish O
population O
in O
Dyneburg B-LOC
was O
from O
10,000 O
- O
14,000 O
. O

) O
Those O
who O
were O
assembled O
were O
arrested B-TER
and O
liquidated B-TER
over O
the O
course O
of O
2 O
weeks O
. O

This O
is O
how O
the O
Germans B-TER
began O
their O
Schreckensherrschaft O
. O

Schreckensherrschaft O
( O
German O
) O
– O
reign O
of O
terror O
. O

Only O
doctors B-TER
and O
pharmacists O
were O
released B-TER
. O

The O
rest O
, O
about O
6,000 O
, O
were O
moved O
on O
July O
26 O
to O
the O
ghetto B-TER
outside O
of O
town O
. O

They O
lived O
in O
former O
artillery O
barracks B-TER
in O
stables O
in O
terribly O
sanitary B-TER
conditions I-TER
. O

After O
a O
while O
, O
Jews O
were O
concentrated B-TER
there O
from O
the O
entire O
area O
. O

The O
total O
number O
was O
7,200 O
. O

They O
were O
caught O
and O
shot B-TER
in O
groups O
of O
5,000 O
and O
1,000 O
from O
the O
ghetto B-TER
. O

The O
approximately O
1,200 O
who O
remained O
were O
put O
in O
prison B-TER
. O

On O
November O
9 O
, O
1941 O
, O
most O
of O
the O
working O
families B-TER
were O
taken O
, O
who O
up O
to O
that O
time O
had O
been O
protected O
, O
and O
on O
May O
1 O
, O
1942 O
, O
the O
final O
liquidation B-TER
of O
the O
ghetto B-TER
began O
by O
means O
of O
shooting B-TER
people O
on O
the O
spot O
. O

Those O
who O
were O
working B-TER
for O
the O
Germans B-TER
that O
day O
remained O
alive O
, O
about O
380 O
- O
400 O
people O
. O

They O
worked B-TER
at O
various O
German B-TER
Einheits O
Einheit O
( O
German O
) O
– O
unit O
( O
military O
) O
in O
Dyneburg B-LOC
until O
October O
1943 O
. O

I O
was O
not O
faring O
badly O
. O

The O
Jews O
cooked B-TER
for O
themselves O
, O
received O
120 O
g O
of O
bread B-TER
, O
from O
time O
to O
time O
butter B-TER
, O
or O
sugar B-TER
, O
salt B-TER
etc O
. O

In O
October O
, O
they O
were O
taken O
to O
Riga B-LOC
to O
the O
electrotechnical O
factory B-TER
, O
[ O
where O
] O
parts O
[ O
were O
made O
] O
for O
cables O
, O
radios O
, O
etc O
. O

at O
the O
AEG B-ORG
Allgemeine I-ORG
Elektrotechnische I-ORG
Genossenschaft I-ORG
. O

They O
were O
divided O
into O
sections O
, O
they O
worked B-TER
on O
3 O
shifts O
. O

Others O
worked B-TER
for O
11 O
hours O
from O
6 O
a.m. O
to O
5 O
p.m. O
without O
any O
breaks O
( O
only O
½ O
hour O
for O
lunch B-TER
) O
. O

The O
SS B-ORG
Oberscharführer O
and O
Blitzmädel O
Blitzmädel O
( O
German O
) O
– O
girl O
with O
the O
lighting O
emblem O
, O
femaleWehrmacht O
auxiliary O
( O
Wehrmachthelferin O
) O
, O
in O
concentration O
camps O
the O
SS O
auxiliary O
( O
SS‑helferin O
) O
. O

did O
not O
treat O
them O
badly O
. O

Jewish O
women B-TER
of O
all O
nationalities O
were O
concentrated O
in O
the O
Riga B-LOC
camp I-LOC
, O
from O
the O
Czech B-LOC
lands I-LOC
, O
Hungary B-LOC
, O
Poland B-LOC
, O
Lithuania B-LOC
, O
Germany B-LOC
, O
etc O
. O

Only O
one O
German B-TER
woman B-TER
was O
in O
charge O
of O
all O
of O
them O
. O

They O
got O
250 O
g O
of O
bread B-TER
, O
some O
marmalade B-TER
or O
alternately O
a O
piece O
of O
fat B-TER
, O
a O
little O
sugar B-TER
, O
margarine B-TER
, O
sausage B-TER
, O
or O
horse B-TER
meat I-TER
. O

Once O
a O
day O
there O
was O
a O
some O
soup B-TER
, O
and O
coffee B-TER
twice O
a O
day O
. O

The O
Jewish O
kitchen O
stole O
from O
them O
, O
taking O
their O
food B-TER
for O
their O
own O
needs O
, O
exchanging O
it O
with O
Aryans B-TER
for O
other O
things O
, O
etc O
. O

The O
work B-TER
site O
was O
across O
from O
their O
room O
. O

The O
sanitary B-TER
conditions I-TER
were O
very O
good O
, O
warm O
shower O
, O
often O
Entlausung O
, O
Entlausung O
- O
delousing O
light O
, O
warm O
, O
in O
their O
free O
time O
they O
read O
, O
played O
cards O
. O

A O
couple O
times O
they O
had O
evenings O
of O
poetry O
readings O
, O
singing O
in O
Yiddish O
. O

The O
Blitzerki O
„ O
Blitzerki O
” O
- O
Blitzmädel O
also O
attended O
them O
. O

In O
October O
1944 O
, O
they O
were O
suddenly O
transported B-TER
to O
Stutthof B-LOC
( O
Durchgangslager O
) O
. O

Stutthof O
– O
at O
present O
Sztutowo O
. O

Durchgangslager O
( O
German O
) O
– O
transit O
camp O
. O

For O
a O
week O
, O
they O
traveled O
by O
truck O
in O
conditions O
that O
were O
lamentable O
. O

Near O
Gdańsk B-LOC
, O
the O
Gestapos B-ORG
beat O
them O
when O
they O
were O
getting O
out O
of O
the O
trucks O
. O

They O
were O
kept O
at O
Stutthof B-LOC
for O
1 O
month O
. O

The O
Jewish O
women B-TER
from O
Poland B-LOC
and O
Hungary B-LOC
- O
Blockälteste O
Blockälteste O
– O
block O
elder O
. O

beat O
them O
, O
and O
the O
Jewish O
women B-TER
from O
the O
Innendienst O
Innendienst O
– O
internal O
service O
in O
the O
blocks O
beat O
them O
as O
well O
. O

In O
the O
narrow O
bunk O
beds B-TER
, O
four O
women B-TER
would O
sleep O
together O
, O
there O
was O
filth O
everywhere O
. O

The O
harassment O
got O
to O
the O
point O
where O
they O
were O
not O
allowed O
to O
leave O
the O
barracks B-TER
to O
take O
care O
of O
their O
physiological B-TER
needs I-TER
. O

They O
were O
kept O
for O
hours O
at O
roll B-TER
calls I-TER
for O
no O
reason O
. O

They O
did O
not O
work B-TER
at O
all O
. O

The O
camp B-TER
had O
a O
crematorium B-TER
as O
well O
. O

Their O
food B-TER
consisted O
of O
coffee B-TER
twice O
a O
day O
, O
one O
liter O
of O
soup B-TER
, O
300 O
g O
of O
bread B-TER
( O
some O
margarine B-TER
or O
marmalade B-TER
occasionally O
) O
. O

There O
were O
Jews O
here O
from O
all O
over O
the O
world O
. O

There O
were O
also O
Aryans B-TER
there O
. O

The O
whole O
camp B-TER
had O
about O
40,000 O
prisoners B-TER
. O

There O
were O
600 O
people O
to O
a O
barracks B-TER
. O

Leaving O
the O
barracks B-TER
was O
forbidden O
. O

Contact O
with O
the O
Aryan B-TER
world O
was O
banned O
. O

After O
a O
month O
, O
they O
took O
300 O
people O
to O
Toruń B-LOC
to O
work B-TER
in O
the O
electrotechnical O
factory B-TER
. O

There O
were O
already O
about O
200 O
camp B-TER
inmates I-TER
there O
. O

In O
Toruń B-LOC
they O
had O
very O
bad O
conditions B-TER
. O

The O
Oberscharführer B-TER
beat O
them O
for O
no O
reason O
, O
they O
were O
starving B-TER
. O

A O
beating O
with O
club O
( O
25 O
blows O
) O
was O
an O
everyday O
occurrence O
. O

People O
’s O
hair O
was O
cut O
off O
for O
the O
smallest O
offence O
. O

Work O
in O
the O
AEG B-ORG
in O
Toruń B-LOC
was O
supervised O
by O
Latvians B-LOC
. O

They O
treated O
Jews O
very O
badly O
. O

They O
reported O
the O
most O
minor O
infractions O
against O
camp B-TER
law O
to O
the O
Oberscharführer O
. O

Camp B-TER
authorities O
: O
SS B-ORG
Oberscharführer O
SS B-ORG
Unterscharführer O
( O
administrator O
) O
normal O
SS B-TER
soldiers I-TER
as O
camp B-TER
guards I-TER
Blitzmädel O
supervised O
during O
work B-TER
a O
Jewish O
Lagerältester O
Lagerältester O
– O
camp O
elder O
Jewish O
Blockälteste O
Jewish O
Polizei O
- O
2 O
- O
3 O
women B-TER
12 O
people O
were O
employed O
in O
the O
kitchen O
. O

The O
camp B-TER
consisted O
of O
an O
enormous O
square O
surrounded O
by O
barbed O
wire O
which O
was O
made O
up O
of O
5 O
blocks O
, O
and O
one O
that O
was O
not O
yet O
finished O
. O

Women B-TER
lived O
in O
4 O
barracks B-TER
, O
over O
100 O
to O
a O
barrack B-TER
. O

The O
kitchen O
and O
supply O
room O
was O
in O
the O
fifth O
. O

A O
Waschraum O
, O
Waschraum O
- O
washroom O
shoemakers O
’ O
workshop B-TER
and O
laundry O
were O
set O
up O
in O
the O
sixth O
. O

The O
Häftlinge O
Häftlinge O
- O
prisoners O
wore O
gray O
prison B-TER
clothing B-TER
and O
underwear B-TER
, O
numbers O
that O
were O
assigned O
back O
in O
Stutthof B-LOC
. O

The O
barracks B-TER
were O
built O
of O
boards O
, O
one O
store O
high O
. O

Triple O
bunk O
beds O
were O
put O
in O
them O
in O
rows O
, O
without O
any O
bed O
linens O
. O

One O
blanket O
and O
straw O
mattress O
were O
assigned O
to O
4 O
women B-TER
. O

They O
worked B-TER
for O
8 O
hours O
a O
day O
with O
the O
cables O
, O
and O
then O
they O
shoveled O
snow O
and O
helped O
in O
the O
kitchen O
. O

There O
were O
2 O
work B-TER
halls O
. O

The O
first O
was O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
, O
the O
second O
was O
in O
the O
Stadthalle O
Stadthalle O
– O
hall O
in O
the O
town O
in O
town O
. O

People O
worked B-TER
for O
12 O
hours O
a O
day O
in O
the O
second O
hall O
. O

Those O
who O
worked B-TER
8 O
hours O
a O
day O
also O
had O
to O
work O
on O
Sundays O
. O

Part O
of O
the O
first O
barracks B-TER
was O
used O
for O
the O
hospital B-TER
. O

The O
doctor B-TER
was O
a O
Jewish O
woman B-TER
. O

The O
SS B-TER
had O
3 O
Jewish O
cooks O
for O
their O
needs O
. O

They O
treated O
them O
better O
than O
the O
others O
. O

In O
the O
morning O
, O
they O
were O
woken O
up O
with O
a O
shout O
of O
: O
Aufstehen O
! O
Apell O
! O
Aufstehen O
, O
Apell O
– O
stand O
up O
, O
roll O
call O
They O
were O
counted O
, O
and O
if O
the O
Oberscharführer B-TER
was O
in O
a O
good O
mood O
, O
they O
were O
sent O
to O
work B-TER
. O

If O
he O
was O
in O
a O
bad O
mood O
, O
he O
kept O
them O
for O
hours O
in O
the O
field O
. O

It O
was O
the O
same O
with O
those O
who O
were O
returning O
from O
the O
Nachtschicht O
. O

Nachtschicht O
– O
night O
shift O
In O
the O
evening O
, O
100 O
women B-TER
would O
return O
from O
the O
Stadthalle O
and O
300 O
from O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

It O
was O
always O
terribly O
crowded O
in O
the O
barracks B-TER
. O

At O
nine O
, O
the O
lights O
were O
turned O
off O
. O

When O
the O
Soviets B-ORG
were O
approaching O
, O
the O
Oberscharführer B-TER
assembled O
them O
. O

They O
were O
given O
bread B-TER
for O
the O
journey O
, O
sausage B-TER
and O
half O
a O
package O
of O
margarine B-TER
and O
they O
left O
on O
foot O
. O

They O
walked B-TER
for O
50 O
kilometers O
to O
Bromberg B-LOC
, O
Bromberg O
– O
Bydgoszcz O
. O

on O
the O
way O
many O
escaped B-TER
, O
and O
the O
Oberscharführer B-TER
no O
longer O
paid O
any O
attention O
. O

They O
marched B-TER
to O
Germany B-TER
half O
- O
dead O
through O
the O
January O
snows O
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
and O
Blitzerki O
also O
escaped B-TER
on O
foot O
. O

The O
sick B-TER
were O
moved O
on O
sleds O
, O
which O
Jews O
pulled O
. O

In O
Bromberg B-LOC
, O
almost O
everyone O
ran B-TER
away I-TER
, O
taking O
advantage O
of O
the O
confusion O
was O
prevailing O
among O
the O
Germans B-TER
. O

Lewinówna B-PER
taking O
the O
record O
( O
Lublin B-LOC
) O
