Dwojra B-PER
Szczuczyńska I-PER
Testimony O
( O
doc O
. O

301/2 O
) O
Original O
, O
manuscript O
, O
2 O
pages O
, O
210 O
x O
295 O
mm O
, O
Polish O
language O
Dwojra B-PER
Szczuczyńska I-PER
, O
residing O
in O
Warsaw B-LOC
, O
tells O
about O
the O
Hotel O
for O
Jews O
that O
was O
set O
up O
by O
Germans B-TER
in O
cooperation O
with O
the O
Jewish O
Gestapo B-ORG
men O
. O

In O
May O
1943 O
, O
the O
news O
came O
that O
Jews O
who O
were O
foreign B-TER
citizens I-TER
could O
leave O
the O
country O
. O

This O
was O
a O
trap O
for O
Jews O
who O
were O
settled O
or O
in O
hiding B-TER
on O
the O
Aryan B-TER
side O
. O

There O
were O
( O
it O
was O
said O
) O
certificates O
at O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
for O
Jews O
who O
had O
died B-TER
in O
action O
, O
Germans B-TER
making O
it O
convenient O
for O
the O
Jews O
who O
had O
survived O
, O
sold O
citizenships B-TER
and O
with O
that O
underhanded O
method O
caught O
the O
naïve O
ones O
. O

There O
were O
two O
types O
of O
documents O
which O
were O
supposed O
to O
provide O
their O
holders O
security O
: O
certificates O
issued O
by O
British O
authorities O
, O
authorizing O
entry O
to O
Palestine O
, O
and O
the O
passports O
of O
the O
Latin O
American O
countries O
. O

At O
the O
head O
of O
this O
scam O
was O
a O
Jewish O
Gestapo B-ORG
officer O
named O
Lolek B-PER
Skosowski I-PER
, O
a O
resident O
of O
Łódź B-LOC
( O
who O
lived O
until O
the O
last O
minute O
in O
Lwów B-LOC
at O
4 B-LOC
Teresy I-LOC
Street I-LOC
and O
was O
killed B-TER
by O
the O
party O
) O
, O
who O
sacrificed O
his O
own O
family B-TER
to O
underscore O
the O
trustworthiness O
of O
this O
program O
, O
having O
taken O
them O
out O
of O
the O
Łódź B-LOC
ghetto I-LOC
. O

Naïve O
people O
were O
recruited O
at O
the O
Hotel O
Polski O
on O
Długa O
Street O
. O

At O
the O
gate O
there O
was O
an O
armed O
guard O
[ O
wacha O
] O
, O
Wacha O
( O
German O
‑ O
Wache O
) O
– O
guard O
post O
. O

who O
kept O
order O
and O
chased O
away O
onlookers O
. O

The O
richest O
Jews O
fell O
victim O
to O
this O
, O
who O
would O
pay O
several O
hundred O
thousand O
złotys O
each O
for O
a O
certificate O
. O

They O
came O
with O
their O
fancy O
baggage O
. O

There O
was O
a O
restaurant O
and O
barber O
shop O
right O
there O
. O

The O
ladies O
and O
gentlemen O
felt O
as O
if O
they O
were O
on O
a O
fancy O
ship O
. O

A O
committee O
was O
formed O
from O
among O
the O
Jews O
, O
which O
took O
care O
of O
orphaned B-TER
children B-TER
who O
were O
allegedly O
supposed O
to O
leave O
for O
Palestine B-LOC
. O

Thanks O
to O
the O
big O
- O
heartedness O
of O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
, O
poor O
orphans B-TER
were O
accepted O
in O
exchange O
for O
payments O
in O
- O
kind O
and O
similar O
arrangements O
. O

Transports B-TER
were O
sent O
depending O
on O
how O
many O
naïve O
people O
were O
taken O
in O
. O

There O
were O
three O
such O
transports B-TER
. O

The O
first O
was O
to O
Wittel B-LOC
Wittel O
– O
Vittel O
, O
a O
spa O
town O
in O
France O
. O

Group O
held O
in O
Vittel O
was O
then O
deported O
to O
the O
death O
camp O
at O
Auschwitz O
. O

, O
from O
whence O
letter O
were O
even O
sent O
, O
the O
second O
went O
to O
Hannover B-LOC
, O
the O
third O
and O
last O
to O
Pawiak B-LOC
. O

Further O
groups O
of O
residents O
of O
Hotel O
Polski O
were O
deported O
to O
the O
concentration O
camp O
at O
Bergen‑Belsen O
. O

After O
a O
while O
, O
there O
ceased O
to O
be O
any O
news O
. O

A O
card O
from O
Hannover B-LOC
came O
from O
one O
woman B-TER
, O
written O
in O
an O
arranged O
code O
to O
her O
friends O
, O
which O
unmasked O
the O
enormity O
of O
the O
scam O
, O
namely O
the O
sentence O
we O
are O
doing O
very O
well O
was O
to O
mean O
the O
group O
’s O
extermination B-TER
. O

The O
last O
transport B-TER
did O
not O
go O
far O
, O
only O
to O
the O
prison B-TER
known O
as O
Pawiak B-LOC
, O
hundreds O
of O
thousands O
of O
people O
were O
killed B-TER
. O

The O
hotel O
scam O
caught O
about O
3,000 O
people O
from O
the O
Aryan B-TER
neighborhood O
. O

They O
were O
people O
who O
had O
every O
opportunity O
: O
they O
looked O
good O
, O
had O
living B-TER
conditions I-TER
, O
and O
were O
set O
up O
, O
which O
means O
they O
had O
work B-TER
in O
various O
places O
( O
railroad O
, O
post O
office O
, O
fire O
department O
) O
and O
they O
had O
the O
possibility O
of O
surviving O
the O
period O
of O
German B-TER
barbarity O
. O

[ O
Signature O
:] O
Szczuczyńska B-PER
Lublin B-LOC
, O
September O
4 O
, O
1944 O
Collected O
by O
M. B-PER
Asz I-PER
