Addressed O
to O
R. O
Ministry B-ORG
of I-ORG
Foreign I-ORG
Affairs I-ORG
, O
Rome B-LOC
Zagreb B-LOC
, O
6th O
August O
1942 O
, O
Year O
XX O
Re O
: O
The B-TER
Jews I-TER
in O
Croatia B-LOC
– O
New O
measures B-TER
concerning O
them O
. O

Ref O
. O

Ministerial O
Cable O
no O
. O

8/13948 O
of O
29th O
July O
last O
. O

While O
, O
by O
arrangement O
with O
Supersloda B-ORG
, O
the O
Jews B-TER
living O
in O
the O
coastal O
strip O
of O
Croatia B-LOC
are O
about O
to O
be O
transferred B-TER
and O
concentrated B-TER
, O
several O
messages O
from O
R. O
subordinate O
Offices O
– O
cable O
no O
. O

432 O
from O
R. O
Consul O
in O
Osijek B-LOC
, O
dated O
24th O
July O
, O
cable O
from O
the O
R.Vice O
Consulate O
in O
Banja B-LOC
Luka I-LOC
of O
30th O
July O
, O
etc O
. O

– O
give O
the O
impression O
that O
this O
country O
’s O
Jewish B-TER
problem I-TER
, O
which O
has O
repeatedly O
been O
the O
object O
of O
drastic O
measures B-TER
, O
is O
now O
entering O
a O
new O
stage O
that O
might O
be O
the O
conclusive O
one O
. O

The O
new O
actions O
for O
concentrating B-TER
people I-TER
– O
approx O
. O

2,000 O
in O
Osijek B-LOC
, O
approx O
. O

200 O
in O
Banja B-LOC
Luka I-LOC
– O
seem O
to O
foreshadow O
a O
mass O
transfer O
at O
the O
disposal O
of O
German B-TER
authorities I-TER
in O
the O
occupied B-TER
Oriental I-TER
territories I-TER
, O
in O
accordance O
with O
a O
plan O
of O
which O
I O
have O
already O
reported O
on O
another O
occasion O
. O

As O
for O
Zagreb B-LOC
, O
a O
poster O
put O
up O
in O
the O
streets O
on O
27th O
July O
last O
requested O
all O
Jews B-TER
, O
regardless O
of O
their O
subjectship O
, O
to O
report O
to O
police B-TER
authorities I-TER
. O

Two O
days O
later O
, O
this O
decree B-TER
has O
been O
withdrawn O
. O

This O
is O
evidently O
a O
setback O
, O
which O
has O
given O
rise O
in O
public B-TER
opinion I-TER
to O
various O
comments O
that O
are O
not O
worthy O
of O
being O
repeated O
, O
and O
at O
the O
same O
time O
leaves O
the O
question O
unaltered O
and O
, O
as O
before O
, O
heading O
for O
a O
solution O
that O
neither O
diocesan B-TER
authorities I-TER
nor O
others O
are O
able O
to O
oppose O
. O

Giustiniani B-PER
