Statement O
written O
with O
Zdeněk B-PER
and O
Jiří B-PER
Steiner I-PER
, O
born O
20 O
. O

5 O
. O

1929 O
in O
Prague B-LOC
, O
residents O
of O
Prague B-LOC
, O
former O
prisoners B-TER
in O
the O
concentration B-TER
camps I-TER
of O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
and O
Auschwitz B-LOC
, O
residing O
in O
Prague B-LOC
XI I-LOC
. I-LOC

, O
Vratislavova B-LOC
13 O
, O
Czech B-TER
nationality O
. O

We O
left B-TER
Prague B-LOC
bound O
for O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
on O
22 O
. O

12 O
. O

1942 O
together O
with O
our O
parents B-TER
and O
a O
great O
number O
of O
relatives B-TER
. O

We O
spent O
8½ O
months O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
, O
where O
things O
had O
been O
so O
- O
so O
for O
us O
. O

We O
left B-TER
Theresienstadt B-LOC
on O
September O
6th O
, O
1943 O
, O
and O
, O
after O
a O
miserable O
two O
- O
day O
journey O
, O
we O
finally O
arrived O
at O
the O
Neu O
- O
Berun O
train O
station O
. O

From O
there O
, O
they O
took O
us O
to O
the O
concentration B-TER
camp I-TER
in O
Birkenau B-LOC
. O

We O
were O
told O
that O
it O
was O
only O
a O
quarantine B-TER
. O

After O
the O
usual O
procedures O
, O
such O
as O
a O
bath O
and O
a O
getting O
a O
tattoo O
( O
we O
were O
given O
the O
numbers O
147742 O
and O
147743 O
) O
, O
we O
were O
clothed O
in O
old O
rags B-TER
( O
children B-TER
in O
adult B-TER
clothing B-TER
) O
and O
housed B-TER
in O
camp B-TER
B I-TER
II I-TER
b I-TER
, O
where O
we O
spent O
6 O
whole O
months O
. O

We O
experienced O
so O
much O
in O
this O
place O
. O

Through O
the O
efforts O
of O
Fredy B-PER
Hirsch I-PER
, O
a O
children B-TER
’s I-TER
home I-TER
was O
established O
. O

We O
children B-TER
were O
better O
off O
than O
the O
adults B-TER
because O
we O
did O
n’t O
have O
to O
work B-TER
, O
our O
food B-TER
was O
a O
little O
bit O
better O
, O
and O
, O
later O
, O
our O
clothes B-TER
were O
better O
as O
well O
. O

Such O
was O
our O
life O
in O
the O
Birkenau B-LOC
children B-TER
’s I-TER
camp I-TER
under O
extremely O
harsh O
conditions B-TER
. O

A O
doctor B-TER
arrived O
in O
December O
( O
each O
camp B-TER
had O
a O
building B-TER
for O
the O
sick B-TER
and O
a O
single O
German O
doctor B-TER
, O
who O
generally O
did O
n’t O
know O
how O
to O
do O
much O
else O
besides O
sending O
as O
many O
people O
as O
possible O
to O
their O
graves O
, O
served O
several O
of O
these O
buildings B-TER
) O
. O

With O
a O
wave O
of O
his O
fingers O
, O
Dr. O
Mengele B-PER
decided O
who O
lived O
and O
who O
died O
, O
just O
like O
Nero O
did O
in O
ancient O
times O
. O

This O
renowned O
doctor B-TER
was O
very O
interested O
in O
us O
twins B-TER
, O
which O
was O
actually O
what O
saved O
us O
despite O
the O
fact O
that O
we O
came O
down O
with O
so O
many O
illnesses B-TER
. O

Once O
, O
Dr. O
Mengele B-PER
took O
a O
closer O
look O
at O
us O
, O
but O
then O
he O
contracted B-TER
spotted O
typhus B-TER
. O

In O
addition O
to O
him O
, O
we O
were O
tortured O
by O
the O
SSman B-TER
Buntrock B-PER
, O
who O
had O
a O
preference O
for O
beating O
children B-TER
. O

Another O
SSman B-TER
, O
probably O
a O
Russian B-TER
spy O
, O
who O
helped O
one O
of O
our O
people O
escape B-TER
, O
was O
shot B-TER
by O
other O
SS B-TER
officers I-TER
after O
he O
returned O
. O

In O
the O
meantime O
, O
the O
fateful O
month O
of O
March O
began O
. O

This O
month O
took O
away O
our O
parents B-TER
and O
all O
of O
our O
closest O
friends O
— O
the O
only O
thing O
that O
we O
still O
had O
in O
our O
lives O
. O

At O
the O
start O
of O
the O
month O
, O
it O
was O
rumored O
that O
the O
entire O
transport B-TER
that O
had O
arrived O
in O
September O
1943 O
would O
be O
taken O
to O
the O
labor B-TER
camp I-TER
in O
Heidebreck B-LOC
. O

And O
that O
’s O
exactly O
what O
happened O
. O

On O
March O
5th O
, O
postcards B-TER
on O
which O
we O
were O
supposed O
to O
write O
to O
our O
relatives O
that O
we O
were O
healthy O
and O
doing O
fine O
were O
handed O
out O
. O

These O
cards B-TER
were O
sent O
dated O
March O
25 O
th- O
27 O
th O
. O

We O
were O
n’t O
allowed O
to O
write O
about O
our O
departure O
. O

On O
the O
morning O
of O
March O
6th O
, O
as O
usual O
: O
Blockälteste O
antreten O
— O
an O
order O
for O
the O
entire O
transport B-TER
to O
go O
to O
the O
lower O
section O
of O
the O
camp B-TER
immediately O
. O

From O
there O
they O
took O
us O
to O
camp B-TER
B B-LOC
II I-LOC
a I-LOC
. O

There O
were O
so O
many O
rumors O
going O
about O
, O
for O
example O
that O
it O
was O
n’t O
a O
labor B-TER
transport I-TER
, O
but O
a O
chimney B-TER
. O

We O
did O
n’t O
believe O
it O
because O
we O
thought O
it O
was O
impossible O
. O

We O
waited O
all O
day O
, O
and O
in O
the O
evening O
we O
were O
told O
that O
the O
transport B-TER
could O
n’t O
depart O
because O
100 O
persons B-TER
were O
to O
be O
reclaimed B-TER
. O

This O
news O
greatly O
disturbed O
us O
. O

A O
terrible O
sleepless O
night O
wreaked O
havoc O
with O
our O
nerves O
. O

The O
people B-TER
, O
who O
were O
now O
extremely O
distraught O
, O
did O
n’t O
pay O
attention O
to O
anything O
; O
everyone O
just O
wished O
for O
this O
uncertainty O
to O
end O
. O

Midday O
, O
on O
March O
7th O
, O
a O
call O
: O
Ordnung O
am O
Block O
, O
Raportführer O
Buntrok O
geht O
. O

And O
he O
really O
came O
, O
read O
the O
names O
of O
several O
doctors B-TER
, O
and O
then O
we O
heard O
our O
names O
. O

We O
became O
very O
frightened O
, O
because O
father B-PER
's I-PER
name O
was O
n’t O
read O
, O
and O
mother B-PER
was O
n’t O
present O
on O
the O
block O
. O

Buntrok B-PER
assured O
father B-PER
that O
we O
would O
see O
one O
another O
in O
the O
evening O
, O
and O
we O
were O
taken O
to O
the O
Krankenbau B-TER
of O
camp B-TER
B B-TER
II I-TER
b I-TER
. O

There O
, O
we O
found O
out O
what O
it O
was O
really O
all O
about O
. O

There O
were O
32 O
of O
us O
in O
total O
, O
twins B-TER
and O
doctors B-TER
combined O
. O

Mengele B-PER
reclaimed B-TER
us O
twins B-TER
because O
he O
was O
interested O
in O
us O
, O
as O
we O
’ve O
already O
mentioned O
. O

He O
came O
to O
see O
us O
the O
next O
day O
. O

When O
we O
told O
him O
that O
our O
parents B-TER
had O
left O
on O
the O
transport B-TER
, O
he O
said O
: O
Schade O
. O

In O
the O
meantime O
, O
we O
found O
out O
that O
the O
cars O
had O
driven O
off O
during O
the O
night O
¨ O
in O
the O
direction O
of O
the O
crematorium B-TER
. O

The O
camp B-TER
was O
empty O
; O
flames O
shot O
up O
from O
the O
crematorium B-TER
. O

We O
will O
never O
forget O
this O
scene O
. O

But O
we O
did O
n’t O
believe O
that O
our O
parents B-TER
were O
dead B-TER
. O

However O
, O
we O
soon O
found O
out O
the O
truth O
from O
a O
doctor B-TER
who O
was O
a O
member O
of O
the O
Sonderkommando B-TER
, O
who O
was O
forced O
to O
do O
this O
work B-TER
. O

Mengele B-PER
arrived O
the O
following O
day O
, O
and O
took O
us O
by O
car O
to O
the O
Roma B-LOC
camp I-LOC
, O
which O
was O
where O
his O
station O
was O
. O

There O
, O
he O
precisely O
measured O
and O
weighed O
us O
, O
measured O
the O
length O
and O
width O
of O
our O
fingers O
and O
nails O
, O
the O
length O
and O
width O
of O
our O
noses O
, O
and O
anything O
else O
that O
could O
be O
measured O
and O
weighed O
. O

He O
also O
took O
down O
the O
color O
of O
our O
hair O
and O
skin O
. O

He O
carefully O
inspected O
us O
. O

He O
took O
fingerprints O
of O
our O
hands O
and O
feet O
. O

He O
worked O
alone O
; O
he O
never O
entrusted O
anyone O
else O
with O
the O
tasks O
he O
was O
performing O
. O

Then O
they O
brought O
us O
to O
the O
Krankenbau B-TER
and O
life O
went O
on O
. O

We O
received O
2 O
liters O
of O
soup B-TER
per O
day O
, O
otherwise O
the O
food B-TER
was O
the O
same O
as O
before O
. O

We O
were O
also O
photographed O
and O
x O
- O
rayed O
. O

Jewish O
doctors B-TER
, O
who O
guaranteed O
the O
correctness O
of O
the O
examinations O
with O
their O
lives O
, O
had O
to O
examine O
our O
nerves O
, O
eyes O
, O
teeth O
, O
and O
ears O
. O

The O
first O
labor B-TER
transport B-TER
from O
camp B-TER
B B-TER
II I-TER
b I-TER
left O
on O
1 O
. O

7 O
. O

In O
the O
meantime O
, O
another O
transport B-TER
from O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
with O
7½ O
thousand O
people B-TER
arrived O
in O
May O
. O

This O
brought O
the O
number O
of O
people B-TER
in O
the O
camp B-TER
to O
12,500 O
, O
3,000 O
of O
whom O
left O
to O
work B-TER
. O

The O
rest O
were O
incinerated B-TER
within O
2 O
nights O
. O

We O
were O
taken O
to O
B B-LOC
II I-LOC
f I-LOC
. O

In O
this O
new O
camp B-LOC
, O
they O
drew B-TER
our I-TER
blood I-TER
, O
which O
made O
our O
weakened O
bodies O
feel O
even O
worse O
. O

There O
is O
one O
horrible O
experience O
that O
we O
will O
never O
forget O
: O
one O
of O
our O
torturers O
, O
the O
camp B-TER
doctor B-TER
Thilo B-PER
, O
was O
making O
a O
selection B-TER
, O
i.e. O
choosing O
the O
people B-TER
who O
would O
be O
sent O
to O
the O
crematorium B-TER
, O
and O
he O
took O
our O
names O
down O
. O

What O
we O
felt O
when O
he O
did O
this O
can O
not O
be O
described O
. O

Fortunately O
, O
Mengele B-PER
heard O
this O
and O
saved O
us O
because O
he O
still O
needed O
us O
. O

The O
front O
was O
approaching O
and O
the O
mood O
in O
the O
camp B-LOC
lifted O
. O

During O
this O
time O
, O
I O
became O
a O
Pipel O
in O
the O
Krankenbau B-TER
, O
i.e. O
a O
runner O
, O
and O
so O
I O
was O
slightly O
better O
off O
. O

But O
then O
came O
winter O
and O
a O
new O
year O
, O
which O
was O
happier O
because O
we O
could O
hear O
the O
thunder O
of O
cannons O
. O

A O
rumor O
went O
around O
that O
the O
camp B-LOC
was O
going O
to O
be O
liquidated O
, O
but O
nothing O
happened O
. O

Finally O
, O
on O
January O
16th O
, O
they O
led O
the O
first O
transport B-TER
on I-TER
foot I-TER
out O
of O
Birkenau B-LOC
. O

The O
following O
days O
were O
extremely O
vexing O
, O
because O
one O
transport B-TER
after O
another O
departed O
. O

Everyone O
left O
voluntarily O
and O
we O
children B-TER
were O
the O
last O
to O
leave O
, O
partly O
because O
we O
did O
n’t O
want O
to O
go O
. O

People O
had O
to O
walk B-TER
60 O
km O
in O
the O
cold O
and O
frost O
, O
poorly O
clothed B-TER
and O
hungry B-TER
. O

We O
expected O
to O
be O
told O
that O
trains B-TER
would O
come O
pick O
us O
up O
. O

We O
finally O
got O
what O
we O
wanted O
on O
January O
20th O
, O
the O
day O
the O
last O
SSman B-TER
left O
the O
camp B-LOC
. O

This O
was O
a O
wonderful O
time O
for O
us O
. O

We O
went O
wherever O
we O
wanted O
, O
ate B-TER
whatever O
we O
wanted O
, O
did O
whatever O
we O
felt O
like O
doing O
. O

We O
roamed O
around O
the O
SS B-TER
camp O
. O

In O
short O
, O
we O
were O
having O
a O
great O
time O
. O

We O
went O
without O
supervision O
for O
5 O
days O
. O

Then O
, O
a O
group O
of O
SDmen O
arrived O
. O

They O
wanted O
to O
do B-TER
us I-TER
in I-TER
, O
but O
did O
n’t O
get O
the O
chance O
. O

They O
, O
too O
, O
fled O
, O
and O
so O
we O
stayed O
until O
January O
27th O
, O
when O
the O
victorious O
Red B-ORG
Army I-ORG
took B-TER
over I-TER
. O

On O
March O
27th O
, O
the O
Czech B-TER
Svoboda B-TER
’s I-TER
Army I-TER
took O
charge O
of O
us O
and O
brought O
us O
to O
Prague B-LOC
. O

Out O
of O
our O
family B-TER
of O
18 O
, O
only O
3 O
of O
us O
survived O
. O

Statement O
accepted O
by O
: O
Berta B-PER
Gerzonová I-PER
Signature O
: O
Jiří B-PER
Steiner I-PER
Zdeněk B-PER
Steiner I-PER
Accepted O
on O
behalf O
of O
the O
Documentation B-TER
campaign I-TER
by O
: O
4 O
. O

IX O
. O

1945 O
Scheck B-PER
Accepted O
on O
behalf O
of O
the O
archive O
: O
Alex B-PER
. I-PER

Schmiedt I-PER
