Policy B-TER
of O
Bulgarian B-ORG
Government I-ORG
upon O
its O
self O
- O
created O
Jewish B-TER
problem I-TER
has O
in O
the O
last O
few O
days O
clearly O
become O
directed O
towards O
elimination B-TER
of O
the O
Jewish B-TER
population I-TER
. O

In O
closed O
meeting O
of O
government O
’s O
staunch O
parliamentary O
supporters O
Minister O
Gabrovski B-PER
reportedly O
stated O
government O
had O
in O
resisting O
pressure O
to O
declare O
war B-TER
on O
Russia O
accepted O
German B-TER
pressure O
to O
liquidate B-TER
Jewish B-TER
communities I-TER
. O

Liquidation B-TER
is O
now O
being O
ruthlessly O
carried O
out O
in O
annexed B-TER
territories I-TER
where O
Jewish B-TER
deportees B-TER
are O
shipped O
in O
open O
freight O
cars O
to O
concentration B-TER
camps I-TER
. O

Each O
deportee B-TER
is O
stripped B-TER
his I-TER
valuables I-TER
and O
warm O
clothing O
. O

The O
daily O
food O
ration O
is O
200 O
grams O
of O
bread O
. O

[ O
... O
] O
In O
Bulgaria B-LOC
proper O
the O
authorities O
are O
acting O
more O
temperately O
where O
the O
sensibilities O
non B-TER
- I-TER
Jewish I-TER
Bulgarians I-TER
are O
involved O
. O

Preparations O
made O
for O
deportation B-TER
to O
Poland B-LOC
of O
Jews B-TER
from O
Kyustendil B-LOC
, O
Plovdiv B-LOC
, O
Yambol B-LOC
, O
Burgas B-LOC
and O
other O
towns O
of O
Bulgaria B-LOC
proper O
were O
suspended O
after O
strong O
protests O
by O
prominent O
Bulgarians B-TER
in O
these O
towns O
supported O
by O
the O
Archbishops O
of O
Sofia O
and O
Plovdiv O
. O

