Statement O
Written O
in O
Zeisheim B-LOC
D.P. B-TER
– I-TER
camp I-TER
near O
Frankfurt B-LOC
on O
3 O
. O

and O
4 O
. O

11 O
. O

1945 O
with O
Hermann B-PER
Przewozník I-PER
, O
Šlomo B-PER
Fuchs I-PER
, O
and O
Chaim B-PER
Schwarzwald I-PER
about O
the O
concentration B-TER
camps I-TER
Auschwitz B-LOC
II I-LOC
. I-LOC

, I-LOC
Birkenau I-LOC
. O

Przewoznik B-PER
, O
born O
16 O
. O

1 O
. O

1914 O
in O
Plonsk B-LOC
, O
prisoner B-TER
of O
the O
concentration B-TER
camp I-TER
Auschwitz B-LOC
II I-LOC
. I-LOC

Birkenau I-LOC
( O
prisoner B-TER
number O
84256 O
) O
, O
Oranienburg B-LOC
, I-LOC
Sachsenhausen B-LOC
, O
Kauffering B-LOC
, O
Dachau B-LOC
. O

Fuchs O
, O
born O
3 O
. O

5 O
. O

1908 O
was O
imprisoned B-TER
in O
Auschwitz B-LOC
II I-LOC
. I-LOC

Birkenau I-LOC
( O
Prisoner B-TER
number O
84033 O
) O
, O
Oranienburg B-LOC
, O
Flossenbürg B-LOC
, O
Dachau B-LOC
, O
Schwarzwald O
, O
born O
12 O
. O

11 O
. O

1921 O
in O
Plonsk B-LOC
, O
imprisoned B-TER
in O
Auschwitz B-LOC
I I-LOC
( O
60.423 O
) O
, O
Birkenau B-LOC
, O
Oranienburg B-LOC
, O
Sachsenhausen B-LOC
, O
Dachau B-LOC
. O

All O
three O
are O
currently O
in O
the O
Zeisheim B-LOC
D. B-TER
P. I-TER
Camp I-TER
near O
Frankfurt B-LOC
. O

We O
worked B-TER
in O
the O
Sauna O
– O
Birkenau B-LOC
disinfection O
chamber O
– O
from O
January O
1943 O
to O
January O
1945 O
, O
i.e. O
until O
the O
evacuation B-TER
, O
I O
, O
Herman B-PER
Przewoznik I-PER
, O
as O
a O
scribe B-TER
, O
I O
, O
Šlomo B-PER
Fuchs I-PER
, O
as O
a O
worker B-TER
on O
the O
so O
- O
called O
unclean O
side O
, O
and O
I O
, O
Chaim B-PER
Schwarzwald I-PER
, O
as O
a O
worker B-TER
on O
the O
ramp O
. O

When O
the O
transports B-TER
arrived O
, O
the O
people B-TER
were O
pulled O
out O
of O
the O
carriages B-TER
, O
their O
things O
were O
taken O
away O
, O
and O
then O
they O
were O
turned O
over O
– O
men B-TER
and O
women B-TER
separately O
– O
for O
selection B-TER
by O
the O
SS B-TER
doctors B-TER
Mengele B-PER
, O
Thilo B-PER
, O
Horstmann B-PER
, O
König B-PER
and O
others O
, O
who O
had O
the O
SS B-TER
rank O
of O
Ober B-TER
- O
or O
Hauptsturmführer B-TER
. O

Men B-TER
always O
stood O
on O
the O
right O
, O
and O
women B-TER
on O
the O
left O
. O

The O
people B-TER
selected B-TER
for O
the O
camp B-TER
were O
sent O
to O
the O
left O
side O
, O
the O
others O
, O
who O
were O
to O
be O
gassed B-TER
, O
to O
the O
right O
. O

In O
the O
years O
‘ O
42 O
and O
‘ O
43 O
, O
on O
average O
20 O
% O
percent O
of O
the O
people B-TER
were O
sent O
to O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

However O
, O
there O
were O
transports B-TER
out O
of O
which O
only O
5 O
% O
or O
10 O
% O
were O
sent O
to O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

Some O
transports B-TER
were O
sent O
to O
the O
gas B-TER
chambers I-TER
without O
going O
through O
selection B-TER
. O

This O
happened O
, O
for O
example O
, O
to O
the O
transports B-TER
from O
Plonsk B-LOC
and O
Nový B-LOC
Dvůr I-LOC
, O
carrying O
2,000 O
people B-TER
, O
and O
other O
transports B-TER
of O
Polish B-TER
Jews I-TER
. O

In O
1944 O
, O
a O
larger O
portion O
, O
up O
to O
40 O
% O
, O
were O
sent O
to O
the O
camp B-TER
, O
but O
nevertheless O
even O
during O
this O
time O
entire O
transports B-TER
were O
sent O
to O
the O
gas B-TER
chambers I-TER
, O
such O
as O
the O
transport B-TER
of O
Lithuanian B-LOC
Jews B-TER
( O
1,886 O
women B-TER
and O
children B-TER
) O
, O
who O
were O
sent O
to O
the O
gas B-TER
chamber I-TER
from O
the O
sauna O
under O
the O
direct O
orders O
of O
Mengele B-PER
and O
Kramer B-PER
in O
the O
beginning O
of O
October O
. O

Around O
October O
1943 O
, O
a O
transport B-TER
arrived O
from O
Theresienstadt B-TER
with O
roughly O
1,000 O
to O
1,200 O
children B-TER
from I-TER
Bialystok I-TER
with O
their O
caretakers B-TER
and O
nurses B-TER
. O

They O
had O
Palestinian B-LOC
visas B-TER
, O
but O
they O
were O
all O
gassed B-TER
in O
Crematorium B-TER
I. O
Four O
weeks O
later O
, O
a O
transport B-TER
arrived O
from O
Hannover B-LOC
. O

Its O
occupants O
had O
American B-LOC
visas B-TER
as O
American B-LOC
citizens O
, O
and O
we O
heard O
that O
they O
were O
to O
be O
exchanged O
for O
German B-TER
prisoners B-TER
of I-TER
war I-TER
. O

The O
artist O
Lola B-PER
Lipmann I-PER
from O
Warsaw B-LOC
was O
a O
passenger O
on O
this O
transport B-TER
. O

In O
the O
sauna O
, O
Rapportführer B-TER
Schillinger B-PER
, O
who O
was O
known O
and O
feared O
as O
the O
Birkenau B-LOC
executioner B-TER
, O
wanted O
to O
hurry O
her O
along O
when O
she O
suddenly O
shot B-TER
him O
with O
his O
own O
revolver O
and O
seriously O
wounded O
the O
Arbeitsdienstführer O
from O
Auschwitz B-LOC
I I-LOC
. O

Until O
this O
incident O
, O
men B-TER
were B-TER
gassed I-TER
in O
Crematorium B-TER
II O
and O
women B-TER
in O
Crematorium B-TER
I. O
Afterwards O
, O
men B-TER
and O
women B-TER
were O
immediately O
separated O
, O
and O
women B-TER
were O
either O
shot B-TER
or O
gassed B-TER
by O
SS B-TER
helpers O
. O

Men B-TER
were B-TER
gassed I-TER
in O
Crematorium B-TER
II O
. O

The O
people B-TER
who O
were O
selected B-TER
to O
be O
sent O
to O
the O
camp B-TER
went O
into O
the O
sauna O
, O
where O
their O
hair O
was O
cut O
, O
they O
bathed O
, O
and O
changed O
into O
different O
clothes B-TER
. O

The O
rest O
of O
the O
things O
they O
were O
allowed O
to O
take O
with O
them O
from O
the O
train O
station O
were O
also O
taken O
from O
them O
here O
. O

Each O
person B-TER
was O
given O
a O
tattered O
shirt B-TER
, O
sometimes O
underwear B-TER
, O
a O
skirt B-TER
or O
pants B-TER
, O
and O
so O
- O
called O
Dutch B-TER
clogs I-TER
. O

Starting O
in O
1944 O
, O
women B-TER
were O
no O
longer O
given O
any O
underwear B-TER
, O
but O
only O
a O
dress B-TER
or O
skirt B-TER
, O
and O
a O
pyjama B-TER
camisole I-TER
. O

From O
the O
year O
left O
blank O
, O
selection B-TER
was O
conducted O
in O
Sauna O
II O
, O
during O
which O
pregnant B-TER
women B-TER
and O
other O
weak O
or O
injured O
people B-TER
were O
sent O
to O
the O
crematorium B-TER
’s O
sauna O
or O
to O
Bunker B-TER
V I-TER
. O

This O
selection B-TER
was O
ordered O
by O
SS B-TER
doctors B-TER
, O
SS B-TER
members B-TER
Schniders B-PER
and O
Haagen B-PER
. O

Haagen B-PER
regularly O
beat O
the O
women B-TER
and O
personally O
brought O
them O
to O
the O
crematorium B-TER
. O

People B-TER
who O
were O
selected B-TER
to O
be O
gassed B-TER
were O
taken O
directly O
from O
the O
ramp O
to O
one O
of O
the O
4 O
crematoria B-TER
or O
to O
Bunker B-TER
V I-TER
, O
which O
was O
a O
rustic O
house O
with O
a O
straw O
roof O
and O
4 O
small O
rooms O
. O

Everywhere O
there O
were O
signs O
: O
Zum O
Bad O
. O

People B-TER
had O
to O
get O
undressed O
there O
. O

Some O
transports B-TER
were O
ordered O
to O
write O
letters B-TER
in O
which O
they O
stated O
that O
they O
had O
arrived O
in O
one O
piece O
, O
were O
reunited O
with O
their O
friends O
, O
and O
were O
on O
their O
way O
to O
the O
baths O
. O

In O
Crematoria B-TER
I O
and O
II O
, O
gas B-TER
was O
introduced O
from O
the O
top O
. O

The O
gas B-TER
used O
was O
zyklon B-TER
B I-TER
Degesch O
( O
Deutsche O
Gesellschaft O
für O
Schädlingsbekämpfung O
, O
Hamburg B-LOC
) O
. O

In O
Crematoria B-TER
III O
and O
IV O
, O
gas B-TER
was O
let O
in O
through O
small O
windows O
. O

Bunker B-TER
V I-TER
used O
the O
same O
method O
. O

In O
the O
middle O
of O
Crematoria B-TER
I O
and O
II O
, O
there O
were O
4 O
four O
- O
sided O
poles O
out O
of O
tangled O
wire O
, O
into O
which O
gas B-TER
was O
let O
in O
from O
the O
top O
( O
through O
green O
or O
yellow O
pieces O
of O
cardboard O
that O
released O
hydrogen O
cyanide O
gas B-TER
when O
they O
came O
in O
contact O
with O
the O
humidity O
of O
the O
air O
) O
. O

In O
Crematoria B-TER
III O
and O
IV O
and O
in O
Bunker B-TER
V I-TER
, O
these O
gas B-TER
carriers O
were O
thrown O
into O
the O
chambers B-TER
through O
a O
side O
window O
by O
SS B-TER
members I-TER
wearing O
gas B-TER
masks O
. O

The O
windows O
were O
then O
hermetically O
sealed O
. O

Crematoria B-TER
I O
and O
II O
had O
a O
capacity O
of O
3,000 O
people B-TER
; O
Crematoria B-TER
III O
and O
IV O
and O
Bunker B-TER
V I-TER
had O
a O
capacity O
of O
1,500 O
people B-TER
. O

Rottenführer B-TER
Schniders B-PER
, O
Haagen B-PER
( O
at O
the O
time O
in O
Dachau B-LOC
) O
, O
Sturmmann B-TER
Gräf B-PER
from O
Romania B-LOC
, O
Dobrovolský B-PER
from O
Slovakia B-LOC
, O
and O
George O
from O
Katovice B-LOC
were O
in O
charge O
of O
the O
gassing B-TER
. O

Moll B-PER
was O
the O
head O
of O
the O
crematoria B-TER
. O

Jews O
worked B-TER
in O
all O
of O
the O
crematoria B-TER
. O

Fifteen O
Russians B-TER
, O
3 O
Polish B-TER
Kapos B-TER
, O
2 O
German B-TER
head O
Kapos B-TER
, O
and O
the O
Jewish O
Kapo B-TER
Kaminský B-PER
from O
Grodno B-LOC
, O
who O
was O
shot B-TER
by O
Moll B-PER
in O
1944 O
, O
worked O
alongside O
them O
. O

Death B-TER
in I-TER
the I-TER
gas I-TER
chamber I-TER
took O
about O
3 O
minutes O
for O
men B-TER
, O
5 O
minutes O
for O
women B-TER
. O

Children B-TER
, O
when O
they O
held O
onto O
their O
mothers B-TER
, O
died O
in O
about O
7 O
minutes O
. O

If O
the O
bunker B-TER
was O
damp O
, O
it O
took O
longer O
to O
die B-TER
in I-TER
the I-TER
gas I-TER
chamber I-TER
. O

The O
necessary O
dose O
of O
gas B-TER
for O
3,000 O
people B-TER
was O
3 O
kg O
of O
Zyklon B-TER
. O

Schniders B-PER
sometimes O
let O
less O
gas B-TER
in O
, O
thereby O
prolonging O
the O
suffering B-TER
of O
those O
inside O
the O
chamber B-TER
. O

When O
an O
Italian B-LOC
transport B-TER
, O
arriving O
probably O
in O
January O
‘ O
44 O
and O
carrying O
1,500 O
people O
, O
was O
sent O
to O
the O
gas B-TER
chamber I-TER
( O
Haagen B-PER
administered O
the O
gas B-TER
) O
, O
a O
prisoner B-TER
managed O
to O
throw O
a O
box O
containing O
the O
gas B-TER
out O
of O
the O
window O
, O
and O
only O
a O
small O
amount O
of O
gas B-TER
was O
released O
into O
the O
chamber B-TER
. O

Then O
the O
bunker B-TER
was O
hermetically O
sealed O
. O

Mengele B-PER
, O
Kramer B-PER
, O
and O
Haagen B-PER
listened O
at O
the O
doors O
. O

For O
a O
long O
time O
, O
about O
½ O
an O
hour O
, O
we O
could O
hear O
the O
desperate O
cries O
of O
the O
prisoners B-TER
. O

Hauptschaarführer B-TER
Moll B-PER
, O
who O
beat O
women B-TER
with O
a O
2 O
- O
meter O
whip O
, O
or O
used O
them O
for O
target O
practice O
, O
was O
also O
active O
around O
those O
sent O
to O
be O
gassed B-TER
. O

He O
once O
tried O
to O
shoot B-TER
5 O
selected O
women B-TER
with O
one O
shot O
. O

He O
like O
to O
pick O
beautiful O
women B-TER
who O
he O
then O
shot B-TER
in O
the O
neck O
while O
the O
others O
were O
killed B-TER
by I-TER
gas I-TER
. O

He O
would O
then O
clean O
his O
jackboots O
with O
their O
blood O
. O

Our O
friend O
Jankel B-PER
Silberberg I-PER
from O
Zakroczym B-LOC
, O
who O
previously O
resided O
in O
Plonsk B-LOC
and O
is O
currently O
in O
the O
Polish B-LOC
Army B-TER
, O
and O
who O
worked B-TER
in O
the O
so O
- O
called O
Sonderkommando B-TER
, O
can O
corroborate O
this O
. O

We O
know O
this O
because O
we O
brought O
gas B-TER
for O
delousing O
to O
the O
crematoria B-TER
every O
day O
. O

In O
front O
of O
Bunker B-TER
V I-TER
there O
was O
a O
small O
birch O
grove O
that O
we O
called O
the O
little O
birch O
. O

It O
was O
mostly O
women B-TER
who O
were O
gassed B-TER
in O
Bunker B-TER
V I-TER
. O

If O
the O
transport B-TER
contained O
more O
than O
1,500 O
women B-TER
, O
the O
rest O
waited O
behind O
the O
bunker B-TER
until O
the O
first O
1,500 O
were O
gassed B-TER
and O
made O
ready O
to O
be O
burned O
in O
the O
ditch B-TER
. O

Bunker B-TER
V I-TER
did O
not O
have O
a O
crematorium B-TER
nearby O
, O
but O
a O
ditch B-TER
in O
which O
the O
bodies B-TER
were O
doused O
with O
gasoline O
and O
burned O
in O
piles O
. O

About O
6,000 O
bodies B-TER
were O
burned O
all O
at O
once O
. O

The O
ash O
was O
used O
as O
fertilizer O
for O
the O
tree O
nursery O
, O
to O
seal O
potato O
bunkers O
in O
order O
to O
keep O
out O
the O
humidity O
, O
or O
to O
scatter O
over O
the O
paths O
in O
Buna B-LOC
. O

The O
rest O
was O
thrown O
into O
water O
. O

Crematoria B-TER
I O
and O
II O
were O
put O
into O
operation O
in O
March O
1943 O
. O

The O
first O
transport B-TER
was O
from O
Krakow B-LOC
. O

Its O
men B-TER
arrived O
at O
the O
camp B-TER
and O
received O
the O
numbers O
108 O
thousand O
and O
higher O
. O

It O
was O
followed O
by O
transports B-TER
from O
Greece B-LOC
with O
numbers O
109 O
all O
the O
way O
up O
to O
117 O
thousand O
. O

About O
2 O
months O
later O
, O
Crematoria B-TER
II O
and O
IV O
were O
put O
into O
operation O
. O

Bunker B-TER
5 I-TER
was O
used O
until O
the O
crematoria B-TER
were O
ready O
, O
which O
was O
later O
, O
once O
again O
in O
1944 O
, O
when O
Hungarian B-LOC
transports B-TER
arrived O
carrying O
850,000 O
Jews O
, O
70,000 O
Jews O
from O
Lodz B-LOC
, O
and O
2 O
transports B-TER
from I-TER
Theresienstadt I-TER
. O

The O
Birkenau B-LOC
camp B-TER
had O
27 O
buildings B-TER
, O
12 O
of O
which O
were O
wooden O
( O
former O
horse O
stables B-TER
) O
and O
15 O
of O
which O
were O
made O
of O
stone O
. O

There O
were O
up O
to O
1,000 O
prisoners B-TER
in O
each O
wooden O
building B-TER
, O
and O
up O
to O
1,500 O
prisoners B-TER
in O
each O
stone O
building O
. O

This O
was O
in O
the O
old O
men B-TER
’s I-TER
camp I-TER
, O
which O
was O
changed O
to O
the O
women B-TER
’s I-TER
camp I-TER
later O
in O
June O
, O
1943 O
. O

At O
the O
time O
, O
men B-TER
were O
sent O
to O
Camp B-TER
D O
, O
Bauabschnitt O
II O
( O
B B-LOC
II I-LOC
d O
) O
. O

Until O
March O
1943 O
, O
the O
Blockälteste O
of O
block O
15 O
was O
the O
Polish B-TER
priest B-TER
Vladyk B-PER
. O

He O
was O
followed O
by O
the O
French B-LOC
Jew O
Leon B-PER
Cimbler I-PER
, O
nicknamed O
the O
boxer O
, O
who O
killed B-TER
up O
to O
50 O
Jews B-TER
a O
day O
. O

The O
Blockälteste O
of O
block O
21 O
was O
the O
Polish B-TER
officer O
Januš B-PER
Pokřivnický I-PER
, O
who O
sadistically O
beat O
and O
tortured O
the O
prisoners B-TER
of O
his O
block O
. O

The O
Blockälteste O
of O
block O
5 O
was O
a O
German B-TER
named O
Albert B-PER
Hammerle I-PER
, O
who O
tortured O
and O
killed B-TER
many O
Jews B-TER
every O
day O
. O

French B-LOC
Jew B-TER
Schaffmann B-PER
carried O
out O
acts O
of O
equal O
cruelty O
in O
block O
27 O
. O

The O
French B-LOC
Jew B-TER
Pinkus B-PER
was O
in O
block O
22 O
, O
where O
members B-TER
of O
the O
new O
transports B-TER
were O
sent O
. O

He O
greeted O
newcomers O
by O
striking O
them O
with O
a O
cane O
, O
hammer O
, O
and O
an O
iron O
strap O
. O

He O
tried O
to O
kill B-TER
as O
many O
as O
he O
could O
and O
also O
took O
from O
them O
what O
money O
, O
gold O
, O
and O
valuables O
they O
had O
left O
. O

He O
greeted O
them O
with O
the O
words O
: O
I O
’ll O
make O
sure O
you O
’ll O
live O
for O
only O
1 O
or O
2 O
hours O
, O
you O
Hurensöhne O
. O

The O
head O
of O
the O
sauna O
until O
March O
43 O
was O
a O
Pole B-TER
named O
Štefan B-PER
, O
who O
was O
a O
dangerous O
sadist O
, O
especially O
towards O
the O
Jews B-TER
. O

Other O
dangerous O
sadists O
were O
the O
Germans B-TER
Alois O
and O
Martin O
, O
a O
certain O
Stefan O
– O
a O
Volksdeutscher B-TER
from O
Poland B-LOC
‒ O
Schilfsmeer O
, O
the O
camp B-TER
kapo B-TER
Thin O
, O
the O
kapo B-TER
Chaim B-PER
Kleinmann I-PER
from O
Plonsk B-LOC
, O
and O
head O
kapo B-TER
Rudi(a O
German B-TER
who O
was O
also O
an O
executioner B-TER
) O
from O
the O
More O
commando O
. O

Camps B-TER
B B-LOC
I I-LOC
A O
and O
B B-LOC
I I-LOC
B O
were O
F B-TER
KL B-TER
( O
women B-TER
’s I-TER
concentration B-TER
camps I-TER
) O
. O

The O
head O
SS B-TER
women B-TER
were O
, O
among O
others O
: O
Mandler B-PER
, O
Drexler B-PER
, O
Greise B-PER
, O
Hasse B-PER
, O
Brandl B-PER
, O
Zarecki B-PER
, O
Müller B-PER
, O
and O
the O
SS B-TER
men I-TER
were O
: O
Perschel B-PER
– O
Arbeitsdienstführer O
, O
Teller B-PER
– O
Rapportführer B-TER
, O
Schluz B-PER
– O
Arbeitsdienstführer O
. O

Hössler B-PER
was O
the O
Lagerführer B-TER
. O

All O
of O
them O
tortured O
prisoners B-TER
in O
indescribable O
ways O
. O

Schulz B-PER
once O
grabbed O
a O
woman B-TER
who O
was O
working B-TER
on O
the O
road O
construction O
by O
the O
legs O
and O
beat O
her O
head O
with O
a O
stone O
. O

I O
, O
Chaim B-PER
Schwarzwald I-PER
, O
saw O
this O
with O
my O
own O
eyes O
. O

B B-LOC
II I-LOC
A I-LOC
. O

A O
Quarantine B-TER
Camp B-TER
for O
newcomers O
. O

Quarantine B-TER
lasted O
from O
3 O
weeks O
to O
3 O
months O
. O

It O
consisted O
of O
16 O
wooden O
buildings B-TER
. O

Sometimes O
, O
Dr. O
Mengele B-PER
, O
Thilo B-PER
, O
and O
others O
carried O
out O
the O
selection B-TER
process O
there O
. O

Most O
were O
sent O
to O
the O
gas B-TER
chambers I-TER
, O
and O
the O
rest O
was O
transferred O
to O
Camp B-LOC
D I-LOC
or O
other O
camps B-TER
. O

This O
camp B-LOC
was O
put O
into O
operation O
when O
the O
transports B-TER
from O
Sosnowiec B-LOC
and O
Bedzin B-LOC
arrived O
. O

At O
the O
beginning O
of O
August O
1943 O
, O
the O
people B-TER
from O
these O
transports B-TER
received O
the O
numbers O
132,000 O
and O
higher O
. O

B B-TER
II I-TER
A I-TER
. O

The O
so O
- O
called O
Czech B-TER
camp I-TER
was O
opened O
to O
accommodate O
the O
Theresienstadt B-TER
transports I-TER
in O
September O
1943 O
with O
numbers O
146,000 O
and O
higher O
. O

Men B-TER
, O
women B-TER
, O
and O
children B-TER
were O
housed O
together O
in O
this O
camp B-TER
. O

When O
these O
transports B-TER
arrived O
, O
selection B-TER
did O
n’t O
take O
place O
by O
the O
tracks O
and O
the O
arrivals O
did O
not O
have O
their O
hair O
cut O
. O

On O
8 O
. O

3 O
. O

1944 O
during O
Purim B-TER
, O
the O
entire O
transport B-TER
but O
for O
a O
few O
exceptions O
was O
gassed B-TER
. O

Later O
, O
this O
camp B-TER
was O
changed O
to O
an O
FKL B-TER
. O

At O
the O
time O
, O
Greise B-PER
was O
the O
Rapportführer O
there O
. O

B B-LOC
II I-LOC
C I-LOC
. O

It O
was O
opened O
in O
June O
1944 O
for O
the O
women B-TER
from O
the O
transports B-TER
from O
Hungary B-LOC
and O
Lodz B-LOC
. O

The O
SS B-TER
woman I-TER
Kuk B-PER
was O
the O
Rapportführer O
. O

This O
camp B-LOC
was O
liquidated O
in O
October O
1944 O
. O

The O
majority O
was O
sent O
to O
the O
gas B-TER
chambers I-TER
. O

Only O
the O
women B-TER
employed O
in O
the O
weaving O
mill O
were O
spared O
. O

SS B-TER
guard B-TER
Hasse B-PER
oversaw B-TER
this O
selection B-TER
. O

B B-LOC
III I-LOC
D I-LOC
. O

A O
labor B-TER
camp I-TER
for O
men B-TER
, O
32 O
blocks O
. O

The O
camp B-TER
opened O
in O
1943 O
and O
was O
in O
operation O
until O
the O
evacuation B-TER
of O
Auschwitz B-LOC
. O

B B-LOC
II I-LOC
E I-LOC
. O

The O
so O
- O
called O
Gypsy B-TER
camp B-LOC
opened O
in O
the O
spring O
of O
of O
1943 O
. O

Gypsies B-TER
from O
everywhere O
in O
Europe O
were O
there O
until O
1944 O
. O

Afterwards O
, O
some O
were O
put O
onto O
transports B-TER
and O
the O
rest O
were O
killed B-TER
in O
the O
gas B-TER
chambers I-TER
. O

Transports B-TER
from O
Hungary B-LOC
, O
Lodz B-LOC
, O
and O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
then O
arrived O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

This O
camp B-LOC
was O
in O
operation O
until O
the O
evacuation B-TER
. O

B B-LOC
II I-LOC
F I-LOC
. O

Krankenbau B-TER
was O
supervised B-TER
by O
the O
Polish B-TER
doctor B-TER
Zengfeller B-PER
, O
a O
mass O
murderer B-TER
and O
assistant B-TER
to I-TER
the I-TER
doctors I-TER
during O
the O
selection B-TER
process I-TER
. O

B B-LOC
II I-LOC
g I-LOC
. O

The O
so O
- O
called O
Effektenlager O
and O
sauna O
. O

At O
the O
beginning O
of O
May O
1944 O
, O
all O
of O
the O
luggage O
from O
the O
people B-TER
on O
the O
latest O
transports B-TER
was O
brought O
there O
. O

A O
total O
of O
1,200 O
women B-TER
and O
600 O
men B-TER
worked B-TER
in O
the O
Effektenlager O
, O
which O
was O
called O
Kanada B-TER
. O

The O
head O
of O
the O
Effektenlager O
was O
Oberstrumführer B-TER
Kratzer B-PER
who O
said O
that O
luggage O
was O
insignificant O
, O
the O
main O
thing O
was O
the O
destruction O
of O
the O
Jews O
. O

The O
luggage O
was O
sorted O
by O
women B-TER
and O
sent O
to O
Germany B-TER
. O

Also O
, O
human O
hair O
was O
disinfected O
, O
packed O
, O
and O
sent O
. O

B B-LOC
III I-LOC
. I-LOC

, O
so O
- O
called O
Mexico O
. O

This O
camp B-LOC
opened O
in O
May O
1944 O
for O
transports B-TER
from O
Hungary B-LOC
, O
Lodz B-LOC
, O
and O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
. O

Here O
, O
too O
, O
there O
were O
only O
women B-TER
, O
at O
least O
90 O
% O
of O
whom O
were O
sent O
to O
the O
gas B-TER
chamber I-TER
at O
the O
beginning O
of O
1944 O
. O

Kramer B-PER
, O
Mengele B-PER
, O
and O
most O
of O
the O
doctors B-TER
and O
SS B-TER
female B-TER
wardens I-TER
personally O
took O
part O
in O
this O
selection B-TER
process I-TER
. O

The O
newly O
arrived O
generally O
did O
n’t O
know O
what O
lay O
ahead O
for O
them O
. O

At O
night O
, O
they O
sometimes O
saw O
the O
glow O
of O
the O
fire O
and O
the O
loading O
of O
dead B-TER
bodies I-TER
. O

Acts O
of O
resistance B-TER
would O
sometimes O
occur O
. O

There O
was O
shooting O
, O
but O
the O
SS B-TER
usually O
managed O
to O
calm O
them O
down O
. O

They O
were O
shown O
the O
sauna O
and O
told O
it O
was O
a O
delousing B-TER
station O
, O
and O
, O
when O
their O
anger O
subsided O
, O
people O
were O
led O
to O
the O
gas B-TER
chambers I-TER
. O

I O
, O
Herman B-PER
Przewoznik I-PER
, O
saw O
with O
my O
own O
eyes O
a O
mother B-TER
with O
3 O
small O
children B-TER
try O
to O
run B-TER
away I-TER
at O
night O
, O
horrified O
at O
what O
she O
’d O
seen O
. O

She O
came O
upon O
Sturmmann B-TER
Wagner B-PER
in O
Camp B-LOC
D I-LOC
. O

He O
calmed O
her O
down O
and O
led O
her O
to O
the O
gas B-TER
chamber I-TER
. O

One O
night O
during O
the O
arrival O
of O
a O
transport B-TER
from I-TER
Theresienstadt I-TER
in O
October O
1944 O
the O
women B-TER
supposedly O
resisted B-TER
. O

We O
heard O
a O
scream O
and O
Moll B-PER
’s O
voice O
, O
shouting O
: O
Quickly O
get O
back O
inside O
. O

You O
’re O
only O
going O
for O
a O
bath O
and O
then O
you O
’ll O
be O
out O
again O
. O

Then O
we O
heard O
them O
being O
hit O
with O
canes O
and O
dogs O
barking O
. O

During O
the O
selection B-TER
processes I-TER
in O
the O
camps B-TER
people B-TER
knew O
what O
was O
truly O
happening O
, O
but O
they O
never O
resisted B-TER
. O

In O
1942 O
, O
when O
the O
crematoria B-TER
were O
n’t O
yet O
in O
operation O
, O
Bunker B-TER
V I-TER
was O
never O
enough O
. O

Once O
, O
children B-TER
were O
thrown O
into O
the O
fire O
. O

Some O
had O
previously O
been O
killed B-TER
, O
but O
some O
were O
still O
alive O
. O

Until O
March O
1943 O
the O
selection B-TER
process I-TER
took O
place O
2 O
to O
3 O
times O
a O
week O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

The O
selection B-TER
process I-TER
was O
carried O
out O
by O
SS B-TER
doctors B-TER
, O
with O
the O
help O
of O
a O
Polish B-TER
doctor B-TER
named O
Dr. O
Zenkfeller B-PER
, O
who O
was O
a O
dangerous O
anti B-TER
- I-TER
semite I-TER
. O

During O
the O
roll B-TER
calls I-TER
, O
the O
selected O
had O
their O
numbers O
taken O
down O
and O
they O
were O
sent O
to O
block O
7 O
. O

Prior O
to O
this O
, O
they O
were O
tattooed O
with O
the O
letter O
L O
next O
to O
their O
number O
. O

During O
each O
selection B-TER
process I-TER
1,500 O
men B-TER
and O
1,500 O
women B-TER
were O
selected O
to O
be O
gassed B-TER
. O

Then O
, O
from O
March O
until O
Yom B-TER
Kippur I-TER
1943 O
, O
the O
selection B-TER
process I-TER
did O
n’t O
occur O
. O

At O
that O
time O
, O
the O
women B-TER
from O
Camp B-LOC
B I-LOC
I I-LOC
a I-LOC
and O
B B-LOC
I I-LOC
b I-LOC
were O
taken O
to O
their O
camp B-LOC
’s O
sauna O
, O
and O
Obersturmführer B-TER
Roder B-PER
selected B-TER
and O
ordered O
5,500 O
women B-TER
to O
be O
gassed B-TER
. O

At O
the O
same O
time O
, O
6,500 O
men B-TER
from O
all O
of O
the O
camps B-TER
that O
were O
part O
of O
Auschwitz B-LOC
were O
selected B-TER
to O
be O
gassed B-TER
. O

These O
12,000 O
Jews B-TER
were O
led O
to O
the O
gas B-TER
chambers I-TER
at O
the O
same O
time O
as O
the O
Kol O
Nidre O
was O
being O
sung O
. O

Naked O
men B-TER
and O
women B-TER
were O
led O
to O
the O
crematoria B-TER
to O
the O
sound O
of O
the O
Kol O
Nidre O
and O
Hatikvah O
being O
sung O
. O

Afterwards O
, O
only O
smaller O
selection B-TER
processes I-TER
resumed O
, O
until O
the O
day O
of O
1.1.1944 O
, O
when O
Drs O
. O

Mengele B-PER
and O
Thilo B-PER
conducted O
a O
large O
selection B-TER
process I-TER
in O
the O
men B-TER
’s I-TER
and O
women B-TER
’s I-TER
camp I-TER
. O

This O
was O
repeated O
on O
19.1.1944 O
. O

After O
these O
selection B-TER
processes I-TER
, O
only O
about O
800 O
Jews B-TER
remained O
in O
the O
camp B-LOC
. O

On O
7 O
. O

3 O
. O

1944 O
, O
the O
September O
transport B-TER
from I-TER
Theresienstadt I-TER
, O
numbering O
5,000 O
people B-TER
, O
were O
gassed B-TER
. O

This O
is O
how O
it O
happened O
: O
On O
March O
7th O
, O
the O
entire O
transport B-TER
was O
led O
to O
Camp B-LOC
B I-LOC
II I-LOC
a I-LOC
. O

During O
the O
evening O
of O
March O
8th O
( O
Purim B-TER
) O
at O
11 O
o’clock O
at O
night O
they O
received O
refreshment O
packages O
and O
the O
order O
to O
write O
the O
date O
March O
27th O
on O
pieces B-TER
of I-TER
paper I-TER
. O

They O
were O
told O
that O
they O
would O
be O
taken O
to O
another O
camp B-TER
in O
Heidebreck B-LOC
. O

In O
order O
to O
confuse O
them O
, O
they O
were O
first O
taken O
to O
Auschwitz B-LOC
I I-LOC
and O
from O
there O
back O
to O
Birkenau B-LOC
. O

During O
the O
arrival O
of O
the O
December O
transport B-TER
from I-TER
Theresienstadt I-TER
, O
when O
the O
people B-TER
were O
having O
their O
jewelry O
and O
gold O
taken O
away O
, O
an O
older O
woman B-TER
wanted O
to O
keep O
her O
wedding O
ring O
. O

Rottenführer B-TER
Waldemar B-PER
Bedarf I-PER
, O
a O
Volksdeutscher B-TER
from O
Poland B-LOC
, O
violently O
pulled O
her O
ring O
off O
and O
beat O
her O
. O

Bedarf B-PER
was O
one O
of O
the O
leading O
executioners B-TER
in O
Birkenau B-LOC
. O

The O
transport B-TER
that O
I O
have O
just O
mentioned O
was O
taken O
to O
Family B-TER
Camp I-TER
B I-TER
II I-TER
b I-TER
without O
going O
through O
the O
selection B-TER
process I-TER
. O

One O
thousand O
six O
hundred O
and O
twenty O
five O
men B-TER
and O
about O
500 O
women B-TER
from O
this O
transport B-TER
were O
sent O
to O
work O
and O
the O
rest O
were O
gassed B-TER
in O
May O
1944 O
, O
with O
the O
exception O
of O
roughly O
80 O
children B-TER
aged O
10 O
- O
12 O
, O
who O
arrived O
at O
Camp B-LOC
D I-LOC
and O
later O
departed O
on O
another O
transport B-TER
. O

In O
May O
1944 O
, O
transports B-TER
of O
Hungarian B-LOC
Jews B-TER
began O
arriving O
in O
Birkenau B-LOC
, O
first O
from O
Transylvania B-LOC
, O
and O
then O
from O
Carpatho O
- O
Ukraine O
. O

Eight O
to O
ten O
transports B-TER
arrived O
every O
day O
, O
each O
carrying O
2,000 O
people B-TER
. O

The B-TER
selection I-TER
process I-TER
took O
place O
on O
the O
ramp O
. O

J. B-PER
Kramer I-PER
was O
personally O
charged O
with O
liquidating O
the O
Hungarian B-LOC
transports B-TER
. O

A O
total O
of O
800,000 O
Jews B-TER
came O
from O
Hungary B-LOC
, O
115,000 O
of O
whom O
were O
sent O
to O
the O
camp B-LOC
, O
most O
of O
them O
women B-TER
. O

After O
the O
transports B-TER
from O
Hungary B-LOC
, O
in O
August O
several O
transports B-TER
arrived O
from O
Lodz B-LOC
, O
totaling O
about O
70,000 O
people B-TER
. O

Roughly O
9,000 O
of O
them O
were O
sent O
to O
the O
camp B-LOC
. O

At O
about O
the O
same O
time O
, O
7,000 O
women B-TER
arrived O
from O
other O
Polish B-LOC
labor B-TER
camps I-TER
and O
from O
Lublin B-LOC
. O

A O
transport B-TER
arrived O
with O
about O
5,000 O
non O
- O
Jewish O
people B-TER
, O
among O
them O
around O
300 O
young O
, O
healthy O
, O
Jewish O
women B-TER
and O
girls B-TER
from O
the O
Lublin B-LOC
labor B-TER
camp I-TER
. O

These O
women B-TER
were O
sent O
to O
the O
quarantine B-TER
camp B-LOC
, O
and O
3 O
days O
later O
were O
sent O
from O
there O
to O
the O
crematorium B-TER
to O
be O
gassed B-TER
. O

They O
fought O
back O
, O
but O
were O
quickly O
subdued O
. O

They O
then O
asked O
to O
be O
given O
more O
gas B-TER
, O
and O
their O
wish O
was O
granted O
. O

It O
’s O
unclear O
why O
these O
young O
, O
fit O
to O
work B-TER
women B-TER
were O
gassed B-TER
. O

Before O
the O
arrival O
of O
the O
Hungarian B-LOC
transports B-TER
, O
a O
transport B-TER
from I-TER
Theresienstadt I-TER
arrived O
in O
the O
Czech B-TER
family I-TER
camp I-TER
in O
May O
1944 O
, O
again O
without O
going O
through O
the O
selection B-TER
process I-TER
. O

Later O
, O
those O
able O
to O
work B-TER
were O
sent O
away O
. O

In O
the O
fall O
of O
1944 O
, O
many O
transports B-TER
from I-TER
Theresienstadt I-TER
arrived O
, O
totalling O
20,000 O
people B-TER
. O

These O
transports B-TER
were O
n’t O
sent O
to O
the O
family B-TER
camp I-TER
like O
the O
previous O
ones O
from O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
, O
but O
went O
through O
the O
selection B-TER
process I-TER
on O
the O
ramp O
. O

The O
number O
of O
the O
people B-TER
selected B-TER
is O
unknown O
, O
but O
it O
can O
be O
assumed O
that O
no O
more O
than O
25 O
% O
of O
the O
individual O
transports B-TER
were O
sent O
to O
the O
camp B-LOC
. O

On O
January O
24th O
, O
1945 O
, O
a O
sauna O
was O
to O
be O
prepared O
for O
the O
rest O
of O
the O
inhabitants B-TER
from O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
. O

Since O
all O
of O
the O
mothers B-TER
who O
had O
their O
children B-TER
with O
them O
from O
the O
Theresienstadt B-TER
transports I-TER
– O
like O
all O
the O
others O
– O
were O
gassed B-TER
, O
sometimes O
the O
mothers B-TER
were O
advised O
to O
give O
their O
children B-TER
to O
older O
women B-TER
. O

There O
were O
even O
cases O
of O
children B-TER
being O
violently O
torn O
away O
from O
their O
mothers B-TER
. O

Only O
rarely O
did O
a O
mother B-TER
know O
what O
awaited O
her O
and O
still O
handed O
over O
her O
child B-TER
. O

There O
were O
some O
cases O
of O
children B-TER
who O
were O
more O
mature O
and O
understood O
the O
situation O
, O
who O
stated O
that O
they O
were O
orphans B-TER
and O
thus O
saved O
their O
parents O
. O

If O
a O
smaller O
transport B-TER
– O
under O
50 O
people B-TER
– O
arrived O
, O
its O
occupants O
were O
n’t O
taken O
to O
be O
gassed B-TER
, O
but O
were O
killed B-TER
with O
a O
shot O
to O
the O
back O
of O
the O
head O
. O

This O
was O
done O
with O
a O
nail O
gun O
and O
then O
the O
corpses B-TER
were O
burned O
. O

This O
was O
also O
done O
in O
the O
crematoria B-TER
. O

These O
executions B-TER
were O
often O
carried O
out O
by O
SS B-TER
men I-TER
: O
Moll B-PER
and O
a O
certain O
Unterschaarführer B-TER
nicknamed O
Mojše O
Borek O
. O

People B-TER
who O
were O
sentenced O
to O
death B-TER
were O
led O
to O
their O
executions B-TER
individually O
by O
a O
special O
commando O
of O
12 O
prisoners B-TER
called O
shooters O
. O

The O
corpses B-TER
were O
then O
dragged O
away O
, O
and O
so O
the O
next O
people B-TER
in O
line O
did O
n’t O
know O
what O
was O
happening O
, O
although O
blood O
could O
be O
seen O
. O

After O
the O
transports B-TER
from I-TER
Theresienstadt I-TER
came O
the O
transports B-TER
from I-TER
Slovakia I-TER
, O
roughly O
10,000 O
people B-TER
. O

They O
were O
put O
through O
the O
usual O
selection B-TER
process I-TER
. O

On O
December O
10th O
, O
1944 O
, O
Crematoria B-TER
I O
and O
II O
and O
Bunker B-TER
V I-TER
began O
to O
be O
torn O
down O
. O

The O
whole O
camp B-LOC
was O
mobilized O
and O
made O
to O
perform O
this O
work B-TER
under O
the O
supervision O
of O
several O
SS B-TER
men I-TER
. O

After O
this O
date O
, O
only O
very O
small O
transports B-TER
arrived O
. O

Gassing B-TER
stopped O
altogether O
. O

The O
crematoria B-TER
gas B-TER
chambers I-TER
were O
blown O
up O
on O
January O
7th O
, O
1945 O
, O
several O
hours O
before O
the O
camp B-LOC
was O
evacuated B-TER
. O

Crematorium B-TER
IV O
remained O
standing O
. O

During O
this O
whole O
time O
, O
smaller O
and O
larger O
transports B-TER
continued O
to O
arrive O
from O
all O
over O
Europe O
. O

Once O
, O
3 O
Jews B-TER
from O
Tunisia B-LOC
, O
Corfu B-LOC
, O
and O
Rhodes B-LOC
, O
and O
a O
Jewish O
American B-LOC
navy O
soldier B-TER
arrived O
by O
airplane O
. O

Later O
, O
they O
were O
gassed B-TER
with O
a O
group O
of O
pregnant B-TER
women B-TER
. O

During O
Passover B-TER
43 O
, O
2 O
Rabbis B-TER
who O
had O
privileged O
positions O
arrived O
from O
Thessaloniki B-LOC
. O

They O
were O
allowed O
to O
keep O
their O
clothes B-TER
, O
their O
hair O
and O
beards O
were O
n’t O
cut O
, O
they O
did O
n’t O
have O
to O
work B-TER
, O
they O
were O
often O
photographed O
, O
and O
had O
to O
write O
a O
letter B-TER
stating O
that O
they O
were O
treated O
well O
and O
that O
they O
were O
performing O
their O
religious O
functions O
. O

This O
comedy O
did O
n’t O
last O
long O
. O

They O
were O
sent O
to O
the O
gas B-TER
chambers I-TER
. O

In O
the O
fall O
of O
1944 O
, O
twins O
, O
midgets O
, O
and O
people B-TER
with O
other O
physical B-TER
disabilities I-TER
were O
selected B-TER
from O
the O
Hungarian B-LOC
, O
Theresienstadt B-TER
, O
and O
Slovak B-TER
transports I-TER
and O
sent O
to O
the O
Krankenbau B-TER
in O
order O
to O
be O
experimented B-TER
upon O
. O

From O
1942 O
to O
1944 O
, O
the O
Lagerführers B-TER
in O
Birkenau B-LOC
were O
: O
Obersturmführer B-TER
Schwarzhuber B-PER
, O
who O
was O
replaced O
for O
a O
short O
time O
by O
Obersturmführer B-TER
Thumann B-PER
, O
then O
Obersturmführer B-TER
Krause B-PER
. O

Of O
the O
Lagerältestes O
from O
B B-LOC
I I-LOC
a I-LOC
and O
B B-LOC
I I-LOC
b I-LOC
, O
we O
mention O
additionally O
the O
Polish B-TER
woman I-TER
Stenia B-PER
( O
currently O
a O
defendant O
in O
the O
Lüneburg B-LOC
trial B-TER
) O
and O
the O
Slovak B-TER
woman I-TER
Ila B-PER
Klein I-PER
from O
Bardejov B-LOC
, O
both O
of O
whom O
are O
responsible O
for O
the O
deaths B-TER
of O
a O
countless O
number O
of O
women B-TER
. O

The O
underground B-TER
movement I-TER
in O
the O
camp B-LOC
began O
in O
May O
1943 O
in O
the O
sauna O
in O
the O
old O
men B-TER
’s I-TER
camp I-TER
. O

One O
Polish B-TER
Jew I-TER
( O
Fuchs B-PER
) O
and O
2 O
Jews B-TER
from O
France B-LOC
( O
Stein B-PER
and O
Handelsmann B-PER
) O
first O
agreed O
to O
mutually O
help O
illegal B-TER
workers O
. O

Those O
who O
worked B-TER
in O
the O
so O
- O
called O
better O
commandos O
agreed O
to O
help O
their O
comrades O
. O

The O
movement B-TER
did O
not O
have O
a O
clear O
ideology O
. O

It O
was O
an O
underground B-TER
liberation I-TER
movement I-TER
. O

The O
organization B-TER
could O
exist O
because O
at O
the O
time O
people B-TER
could O
move O
around O
the O
camp B-LOC
with O
greater O
freedom O
than O
before O
( O
prisoners B-TER
could O
meet O
after O
work B-TER
, O
the O
death B-TER
penalty O
was O
banned O
, O
etc O
. O

) O
Their O
membership B-TER
was O
small O
because O
they O
only O
accepted O
people B-TER
who O
were O
known O
to O
have O
performed O
illegal B-TER
work I-TER
before O
arriving O
in O
the O
camp B-LOC
. O

Later O
, O
the O
organization B-TER
also O
contained O
women B-TER
, O
mainly O
French B-LOC
and O
Polish B-LOC
. O

In O
terms O
of O
nationality O
, O
its O
members O
were O
mainly O
Polish B-TER
and O
French B-LOC
Jews B-TER
, O
there O
were O
also O
several O
Czech B-TER
Jews I-TER
, O
several O
Jewish O
women B-TER
, O
and O
one O
German B-TER
who O
was O
not O
a O
Jew O
. O

When O
the O
Hungarian B-LOC
transports B-TER
began O
to O
arrive O
, O
gassing B-TER
was O
supposed O
to O
cease O
and O
so O
we O
decided O
to O
procure O
explosives O
and O
weapons O
. O

The O
women B-TER
who O
worked B-TER
in O
the O
Union O
commando O
, O
Auschwitz B-LOC
I I-LOC
( O
a O
munitions O
factory O
) O
, O
acquired O
dynamite O
in O
small O
doses O
. O

The O
dynamite O
was O
used O
to O
make O
small O
handmade O
grenades O
in O
Crematorium B-TER
I. O
With O
the O
help O
of O
Russian B-TER
prisoners B-TER
, O
we O
managed O
to O
acquire O
4 O
revolvers O
. O

One O
Belgian B-LOC
Jew B-TER
got O
a O
machine O
gun O
with O
the O
help O
of O
the O
Russians B-TER
. O

The O
committee O
that O
orchestrated O
the O
uprising B-TER
was O
composed O
of O
Alexandre B-PER
Lazar I-PER
( O
France B-LOC
) O
and O
two O
Polish B-TER
Jews I-TER
, O
David O
and O
Minko O
, O
who O
fought O
in O
the O
Spanish B-LOC
Civil O
War B-TER
. O

To O
establish O
contact O
with O
the O
outside O
world O
, O
the O
Pole B-TER
Kostek B-PER
was O
sent O
to O
the O
join O
the O
partisans B-TER
in O
the O
area O
. O

We O
soon O
received O
an O
order O
from O
the O
outside O
that O
we O
should O
n’t O
start O
anything O
without O
outside O
help O
. O

Nevertheless O
, O
we O
continued O
organizing B-TER
and O
creating O
cells B-TER
. O

The O
movement B-TER
was O
rather O
strong O
at O
the O
time O
. O

For O
example O
, O
in O
the O
Effektenlager O
110 O
people B-TER
were O
part O
of O
the O
movement B-TER
. O

We O
were O
never O
betrayed O
. O

We O
got O
in O
touch O
with O
the O
Russians B-TER
and O
began O
planning O
an O
uprising B-TER
. O

But O
the O
Russians B-TER
were O
also O
of O
the O
opinion O
that O
we O
should O
n’t O
prepare O
anything O
more O
without O
help O
from O
the O
outside O
. O

On O
7 O
. O

10 O
. O

1944 O
, O
at O
1 O
in O
the O
afternoon O
, O
300 O
men B-TER
from O
the O
special B-TER
commando I-TER
were O
to O
be O
gassed B-TER
. O

They O
attacked O
Crematorium B-TER
III O
, O
threw O
dynamite O
grenades O
into O
the O
fire O
, O
and O
crematorium B-TER
III O
caught O
fire O
was O
reduced O
to O
ashes O
. O

The O
SS B-TER
, O
headed O
by O
Hauptsturmführer B-TER
Hahn B-PER
, O
who O
was O
personally O
armed O
with O
a O
rifle O
, O
arrived O
at O
the O
scene O
. O

They O
killed B-TER
378 O
men B-TER
. O

Half O
an O
hour O
later O
, O
the O
Sonderkommando B-TER
of O
Crematorium B-TER
I O
killed B-TER
the O
head O
capo B-TER
and O
threw O
him O
into O
the O
fire O
. O

Then O
, O
they O
cut O
the O
wires O
, O
shouted O
: O
The O
Russians O
are O
here O
! O
and O
ran O
. O

The O
SS B-TER
surrounded O
the O
area O
and O
all O
of O
them O
were O
shot B-TER
. O

All O
in O
all O
, O
455 O
men B-TER
were O
killed B-TER
that O
day O
. O

The O
whole O
uprising B-TER
was O
spearheaded O
by O
a O
special B-TER
commando I-TER
, O
but O
the O
illegal B-TER
organization O
did O
n’t O
participate O
in O
it O
because O
it O
did O
n’t O
get O
an O
order O
from O
the O
outside O
. O

On O
January O
17th O
, O
1945 O
, O
the O
camp B-LOC
was O
finally O
liquidated O
. O

At O
the O
time O
, O
it O
still O
had O
6,000 O
people B-TER
in O
it O
. O

On O
January O
18th O
, O
it O
was O
completely O
liquidated O
. O

Only O
the O
sick B-TER
from O
Camp B-LOC
B I-LOC
II I-LOC
f I-LOC
remained O
. O

Dr. O
Robert B-PER
Weinberger I-PER
Statement O
written O
up O
by O
: O
Dr. O
Robert B-PER
Weinberger I-PER
and O
Dr. O
Erich B-PER
Nasch I-PER
during O
his O
visit O
to O
Zeisheim B-LOC
near O
Frankfurt B-LOC
. O

