In O
Prague B-LOC
, O
24 O
. O

VIII O
. O

1921 O
Statement O
Alex B-PER
. I-PER

Schmiedt I-PER
, O
born O
27 O
. O

I. O
1921 O
, O
former O
prisoner B-TER
of O
the O
conc B-TER
. I-TER

camps I-TER
Kaufering B-LOC
III O
, O
Türkheim B-LOC
, O
and O
Dachau B-LOC
. O

Praha B-LOC
II I-LOC
. I-LOC

, O
Biskupská B-LOC
5 O
, O
Jewish O
nationality O
, O
profession O
clerk O
. O

From O
July O
1942 O
to O
the O
end O
of O
September O
1944 O
I O
was O
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
. O

I O
went O
on O
the O
first O
of O
the O
labor B-TER
transports B-TER
to I-TER
Auschwitz B-LOC
, O
where O
I O
spent O
5 O
days O
. O

On O
October O
5th O
, O
we O
were O
stuffed O
into O
cattle B-TER
cars I-TER
and O
went O
through O
Olomouc B-LOC
, O
Vienna B-LOC
, O
and O
Salzburg B-LOC
to O
Kaufering B-LOC
. O

The O
journey O
took O
3 O
days O
and O
we O
had O
a O
1½ O
kg O
loaf O
of O
bread B-TER
, O
10 O
dkg O
of O
margarine B-TER
and O
10 O
dkg O
of O
salami B-TER
. O

But O
we O
were O
happy O
to O
be O
leaving O
terrible O
Auschwitz B-LOC
behind O
. O

At O
the O
Kaufering B-LOC
train O
station O
, O
our O
transport B-TER
( O
about O
1,500 O
men B-TER
from O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
) O
was O
divided O
and O
I O
arrived O
together O
with O
about O
500 O
men B-TER
to O
3rd O
camp O
. O

The O
first O
2 O
- O
3 O
weeks O
it O
was O
bearable O
. O

There O
was O
n’t O
a O
lot O
of O
food B-TER
, O
but O
we O
still O
had O
a O
certain O
amount O
of O
bodily O
strength O
, O
and O
therefore O
we O
were O
n’t O
that O
starving B-TER
. O

But O
with O
the O
increasingly O
cold O
weather O
the O
food B-TER
rations O
got O
smaller O
and O
smaller O
and O
in O
November O
our O
first O
friend O
, O
Meir B-PER
Lindenbaum I-PER
, O
died B-TER
. O

After O
that O
, O
the O
chain O
of O
illnesses B-TER
, O
misery O
, O
and O
death B-TER
was O
never O
broken O
. O

The O
camp B-TER
contained O
about O
1,800 O
men B-TER
, O
mostly O
Hungarian B-TER
Jews O
, O
and O
you O
were O
basically O
lost O
if O
you O
could O
n’t O
speak O
Hungarian O
. O

We O
lived B-TER
in O
the O
so O
- O
called O
Erdbunker O
– O
long O
, O
underground O
buildings B-TER
with O
a O
single O
window O
, O
two O
rows O
of O
boards O
for O
sleeping O
, O
and O
a O
stove O
and O
a O
chimney O
in O
the O
middle O
. O

Every O
prisoner B-TER
had O
a O
blanket O
, O
a O
bowl O
, O
and O
a O
spoon O
. O

I O
worked B-TER
in O
the O
so O
- O
called O
Holzman O
commando B-TER
digging O
in O
the O
forest O
. O

After O
several O
weeks O
of O
work B-TER
, O
most O
of O
my O
friends O
had O
feet O
covered O
in O
sores O
and O
frostbite O
, O
and O
could O
barely O
drag O
themselves O
to O
their O
workplace B-TER
. O

This O
was O
the O
construction O
of O
an O
enormous O
munitions O
plant B-TER
, O
in O
fact O
of O
a O
whole O
town O
hidden O
in O
the O
woods O
. O

The O
forest O
was O
about O
2 O
km O
away O
from O
our O
camp B-TER
. O

In O
the O
first O
few O
months O
, O
one O
had O
to O
work B-TER
even O
if O
one O
had O
open O
, O
festering O
sores O
and O
a O
high O
fever B-TER
. O

Every O
day O
they O
would O
bring O
back O
from O
the O
commandos B-TER
the O
bodies B-TER
of O
friends O
who O
had O
died B-TER
while O
working B-TER
. O

Later O
, O
the O
sick B-TER
people I-TER
’s O
situation O
improved O
slightly O
, O
but O
the O
food B-TER
got O
worse O
. O

In O
the O
beginning O
, O
we O
were O
given O
about O
37 O
dkg O
of O
bread B-TER
per O
day O
, O
Zulags O
( O
2 O
dkg O
of O
margarine B-TER
, O
or O
a O
slice O
of O
salami B-TER
, O
a O
piece O
of O
cheese B-TER
, O
a O
pinch O
of O
butter B-TER
, O
a O
spoonful O
of O
marmalade B-TER
or O
synthetic O
honey B-TER
) O
, O
and O
a O
liter O
of O
watery O
soup B-TER
in O
the O
evening O
. O

Workers B-TER
were O
also O
given O
about O
20 O
dkg O
of O
bread B-TER
with O
margarine B-TER
and O
warm O
water O
( O
soup B-TER
) O
at O
noon O
at O
the O
place O
where O
we O
worked B-TER
. O

In O
the O
end O
, O
the O
extra O
food B-TER
for O
workers B-TER
was O
cut O
and O
the O
portion O
of O
bread B-TER
fluctuated O
between O
15 O
- O
25 O
dkg O
per O
day O
. O

The O
workday O
went O
like O
this O
: O
alarm O
at O
4:45 O
in O
the O
morning O
, O
roll B-TER
call I-TER
at O
5:30 O
in O
the O
morning O
, O
7:00 O
leave O
for O
work B-TER
, O
at O
6:00 O
in O
the O
evening O
return O
from O
the O
commando B-TER
, O
roll B-TER
call I-TER
, O
get O
in O
line O
in O
front O
of O
the O
kitchen O
. O

Lights O
were O
turned O
off O
in O
the O
bunkers O
at O
9:00 O
at O
night O
. O

This O
was O
the O
schedule O
and O
the O
food B-TER
was O
a O
regular O
häftling O
. O

The O
camp B-TER
’s O
block O
staff O
, O
medical B-TER
staff O
, O
and O
others O
had O
significant O
privileges O
in O
terms O
of O
the O
food B-TER
they O
were O
given O
, O
as O
well O
as O
at O
their O
work B-TER
, O
lodgings B-TER
, O
and O
the O
clothes B-TER
they O
received O
. O

The O
Lägerältester O
, O
his O
representative O
, O
and O
the O
leading O
capos B-TER
were O
aryans O
. O

They O
were O
housed B-TER
separately O
and O
the O
kitchens O
prepared O
food O
especially O
for O
them O
. O

Like O
everywhere O
else O
, O
people O
were O
afraid O
of O
infectious B-TER
diseases B-TER
, O
especially O
spotted O
typhus B-TER
. O

The O
gravely O
ill B-TER
were O
transported O
to O
the O
Krankenlager O
. O

All O
of O
us O
knew O
that O
there O
was O
very O
little O
hope O
of O
returning O
from O
there O
. O

Most O
of O
the O
sick B-TER
were O
from O
the O
Moll O
commando B-TER
, O
where O
working B-TER
conditions O
were O
unbearable O
. O

After O
a O
commute O
of O
1½ O
hours O
, O
we O
worked B-TER
for O
12 O
hours O
with O
a O
half O
- O
hour O
break O
and O
then O
once O
again O
the O
1½ O
hour O
long O
commute O
back O
home O
. O

Work B-TER
was O
hard O
( O
carrying O
bags O
of O
cement O
, O
laying O
cement O
, O
etc O
. O

) O
and O
the O
only O
food B-TER
we O
received O
was O
a O
bowl O
of O
cold O
tea O
made O
from O
grass O
. O

The O
strongest O
of O
us O
did O
n’t O
last O
longer O
than O
3 O
weeks O
. O

Many O
of O
our O
best O
people B-TER
, O
mainly O
from O
the O
1st B-LOC
camp I-LOC
, O
lost O
their O
lives O
there O
. O

Out O
of O
the O
1,500 O
men B-TER
who O
came O
to O
the O
Kaufering B-LOC
camps B-TER
, O
in O
my O
opinion O
, O
40 O
- O
50 O
returned O
. O

On O
March O
8th O
, O
a O
transport O
left O
from O
the O
3rd B-LOC
camp I-LOC
to O
Türkheim B-LOC
( O
5th B-LOC
camp I-LOC
) O
Kaufering O
- O
Lager O
V O
was O
Utting O
, O
Lager O
VI O
was O
Türkheim O
. O

I O
was O
also O
slated O
to O
be O
transported O
and O
I O
was O
happy O
because O
I O
told O
myself O
that O
nowhere O
could O
be O
worse O
than O
Kaufering B-LOC
. O

For O
the O
first O
few O
days O
I O
regretted O
it O
because O
we O
were O
so O
hungry B-TER
, O
but O
the O
conditions B-TER
soon O
improved O
and O
during O
the O
last O
weeks O
we O
received O
peeled O
potatoes B-TER
every O
day O
– O
the O
most O
ideal O
camp B-TER
food B-TER
, O
not O
only O
because O
it O
filled O
one O
up O
better O
than O
soup B-TER
, O
but O
it O
contained O
on O
the O
side O
potato B-TER
peels I-TER
, O
whole O
bowls O
of O
which O
, O
with O
a O
bit O
of O
luck O
and O
impertinence O
, O
could O
sometimes O
be O
collected O
from O
the O
capitalists O
. O

I O
worked B-TER
during O
the O
the O
first O
three O
weeks O
in O
Türkheim B-LOC
– O
unlike O
in O
other O
camps B-TER
, O
we O
were O
guarded O
only O
by O
Death O
’s O
Headers O
, O
and O
, O
when O
we O
were O
lucky O
, O
Czechs O
, O
of O
whom O
there O
were O
many O
. O

Then O
I O
became O
so O
weak O
and O
exhausted O
that O
the O
doctor B-TER
pronounced O
me O
a O
sick O
person O
and O
sent O
me O
to O
the O
krankenblock O
. O

An O
epidemic O
of O
spotted O
typhus B-TER
broke O
out O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
at O
the O
end O
of O
March O
. O

The O
number O
of O
those O
infected B-TER
rose O
every O
day O
at O
an O
alarming O
rate O
and O
in O
the O
end O
the O
doctors B-TER
stopped O
doing O
check O
- O
ups O
and O
marched O
whoever O
had O
a O
fever O
of O
over O
38 O
degrees O
straight O
to O
the O
typhus B-TER
ward O
. O

I O
was O
suffering O
from O
horrible O
diarrhea B-TER
, O
and O
since O
I O
also O
had O
a O
fever B-TER
, O
I O
, O
too O
, O
was O
placed O
among O
the O
typhus O
sufferers O
. O

Protests O
and O
screams O
did O
n’t O
help O
. O

I O
could O
n’t O
escape O
from O
typhus B-TER
in O
any O
case O
. O

There O
was O
nothing O
one O
could O
do O
about O
the O
everpresent O
lice B-TER
. O

I O
lay O
for O
10 O
days O
with O
a O
high O
fever B-TER
and O
began O
to O
get O
better O
right O
when O
the O
order O
to O
evacuate B-TER
the O
camp B-TER
was O
issued O
. O

Whoever O
could O
walk O
went O
on O
foot O
; O
we O
, O
the O
sick B-TER
, O
were O
driven O
by O
car O
to O
Landsberg B-LOC
( I-LOC
1st I-LOC
camp I-LOC
) I-LOC
. O

I O
spent O
two O
horrible O
days O
there O
in O
indescribable O
squalor O
and O
with O
barely O
any O
food B-TER
( O
at O
the O
time O
I O
weighed O
about O
45 O
kg O
, O
my O
height O
being O
187 O
cm O
) O
. O

Finally O
, O
this O
camp B-TER
, O
too O
, O
was O
evacuated B-TER
, O
and O
although O
I O
could O
barely O
stand O
, O
I O
walked O
, O
or O
rather O
crawled O
, O
to O
the O
train O
station O
near O
Holzmann O
, O
which O
was O
situated O
about O
3 O
kilometers O
away O
. O

There O
, O
they O
packed O
us O
onto O
cattle B-TER
cars I-TER
, O
and O
with O
the O
last O
of O
my O
strength O
I O
managed O
to O
get O
a O
spot O
in O
a O
covered O
car O
because O
I O
was O
afraid O
of O
the O
rain O
of O
and O
air B-TER
strikes I-TER
. O

My O
fears O
were O
justified O
. O

We O
traveled O
a O
distance O
of O
30 O
km O
from O
Landsberg B-LOC
to O
Dachau B-LOC
for O
two O
days O
and O
two O
nights O
. O

On O
the O
last O
day O
and O
night O
it O
rained O
hard O
and O
constantly O
. O

We O
also O
experienced O
several O
serious O
air B-TER
strikes I-TER
– O
American B-TER
pilots O
probably O
thought O
we O
were O
a O
military O
transport O
. O

Many O
ran B-TER
away I-TER
; O
I O
was O
too O
weak O
and O
did O
n’t O
move O
from O
the O
car O
even O
when O
the O
shooting O
was O
at O
its O
peak O
. O

About O
3,000 O
of O
us O
left O
Landsberg B-LOC
and O
only O
about O
1,000 O
of O
us O
made O
it O
to O
Dachau B-LOC
alive O
. O

About O
200 O
ran B-TER
away I-TER
during O
the O
journey O
. O

These O
figures O
are O
not O
exact O
and O
are O
just O
my O
own O
estimate O
. O

In O
Dachau B-LOC
, O
we O
went O
through O
the O
disinfection O
process O
during O
the O
night O
of O
April O
28th O
, O
and O
then O
I O
slept O
like O
the O
dead O
for O
15 O
hours O
. O

I O
slept O
through O
the O
constant O
shelling O
of O
the O
town O
all O
through O
the O
night O
and O
even O
when O
the O
fight O
reached O
the O
camp B-TER
the O
following O
morning O
. O

Prisoners B-TER
participated O
in O
the O
fighting O
, O
and O
by O
the O
afternoon O
the O
U.S. B-LOC
flag O
flew O
over O
the O
main O
guard O
tower O
. O

Our O
liberators B-TER
arrived O
not O
a O
moment O
too O
soon O
, O
for O
we O
later O
learned O
that O
Himmler B-PER
had O
issued O
a O
special O
order O
to O
shoot B-TER
all O
of O
the O
Dachau B-LOC
prisoners B-TER
on O
the O
evening O
of O
April O
29th O
. O

Alex B-PER
. I-PER

Schmiedt I-PER
Signature O
of O
witnesses O
: O
Marta B-PER
Kratková I-PER
Robert B-PER
Weinberger I-PER
Documentation B-TER
campaign I-TER
: O
Zeev B-PER
Scheck I-PER
21 O
. O

VIII O
. O

1945 O
On O
behalf O
of O
the O
archive O
: O
Alex B-PER
Schmiedt I-PER
