- O
1 O
- O
Remarks O
by O
Dr. B-PER
Ball I-PER
- I-PER
Kaduri I-PER
A O
testimony B-TER
by O
Ernestine B-PER
Rosengarten I-PER
, O
Afula B-LOC
The O
Fate O
of O
the O
Jews O
in O
Tarasivka O
Beyond O
the O
River O
Bug O
I O
present O
: O
1/ O
Witness B-TER
report I-TER
by O
E. B-PER
Rosengarten I-PER
in O
the O
original O
and O
copies O
in O
German B-LOC
2/ O
the O
Hebrew O
letter B-TER
by O
E. B-PER
R. I-PER
to O
Yad B-ORG
Vashem I-ORG
from O
November O
10 O
, O
1955 O
in O
the O
original O
and O
copies O
with O
attachment O
as O
well O
as O
a O
photocopy O
( O
letter B-TER
of O
the O
military B-ORG
in O
Ukrainian B-LOC
language O
of O
31 O
October O
31 O
, O
1944 O
) O
3/ O
German B-LOC
translation O
of O
the O
above O
letter B-TER
with O
attachment O
4/ O
Copies O
of O
the O
Romanian B-LOC
letter B-TER
, O
prepared O
by O
Heinz B-PER
Rosengarten I-PER
’s I-PER
brother B-PER
. O

The O
testimony B-TER
of O
Ernestine B-PER
Rosengarten I-PER
is O
of O
particular O
relevance O
, O
because O
it O
is O
one O
of O
the O
few O
reports B-TER
about O
a O
camp O
beyond O
the O
river O
Bug O
, O
and O
apart O
from O
that O
because O
it O
confirms O
and O
complements O
another O
report B-TER
. O

So O
far O
it O
was O
only O
known O
from O
the O
first O
letter B-TER
of O
Mrs. B-PER
Rosengarten I-PER
from O
November O
10 O
, O
1955 O
that O
there O
is O
a O
book B-TER
by O
Arnold B-PER
Daghani I-PER
( O
Korn O
) O
, O
which O
deals O
with O
the O
camp B-LOC
Tarasivka I-LOC
and O
also O
contains O
sections O
about O
the O
son B-PER
of O
Mrs. B-PER
Rosengarten I-PER
. O

We O
had O
tried O
in O
vain O
so O
far O
to O
obtain O
it O
for O
the O
library B-TER
, O
because O
Dr. B-PER
Weinstein I-PER
, O
who O
is O
mentioned O
in O
the O
letter B-TER
as O
the O
owner O
of O
a O
Romanian B-LOC
copy O
, O
once O
lent O
it O
to O
someone O
and O
does O
not O
remember O
to O
whom O
and O
did O
not O
get O
it O
back O
. O

Our O
library B-TER
has O
so O
far O
also O
tried O
in O
vain O
to O
obtain O
an O
English B-LOC
copy O
through O
the O
Jewish B-ORG
World I-ORG
Congress I-ORG
, O
which O
is O
said O
to O
have O
helped O
to O
publish O
an O
English B-LOC
edition O
at O
that O
time O
in O
Romania B-LOC
. O

– O
As O
a O
result O
, O
we O
then O
put O
a O
search O
note O
in O
the O
newspaper B-TER
of O
the O
Bukovina B-LOC
Jews O
in O
Israel B-LOC
Die O
Stimme O
, O
and O
subsequently O
Dr. B-PER
Fischer I-PER
, O
who O
works O
at O
the O
URO B-ORG
in O
Tel B-LOC
Aviv I-LOC
, O
lent O
a O
Romanian B-LOC
copy O
to O
the O
library B-TER
. O

However O
, O
- O
2 O
- O
I O
myself O
have O
not O
yet O
had O
the O
opportunity O
to O
take O
note O
of O
the O
content O
, O
as O
it O
has O
been O
lent O
for O
scientific O
work O
. O

– O
Furthermore O
, O
as O
a O
result O
of O
my O
trip O
to O
Europe B-LOC
I O
became O
aware O
of O
another O
report B-TER
on O
the O
Tarasivka B-LOC
camp I-LOC
, O
which O
is O
located O
at O
the O
Wiener B-ORG
Library I-ORG
and O
whose O
author O
is O
a O
Mr. O
Segall B-PER
probably O
Nathan O
Segall O
, O
murdered O
in O
Tarasivka O
1943 O
, O
who O
wrote O
this O
report B-TER
in O
Mogilev B-LOC
. O

An O
accompanying O
report B-TER
by O
another O
author O
, O
who O
is O
not O
mentioned O
, O
shows O
that O
Segall B-PER
wrote O
this O
report B-TER
in O
Mogilev B-LOC
, O
whereto O
he O
traveled O
from O
Tarasivka B-LOC
in O
the O
company O
of O
an O
SS B-ORG
man O
. O

The O
SS B-ORG
man O
then O
continued O
to O
Bukovina B-LOC
and O
Romania B-LOC
to O
seek O
help B-TER
for O
the O
Jews O
in O
Tarasivka B-LOC
, O
and O
later O
Segall B-PER
returned O
there O
with O
the O
SS B-ORG
man O
, O
and O
, O
according O
to O
the O
accompanying O
report B-TER
, O
died O
there O
during O
the O
liquidation B-TER
of O
the O
camp B-LOC
on O
December O
13 O
, O
1943 O
. O

As O
I O
heard O
from O
the O
Wiener B-ORG
Library I-ORG
, O
the O
transmission O
of O
this O
Segall B-PER
report B-TER
to O
Yad B-ORG
Vashem I-ORG
with O
the O
next O
shipment O
of O
testimonies B-TER
is O
imminent O
. O

The O
name O
of O
the O
author O
of O
the O
accompanying O
report B-TER
is O
not O
given O
, O
and O
must O
not O
yet O
be O
given O
by O
the O
Wiener B-ORG
Library I-ORG
, O
because O
he O
himself O
intends O
to O
publish O
it O
. O

- O
It O
is O
now O
very O
interesting O
that O
this O
SS B-ORG
Lieutenant O
Elsässer B-PER
, O
who O
visited O
Chernivtsi B-LOC
according O
to O
the O
report B-TER
of O
Mrs. O
Rosengarten B-PER
and O
provided O
help B-TER
for O
the O
Jews O
in O
Tarasivka B-LOC
, O
is O
the O
same O
who O
had O
previously O
been O
in O
Mogilev B-LOC
and O
about O
whom O
the O
Wiener B-ORG
Library I-ORG
has O
the O
mentioned O
report B-TER
, O
because O
Mrs. O
Rosengarten B-PER
told O
me O
in O
the O
course O
of O
her O
testimony B-TER
that O
Elsässer B-PER
first O
went O
to O
Mogilev B-LOC
with O
a O
Jew O
named O
Segall B-PER
, O
but O
could O
not O
take O
him O
further O
, O
and O
then O
came O
to O
Chernivtsi B-LOC
alone O
with O
a O
sergeant O
. O

So O
one O
report B-TER
confirms O
the O
other O
! O
There O
are O
some O
more O
details O
to O
note O
about O
Mrs. O
Rosengarten B-PER
’s I-PER
statement B-TER
: O
the O
assumption O
of O
Mrs. O
Rosengarten B-PER
that O
Elsässer B-PER
is O
at O
the O
same O
time O
the O
head O
of O
the O
Todt B-ORG
organization I-ORG
and O
the O
camp B-LOC
- O
3 O
- O
is O
not O
very O
likely O
, O
because O
in O
general O
these O
functions O
were O
separate O
. O

On O
the O
other O
hand O
, O
the O
whole O
action O
of O
Elsässer B-PER
and O
his O
behavior O
is O
something O
unique O
. O

There O
is O
no O
other O
case O
known O
that O
a O
German B-LOC
SS B-ORG
man O
or O
officer O
undertook O
such O
a O
journey O
, O
which O
was O
apparently O
officially O
approved O
or O
at O
least O
permitted O
. O

According O
to O
the O
descriptions B-TER
of O
Mrs. O
R. B-PER
and O
also O
of O
Segall B-PER
he O
also O
seems O
to O
have O
really O
wanted O
to O
help B-TER
in O
the O
first O
place O
, O
and O
not O
to O
make O
money O
for O
the O
SS B-ORG
or O
to O
go O
raiding B-TER
. O

It O
would O
be O
worth O
considering O
whether O
one O
should O
try O
to O
determine O
if O
he O
survived O
the O
war B-TER
and O
to O
contact O
him O
. O

[ O
Signature O
:] O
Dr. B-PER
Ball I-PER
- I-PER
Kaduri I-PER
April O
1958 O
Dr. B-PER
Ball I-PER
- I-PER
Kaduri I-PER
- O
4 O
– O
The O
Fate O
of O
the O
Jews O
in O
the O
Tarasivka B-LOC
Camp I-LOC
Beyond O
the O
River O
Bug O
Testimony B-TER
of O
Mrs O
Ernestine B-PER
Rosengarten I-PER
in O
Afula B-LOC
, O
Shikun B-LOC
Owdei I-LOC
Solel I-LOC
Boneh I-LOC
, O
Mother B-TER
of O
the O
engineer O
Victor B-PER
Heinz I-PER
Rosengarten I-PER
, O
recorded O
in O
Afula B-LOC
7 O
April O
7 O
, O
1958 O
by O
Dr B-PER
Ball I-PER
- I-PER
Kaduri I-PER
First O
crossed O
out O
in O
the O
original O
, O
I O
present O
a O
Romanian B-LOC
copy O
and O
a O
German B-LOC
translation O
of O
a O
letter B-TER
from O
my O
son O
Victor B-PER
Heinz I-PER
from O
the O
Tarasivka B-LOC
camp I-LOC
dated O
September O
14 O
, O
1943 O
with O
a O
preliminary O
remark O
by O
myself O
. O

In O
my O
letter B-TER
of O
November O
10 O
, O
1955 O
to O
Yad B-ORG
Vashem I-ORG
, O
I O
already O
gave O
a O
brief O
account B-TER
of O
my O
son B-PER
’s I-PER
fate O
. O

In O
summary O
of O
this O
information O
and O
for O
further O
details O
, O
I O
report B-TER
: O
My O
son B-PER
and O
his O
wife B-TER
Anni B-PER
( I-PER
Hanna I-PER
) I-PER
were O
taken O
out O
of O
their O
home O
in O
Chernivtsi B-LOC
on O
June O
14 O
, O
1942 O
and O
taken O
to O
the O
camp B-LOC
Laidzin I-LOC
probably O
Ladyzhin O
in O
Transnistria B-LOC
. O

From O
there O
they O
were O
taken O
to O
work B-TER
across O
the O
river O
Bug B-LOC
. O

On O
the O
way O
they O
came O
through O
Bershad B-LOC
from O
there O
we O
received O
a O
postcard O
with O
a O
greeting O
. O

My O
son B-PER
was O
an O
excellent O
engineer O
, O
and O
beyond O
the O
river O
Bug B-LOC
, O
where O
they O
were O
probably O
in O
different O
camps B-TER
, O
at O
least O
in O
the O
Tarasivka B-LOC
camp I-LOC
in O
the O
end O
, O
he O
worked B-TER
for O
the O
Organisation B-ORG
Todt I-ORG
( O
as O
all O
other O
camp B-TER
inmates I-TER
did O
handwritten O
addition O
) O
. O

In O
the O
middle O
or O
end O
of O
October O
1943 O
, O
a O
senior O
lieutenant O
of O
the O
SS B-ORG
came O
to O
Chernivtsi B-LOC
with O
a O
sergeant O
from O
Tarasivka B-LOC
to O
collect O
donations O
for O
the O
Jews O
in O
Tarasivka B-LOC
. O

He O
lodged O
with O
the O
grammar O
school O
professor O
Schwarz B-PER
, O
the O
father B-TER
of O
my O
daughter B-PER
- I-PER
in I-PER
- I-PER
law I-PER
, O
he O
brought O
a O
general O
letter B-TER
( O
of O
the O
Jews O
in O
... O
crossed O
out O
in O
the O
original O
) O
from O
my O
son B-PER
to O
the O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
in O
Chernivtsi B-LOC
in O
which O
he O
asked O
for O
help B-TER
for O
all O
Jews O
in O
Tarasivka B-LOC
, O
and O
a O
second O
letter B-TER
from O
my O
son B-PER
to O
us O
. O

Everything O
I O
report B-TER
in O
the O
following O
is O
based O
on O
this O
lieutenant O
’s O
statements B-TER
. O

His O
name O
was O
Elsässer B-PER
, O
in O
civilian O
life O
he O
was O
a O
contractor O
and O
came O
from O
Cologne B-LOC
. O

He O
came O
at O
the O
instigation O
of O
the O
Jews B-TER
in O
the O
Tarasivka B-LOC
camp I-LOC
to O
fetch O
gifts O
for O
them O
. O

On O
his O
departure O
from O
- O
5 O
- O
Tarasivka B-LOC
with O
the O
sergeant O
he O
took O
two O
Jews O
with O
him O
, O
my O
son B-PER
and O
another O
one O
called O
Segall B-PER
. O

But O
my O
son B-PER
had O
to O
stay O
on O
the O
other O
side O
of O
the O
Bug B-LOC
and O
was O
not O
allowed O
to O
go O
any O
further O
. O

The O
other O
one O
, O
Segall B-PER
, O
accompanied O
him O
to O
Mogilev B-LOC
in O
Transnistria B-LOC
, O
where O
he O
also O
had O
to O
stay O
. O

The O
lieutenant O
and O
the O
sergeant O
continued O
to O
Chernivtsi B-LOC
Elsässer B-PER
was O
the O
leader O
of O
a O
group O
of O
the O
organization B-ORG
Todt I-ORG
, O
which O
was O
building O
roads O
in O
the O
German B-LOC
-controlled O
area O
beyond O
the O
Bug B-LOC
. O

Since O
he O
was O
powerful O
, O
I O
assume O
that O
he O
coincidentally O
was O
the O
leader O
of O
the O
camp B-LOC
Tarasivka I-LOC
, O
too O
. O

It O
was O
not O
only O
Jews B-TER
coming O
from O
Transnistria B-LOC
working B-TER
there O
but O
also O
two O
other O
groups O
, O
i.e. O
not O
only O
Bukovina B-LOC
Jews O
, O
but O
also O
Ukrainian B-LOC
Jews O
. O

Jews O
who O
came O
from O
Ukraine B-LOC
( O
Transnistria B-LOC
) O
, O
and O
Polish B-LOC
Jews O
. O

But O
in O
total O
there O
were O
only O
300 O
people O
. O

The O
conditions B-TER
in O
the O
camp B-LOC
can O
be O
seen O
from O
the O
enclosed O
letter B-TER
by O
my O
son B-PER
. O

Elsässer B-PER
brought O
a O
letter B-TER
from O
the O
Jews O
in O
T. B-LOC
to O
the O
congregation O
. O

in O
Chernivtsi B-LOC
, O
with O
a O
cry O
for O
help O
. O

He O
also O
brought O
a O
letter B-TER
from O
my O
son B-PER
, O
whose O
transcript O
I O
have O
handed O
over O
. O

My O
son B-PER
’s I-PER
letter B-TER
is O
written O
in O
Romanian B-LOC
. O

Since O
we O
only O
ever O
spoke O
and O
wrote O
German B-LOC
, O
so O
I O
can O
only O
assume O
that O
my O
son B-PER
did O
not O
want O
the O
German B-LOC
officer O
to O
read O
the O
letter B-TER
. O

The O
Jews O
of O
the O
community B-TER
of O
Chernivtsi B-LOC
behaved O
magnificently O
, O
although O
most O
of O
them O
were O
already O
impoverished B-TER
. O

They O
donated B-TER
food B-TER
, O
clothes B-TER
and O
shoes B-TER
in O
large O
amounts O
. O

They O
also O
gave O
Elsässer B-PER
a O
large O
shipment O
of O
champagne O
, O
ham B-TER
, O
bacon B-TER
, O
new O
shoes B-TER
and O
fur B-TER
coats I-TER
for O
the O
SS B-ORG
in O
the O
camp B-LOC
, O
so O
that O
the O
SS B-ORG
was O
satisfied O
and O
refrained O
from O
taking O
possession O
of O
things O
intended O
for O
the O
Jews O
. O

Overall O
, O
it O
was O
a O
shipment O
of O
4 O
- O
5 O
trucks O
. O

( O
us O
personally O
, O
El- B-PER
crossed O
out O
in O
the O
original O
) O
The O
jeweler O
Goldstein O
from O
Chernivtsi B-LOC
( O
whose O
famil B-TER
y O
was O
together O
with O
my O
son B-PER
) O
gave O
Elsässer B-PER
, O
among O
other O
innumerable O
gifts O
handwritten O
addition O
, O
- O
6 O
- O
( O
sässer B-PER
crossed O
out O
in O
the O
original O
) O
a O
golden O
watch O
for O
himself O
and O
other O
objects O
for O
his O
wife B-TER
and O
daughter B-TER
. O

From O
us O
personally O
, O
Elsässer B-PER
received O
valuable O
gifts O
, O
leather O
goods O
, O
jewelry O
, O
etc O
.. O
handwritten O
addition O
Elsässer B-PER
told B-TER
us O
further O
: O
My O
son B-PER
was O
his O
most O
outstanding O
worker B-TER
. O

When O
a O
difficult O
part O
of O
the O
technical O
work B-TER
was O
finished O
, O
a O
big O
party O
was O
celebrated O
. O

Elsässer B-PER
had O
succeeded O
in O
having O
my O
son B-PER
and O
daughter B-PER
- I-PER
in I-PER
- I-PER
law I-PER
invited O
. O

At O
the O
end O
of O
the O
festival O
he B-PER
and O
his O
wife B-PER
were O
sent O
back O
to O
the O
camp B-LOC
on O
a O
sleigh O
. O

Elsässer B-PER
gave O
the O
coachman O
the O
instruction O
: O
Go O
where O
Mr. O
Rosengarten O
wants O
you O
to O
go O
. O

Apparently O
he O
wanted O
to O
give O
him O
the O
opportunity O
to O
escape B-TER
back O
to O
Transnistria B-LOC
via O
the O
river B-LOC
Bug I-LOC
. O

But O
my O
son B-PER
did O
not O
take O
that O
chance O
. O

Because O
for O
every O
Jew O
who O
fled B-TER
, O
10 O
others O
were O
shot B-TER
. O

Elsässer B-PER
told O
us O
this O
, O
albeit O
not O
with O
these O
very O
words O
, O
and O
added O
: O
A O
Rosengarten O
does O
not O
do O
such O
a O
thing O
. O

My O
son B-PER
’s I-PER
letter B-TER
was O
dated O
September O
14 O
, O
1943 O
, O
but O
my O
statement O
in O
the O
preface O
to O
the O
letter B-TER
, O
namely O
that O
Elsässer B-PER
came O
to O
us O
in O
September O
, O
is O
inaccurate O
, O
he O
did O
n’t O
come O
until O
mid- O
October O
or O
late O
October O
. O

After O
he O
had O
travelled O
back O
with O
all O
this O
things O
, O
a O
short O
time O
later O
, O
a O
message O
came O
from O
Tarasivka B-LOC
to O
Chernivtsi B-LOC
, O
in O
a O
safe O
way O
, O
that O
the O
things O
had O
been O
received O
there O
. O

We O
always O
said O
later O
that O
they O
could O
not O
even O
have O
eaten O
the O
food B-TER
because O
the O
camp B-LOC
was O
liquidated O
on O
December O
13 O
. O

( O
if O
the O
date O
, O
which O
is O
mentioned O
in O
the O
later O
mentioned O
book B-TER
of O
Mr. O
Korn B-PER
, O
is O
correct O
handwritten O
addition O
) O
My O
daughter B-PER
- I-PER
in I-PER
- I-PER
law I-PER
once O
had O
a O
severe O
typhoid B-TER
fever I-TER
. O

My O
son B-PER
gave O
her O
the O
only O
coat B-TER
he O
still O
owned O
for O
covering O
. O

Sometime O
before O
that O
, O
a O
letter B-TER
from O
my O
son B-PER
had O
arrived O
, O
obviously O
in O
his O
own O
handwriting O
, O
which O
contained O
a O
sign O
of O
life O
from O
T. B-LOC
. O

The O
letter B-TER
was O
written O
on O
very O
good O
white O
stationery O
- O
7 O
- O
and O
sent O
in O
an O
equally O
good O
white O
envelope O
from O
a O
post O
office O
in O
Berlin B-LOC
, O
and O
addressed O
to O
his O
father B-PER
- I-PER
in I-PER
- I-PER
law I-PER
, O
with O
the O
outside O
address O
Mr. O
B. B-PER
Schwarz I-PER
, O
Prof. O
a. O
D O
.. O
This O
was O
a O
very O
unusual O
formulation O
in O
the O
style O
of O
the O
German B-LOC
of O
the O
Reich O
, O
and O
the O
letter O
was O
also O
written O
in O
this O
style O
. O

Apparently O
he O
had O
given O
it O
to O
an O
officer O
who O
went O
on O
vacation O
to O
Germany B-LOC
, O
and O
the O
letter O
should O
not O
be O
noticed O
in O
an O
inspection O
. O

Arnold B-PER
Korn I-PER
( O
Daghani O
) O
, O
the O
author O
of O
the O
book B-TER
Das O
Grab O
ist O
handwritten O
addition O
i O
m O
Garten O
der O
Kirschen O
( O
The O
grave O
is O
in O
the O
cherry O
- O
orchard O
) O
, O
which O
describes O
the O
Tarasivka B-LOC
camp I-LOC
, O
escaped B-TER
( O
on O
the O
occasion O
of O
a O
partisan B-TER
attack O
crossed O
out O
in O
the O
original O
) O
with O
his O
wife B-TER
handwritten O
addition O
a O
few O
days O
before O
the O
liquidation O
( O
with O
the O
partisans B-TER
crossed O
out O
in O
the O
original O
) O
, O
and O
as O
far O
as O
we O
know O
he O
now O
lives O
in O
Bucharest B-LOC
. O

He O
and O
a O
few O
others O
are O
the O
only O
ones O
rescued B-TER
from O
this O
camp O
. O

In O
his O
book B-TER
he O
also O
reports B-TER
quite O
extensively O
about O
my O
son B-PER
. O

Korn O
was O
a O
painter O
and O
graphic O
artist O
, O
his O
book B-TER
contains O
some O
drawings O
, O
too O
. O

A O
German B-LOC
officer O
was O
interested O
in O
his O
work O
and O
helped B-TER
him O
with O
the O
rescue B-TER
. O

On O
the O
occasion O
of O
a O
partisan B-TER
attack O
handwritten O
addition O
, O
among O
the O
rescued B-TER
was O
the O
Semmel O
family B-TER
who O
is O
said O
to O
be O
here O
in O
the O
country B-LOC
. O

Perhaps O
they O
could O
be O
found O
through O
an O
announcement O
in O
the O
newspapers O
. O

My O
second O
son B-TER
, O
Leander B-PER
Philipp I-PER
, O
was O
sent O
to O
Romania B-LOC
to O
various O
forced B-TER
labor I-TER
camps I-TER
in O
1942 O
. O

There O
he O
received O
a O
postcard O
from O
my O
son B-PER
Heinz I-PER
as O
late O
as O
1942 O
. O

It O
was O
in O
the O
autumn O
of O
1942 O
, O
and O
this O
card O
contained O
the O
7 O
lines O
allowed O
at O
that O
time O
. O

The O
card O
was O
sent O
from O
the O
camp B-TER
in O
Transnistria B-LOC
and O
contained O
the O
imploring O
request O
to O
send O
medicaments B-TER
. O

About O
my O
family B-TER
, O
I O
make O
the O
following O
statements O
: O
Adolf B-PER
Rosengarten I-PER
, O
born O
15 O
. O

4 O
. O

1884 O
in O
Stanislau B-LOC
, O
since O
1887 O
in O
Chernivtsi B-LOC
, O
occupation O
railway O
inspector O
, O
died B-TER
here O
in O
the O
country B-LOC
in O
1954 O
. O

- O
8 O
- O
Ernestine B-PER
Rosengarten I-PER
, O
née O
Sternberg O
( O
myself O
) O
, O
born O
April O
25 O
, O
1888 O
in O
Chernivtsi B-LOC
. O

Heinz B-PER
Victor I-PER
Rosengarten I-PER
, O
born O
in O
Chernivtsi B-LOC
August O
22 O
, O
1908 O
, O
died O
in O
Tarasivka B-LOC
on O
December O
13 O
, O
1943 O
. O

Anni B-PER
Rosengarten I-PER
, I-PER
née I-PER
Schwarz I-PER
, O
born O
in O
1918 O
, O
daughter B-TER
of O
Baruch B-PER
Schwarz I-PER
in O
Chernivtsi B-LOC
, O
a O
grammar O
school O
teacher O
of O
physics O
, O
chemistry O
etc O
.. O
Leander B-PER
Philipp I-PER
Rosengarten I-PER
, O
born O
August O
29 O
, O
1924 O
in O
Chernivtsi B-LOC
. O

My O
husband B-PER
and O
I O
stayed O
in O
Chernivtsi B-LOC
until O
1946 O
, O
then O
lived O
in O
Bucharest B-LOC
from O
1946 O
to O
1950 O
, O
and O
immigrated O
here O
in O
August O
1950 O
. O

My O
second O
son B-PER
was O
from O
1942 O
- O
1944 O
in O
Romanian B-LOC
labour B-TER
camps I-TER
, O
then O
stayed O
in O
Romania B-LOC
, O
and O
immigrated O
here O
in O
December O
1950 O
. O

He O
is O
an O
engineer O
with O
Solel O
Boneh O
in O
Afula B-LOC
, O
and O
lives O
Shikun B-LOC
Ovdei I-LOC
Solel I-LOC
Boneh I-LOC
in O
Afula B-LOC
. O

My O
son B-TER
Heinz B-PER
was O
a O
student B-TER
at O
the O
Technical O
University O
in O
Prague B-LOC
, O
and O
as O
the O
8th O
student B-TER
( O
and O
first O
Jewish B-TER
student I-TER
) O
there O
he O
passed O
the O
exams O
with O
distinction O
. O

Ball B-PER
- I-PER
Kaduri I-PER
signed O
by O
Ernestine B-PER
Rosengarten I-PER
in O
April O
1953 O
signed O
Leander B-PER
Rosengarten I-PER
( O
Dr. B-PER
Ball I-PER
- I-PER
Kaduri I-PER
) O
- O
9 O
- O
[ O
Letter B-TER
in O
Hebrew O
by O
E. B-PER
Rosengarten I-PER
to O
Yad B-ORG
Vashem I-ORG
, O
November O
10 O
, O
1955 O
, O
see O
pp O
. O

11 O
– O
12 O
] O
- O
10 O
- O
[ O
Hebrew O
translation O
of O
the O
annex O
in O
Ukrainian B-LOC
language O
to O
the O
letter B-TER
of O
November O
10 O
, O
1955 O
, O
see O
p. O
13 O
] O
- O
11 O
- O
Letter B-TER
from O
Mrs. O
Ernestine B-PER
Rosengarten I-PER
to O
Yad B-ORG
Vashem I-ORG
from O
November O
10 O
, O
1955 O
( O
translation O
from O
Hebrew O
) O
My O
son B-TER
Rosengarten B-PER
, I-PER
Victor I-PER
Heinz I-PER
, O
and O
his O
wife B-TER
Anni B-PER
( I-PER
Hanna I-PER
) I-PER
were O
taken O
from O
their O
home O
in O
Chernivtsi B-LOC
on O
June O
14 O
, O
1942 O
and O
brought B-TER
to O
the O
concentration B-TER
camp I-TER
in O
Transnistria B-LOC
, O
camp B-LOC
Laidzin I-LOC
Ladyzhin O
. O

From O
there O
the O
Nazis O
brought B-TER
them O
to O
work B-TER
across O
the O
river B-LOC
Bug I-LOC
. O

They O
passed O
Bershad B-LOC
, O
from O
where O
we O
received O
a O
postcard O
. O

They O
were O
sent O
to O
a O
German B-LOC
camp B-LOC
which O
had O
to O
provide O
manpower B-TER
for O
the O
Organisation O
Todt O
. O

Life B-TER
was O
horrible O
under O
supervision O
of O
the O
SS O
, O
which O
was O
composed O
of O
volunteers B-ORG
from O
Lithuania B-LOC
and O
Ukraine B-LOC
. O

The O
last O
camp B-LOC
was O
in O
Tarasivka B-LOC
. O

The O
commander O
of O
the O
camp B-LOC
was O
a O
German B-LOC
, O
Elsässer B-PER
( O
foreman O
in O
civilian O
life O
in O
Germany B-LOC
) O
. O

He O
came O
to O
Chernivtsi B-LOC
in O
1943 O
with O
a O
letter B-TER
from O
my O
son B-PER
to O
the O
community B-TER
of O
Chernivtsi B-LOC
asking O
to O
help B-TER
the O
few O
who O
were O
still O
alive O
. O

The O
Jews O
who O
had O
managed O
to O
stay O
in O
Chernivtsi B-LOC
donated B-TER
food B-TER
and O
clothing B-TER
. O

The O
inhabitants B-TER
of O
the O
camp B-LOC
in O
Tarasivka B-LOC
received O
the O
donation O
but O
as O
a O
result O
of O
the O
rapid O
progress O
of O
the O
Russians B-ORG
on O
the O
eastern O
front O
, O
the O
Germans B-LOC
decided O
to O
liquidate O
the O
whole O
camp B-LOC
. O

This O
action B-TER
was O
carried O
out O
in O
the O
morning O
hours O
of O
13 O
December O
1943 O
, O
when O
my O
son B-PER
and O
his O
wife B-PER
also O
died O
. O

Only O
a O
few O
people O
were O
rescued B-TER
from O
this O
camp B-LOC
, O
who O
were O
taken O
away O
by O
the O
Russian B-LOC
partisans B-TER
during O
one O
of O
their O
actions O
against O
the O
Germans B-LOC
. O

In O
the O
book B-TER
The O
grave O
is O
in O
the O
cherry O
- O
orchard O
) O
, O
written O
by O
one O
of O
the O
rescued B-TER
, O
Arnold B-PER
Daghani I-PER
( O
Korn O
) O
, O
in O
English B-LOC
, O
and O
in O
Romanian B-LOC
under O
the O
title O
Groapa O
este O
intre O
, O
livada O
de O
visini O
, O
one O
can O
read O
- O
12 O
- O
about O
life O
in O
Tarasivka B-LOC
. O

Some O
chapters O
of O
this O
book B-TER
, O
written O
in O
the O
form O
of O
a O
diary B-TER
, O
are O
dedicated O
to O
the O
character O
and O
behaviour O
of O
my O
son B-TER
Heinz B-PER
Rosengarten I-PER
. O

A O
copy O
of O
the O
book B-TER
can O
be O
found O
at O
Dr. O
Weinstein B-PER
from O
Chernivtsi B-LOC
, O
today O
Tel B-LOC
Aviv I-LOC
, O
POB O
4003 O
, O
editor O
of O
the O
newspaper O
Die O
Stimme O
. O

The O
book B-TER
is O
contains O
additional O
drawings O
by O
the O
author O
about O
life O
and O
work B-TER
in O
the O
German B-LOC
camp B-LOC
Tarasivka I-LOC
. O

If O
you O
want O
to O
know O
additional O
details O
more O
precisely O
about O
a O
number O
- O
relatively O
few O
- O
of O
Jews O
from O
Chernivtsi B-LOC
who O
were O
taken B-TER
beyond O
the O
river B-LOC
Bug I-LOC
, O
I O
am O
at O
your O
disposal O
, O
being O
convinced O
that O
every O
detail O
about O
this O
dark O
epoch O
in O
our O
days O
will O
serve O
to O
pass O
on O
the O
memory O
of O
our O
victims B-TER
to O
future O
generations O
. O

Afula B-LOC
, O
November O
10 O
, O
1955 O
Respectfully O
Ernestine B-PER
Rosengarten I-PER
Afula B-LOC
Shchunat B-LOC
Ovdei I-LOC
Solel I-LOC
Boneh I-LOC
- O
13 O
- O
Annex O
to O
the O
letter B-TER
of O
November O
10 O
, O
1955 O
Translation O
from O
Ukrainian B-LOC
To O
Rosengarten B-PER
Adolf I-PER
Philipowicz I-PER
City O
of O
Chernivtsi B-LOC
Georgi B-LOC
Schandri I-LOC
st I-LOC
. I-LOC

no O
. O

9 O
, O
Apartment O
6 O
In O
view O
of O
the O
fact O
that O
the O
grave B-TER
of O
your O
children B-TER
is O
in O
the O
Vinnica B-LOC
district I-LOC
, O
in O
order O
to O
obtain O
permission O
for O
exhumation O
, O
you O
must O
contact O
the O
Vinnica B-LOC
district I-LOC
commander O
M. O
M. O
Commander O
Chernivtsi B-LOC
District I-LOC
Kwitanabaski O
Remarks O
After O
the O
Russians O
had O
liberated O
Chernivtsi B-LOC
, O
my O
husband B-PER
turned O
to O
the O
district O
commander O
of O
Chernivtsi B-LOC
to O
obtain O
the O
permission O
to O
exhume B-TER
all O
the O
graves B-TER
of O
the O
murdered B-TER
, O
who O
were O
all O
buried O
together O
with O
our O
children B-TER
( O
because O
we O
knew O
exactly O
where O
their O
brothers B-TER
were O
buried B-TER
) O
. O

The O
document O
, O
which O
I O
attach O
here O
in O
photocopy O
, O
is O
the O
only O
answer O
we O
got O
to O
our O
request O
. O

The O
original O
is O
with O
me O
. O

November O
10 O
, O
1955 O
Ernestine B-PER
Rosengarten I-PER
- O
14 O
- O
Notes O
by O
Mrs. O
E. B-PER
Rosengarten I-PER
handwritten O
addition O
The O
following O
letter B-TER
, O
written O
in O
Romanian B-LOC
, O
was O
sent O
by O
SS B-ORG
officer O
Oberleutnant O
Senior O
Lieutenant O
Elsässer B-PER
from O
Cologne B-LOC
, O
leader O
of O
the O
Tarasivka B-LOC
concentration I-LOC
camp I-LOC
, O
to O
the O
parents B-TER
of O
the O
engineer O
Heinz B-PER
Victor I-PER
Rosengarten I-PER
s[eligen O
] O
A[ndenkens O
] O
in O
Chernivtsi B-LOC
at O
the O
end O
of O
September O
1943 O
. O

Oberlt O
. O

Elsässer B-PER
took O
a O
large O
transport O
of O
clothes B-TER
, O
shoes O
and O
food B-TER
with O
him O
for O
all O
camp B-TER
inmates I-TER
, O
only O
Jews O
. O

The O
things O
were O
donated O
by O
the O
Jews O
still O
remaining O
in O
Chernivtsi B-LOC
, O
most O
of O
whom O
had O
been O
robbed B-TER
. O

In O
order O
to O
make O
the O
SS B-ORG
guards O
in O
the O
camp B-LOC
more O
favourable O
, O
Elsässer B-PER
took O
with O
him O
a O
large O
transport O
of O
champagne O
, O
ham B-TER
, O
bacon B-TER
, O
new O
shoes B-TER
[ O
and O
] O
furs B-TER
, O
most O
of O
which O
were O
found O
by O
the O
remaining O
Jews O
. O

It O
was O
also O
[ O
un]counted O
Christians O
who O
gave O
donations B-TER
, O
and O
it O
would O
be O
right O
to O
mention O
that O
the O
Polish O
- O
Christian O
food B-TER
manufacturer O
Podzudek O
donated B-TER
several O
hundred O
kilograms O
of O
smoked B-TER
goods I-TER
. O

The O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
in O
Chernivtsi B-LOC
actively O
participated O
in O
the O
collection B-TER
despite O
the O
bad O
situation B-TER
. O

Translation O
from O
Romanian B-LOC
Tarasivka B-LOC
, O
September O
14 O
, O
1943 O
My O
Dearest O
! O
My O
wife B-PER
and O
I O
are O
still O
healthy O
yet O
, O
but O
death O
lurks O
for O
us O
every O
moment O
. O

We O
are O
completely O
destitute B-TER
and O
have O
nothing O
to O
dress B-TER
in O
. O

Send O
us O
a O
lot O
of O
money O
and O
warm O
clothes B-TER
for O
the O
winter O
, O
for O
me O
and O
my O
wife B-PER
. O

Last O
winter O
my O
wife B-PER
was O
seriously O
ill B-TER
and O
I O
sold O
everything O
to O
save O
and O
cure O
her O
. O

We O
are O
both O
still O
healthy O
, O
but O
death O
awaits O
us O
every O
moment O
. O

Go O
to O
any O
trouble O
, O
spare O
no O
expense O
, O
even O
if O
it O
has O
to O
be O
begged O
for O
by O
strangers O
, O
to O
get B-TER
us I-TER
out I-TER
as O
soon O
as O
possible O
by O
official O
means O
through O
a O
messenger O
, O
beyond O
the O
river B-LOC
Bug I-LOC
, O
to O
Transnistria B-LOC
. O

If O
You O
do O
not O
succeed O
- O
15 O
- O
as O
soon O
as O
possible O
, O
You O
will O
lose O
hope O
of O
seeing O
us O
again O
. O

The O
colours O
in O
which O
I O
describe O
the O
situation B-TER
to O
You O
are O
not O
blacker O
than O
in O
reality O
. O

Even O
millions O
You O
must O
get O
together O
by O
begging O
to O
take B-TER
us I-TER
out I-TER
. O

Every O
day O
we O
see O
death O
before O
our O
eyes O
. O

If O
we O
are O
saved O
, O
I O
will O
repay O
everything O
. O

Be O
sure O
about O
this O
. O

My O
wife B-PER
is O
not O
here O
. O

You O
can O
see O
her O
handwriting O
on O
the O
note O
for O
Poldi B-PER
Fleminger I-PER
. O

Again O
, O
if O
you O
want O
to O
see O
us O
resurrected B-TER
, O
do O
everything O
, O
more O
than O
what O
is O
possible O
. O

In O
any O
case O
, O
we O
are O
waiting O
for O
money B-TER
, O
socks B-TER
, O
warm O
clothes B-TER
, O
trousers B-TER
, O
dresses B-TER
, O
gloves B-TER
, O
caps B-TER
, O
etc O
. O

We O
can O
not O
know O
how O
much O
the O
provisions O
and O
the O
money O
collected O
from O
strangers O
can O
achieve O
. O

I O
have O
faith O
in O
You O
, O
Dolin B-PER
and O
Tina B-PER
( O
father B-TER
and O
mother B-TER
) O
, O
Willy B-PER
and O
Andy B-PER
( O
brother B-TER
- I-TER
in I-TER
- I-TER
law I-TER
and O
brother B-TER
) O
. O

With O
strong O
faith O
in O
You O
, O
with O
love O
Your O
unfortunate O
Heinz B-PER
and O
Anny B-PER
Once O
again O
, O
certain O
death O
lurks O
for O
us O
at O
every O
moment O
. O

Save B-TER
us O
by O
official O
means O
, O
at O
all O
costs O
and O
at O
all O
risks O
. O

We O
are O
convinced O
that O
You O
will O
understand O
our O
last O
cry O
for O
help B-TER
at O
the O
last O
moment O
. O

Note O
: O
Since O
his O
mother O
tongue O
was O
German B-LOC
, O
and O
we O
only O
spoke O
German B-LOC
in O
our O
house O
, O
I O
am O
convinced O
that O
the O
only O
reason O
that O
my O
son B-PER
wrote O
the O
letter B-TER
in O
Romanian B-LOC
is O
that O
the O
letter B-TER
was O
delivered O
by O
a O
German B-LOC
officer O
, O
and O
my O
son B-PER
, O
God O
bless O
him O
, O
did O
not O
want O
him O
to O
understand O
the O
contents O
. O

Ernestine B-PER
Rosengarten I-PER
- O
16 O
- O
[ O
Letter B-TER
by O
Heinz B-PER
V. I-PER
Rosengarten I-PER
from O
Tarasivka B-LOC
, O
September O
14 O
, O
1943 O
; O
Romanian B-LOC
transcription O
, O
] O
… O
I O
the O
undersigned O
E. B-PER
Rosengarten I-PER
, O
resident O
in O
Afula B-LOC
– O
Israel B-LOC
, O
Shikun B-LOC
Ovdei B-LOC
Solel I-LOC
Boneh I-LOC
, O
certify O
that O
this O
copy O
is O
in O
conformity O
with O
the O
original O
. O

Ernestine B-PER
Rosengarten I-PER
May O
3 O
, O
1952 O
. O

- O
17 O
- O
Additions O
to O
the O
testimony B-TER
of O
Ernestine B-PER
Rosengarten I-PER
Beyond O
the O
river O
Bug O
In O
this O
statement B-TER
, O
which O
I O
recently O
handed O
over O
, O
the O
book B-TER
by O
Arnold B-PER
Daghani I-PER
( O
Korn O
) O
Das O
Grab O
i O
m O
Garten O
der O
KirschenThe O
Grave O
in O
the O
Cherry O
- O
Orchard O
is O
mentioned O
, O
which O
, O
as O
Mrs. O
Rosengarten B-PER
said O
, O
should O
have O
been O
published O
in O
Romanian B-LOC
and O
, O
with O
the O
help O
of O
the O
World B-ORG
Jewish I-ORG
Congress I-ORG
, O
in O
English B-LOC
. O

In O
the O
meantime O
, O
the O
following O
has O
emerged O
with O
regard O
to O
this O
book B-TER
: O
1 O
. O

As O
is O
known O
at O
Yad B-ORG
Vashem I-ORG
, O
a O
copy O
in O
the O
Romanian B-LOC
language O
was O
found O
through O
an O
advertisement O
in O
the O
newspaper O
of O
the O
Bukovina B-LOC
Jews O
Die O
Stimme O
, O
in O
the O
possession O
of O
Dr. O
Fischer B-PER
handwritten O
addition O
, O
who O
works O
at O
the O
URO B-ORG
in O
Tel B-LOC
Aviv I-LOC
, I-LOC
and O
who O
lent O
this O
copy O
to O
Yad B-ORG
Vashem I-ORG
. O

2 O
. O

Recently O
I O
learned O
of O
a O
second O
copy O
in O
this O
country B-LOC
. O

44 O
, O
and O
who O
also O
does O
special O
work O
for O
Yad B-ORG
Vashem I-ORG
, O
owns O
a O
Romanian B-LOC
copy O
with O
a O
personal O
dedication O
by O
Daghani B-PER
( O
Korn O
) O
. O

She O
reports O
further O
that O
Korn O
is O
a O
gifted O
painter O
and O
graphic O
artist O
and O
that O
he O
now O
lives O
in O
Bucharest B-LOC
. O

3 O
. O

The O
husband B-TER
of O
Dr. B-PER
Litani I-PER
, O
who O
is O
also O
here O
in O
the O
country B-LOC
, O
is O
a O
member O
of O
the O
Assirei O
Zion O
and O
was O
the O
chairman O
of O
the O
Romanian B-LOC
section O
of O
the O
World B-ORG
Jewish I-ORG
Congress I-ORG
in O
Bucharest B-LOC
. O

With O
his O
assistance O
, O
Daghani B-PER
's I-PER
book B-TER
was O
published O
in O
Romanian B-LOC
. O

The O
original O
manuscript O
is O
written O
in O
English B-LOC
, O
but O
both O
spouses B-TER
report B-TER
that O
the O
original O
manuscript O
was O
available O
in O
English B-LOC
only O
, O
however O
, O
an O
edition O
printed O
in O
English B-LOC
was O
never O
published O
. O

4 O
. O

Dr. B-PER
Litani I-PER
has O
heard O
that O
the O
English B-LOC
manuscript O
is O
said O
to O
be O
here O
in O
the O
country B-LOC
with O
the O
sister B-TER
of O
Daghani B-PER
. O

She O
- O
18 O
- O
now O
tries O
to O
locate O
the O
address O
, O
and O
if O
she O
finds O
the O
English B-LOC
text O
, O
she O
will O
contact O
Yad B-ORG
Vashem I-ORG
. O

I O
would O
like O
to O
add O
a O
further O
addition O
to O
the O
report B-TER
. O

I O
said O
in O
the O
accompanying O
report B-TER
that O
no O
other O
case O
was O
known O
to O
me O
that O
an O
SS B-ORG
-man O
had O
sought O
help B-TER
for O
Jews O
. O

That O
is O
not O
correct O
. O

I O
had O
parts O
of O
Daghani B-PER
's O
book B-TER
translated O
for O
me O
orally O
by O
Mrs. O
Roll B-PER
in O
Tel B-LOC
Aviv I-LOC
. O

Mrs. O
Roll B-PER
comes O
from O
Chernivtsi B-LOC
, O
and O
she O
knew O
quite O
a O
few O
of O
the O
people O
mentioned O
in O
the O
book B-TER
personally O
. O

She O
told O
me O
that O
relatively O
often O
SS B-ORG
-men O
from O
Bukovina B-LOC
and O
Transnistria B-LOC
came O
to O
Chernivtsi B-LOC
who O
brought O
news O
about O
the O
deportees B-TER
, O
and O
took O
food B-TER
for O
them O
, O
not O
infrequently O
even O
free O
of O
charge O
. O

Her O
own O
father B-TER
was O
interned B-TER
in O
Djwin O
and O
died O
there O
, O
and O
she O
had O
sent O
him O
help B-TER
through O
an O
SS B-ORG
-man O
who O
did O
not O
accept O
payment O
. O

At O
the O
same O
time O
, O
I O
forward O
the O
copy O
of O
Heinz B-PER
Victor I-PER
Rosengarten I-PER
’s I-PER
Romanian B-LOC
handwritten O
addition O
letter B-TER
, O
which O
could O
not O
be O
included O
in O
the O
first O
shipment O
. O

Dr. B-PER
Ball I-PER
- I-PER
Kaduri I-PER
in O
June O
1958 O
( O
Dr B-PER
Ball I-PER
- I-PER
Kaduri I-PER
) O
- O
19 O
– O
[ O
Manuscript O
of O
the O
letter B-TER
from O
Heinz B-PER
Victor I-PER
Rosengarten I-PER
and O
of O
the O
additions O
, O
pp O
. O

14 O
– O
15 O
] O
- O
20 O
– O
[ O
Manuscript O
of O
the O
letter B-TER
from O
Heinz B-PER
Victor I-PER
Rosengarten I-PER
and O
of O
the O
additions O
, O
pp O
. O

14 O
– O
15 O
] O
- O
21 O
- O
Supplement O
to O
the O
statement B-TER
by O
Ernestine B-PER
Rosengarten I-PER
. O

In O
a O
transcript O
of O
a O
letter B-TER
of O
Mr. O
Jaegerndorf B-PER
to O
Dr. B-PER
Fildermann I-PER
from O
1944 O
contained O
in O
our O
archives O
in O
volume O
O-11/12 O
- O
2 O
, O
I O
found O
a O
remark O
referring O
to O
the O
family B-TER
of O
the O
engineer O
Rosengarten B-PER
as O
well O
as O
to O
the O
family B-TER
Segall B-PER
. O

The O
remark O
reads O
: O
Dear O
friends O
! O
... O
nevertheless O
, O
I O
feel O
compelled O
to O
warmly O
word O
missing O
, O
probably O
recommend O
to O
you O
again O
the O
matter O
of O
the O
Tulcin B-LOC
Jews O
, O
and O
I O
will O
assume O
that O
he O
has O
not O
only O
discussed O
this O
case O
with O
you O
, O
but O
that O
he O
will O
also O
bring O
something O
concrete O
with O
him O
. O

I O
myself O
wrote O
to O
you O
in O
detail O
at O
the O
time O
, O
after O
Mr O
Segall B-PER
’s I-PER
visit O
, O
and O
asked O
you O
to O
send O
an O
urgent O
order O
from O
there O
to O
the O
Tulcin B-LOC
Prefecture O
to O
demand O
the O
return O
of O
all O
Jews B-TER
who O
had O
been O
sent O
to O
work B-TER
on O
the O
other O
side O
of O
the O
Bug B-LOC
. O

Unfortunately O
, O
my O
pertaining O
request O
was O
unsuccessful O
and O
today O
there O
is O
nobody O
left O
to O
bring O
back O
. O

My O
personal O
intervention O
in O
Tulcin B-LOC
in O
this O
matter O
probably O
was O
successful O
in O
so O
far O
that O
the O
order O
was O
given O
for O
the O
families B-TER
Segall B-PER
and O
Ing O
. O

Rosengarten B-PER
to O
bring O
them O
back O
, O
but O
unfortunately O
as O
a O
result O
of O
a O
chain O
of O
circumstances O
they O
were O
already O
dead O
two O
days O
before O
that O
, O
just O
like O
all O
the O
others O
... O
Jaegerndorf B-PER
February O
21 O
, O
1944 O
. O

Tel B-LOC
Aviv I-LOC
, I-LOC
December O
21 O
. O

, O
1958 O
handwritten O
Dr B-PER
Ball I-PER
- I-PER
Kaduri I-PER
handwritten O
- O
22 O
- O
[ O
Ukrainian B-LOC
original O
of O
the O
Annex O
to O
the O
letter B-TER
of O
November O
10 O
, O
1955 O
, O
see O
p. O
13 O
] O
