Edita B-PER
Ohrensteinová I-PER
made O
this O
available O
to O
the O
documentation B-TER
campaign I-TER
. O

On O
: O
6.XI.1945 O
The O
Illusion O
of O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
. O

The O
deportation B-TER
of O
Jews O
from O
the O
former O
Protectorate B-TER
to O
Poland B-LOC
began O
in O
1941 O
; O
5,000 O
individuals O
from O
Prague B-LOC
and O
1,000 O
from O
Brno B-LOC
were B-TER
brought I-TER
to O
Polish B-LOC
ghettos B-TER
. O

The O
leadership O
of O
the O
Jewish B-ORG
religious I-ORG
community I-ORG
at O
the O
time O
wrote O
and O
spoke O
out O
to O
prevent O
further O
transports B-TER
to O
Poland B-LOC
, O
and O
the O
Germans B-TER
reassured O
it O
that O
after O
these O
6,000 O
there O
would O
be O
no O
other O
transports B-TER
from I-TER
the I-TER
Protectorate I-TER
to O
Poland B-LOC
. O

In O
the O
meantime O
, O
Edelstein B-PER
continued O
to O
work O
on O
his O
concept O
: O
He O
was O
of O
the O
opinion O
that O
our O
only O
hope O
in O
the O
war O
was O
the O
Jewish O
workforce B-TER
. O

He O
tried O
to O
convince O
the O
Germans O
that O
in O
wartime B-TER
, O
when O
a O
workforce B-TER
is O
vitally O
needed O
, O
it O
’s O
far O
better O
to O
put O
Jews O
to O
work B-TER
within O
the O
Protectorate B-LOC
. O

And O
in O
the O
beginning O
, O
it O
seemed O
( O
after O
the O
Ostrava B-LOC
transport B-TER
to O
Nisko B-LOC
in O
the O
fall O
of O
1939 O
) O
that O
he O
had O
succeeded O
. O

While O
the O
majority O
of O
the O
Jewish B-TER
population I-TER
in I-TER
Germany I-TER
and O
Austria B-TER
that O
was O
able O
to O
work B-TER
was O
deported B-TER
to O
Poland B-LOC
, O
in O
the O
Protectorate B-TER
, O
the O
transports B-TER
did O
n’t O
begin O
until O
October O
1941 O
. O

A O
special O
Jewish O
office O
within O
the O
Jewish B-ORG
religious I-ORG
community I-ORG
in I-ORG
Prague I-ORG
was O
established O
to O
allocate O
and O
guarantee O
Jews O
for O
labor B-TER
. O

When O
our O
efforts O
were O
thwarted O
by O
the O
Germans B-TER
’ I-TER
desire O
to O
isolate O
the O
Jews O
from O
the O
rest O
of O
the O
population O
and O
to O
concentrate O
them O
, O
Edelstein B-PER
tried O
to O
at O
least O
ensure O
that O
this O
concentration O
would O
remain O
within O
the O
territory O
of O
the O
Protectorate B-LOC
. O

This O
effort O
was O
seemingly O
effective O
. O

When O
a O
small O
group O
led O
by O
Edelstein B-PER
and O
Ing O
. O

Zuckr B-PER
went O
to O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
on O
December O
1st O
, O
1941 O
, O
all O
were O
convinced O
that O
they O
would O
truly O
be O
able O
to O
prevent O
the O
deportation B-TER
of O
Jews B-TER
from I-TER
the I-TER
Protectorate I-TER
into O
Poland B-LOC
if O
the O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
ghetto I-LOC
were O
to O
be O
established O
, O
as O
we O
thought O
at O
the O
time O
, O
as O
a O
Jewish O
town O
. O

Feverish O
preparations O
were O
already O
underway O
; O
plans O
were O
developed O
down O
to O
the O
smallest O
details O
and O
approved O
by O
the O
Office B-ORG
of I-ORG
Jewish I-ORG
Resettlement I-ORG
. O

But O
then O
everything O
turned O
out O
completely O
differently O
than O
we O
expected O
. O

We O
built O
a O
Jewish O
town O
– O
what O
an O
illusion O
! O
When O
the O
gates O
of O
the O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
barracks O
closed O
behind O
us O
for O
the O
first O
time O
, O
we O
immediately O
knew O
that O
it O
was O
more O
of O
a O
prison B-TER
than O
a O
Jewish O
town O
. O

It O
is O
n’t O
necessary O
to O
dwell O
more O
closely O
on O
the O
conditions O
at O
the O
time O
. O

When O
Hauptsturmführer B-TER
Günther B-PER
came O
to O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
during O
the O
first O
few O
days O
and O
Edelstein B-PER
reproached O
him O
for O
deceiving O
us O
with O
false O
facts O
, O
he O
answered O
: O
Jetzt O
wenn O
Ihr O
i O
m O
Dreck O
sitzt O
Juden O
, O
zeigt O
was O
Ihr O
könnt O
! O
And O
we O
were O
determined O
to O
show O
what O
we O
are O
capable O
of O
. O

Our O
most O
important O
task O
was O
to O
use O
all O
of O
our O
strength O
to O
wake O
people O
up O
from O
their O
lethargy O
, O
maintain O
cleanliness O
to O
prevent O
diseases B-TER
, O
establish O
kitchens O
to O
ensure O
food B-TER
, O
acquire O
mattresses B-TER
and O
straw B-TER
mattresses I-TER
especially O
for O
the O
sick B-TER
and O
the O
children B-TER
, O
and O
work O
our O
way O
out O
of O
this O
mess O
in O
the O
literal O
sense O
of O
the O
word O
– O
without O
the O
means O
, O
but O
firmly O
believing O
that O
we O
could O
do O
it O
. O

And O
after O
the O
first O
terrible O
days O
of O
shock O
, O
mutual O
hatred O
, O
and O
bitterness O
, O
it O
seemed O
that O
we O
had O
indeed O
succeeded O
. O

Somehow O
, O
a O
kind O
of O
carefree O
life O
set O
in O
. O

Every O
one O
of O
us O
had O
a O
place O
to O
sleep B-TER
and O
for O
his O
or O
her O
things O
, O
more O
or O
less O
had O
a O
job O
, O
and O
most O
importantly O
: O
there O
was O
a O
peaceful O
atmosphere O
. O

This O
was O
one O
of O
Edelstein B-PER
’s I-PER
greatest O
achievements O
. O

He O
was O
truly O
able O
to O
gain O
the O
population B-TER
’s O
trust O
. O

The O
initial O
hatred O
of O
him O
and O
of O
his O
colleagues O
abated O
, O
and O
people O
started O
to O
like O
him O
. O

He O
gradually O
won O
over O
everyone O
’s O
heart O
. O

All O
of O
us O
trusted O
him O
, O
believed O
that O
he O
told O
the O
truth O
, O
that O
our O
affairs O
were O
his O
affairs O
as O
well O
and O
that O
he O
represented O
our O
interests O
before O
the O
Germans B-TER
as O
nobody O
else O
could O
. O

Everyone O
knew O
that O
they O
could O
come O
to O
Edelstein B-PER
with O
any O
worry O
or O
complaint O
, O
day O
or O
night O
. O

And O
the O
Germans B-TER
rightly O
knew O
that O
Edelstein B-PER
presented O
a O
danger O
to O
them O
and O
they O
feared O
him O
as O
a O
leader O
of O
the O
people O
. O

No O
matter O
how O
hard O
they O
tried O
, O
they O
never O
managed O
to O
create O
an O
insurmountable O
barrier O
between O
him O
and O
the O
people O
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
’ I-TER
method O
was O
extremely O
transparent O
. O

Edelstein B-PER
often O
said O
: O
They O
want O
to O
give O
us O
all O
kinds O
of O
possible O
and O
impossible O
advantages O
to O
make O
us O
forget O
that O
I O
am O
the O
representative O
of O
the O
Jews O
and O
to O
make O
us O
feel O
an O
affiliation O
to O
them O
, O
and O
most O
of O
all O
they O
want O
to O
cultivate O
hatred O
for O
me O
in O
the O
people O
. O

A O
small O
example O
to O
illustrate O
this O
. O

Food B-TER
was O
cooked O
in O
a O
communal O
kitchen O
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
demanded O
a O
separate O
kitchen O
for O
the O
leading O
coworkers O
of O
the O
so O
- O
called O
Self B-TER
- I-TER
government I-TER
with O
the O
justification O
that O
even O
during O
military O
service O
officers O
take O
their O
meals O
separately O
from O
simple O
privates O
. O

Edelstein B-PER
refused O
and O
the O
answer O
was O
: O
Communist O
methods O
! O
Then O
January O
1942 O
arrived O
: O
the O
execution B-TER
of O
several O
inhabitants B-TER
of O
the O
camp O
for O
the O
barest O
of O
violations O
of O
the O
camp B-LOC
's I-LOC
rules O
. O

The B-TER
Council I-TER
of I-TER
Elders I-TER
, O
the O
Jewish O
commanders O
of O
the O
barracks B-TER
, O
members O
of O
the O
maintenance O
service O
, O
and O
police B-TER
officers I-TER
had O
to O
be O
present O
. O

Shortly O
thereafter O
, O
Edelstein B-PER
was O
n’t O
present O
during O
the O
second O
wave O
of O
executions B-TER
. O

He O
announced O
that O
he O
would O
n’t O
look O
at O
them O
and O
demanded O
to O
be O
released O
from O
his O
position O
because O
he O
could O
no O
longer O
continue O
to O
be O
a O
Jewish B-TER
elder I-TER
under O
these O
circumstances O
. O

It O
was O
an O
exceptional O
act O
of O
personal O
bravery O
. O

His O
resignation O
was O
n’t O
accepted O
, O
but O
his O
status O
with O
the O
Germans B-TER
unsurprisingly O
did O
n’t O
improve O
. O

January O
also O
brought O
another O
terrible O
thing O
: O
the O
first O
transports B-TER
from I-TER
Theresienstadt I-TER
to O
Poland B-LOC
. O

All O
was O
in O
vain O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
’ I-TER
intention O
was O
solely O
to O
transport B-TER
Jews B-TER
from I-TER
the I-TER
Protectorate I-TER
to O
Poland B-LOC
through O
the O
transit B-TER
camp I-TER
of O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
. O

Why O
did O
we O
voluntarily O
go O
to O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
? O
There O
was O
no O
time O
for O
such O
thoughts O
, O
we O
had O
to O
help O
in O
any O
way O
we O
could O
. O

And O
so O
we O
lost O
another O
illusion O
. O

How O
would O
it O
be O
possible O
to O
prevent O
the O
transports B-TER
? O
Edelstein B-PER
continued O
in O
his O
theory O
of O
the O
Jews O
as O
a O
workforce B-TER
. O

We O
must O
prove O
the O
importance O
of O
the O
Jews O
’ O
suitability B-TER
as I-TER
a I-TER
workforce I-TER
for O
the O
Protectorate B-LOC
. O

In O
order O
to O
combat O
the O
intended O
concentration O
of O
Jews O
, O
we O
must O
send O
workers B-TER
to O
locations O
outside O
of O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
and O
receive O
commissions O
from O
Aryan B-TER
companies O
. O

We O
must O
establish O
workshops O
and O
factories O
in O
the O
ghetto B-LOC
. O

Hopefully O
, O
that O
would O
help O
us O
. O

It O
was O
an O
uneven O
battle O
against O
an O
opponent O
that O
outnumbered O
us O
. O

We O
managed O
to O
send O
a O
group O
of O
workers B-TER
to O
the O
mines O
in O
Kladno B-LOC
and O
Oslavany B-LOC
, O
to O
be O
part O
of O
the O
crew O
that O
constructed O
the O
road O
near O
České B-LOC
Budějovice I-LOC
, O
and O
to O
do O
forest O
work B-TER
in O
the O
Křivoklát B-LOC
region O
. O

Workshops O
and O
factories O
were O
created O
and O
we O
hoped O
that O
we O
were O
one O
step O
ahead O
. O

But O
not O
for O
long O
. O

The O
transports B-TER
continued O
. O

Hundreds O
of O
statistics B-TER
, O
diagrams O
, O
and O
written O
reports O
were O
composed O
and O
we O
continuously O
provided O
proof O
that O
there O
was O
such O
a O
shortage O
of O
workers B-TER
in O
the O
ghetto B-LOC
that O
, O
for O
example O
, O
it O
would O
be O
impossible O
to O
treat O
the O
sick B-TER
if O
other O
workers B-TER
were O
deported B-TER
to O
the O
east O
, O
and O
so O
contagions B-TER
that O
would O
threaten O
the O
entire O
surrounding O
area O
could O
emerge O
, O
etc O
. O

So O
many O
sleepless O
nights O
, O
so O
many O
reams O
of O
paper O
filled O
with O
writing O
, O
sophisticated O
statistical B-TER
calculations O
and O
yet O
no O
success O
, O
or O
only O
minimal O
success O
, O
as O
once O
Edelstein B-PER
was O
able O
to O
prevent O
a O
transport B-TER
and O
here O
and O
there O
gain O
a O
short O
delay O
. O

The O
spectre O
of O
the O
transports B-TER
to O
Poland B-LOC
hung O
over O
the O
labor B-TER
camp I-TER
, O
the O
elderly B-TER
ghetto B-LOC
, O
the O
settlement O
of O
prominent B-TER
persons I-TER
, O
and O
the O
other O
names O
of O
the O
phases O
of O
the O
development O
of O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
, O
and O
our O
work O
consisted O
in O
preventing O
the O
transports B-TER
or O
to O
at O
least O
gain O
some O
time O
. O

Suddenly O
, O
there O
was O
a O
new O
hope O
: O
in O
the O
spring O
of O
1943 O
, O
shops O
and O
a O
cafe B-TER
were O
to O
be O
opened O
. O

What O
did O
this O
mean O
? O
Edelstein B-PER
knew O
the O
answer O
: O
We O
were O
to O
be O
items O
on O
display O
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
wanted O
to O
prove O
that O
they O
were O
n’t O
treating O
the O
Jews O
that O
poorly O
and O
present O
to O
the O
world O
the O
illusion O
of O
a O
Jewish O
town O
. O

We O
had O
to O
capitalize O
on O
this O
situation O
very O
carefully O
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
were O
already O
expecting O
the O
visit O
of O
an O
international B-ORG
committee I-ORG
. O

There O
was O
talk O
of O
having O
radio O
, O
making O
a O
film O
, O
and O
putting O
on O
a O
comedy O
for O
the O
foreign O
visit O
. O

But O
Edelstein B-PER
would O
never O
participate O
in O
this O
comedy O
. O

On O
November O
9th O
, O
1943 O
, O
Edelstein B-PER
was O
arrested B-TER
and O
accused O
of O
helping O
Jews O
escape B-TER
from O
the O
ghetto B-LOC
to O
the O
enemy O
. O

The O
evidence O
: O
the O
census O
report O
did O
n’t O
match O
; O
there O
was O
an O
unexplained O
difference O
of O
about O
50 O
individuals O
. O

This O
was O
a O
hard O
time O
for O
the O
ghetto B-LOC
. O

The O
roll B-TER
call I-TER
of O
the O
entire O
population B-TER
, O
including O
children B-TER
and O
the O
elderly B-TER
, O
in O
the O
Bohušovice B-LOC
basin I-LOC
lasted O
16 O
hours O
. O

There O
was O
an O
oppressive O
premonition O
of O
impending O
doom O
. O

The O
ghetto B-LOC
had O
no O
leadership B-TER
; O
there O
was O
no O
contact O
between O
the O
population B-TER
and O
the O
new O
leadership B-TER
; O
the O
inhabitants B-TER
did O
n’t O
trust O
their O
representatives O
. O

Edelstein B-PER
himself O
had O
no O
illusions O
about O
his O
fate O
. O

In O
December O
1943 O
, O
he O
was O
slated O
to O
be O
transported B-TER
to O
Auschwitz B-LOC
with O
his O
family O
. O

His O
closest O
friends O
and O
colleagues O
once O
again O
volunteered O
to O
go O
with O
him O
. O

The O
Jewish O
warden O
who O
passed O
messages O
on O
to O
Edelstein B-PER
in O
prison B-TER
said O
that O
Edelstein B-PER
wept O
at O
hearing O
this O
proof O
of O
friendship O
, O
but O
resolutely O
forbade O
anyone O
to O
join O
him O
. O

In O
the O
meantime O
, O
we O
learned O
confidentially O
that O
Edelstein B-PER
was O
sentenced O
to O
be O
sent O
to O
Auschwitz B-LOC
, O
but O
we O
never O
learned O
more O
information O
other O
than O
that O
. O

After O
December O
, O
1943 O
, O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
was O
even O
more O
gray O
and O
dreary O
. O

The O
atmosphere O
of O
trust O
disappeared O
from O
the O
ghetto B-LOC
along O
with O
Edelstein B-PER
. O

Many O
of O
his O
colleagues O
from O
the O
section O
he O
led O
left O
at O
the O
same O
time O
as O
he O
did O
; O
they O
were O
put O
on O
the O
list O
of O
persons O
to O
be O
transported B-TER
. O

Ever O
since O
that O
day O
we O
had O
the O
feeling O
that O
there O
was O
no O
concept O
to O
anything O
anymore O
, O
that O
orders O
were O
simply O
dealt O
and O
fulfilled O
. O

Spring O
1944 O
. O

Stadtverschönerung O
. O

We O
all O
still O
remember O
the O
craziness O
that O
was O
summer O
1944 O
. O

We O
founded O
orchards O
and O
green O
spaces O
, O
children B-TER
’s I-TER
homes I-TER
will O
all O
kinds O
of O
toys O
, O
a O
pavilion O
for O
children B-TER
with O
a O
slide O
, O
a B-TER
home I-TER
for I-TER
the I-TER
elderly I-TER
, O
model O
residential B-TER
rooms O
, O
a O
musical B-TER
pavilion O
, O
dining B-TER
rooms I-TER
, O
and O
concert B-TER
a O
theater B-TER
halls O
. O

All O
for O
the O
International B-ORG
Committee I-ORG
of I-ORG
the I-ORG
Red I-ORG
Cross I-ORG
. O

We O
ca O
n’t O
deny O
that O
we O
made O
use O
of O
these O
amenities O
ourselves O
and O
thereby O
a O
temporary O
period O
of O
relief O
set O
in O
. O

But O
it O
was O
a O
dance O
on O
the O
mouth O
of O
a O
volcano O
. O

It O
was O
then O
that O
we O
learned O
that O
camp B-TER
commander I-TER
Rahm B-PER
had O
sent O
a O
report O
to O
Berlin B-LOC
, O
in O
which O
he O
alerted O
to O
the O
growing O
danger O
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
, O
because O
officers O
of O
various O
nationalities O
, O
especially O
Czech B-LOC
officers O
, O
were O
allegedly O
meeting O
in O
groups O
. O

It O
was O
clear O
that O
this O
accusation O
presented O
a O
great O
danger O
. O

Shortly O
thereafter O
, O
the O
officers O
were O
registered O
and O
then O
the O
so O
- O
called O
workers O
’ O
transports B-TER
began O
…… O
. O

On O
October O
28th O
, O
1944 O
, O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
looked O
like O
a O
graveyard O
. O

Everything O
was O
gray O
…… O
. O

A O
town O
without O
men B-TER
. O

The O
contrast O
with O
the O
hot O
summer O
was O
too O
stark O
; O
winter O
was O
upon O
us O
, O
and O
still O
there O
was O
no O
end O
to O
the O
war B-TER
in O
sight O
. O

What O
would O
happen O
to O
our O
men B-TER
, O
children B-TER
, O
and O
siblings O
? O
Would O
we O
ever O
see O
them O
again O
? O
And O
then O
there O
was O
the O
necessity O
to O
do O
all O
of O
the O
work B-TER
in O
the O
ghetto B-LOC
in O
place O
of O
all O
of O
those O
who O
have O
gone O
. O

Most O
of O
the O
quarters B-TER
were O
uninhabitable O
for O
the O
number O
of O
suitcases O
left O
behind O
, O
useless O
things O
, O
and O
furniture O
that O
was O
no O
longer O
needed O
. O

It O
was O
necessary O
to O
clear O
out O
almost O
all O
of O
the O
living O
quarters B-TER
; O
the O
furniture O
had O
to O
be O
hauled O
away O
; O
loaded O
railway O
cars O
stood O
at O
the O
train O
station O
; O
we O
received O
an O
order O
to O
build O
buildings B-TER
; O
the O
sick B-TER
had O
to O
be O
transferred O
, O
etc O
. O

, O
etc O
. O

And O
only O
apathetic O
and O
desperate O
women B-TER
remained O
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
. O

We O
had O
to O
endure O
in O
order O
to O
see O
our O
family O
members O
again O
, O
and O
so O
women B-TER
started O
to O
perform O
the O
most O
difficult O
men B-TER
’s O
work B-TER
. O

Would O
our O
men B-TER
return O
, O
do O
you O
believe O
that O
? O
That O
was O
a O
question O
we O
asked O
ourselves O
a O
thousand O
times O
. O

They O
have O
to O
return O
. O

An O
illusion O
? O
In O
April O
, O
a O
rumor O
suddenly O
spread O
during O
the O
night O
that O
the O
the O
SS B-TER
have O
withdrawn O
and O
that O
we O
were O
now O
being O
handled O
by O
the O
Red B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
. O

We O
sang O
throughout O
the O
night O
and O
praised O
the O
glory O
of O
the O
new O
Czechoslovak O
Republic O
. O

Until O
… O
…… O
armed O
SSmen B-TER
appeared O
. O

Was O
liberation B-TER
also O
just O
an O
illusion O
? O
Beginning O
on O
April O
20th O
, O
1945 O
, O
in O
just O
two O
days O
15,000 O
starving B-TER
, O
sick B-TER
, O
dying B-TER
wretched O
prisoners B-TER
from O
various O
concentration B-TER
camps I-TER
arrived O
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
after O
a O
torturous O
hunger B-TER
and I-TER
death I-TER
march I-TER
. O

Everyone O
was O
out O
on O
the O
streets O
and O
searching O
among O
the O
terrifying O
figures O
for O
a O
familiar O
face O
in O
hope O
and O
fear O
. O

Terrible O
hours O
and O
even O
more O
terrible O
certainty O
. O

The O
last O
hope O
for O
the O
return O
of O
our O
men B-TER
, O
children B-TER
, O
and O
relatives O
disappeared O
…… O
. O

Again O
, O
the O
end O
of O
an O
illusion O
. O

A O
deep O
depression O
took O
hold O
in O
the O
camp B-LOC
, O
where O
there O
were O
thousands O
of O
people O
dying B-TER
and O
sick B-TER
with O
typhus B-TER
. O

We O
had O
to O
pull O
ourselves O
together O
and O
help O
in O
order O
to O
save O
at O
least O
the O
remainder O
of O
those O
who O
had O
survived O
, O
using O
all O
of O
the O
strength O
we O
had O
left O
. O

On O
May O
8th O
, O
we O
were O
liberated B-TER
by O
the O
Red B-ORG
Army I-ORG
. O

There O
was O
no O
real O
joy O
in O
the O
ghetto B-LOC
, O
no O
real O
jubilation O
, O
there O
was O
only O
one O
feeling O
– O
late O
, O
everything O
came O
too O
late O
. O

Only O
in O
books O
does O
liberation B-TER
arrive O
at O
the O
right O
time O
. O

Edelstein B-PER
’s I-PER
concept O
did O
n’t O
have O
to O
be O
an O
illusion O
— O
if O
the O
war B-TER
had O
ended O
at O
least O
half O
a O
year O
earlier O
, O
most O
of O
the O
Jews B-TER
of I-TER
the I-TER
Protectorate I-TER
would O
have O
been O
saved O
. O

And O
the O
rest O
of O
the O
Jews O
here O
, O
who O
survived O
the O
concentration B-TER
camps I-TER
and O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
, O
do O
they O
not O
owe O
their O
lives O
just O
a O
little O
to O
Edelstein B-PER
’s I-PER
illusion O
? O
