Unaccompanied O
child O
Registration O
No O
. O

G O
11367511 O
copy O
1 O
( O
✓ O
) O
2 O
3 O
M(x O
) O
F O
MARITAL O
STATUS O
Sing O
. O

( O
x O
) O
Mar. O
Wid O
. O

Div O
. O

SUPPLEMENTARY O
RECORD O
– O
FACE O
SHEET O
CHILD B-TER
Evidence O
of O
Verification O
Date O
Family O
or O
Surname O
LANDAU B-PER
Given O
or O
Christian O
Names O
Bernat B-PER
( I-PER
Bernard I-PER
) I-PER
Other O
Names O
Used O
Birthdate O
Day O
Month O
Year O
. O

As O
Verified O
: O
Day O
Month O
Year O
10 O
Oct. O
1928 O
Birthplace O
Town O
Province O
Country O
Birthplace O
As O
Verified O
: O
Town O
Province O
Country O
Kisvarda O
Sabolc O
Hungary B-LOC
Nationality O
Claimed O
Nationality O
Verified O
Hungarian B-TER
Jew O
Address O
in O
Country O
of O
Origin O
Prior O
to O
Displacement O
Kisvarda B-LOC
, O
Deag B-LOC
Perenc I-LOC
15 I-LOC
. O

Date O
of O
Displacement O
April O
1944 O
Present O
location O
of O
Child B-TER
including O
Name O
of O
Family B-TER
, O
Center O
or O
institution O
, O
Person O
in O
Charge O
, O
Address O
, O
Date O
arrived O
at O
this O
location O
. O

D.P. B-TER
Camp I-TER
Wolfratshausen B-LOC
, O
Team O
106 O
. O

Dir O
. O

Cohen O
. O

Germany B-LOC
July O
1945 O
Language O
usually O
spoken O
Hungarian O
, O
Hebrew O
, O
Yiddish O
, O
German O
Other O
languages O
used O
Religion O
Jewish O
Occupation O
Bookprinter O
FATHER O
FAMILY O
Family O
Name O
LANDAU B-PER
First O
Lipold B-PER
Middle O
Birthdate O
1904 O
Nationality O
Hungarian B-TER
Jew O
Last O
known O
address O
Sentendre B-LOC
, O
Hungary B-LOC
, O
Labor B-TER
camp I-TER
. O

Date O
last O
heard O
from O
1942 O
Permanent O
address O
Kisvarda B-LOC
, O
Deag B-LOC
Ferenc I-LOC
15 I-LOC
. O

Occupation O
bookbinder O
Place O
of O
Employment O
Had O
a O
printing O
and O
bookbinding O
shop O
. O

MOTHER O
Maiden O
Name O
GODINGER B-PER
Family O
Name O
LANDAU B-PER
First O
Rosa B-PER
Middle O
Birthdate O
1906 O
Nationality O
Hungarian B-TER
Jew O
Last O
known O
address O
Auschwitz B-LOC
. O

Probably O
died B-TER
there O
in O
1944 O
, O
April O
. O

Date O
last O
heard O
from O
Permanent O
address O
Kisvarda B-LOC
, O
Deag B-LOC
Ferenc I-LOC
15 I-LOC
. O

Occupation O
Place O
of O
Employment O
Other O
members O
of O
the O
immediate O
family O
and O
relatives O
. O

List O
for O
each O
the O
Name O
, O
Age O
, O
Relationship O
, O
Last O
known O
address O
, O
Former O
permanent O
address O
, O
Occupation O
and O
Employment O
, O
if O
known O
. O

( O
Continue O
on O
reverse O
side O
of O
page O
as O
necessary O
. O

) O
Lenke O
, O
22 O
, O
sister B-TER
. O

Now O
in O
Hungary B-LOC
. O

Comes O
here O
in O
next O
days O
. O

Herman O
, O
20 O
, O
brother B-TER
. O

At O
present O
in O
same O
camp B-TER
. O

Etel O
, O
19 O
, O
sister B-TER
. O

At O
present O
in O
same O
camp B-TER
. O

Father B-TER
's I-TER
brother I-TER
: O
Eugen B-PER
WEINSTOCK I-PER
, O
108 B-LOC
Lewis I-LOC
st I-LOC
. I-LOC

, O
New B-LOC
York I-LOC
City I-LOC
. O

Uncle B-TER
is O
trying O
to O
get O
affidavit B-TER
for O
all O
4 O
children B-TER
. O

Contact O
made O
. O

Face O
Sheet O
prepared O
by O
: O
Harry B-PER
Liebster I-PER
Team O
: O
567 O
Date O
: O
4 O
April O
1946 O
. O

Information O
obtained O
from O
: O
Landau B-PER
, I-PER
Bernat I-PER
First O
displacement O
: O
April O
1944 O
– O
left O
home O
with O
mother B-TER
and O
brother B-TER
and O
sisters B-TER
. O

Chronological O
record O
. O

April O
1944 O
left O
home O
with O
mother B-TER
, O
brother B-TER
and O
sisters B-TER
. O

Went O
to O
Auschwitz B-LOC
Concentration I-LOC
camp I-LOC
. O

Father B-TER
was O
taken O
to O
Hungarian B-LOC
Labor B-TER
Camp I-TER
in O
1942 O
. O

Mother B-TER
was O
separated O
from O
children B-TER
. O

He O
and O
brother B-TER
went O
to O
Dachau B-LOC
after O
3 O
weeks O
. O

Sisters B-TER
went O
to O
Leipzig B-LOC
. O

Then O
boys B-TER
to O
Allach B-LOC
; O
liberated B-TER
there O
May O
1 O
, O
1945 O
. O

Then O
went O
to O
Feldafing B-LOC
Camp I-LOC
with O
brother B-TER
. O

Sisters B-TER
came O
to O
Feldafing B-LOC
, O
arrived O
in O
Wolfratshausen B-LOC
. O

July O
1945 O
. O

Lenke O
went O
home O
to O
look B-TER
for I-TER
parents I-TER
. O

Will O
come O
back O
. O

According O
to O
last O
letter B-TER
she O
did O
not O
find O
anybody O
there O
. O

Relatives O
Uncle B-TER
Eugen B-PER
Weinstock I-PER
in O
New B-LOC
York I-LOC
City I-LOC
will O
send O
affidavit B-TER
through O
Washington B-LOC
. O

Contact O
made O
. O

Language O
Boy O
speaks O
Hungarian O
, O
German O
, O
Yiddish O
, O
Hebrew O
. O

Documents O
Certificate O
from O
Concentration B-LOC
Camp I-LOC
Dachau I-LOC
, O
dated O
9 O
Jan. O
1946 O
. O

School O
record O
8 O
year O
primary O
school B-TER
( O
Hungarian O
- O
Jewish O
) O
. O

Besides O
that O
learned O
bookprinting O
in O
father B-TER
's I-TER
shop O
. O

History O
of O
family B-TER
. O

Father B-TER
had O
a O
bookpringing O
shop O
in O
Kisvarda B-LOC
; O
besides O
that O
a O
clothing B-TER
-store O
. O

Mother B-TER
worked O
at O
home O
. O

Boy O
wants O
to O
go O
to O
the O
U.S B-LOC
. O

as O
soon O
as O
possible O
with O
his O
sisters B-TER
and O
brother B-TER
. O

Seems O
to O
be O
an O
intelligent O
boy O
, O
good O
- O
looking O
, O
well O
- O
bred O
. O

