Addressed O
to O
R. O
Ministry B-ORG
of I-ORG
Foreign I-ORG
Affairs I-ORG
, O
Rome B-LOC
. O

Bucharest O
, O
19th O
July O
1941 O
/XIX O
Re O
: O
Jewish B-TER
problem I-TER
in O
Romania B-LOC
The O
reconquest O
of O
Bukovina B-LOC
and O
of O
Bessarabia B-LOC
, O
where O
Jewish B-TER
communities I-TER
are O
particularly O
numerous O
, O
has O
prompted O
the O
Government B-TER
to O
adopt O
draconian O
anti B-TER
- I-TER
Jewish I-TER
measures I-TER
. O

The O
Jewish B-TER
- O
Communist B-TER
uprisings O
in O
Galatz B-LOC
and O
in O
Jassy B-LOC
last O
month O
( O
my O
telegrams O
no O
. O

699 O
and O
704 O
of O
29th O
and O
30th O
June O
last O
and O
no O
. O

707 O
of O
1st O
inst O
. O

) O
had O
already O
resulted O
in O
savage O
repressions B-TER
of O
a O
markedly O
anti B-TER
- I-TER
Semitic I-TER
nature O
. O

Now O
, O
although O
it O
has O
not O
been O
officially O
declared O
, O
the O
problem O
of O
cleansing B-TER
the O
eastern O
Romanian B-LOC
territories O
of O
Jews B-TER
is O
being O
tackled O
resolutely O
and O
the O
Authorities O
in O
charge O
strive O
to O
solve O
it O
as O
thoroughly O
as O
possible O
and O
do O
not O
hesitate O
to O
employ O
even O
the O
most O
drastic O
means B-TER
. O

Reportedly O
deportations B-TER
, O
expulsions O
and O
even O
executions B-TER
are O
fairly O
large O
in O
numbers O
. O

Since O
news O
of O
this O
had O
already O
begun O
to O
leak O
out O
in O
the O
other O
regions O
of O
Romania B-LOC
as O
well O
, O
it O
has O
been O
considered O
advisable O
today O
to O
make O
the O
following O
official O
announcement O
which O
attempts O
to O
give O
a O
plausible O
reason O
for O
events O
that O
are O
actually O
quite O
different O
. O

Having O
ascertained O
that O
the O
Jews O
of O
Galicia O
are O
trying O
by O
all O
available O
means O
to O
enter O
Romaniaillegally O
, O
General O
Antonescu O
has O
ordered O
that O
the O
entry O
of O
these O
elements O
into O
Romanian O
territory O
be O
absolutely O
forbidden O
. O

Jews O
who O
have O
crossed O
the O
border O
or O
who O
will O
attempt O
to O
do O
so O
will O
be O
considered O
as O
spies O
and O
shot O
. O

Border O
guards O
who O
allow O
or O
are O
not O
sufficiently O
alert O
to O
prevent O
this O
immigration O
from O
happening O
will O
be O
punished O
as O
accomplices O
and O
shot O
like O
the O
guilty O
immigrants O
. O

R. B-PER
Bova I-PER
Scoppa I-PER
