The O
things O
we O
know O
is O
far O
from O
everything O
there O
is O
… O
Told O
by O
R.H. B-PER
Dogon I-PER
in O
: O
The O
Blood O
Cries O
for O
Vengeance O
! O
: O
What O
Victims O
tell O
about O
the O
Fascist B-TER
Atrocities O
in O
the O
Occupied B-TER
Poland B-LOC
, O
collected O
and O
assembled O
by O
L. B-PER
Kvitko I-PER
, O
Y. B-PER
Nusinov I-PER
, O
and O
Y. B-PER
Katsnelson I-PER
; O
Forword O
: O
Shakhne B-PER
Epshteyn I-PER
( O
Moscow B-LOC
: O
Der O
Emes O
, O
1941 O
) O
, O
96–99 O
On O
the O
Jewish B-TER
cemetery I-TER
of O
Przemyśl B-LOC
, O
there O
is O
a O
fresh O
mass B-TER
grave I-TER
. O

This O
is O
the O
most O
horrific O
document O
of O
the O
savage O
bestiality O
of O
our O
times O
. O

In O
the O
white O
stone O
, O
small O
tablets O
are O
attached O
on O
which O
the O
names O
of O
all O
those O
are O
engraved O
who O
were O
murdered B-TER
in O
a O
horrific O
way O
during O
the O
14 O
days O
of O
German B-TER
occupation B-TER
in O
September O
1939 O
. O

Who O
knows O
, O
how O
many O
would O
have O
been O
added O
to O
their O
number O
, O
if O
the O
Red B-TER
Army I-TER
had O
not O
pulled O
out O
this O
bloody O
piece O
of O
land O
from O
Hitlerites B-TER
’ I-TER
paws O
. O

Ten O
little O
tables O
on O
the O
mass B-TER
grave I-TER
are O
entirely O
empty O
, O
– O
no O
name O
is O
engraved O
on O
them O
. O

They O
were O
people O
who O
did O
not O
have O
any O
documents O
on O
them O
, O
and O
their O
bodies B-TER
were O
so O
crumbled O
up O
that O
one O
could O
not O
establish O
who O
they O
were O
. O

In O
those O
terrible O
days O
, O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
men I-ORG
drove O
around O
the O
city B-LOC
like O
bloodthirsty O
rascals O
. O

They B-TER
snapped I-TER
up I-TER
people I-TER
they I-TER
coincidentally I-TER
bumped I-TER
into I-TER
, I-TER
arranged I-TER
them I-TER
in I-TER
rows I-TER
, O
gave O
the O
order O
hands O
on O
the O
neck O
and O
let O
them O
stand O
like O
this O
for O
several O
hours O
. O

At O
the O
same O
time O
, O
other O
Gestapo B-ORG
- I-ORG
men I-ORG
entered O
different O
houses O
and O
dragged O
out O
people O
from O
them O
, O
– O
very O
often O
it O
was O
sick B-TER
people O
dragged O
from O
their O
beds O
. O

They O
loaded O
the O
people O
group O
by O
group O
on O
trucks O
and O
drove O
them O
out O
of O
the O
city B-LOC
, O
ostensibly O
to O
work B-TER
. O

No B-TER
one I-TER
of I-TER
them I-TER
came I-TER
back I-TER
alive I-TER
, O
however O
. O

There O
, O
they O
were O
arranged O
in O
rows O
of O
five O
. O

They O
ordered O
the O
first O
five O
to O
dig O
up O
graves O
for O
themselves O
, O
shot B-TER
at I-TER
them I-TER
with I-TER
dumdum I-TER
bullets I-TER
, I-TER
pulled I-TER
out I-TER
their I-TER
eyes I-TER
alive I-TER
, I-TER
cut I-TER
off I-TER
limbs I-TER
, I-TER
cut I-TER
out I-TER
tongues I-TER
. O

The O
survivors O
of O
the O
last O
row O
had O
to O
hastily O
bury B-TER
the O
dead B-TER
and O
prepare O
graves O
for O
themselves O
again O
until O
everyone O
was O
dead B-TER
. O

This O
way O
, O
a O
father B-TER
had O
to O
witness O
the O
early O
death B-TER
of O
his O
son B-TER
; O
a O
brother B-TER
had O
to O
bury B-TER
his O
brother B-TER
with O
his O
hands O
before O
he O
himself O
perished B-TER
from O
the O
murderous B-TER
hands I-TER
. O

Only O
from O
one O
family B-TER
with O
the O
name O
of O
Soyfer B-PER
, O
the O
Hitlerites B-TER
killed B-TER
a O
father B-TER
, O
a O
son B-TER
, O
and O
a O
son B-TER
- I-TER
in I-TER
- I-TER
law I-TER
simultaneously O
. O

The O
dry O
goods O
merchant O
Zaltsberg B-PER
, O
a O
calm O
, O
quiet O
, O
and O
in O
the O
city B-LOC
well O
- O
respected O
man B-TER
, O
was O
found O
with O
his O
hands O
around O
the O
throat O
of O
his O
19 B-TER
- I-TER
year I-TER
old I-TER
son I-TER
. O

This O
son B-TER
, O
a O
student B-TER
, O
had O
a O
reputation O
as O
a O
very O
talented O
mathematician O
, O
and O
not O
only O
his O
parents B-TER
prided O
themselves O
with O
him O
; O
his O
professors O
predicted O
a O
career O
of O
a O
scientist O
. O

I O
myself O
saw O
how O
one O
of O
his O
teachers O
, O
the O
Ukrainian B-TER
Makhnatski B-PER
, O
brought O
flowers O
to O
his O
grave O
on O
his O
yortsayt O
anniversary O
of O
death O
. O

. O

Grosman B-PER
, O
a O
quiet O
, O
sick B-TER
person O
, O
who O
did O
nothing O
else O
in O
his O
life O
than O
studying O
books O
, O
was O
dragged O
out O
from O
his O
sickbed B-TER
. O

Ignoring O
the O
pleas O
and O
laments O
of O
his O
old O
, O
disabled O
mother B-TER
, O
who O
is O
not O
able O
to O
move O
and O
for O
whom O
the O
son B-TER
was O
her O
only O
support O
, O
he O
was O
taken O
away O
and O
killed B-TER
. O

The O
Gestapo B-ORG
summoned O
the O
70 O
- O
year O
old O
Nekhemye B-PER
Rozenboym I-PER
and O
informed O
him B-PER
that O
he O
has O
to O
take O
care O
of O
the O
burial B-TER
of O
the O
murdered B-TER
and O
at O
the O
very O
end O
a O
bullet B-TER
awaits I-TER
him I-TER
as I-TER
well I-TER
. O

They O
made O
Rozenboym B-PER
and O
several O
other O
Jews O
stand O
with O
their O
faces O
turned O
to O
the O
wall O
and O
ordered O
them O
to O
say O
vide O
confession O
of O
sin O
said O
collectively O
on O
Yom O
Kippur O
and O
individually O
before O
dying O
. O

, O
because O
they O
would O
be O
shot B-TER
in O
15 O
minutes O
. O

While O
the O
Jews O
said O
vide O
, O
the O
murderers B-TER
prepared O
their O
rifles O
, O
whilst B-TER
making I-TER
fun I-TER
of O
their O
victims B-TER
, O
and O
made O
all O
necessary O
preparations O
for O
the O
execution B-TER
. O

Suddenly O
, O
they O
were O
summoned O
from O
someone O
and O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
men I-ORG
left O
behind O
those O
sentenced O
to O
death B-TER
. O

The O
Jews O
did O
not O
dare O
to O
move O
from O
the O
spot O
convinced O
that O
this O
is O
something O
of O
a O
new O
trick O
of O
the O
bloodhounds O
. O

When O
no O
one O
came O
back O
after O
some O
time O
, O
they O
left O
and O
to O
this O
day O
they O
can O
not O
say O
whether O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
intentionally O
plotted O
this O
game O
or O
whether O
they O
simply O
forgot O
about O
them O
because O
a O
new O
game O
came O
up O
. O

A O
woman B-TER
( O
I O
forgot O
her O
name O
) O
went O
to O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
, O
– O
she O
wanted O
to O
plead O
for O
the O
release O
of O
her O
husband B-TER
from O
their O
hands O
. O

So O
they O
suggested O
to O
her O
that O
she O
should O
bring O
ransom O
in O
the O
amount O
of O
four O
thousand O
Złoty O
. O

The O
woman B-TER
, O
who O
never O
in O
her O
life O
possessed O
such O
a O
sum O
of O
money O
, O
decided O
to O
do O
the O
impossible O
in O
order O
to O
save O
her O
husband B-TER
. O

She O
sold O
everything O
from O
her O
home O
, O
remained O
with O
one O
shirt B-TER
and O
one O
dress B-TER
, O
but O
it O
did O
not O
suffice O
. O

So O
people O
pooled O
however O
much O
one O
could O
afford O
and O
we O
gathered O
the O
necessary O
sum O
of O
money O
. O

On O
the O
second O
day O
, O
the O
woman B-TER
came O
to O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
with O
money O
. O

They O
took B-TER
the I-TER
money I-TER
from I-TER
her I-TER
and O
ordered O
her O
to O
come O
back O
tomorrow O
. O

Then O
they O
will O
release O
her O
husband B-TER
. O

The O
next O
day O
, O
they O
ordered O
her O
to O
wait O
a O
little O
in O
the O
corridor O
. O

Suddenly O
, O
she O
heard O
from O
above O
her O
coming O
from O
the O
first O
floor O
a O
mocking O
laughter O
: O
Here O
you O
have O
your O
husband O
. O

Then O
, O
at O
the O
same O
time O
, O
she O
saw O
something O
dark O
rolling O
down O
the O
stairs O
. O

The O
horribly O
mutilated O
dead B-TER
body I-TER
of O
her O
husband B-TER
rolled O
towards O
her O
feet O
. O

It O
became O
clear O
that O
at O
the O
point O
that O
they O
conducted O
the O
negotiations O
regarding O
the O
ransom O
with O
the O
woman B-TER
, O
her O
husband B-TER
had O
already O
not O
been O
alive O
anymore O
. O

In O
those O
days O
, O
in O
the O
city O
of O
Przemyśl B-LOC
alone O
580 O
people O
were O
killed B-TER
. O

Only O
a O
part O
of O
them O
have O
been O
able O
to O
be O
buried B-TER
so O
far O
– O
168 O
, O
because O
the O
Nazis B-TER
did O
not O
kill B-TER
their O
victims B-TER
in O
one O
place O
but O
dragged O
them O
into O
woods O
and O
to O
fields O
and O
deserted O
mountains O
. O

Those O
, O
who O
were O
found O
, O
were O
found O
thanks O
to O
the O
peasants O
who O
after O
the O
Germans B-TER
had O
left O
pointed O
to O
the O
locations O
from O
where O
wild O
clamor O
and O
shootings O
were O
heard O
. O

Women B-TER
, O
mothers B-TER
, O
daughters B-TER
, O
fathers B-TER
, O
sons B-TER
walking O
around O
the O
fields O
, O
teared O
open O
the O
freshly O
closed O
soil O
and O
searched O
for O
traces O
of O
their O
relatives O
. O

Finding O
mutilated O
bodies B-TER
with O
teared O
- O
out O
eyes O
, O
cut O
- O
out O
tongues O
and O
cut O
- O
off O
limbs O
, O
it O
was O
difficult O
, O
however O
, O
to O
recognize O
the O
former O
individuals O
. O

In O
the O
small O
shtetl O
Dynów B-LOC
, O
the O
Hitlerites B-TER
massacred B-TER
approximately O
400 O
people O
, O
among O
them O
very O
many O
refugees B-TER
– O
from O
Western B-LOC
Poland I-LOC
. O

In O
the O
shtetl O
Milicz B-LOC
, O
the O
Hitlerites B-TER
chased O
70 O
Jews O
into O
the O
beys B-LOC
- I-LOC
medresh I-LOC
, O
among O
them O
many O
old B-TER
men I-TER
, O
locked O
them O
in O
and O
set O
the O
building O
on O
fire O
from O
all O
sides O
. O

Everyone O
burnt B-TER
to O
death B-TER
alive O
. O

The O
Jewish B-TER
writer I-TER
Y. B-PER
Keytlman I-PER
’s O
sister B-TER
, O
a O
young O
girl B-TER
who O
did O
not O
live O
far O
, O
got O
so O
upset O
from O
this O
calamity O
that O
she O
went O
insane O
. O

She O
was O
in O
Lviv B-LOC
in O
a O
mental B-TER
hospital I-TER
. O

In O
the O
city O
Przemyśl B-LOC
, O
the O
Hitlerites B-TER
set O
the O
old O
synagogue B-TER
from O
the O
15th O
century O
on O
fire B-TER
, O
which O
was O
of O
great O
artistic O
value O
. O

When O
the O
firemen O
started O
to O
extinguish O
the O
fire O
, O
Nazis B-TER
came O
running O
and O
cut O
open O
the O
rubber O
hose O
with O
knives O
. O

In O
the O
city O
of O
Jarosław B-LOC
, O
the O
Hitlerite B-TER
general O
was O
killed B-TER
. O

Since O
no O
traces O
of O
the O
one O
behind O
it O
could O
be O
found O
, O
all O
Polish B-TER
students B-TER
of O
the O
gymnasium B-TER
were O
gathered O
, O
boys B-TER
in O
the O
ages O
from O
12 O
to O
18 O
, O
and O
every O
tenth O
of O
them O
was O
shot B-TER
to I-TER
death I-TER
. O

We O
know O
little O
about O
the O
things O
that O
are O
happening O
right O
now O
in O
these O
territories O
because O
the O
people O
who O
managed O
to O
save O
themselves O
, O
escaped B-TER
on O
the O
eve O
the O
Hitlerite B-TER
invasion O
. O

I O
spoke O
to O
a O
Jew O
from O
Przemyśl B-LOC
, O
the O
butcher O
Broyn B-PER
, O
who O
was O
with O
the O
Germans B-TER
for O
24 O
hours O
before O
the O
Red B-TER
Army I-TER
took O
back O
the O
city B-LOC
. O

Immediately O
after O
the O
entry O
into O
the O
city B-LOC
, O
on O
Sunday O
, O
June O
22 O
, O
the O
Hitlerites B-TER
shot B-TER
everyone O
who O
appeared O
on O
the O
streets O
. O

Many O
Ukrainians B-TER
and O
Poles B-TER
died O
who O
went O
out O
to O
welcome O
them O
convinced O
that O
the O
Hitlerites B-TER
would O
receive O
them O
well O
. O

From O
Slovatskega B-LOC
Street I-LOC
No I-LOC
. I-LOC

7 I-LOC
, O
the O
Hitlerites B-TER
dragged O
out O
all O
residents O
and O
chased O
them O
to O
the O
other O
side O
of O
the O
river O
San B-LOC
. O

The O
son B-TER
of O
the O
Nayshteter O
rabbi B-TER
tried O
to O
escape B-TER
. O

They O
caught O
him O
and O
got O
ready O
to O
shoot B-TER
him O
in O
front O
of O
everyone O
’s O
eyes O
. O

An O
elderly O
lady B-TER
with O
the O
name O
of O
Zirber B-PER
threw O
herself O
to O
their O
feet O
and O
begged O
them O
to O
give O
him O
life O
. O

They O
shot B-TER
both O
dead B-TER
. O

