Protocol O
No O
. O

171 O
Pese B-PER
R. I-PER
, O
Suwałki B-LOC
8–2–1940 O
Homeowner O
Now O
: O
Vilnius B-LOC
On O
October O
4 O
or O
5 O
, O
1939 O
, O
the O
Russians B-TER
left O
Suwałki B-LOC
. O

Before O
they O
left O
the O
city B-LOC
, O
they O
ceremonially O
transferred O
the O
city B-LOC
to O
the O
delegates O
of O
the O
German B-TER
army B-TER
on O
Magistrate B-LOC
Square I-LOC
. O

Thereafter O
, O
bigger O
German B-TER
army B-TER
detachments O
entered O
Suwałki B-LOC
. O

The O
initial O
two O
- O
three O
days O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
behaved O
calmly O
and O
did O
not O
bother O
anyone O
. O

They O
only O
issued O
decrees B-TER
that O
when O
Jews O
encounter O
a O
German B-TER
soldier O
on O
the O
street O
, O
they O
have O
to O
go O
down O
from O
the O
sidewalk O
and O
take O
their O
hats O
off O
. O

Simultaneously O
, O
they O
decreed B-TER
for O
all O
shops O
to O
open O
. O

The O
residents O
immediately O
opened O
the O
stores O
. O

Then O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
went O
into O
each O
Jewish O
shop O
, O
took O
the O
cash O
from O
the O
check O
- O
outs O
, O
expelled O
the O
owners O
and O
locked O
the O
stores O
after O
having O
taken O
possession O
of O
the O
keys O
. O

They O
did O
not O
touch O
the O
Christian B-TER
stores O
. O

My O
cousin B-TER
Genye B-PER
Viner I-PER
owned O
a O
rather O
big O
haberdashery O
store O
on O
Kashtshyushka B-LOC
Street I-LOC
10 I-LOC
( O
now O
General O
Bransch O
- O
Straße O
) O
. O

Her O
husband B-TER
enlisted O
to O
the O
Polish B-TER
army B-TER
and O
was O
killed B-TER
near O
Warsaw B-LOC
. O

And O
she O
remained O
a O
widow O
with O
two O
small O
children B-TER
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
entered O
also O
her O
store O
, O
just O
as O
they O
did O
with O
the O
others O
, O
took O
from O
the O
check O
- O
out O
counter O
several O
thousand O
Złoty O
as O
well O
as O
all O
her O
merchandise O
. O

My O
cousin B-TER
went O
to O
the O
German B-TER
captain O
and O
requested O
to O
at O
least O
return O
the O
cash O
to O
her O
since O
she O
was O
a O
miserable O
widow O
with O
two O
orphans B-TER
. O

The O
captain O
wanted O
to O
pay O
her O
back O
thirty O
Złoty O
. O

And O
when O
she O
started O
crying O
claiming O
that O
she O
wo O
n’t O
be O
able O
to O
do O
anything O
with O
such O
a O
small O
sum O
, O
he O
cynically O
replied O
: O
You O
can O
buy O
a O
rope O
with O
the O
money O
and O
hang O
yourself O
. O

I O
myself O
had O
a O
store O
for O
candy B-TER
, O
fruits B-TER
and O
wine O
in O
my O
house O
. O

The O
first O
days O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
did O
not O
bother O
me O
thinking O
that O
mine O
was O
a O
Christian B-TER
store O
. O

Later O
, O
though O
, O
they O
came O
into O
my O
store O
and O
took O
away O
all O
my O
merchandise O
. O

They O
also O
conducted O
a O
search O
in O
my O
home O
looking O
for O
gold O
and O
merchandise O
. O

Soon O
after O
their O
arrival O
in O
the O
city O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
imposed O
taxes O
on O
Jewish O
homeowners O
. O

From O
myself O
they O
demanded O
20 O
thousand O
Mark O
, O
to O
which O
I O
in O
turn O
gave O
an O
advance O
of O
800 O
Guilds O
. O

Whole O
days O
, O
the O
Jews O
remained O
locked O
in O
in O
their O
apartment O
because O
they O
were O
snatched O
up O
for O
the O
dirtiest O
kind O
of O
work B-TER
on O
the O
streets O
. O

They O
did O
not O
even O
spare O
women B-TER
and O
children B-TER
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
also O
started O
to O
go O
to O
the O
homes O
of O
the O
rich O
Jews O
and O
robbed B-TER
everything O
they O
could O
. O

Many O
Jews O
, O
unable O
to O
take O
it O
any O
longer O
, O
began O
to O
flee O
to O
the O
Soviet B-TER
territories O
. O

In O
the O
first O
days O
of O
the O
month O
December O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
suddenly O
issued O
a O
decree B-TER
that O
the O
Jews O
should O
store O
up O
food B-TER
for O
three O
days O
. O

In O
the O
city O
, O
there O
was O
a O
turmoil O
. O

One O
did O
not O
know O
what O
this O
meant O
. O

I O
went O
into O
the O
city O
in O
order O
to O
go O
shopping O
but O
on O
the O
way O
I O
noticed O
how O
the O
German B-TER
police O
led O
Jews O
, O
Jewish O
women B-TER
and O
children B-TER
. O

The O
turmoil O
got O
even O
bigger O
. O

People O
started O
saying O
that O
all O
Jews O
will O
be O
expelled O
from O
the O
city B-LOC
and O
sent O
away O
to O
the O
Lublin B-LOC
Reservation I-LOC
. O

I O
immediately O
returned O
home O
and O
started O
preparing O
myself O
and O
the O
children B-TER
for O
the O
journey O
. O

Soon O
, O
the O
Christian B-TER
woman B-TER
from O
next O
door O
came O
running O
to O
me O
and O
said O
that O
the O
Germans B-TER
are O
already O
coming O
for O
me O
. O

I O
managed O
to O
escape O
with O
my O
children B-TER
from O
the O
apartment O
through O
the O
backdoor O
and O
hid B-TER
in O
the O
basement O
. O

Not O
everyone O
was O
as O
lucky O
. O

Hundreds O
of O
Jews O
with O
their O
families B-TER
were O
chased O
by O
the O
Germans B-TER
to O
the O
synagogue B-TER
courtyard I-TER
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
did O
not O
allow O
them O
to O
take O
any O
baggage O
– O
hitting O
the O
old O
and O
weak O
with O
whips O
if O
they O
were O
not O
able O
to O
walk O
fast O
enough O
. O

I O
was O
laying O
with O
my O
children B-TER
in O
the O
basement O
until O
3 O
am O
when O
an O
acquainted O
Christian B-TER
led O
me O
out O
. O

I O
did O
not O
go O
back O
into O
my O
apartment O
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
had O
looted B-TER
it O
entirely O
in O
the O
interim O
and O
sealed O
the O
doors O
afterwards O
. O

On O
circuitous O
routes O
, O
I O
, O
together O
with O
my O
children B-TER
, O
ran O
away O
and O
we O
met O
many O
acquaintances O
on O
our O
way O
who O
had O
also O
succeeded O
in B-TER
hiding I-TER
from O
the O
Germans B-TER
. O

We O
arrived O
in O
a O
village O
located O
four O
kilometres O
outside O
of O
Suwałki B-LOC
and O
there O
we O
hid B-TER
for O
2 O
days O
. O

In O
the O
village O
, O
we O
later O
got O
a O
ride O
and O
drove O
to O
the O
Lithuanian B-LOC
border B-TER
to O
the O
village O
Madani B-LOC
uncertain O
. O

We O
drove O
for O
2 O
days O
because O
driving O
was O
only O
possible O
at O
night O
. O

In O
the O
daytime O
, O
German B-TER
patrols O
stopped O
[ O
everyone O
] O
and O
sent O
them O
back O
to O
Suwałki B-LOC
. O

All O
in O
all O
, O
we O
were O
50 O
individuals O
at O
the O
Lithuanian B-LOC
border B-TER
. O

From O
the O
remaining O
Suwałki B-LOC
Jews O
– O
around O
3 O
thousand O
persons O
were O
arrested B-TER
by O
the O
Germans B-TER
and O
sent O
off O
to O
the O
Lublin B-LOC
border B-TER
. O

10 O
individuals O
saved O
themselves O
on O
the O
last O
day O
by O
running O
to O
the O
Soviet B-TER
border B-TER
. O

2 O
of O
them O
– O
a O
woman B-TER
called O
Dine B-PER
Maryampolsky I-PER
and O
Keltshinski B-PER
, I-PER
a O
shipping O
clerk O
– O
tragically O
died B-TER
. O

The O
small O
boat O
, O
with O
which O
they O
wanted O
to O
cross O
the O
river O
Varta B-LOC
uncertain O
, O
capsized O
and O
they O
drowned B-TER
. O

We O
, O
on O
the O
other O
hand O
, O
who O
came O
to O
the O
Lithuanian B-LOC
border B-TER
, O
wandered O
about O
no O
man O
’s O
land O
for O
three O
weeks O
in O
horrible O
conditions B-TER
. O

Kotlinska B-PER
, O
an O
elderly O
lady B-TER
, O
got O
ill B-TER
there O
and O
died B-TER
. O

We O
also O
buried O
her O
in O
no O
man O
’s O
land O
. O

Blumberg B-PER
, O
owner O
of O
a O
big O
glass O
- O
store O
, O
committed B-TER
suicide I-TER
, O
and O
his O
wife B-TER
went O
insane O
from O
her O
sufferings O
. O

Also O
the O
dentist O
Shtern B-PER
from O
Suwałki B-LOC
went O
insane O
. O

At O
the O
Lithuanian B-LOC
border B-TER
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
arrested B-TER
me O
and O
my O
daughter B-TER
and O
they O
took O
all O
the O
money O
that O
I O
had O
and O
then O
sent O
us O
back O
to O
Suwałki B-LOC
. O

Coming O
to O
Suwałki B-LOC
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
wanted O
to O
send O
me O
off O
to O
Lublin B-LOC
. O

But O
after O
much O
supplicating O
and O
pleading O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
took O
me O
and O
my O
daughter B-TER
back O
to O
the O
Lithuanian B-LOC
border B-TER
, I-TER
and O
this O
time O
I O
made O
it O
to O
Lithuania B-LOC
. O

Being O
in O
Suwałki B-LOC
for O
the O
second O
time O
, O
I O
learned O
that O
in O
the O
synagogue B-TER
there O
were O
still O
60 O
arrested B-TER
Jews O
sitting O
to O
be O
sent O
off O
to O
Lublin B-LOC
. O

The O
Jews O
there O
literally O
died B-TER
of O
hunger B-TER
. O

At O
the O
same O
time O
, O
the O
Jews O
from O
Kalvarija B-LOC
( O
Lithuania B-LOC
) O
did O
a O
lot O
. O

They O
sent O
special O
envoys O
to O
Suwałki B-LOC
. O

And O
the O
last O
one O
rescued O
the O
Jews O
one O
by O
one O
and O
took O
them O
across O
to O
Lithuania B-TER
. O

In O
general O
, O
the O
Jews O
in O
Kalvarija B-LOC
did O
a O
lot O
for O
the O
Jewish O
refugees B-TER
from O
Suwałki B-LOC
. O

Signed O
: O
P.R. B-PER
