Protocol O
No O
. O

4 O
Taken O
by O
– O
Katshikovitsh B-PER
, I-PER
Pinhas I-PER
Related O
by O
Mrs. B-PER
Midl I-PER
– O
Chortkiv B-LOC
, O
Tarnopol B-LOC
region I-LOC
Born O
1908 O
( O
October O
) O
In O
1941 O
, O
when O
the O
Russian B-TER
- O
German B-TER
war B-TER
broke O
out O
, O
my O
husband B-TER
was O
mobilized O
into O
the O
Soviet B-ORG
military I-ORG
and O
I O
, O
with O
my O
two O
children B-TER
– O
a O
daughter B-TER
aged O
seven O
and O
a O
boy B-TER
aged O
three O
years O
old O
– O
remained O
alone O
, O
living O
at O
home O
in O
the O
shtetl O
of O
Chortkiv B-LOC
– O
western O
Ukraine B-LOC
. O

I O
survived O
innumerable O
slaughters B-TER
. O

The O
first O
Jewish O
victims B-TER
in O
our O
shtetl O
fell O
only O
a O
few O
days O
after O
the O
occupation B-TER
of O
our O
region O
by O
the O
Germans B-TER
. O

They O
ordered O
a O
few O
hundred O
Jewish O
men B-TER
to O
gather O
in O
a O
square O
– O
for O
work B-TER
. O

The O
men B-TER
gathered O
in O
the O
square O
, O
but O
instead O
of O
taking O
them O
to O
work B-TER
, O
they O
took O
them O
to O
prison B-TER
, O
and O
later O
the O
Germans B-TER
, O
together O
with O
the O
local B-TER
Ukrainians I-TER
, O
murdered B-TER
them O
in O
a O
brutal O
fashion O
. O

And O
they O
buried B-TER
some I-TER
alive I-TER
. O

These O
were O
the O
best O
people B-TER
from O
our O
city O
. O

A O
few O
days O
later O
, O
we O
received O
news O
from O
my O
home O
town O
– O
Zalishchyky B-LOC
– O
five O
kilometers O
from O
us O
, O
where O
my O
parents B-TER
and O
sisters B-TER
still O
lived O
, O
that O
the O
gestapo B-ORG
there O
had O
issued O
an O
order B-TER
: O
five O
hundred O
Jews O
should O
come O
to O
clean B-TER
the I-TER
barracks I-TER
. O

If O
they O
would O
not O
heed O
the O
command O
, O
they O
would O
kill B-TER
all O
the O
Jews O
of O
the O
shtetl O
. O

The O
order B-TER
was O
fulfilled O
and O
all O
five O
hundred O
Jews O
were O
taken O
to O
a O
place O
outside O
the O
city O
. O

They O
lined O
them O
up O
ten O
in O
a O
row O
, O
one O
behind O
the O
other O
, O
and O
each O
row O
was O
shot B-TER
with O
one O
bullet O
– O
obviously O
, O
from O
such O
shooting O
most O
were O
only O
wounded O
, O
and O
some O
were O
not O
even O
touched O
, O
but O
the O
Germans B-TER
ignored O
this O
and O
buried B-TER
them I-TER
all I-TER
alive I-TER
. O

Among O
the O
victims B-TER
were O
my O
father B-TER
and O
my O
two O
younger O
sisters B-TER
– O
aged O
eighteen O
and O
twenty O
years O
old O
. O

In O
March O
1942 O
, O
they O
carried O
out O
among O
us O
in O
the O
shtetl O
the O
first O
formal O
slaughter B-TER
. O

And O
immediately O
after O
this O
they O
ordered B-TER
us O
to O
move O
into O
the O
ghetto B-TER
. O

I O
went O
to O
the O
ghetto B-TER
with O
my O
children B-TER
. O

The O
conditions B-TER
there O
were O
terrible O
, O
but O
they O
did O
not O
allow O
us O
to O
stay O
for O
long O
in O
one O
place O
. O

After O
only O
six O
weeks O
they O
sent O
me O
( O
together O
with O
my O
children B-TER
) O
, O
along O
with O
a O
group O
of O
women B-TER
, O
to O
Zalischyky B-LOC
. O

After O
laboring B-TER
three O
months O
in O
Zalischyky B-LOC
, O
in O
September O
1942 O
an O
order B-TER
arrived O
that O
the O
camp B-TER
there O
must O
be O
free B-TER
of I-TER
Jews I-TER
[ O
Judenrein B-TER
] O
. O

Then O
they O
sent O
us O
to O
Tovste B-LOC
( O
Toist B-LOC
) O
. O

Tovste B-LOC
was O
an O
assembly O
point O
for O
the O
murder B-TER
of O
Jews O
. O

And O
we O
arrived O
here O
exactly O
as O
they O
were O
carrying O
out O
an O
extermination B-TER
- O
aktion B-TER
. O

I O
managed O
to O
hide B-TER
, O
together O
with O
my O
children B-TER
. O

We O
did O
not O
rest O
for O
long O
: O
in O
a O
few O
weeks O
’ O
time O
– O
it O
was O
exactly O
one O
day O
after O
Simchat B-TER
Torah I-TER
– O
there O
once O
again O
took O
place O
here O
a O
slaughter B-TER
, O
during O
which O
over O
2,000 O
Jews O
were O
killed B-TER
. O

The O
panic O
in O
the O
city O
was O
terrible O
, O
because O
no O
one O
had O
imagined O
that O
so O
quickly O
, O
after O
such O
a O
short O
breathing O
space O
, O
another O
slaughter B-TER
would O
take O
pace O
. O

I O
hid B-TER
in O
a O
cellar O
, O
together O
with O
my O
children B-TER
and O
another O
seven O
people B-TER
, O
altogether O
there O
were O
ten O
of O
us O
. O

That O
winter O
we O
remained O
in O
Tovste B-LOC
. O

In O
the O
beginning O
of O
May O
1943 O
, O
there O
again O
took O
place O
here O
a O
great O
slaughter B-TER
. O

My O
family B-TER
, O
the O
three O
of O
us O
, O
hid B-TER
in O
an O
attack O
and O
thus O
survived O
. O

Lying O
here O
a O
few O
days O
, O
my O
younger O
child B-TER
seemed O
to O
understand O
the O
situation O
and O
did O
not O
even O
ask O
for O
water B-TER
. O

During O
the O
time O
in O
the O
attic B-TER
we O
heard O
heart O
- O
rending O
cries O
, O
screams O
, O
and O
calls O
for O
help O
. O

Many O
of O
the O
victims B-TER
fled B-TER
, O
but O
the O
local B-TER
population I-TER
– O
the O
Ukrainians B-TER
– O
chased O
after O
them O
, O
beat O
them O
, O
and O
later O
murdered B-TER
them O
in O
a O
terrible O
fashion O
. O

Those O
few O
Jews O
who O
remained O
alive O
, O
in O
hiding B-TER
, O
were O
later O
sorted B-TER
: O
the O
older O
people B-TER
[ O
word O
missing O
] O
were O
sent O
to O
Chortkiv B-LOC
and O
the O
younger O
to O
the O
camps B-TER
. O

Together O
with O
my O
family B-TER
, O
I O
stole B-TER
out I-TER
from O
the O
camp B-TER
and O
night O
and O
alone O
we O
set O
out O
for O
Lysivtsi B-LOC
, O
seven O
kilometers O
from O
Tovste B-LOC
. O

For O
six O
weeks O
it O
was O
calm O
and O
then O
they O
again O
began O
a O
Jewish- O
aktion B-TER
. O

We O
fled B-TER
from O
the O
city O
with O
a O
group O
of O
people B-TER
, O
but O
we O
were O
noticed O
by O
the O
Germans B-TER
and O
they O
immediately O
opened O
fire O
on O
us O
with O
machine O
guns O
. O

Straight O
away O
there O
were O
32 O
victims B-TER
from O
our O
group O
. O

Among O
them O
was O
my O
mother B-TER
. O

My O
daughter B-TER
was O
hit O
by O
a O
bullet O
in O
her O
foot O
, O
but O
we O
were O
already O
in O
the O
field O
. O

We O
hid B-TER
among O
the O
crops O
until O
nightfall O
. O

At O
night O
, O
with O
great O
effort O
, O
we O
returned O
to O
Tovste B-LOC
. O

The O
first O
medical B-TER
help I-TER
that O
my O
daughter B-TER
received O
was O
from O
Doctor B-TER
Greenberg B-PER
. O

And O
only O
thanks O
to O
the O
doctor B-TER
’s O
extraordinary O
efforts O
was O
it O
possible O
to O
save O
the O
foot O
– O
she O
only O
lost O
her O
toes O
. O

Later O
, O
when O
the O
situation O
in O
Tovste B-LOC
was O
again O
in O
a O
state O
of O
tension O
– O
we O
once O
more O
left O
for O
Lysivtsi B-LOC
. O

In O
Lysivtsi B-LOC
there O
was O
still O
a O
camp B-TER
of O
200 O
Jews O
, O
who O
worked B-TER
at O
agricultural O
labor O
– O
the O
men B-TER
in O
the O
stables O
and O
the O
women B-TER
in O
the O
fields O
. O

We O
received O
food B-TER
once I-TER
per I-TER
day I-TER
. O

The O
Ukrainian B-ORG
police I-ORG
would O
very O
often O
fall O
upon O
our O
camp B-TER
and O
murder B-TER
whoever O
fell O
into O
their O
hands O
. O

Likewise O
due O
to O
the O
hunger B-TER
and O
terrible O
living B-TER
conditions I-TER
a O
typhus B-TER
epidemic B-TER
broke O
out O
– O
here O
the O
Ukrainians B-TER
did O
not O
take O
care O
of O
the O
sick B-TER
Word O
missing O
. O

and O
anyone O
who O
became O
ill B-TER
was O
immediately O
murdered B-TER
. O

No O
one O
reacted O
to O
all O
of O
this O
, O
because O
the O
law O
was O
to O
beat O
the O
Jews O
. O

March O
1 O
, O
1944 O
, O
when O
the O
Soviet B-ORG
Armies I-ORG
advanced O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
and O
Ukrainians B-TER
together O
with O
the O
Vlasovites B-PER
became O
completely O
wild O
and O
dealt O
out O
murder B-TER
right O
and O
left O
. O

They O
caught O
a O
Jewish O
woman B-TER
from O
Vienna B-LOC
– O
Mali O
– O
with O
her O
son B-TER
and O
shot B-TER
Should O
be O
slaughtered O
them O
. O

A O
woman B-TER
– O
Shechter O
– O
from O
the O
shtetl O
– O
Igolnitz O
– O
they O
cut B-TER
off I-TER
her O
ears O
and O
nose O
and O
afterwards O
murdered B-TER
her O
. O

A O
young O
man B-TER
from O
Tovste B-LOC
– O
Isaiah B-PER
Rozenstok I-PER
– O
they B-TER
cut B-TER
off I-TER
his I-TER
head I-TER
; O
another O
young O
man B-TER
from O
Tovste B-LOC
– O
Voltshe B-PER
Malier I-PER
– O
they O
tied B-TER
him I-TER
to O
a O
horse B-TER
and O
murdered B-TER
him O
together O
with O
the O
horse B-TER
, O
they O
stabbed O
another O
middle O
aged O
Jew O
from O
Tovste B-LOC
with O
a O
bayonet B-TER
. O

A O
Hungarian B-TER
Jewish O
doctor B-TER
managed O
to O
save O
the O
last O
of O
these O
. O

The O
few O
Jews O
who O
remained O
alive O
– O
around O
two O
hundred O
– O
they O
again O
gathered O
them O
in O
Tovste B-LOC
in O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

For O
eight O
days O
we O
were O
watched O
over O
by O
a O
group O
of O
old O
Germans B-TER
– O
Wehrmacht B-ORG
– O
because O
the O
young O
one O
had O
been O
called O
to O
the O
front O
. O

March O
23 O
, O
1944 O
, O
the O
Soviets B-ORG
liberated B-TER
our O
region O
. O

We O
were O
barley O
eight O
days O
with O
the O
Soviets B-ORG
when O
the O
Germans B-TER
again O
renewed O
their O
attack O
and O
the O
shtetl O
once O
again O
passed O
to O
their O
hands O
. O

Then O
, O
in O
a O
burning B-TER
frost I-TER
, I-TER
starving I-TER
, I-TER
exhausted I-TER
, I-TER
naked I-TER
, I-TER
and I-TER
barefoot I-TER
, O
we O
fled B-TER
for O
60 O
kilometers O
to O
Chernivtsi B-LOC
. O

Many O
of O
us O
froze O
and O
were O
left O
on O
the O
way O
. O

We O
remained O
in O
Chernivtsi B-LOC
until O
the O
end O
of O
the O
war B-TER
. O

