Protocol O
Number O
220 O
12 O
- O
3 O
- O
40 O
Yitskhok O
R. O
, O
26 O
years O
old O
Head O
of O
a O
tannery O
Warsaw B-LOC
Now O
: O
X O
I O
was O
in O
Warsaw B-LOC
from O
the O
outbreak O
of O
the O
war B-TER
until O
the O
Germans B-TER
entered O
the O
city B-LOC
. O

On O
the O
morning O
of O
the O
German B-TER
invasion O
, O
I O
left O
on O
foot O
to O
Pulav B-LOC
( I-LOC
Puławy I-LOC
) I-LOC
in O
order O
to O
see O
how O
my O
mother B-TER
is O
doing O
. O

I O
went O
to O
Pulav B-LOC
passing O
through O
the O
shtetlekh O
Garwolin B-LOC
and O
Ryki B-LOC
. O

In O
Pulav B-LOC
, O
I O
stayed O
for O
3 O
days O
, O
and O
there O
, O
seeing O
that O
the O
Germans B-TER
were O
catching O
Jews O
for O
work B-TER
, O
I O
ran O
to O
Kuzmir B-LOC
( I-LOC
Kazimierz I-LOC
[ I-LOC
Dolny I-LOC
] I-LOC
at O
the O
Vistula B-LOC
) O
. O

In O
Kuzmir B-LOC
, O
I O
stayed O
for O
8 O
days O
. O

From O
Kuzmir B-LOC
, O
I O
drove O
back O
to O
Warsaw B-LOC
and O
, O
staying O
there O
until O
mid- O
November O
, O
I O
left O
for O
the O
Russian B-TER
side O
. O

Soon O
after O
the O
outbreak O
of O
the O
war B-TER
, O
Warsaw B-LOC
was O
overcrowded O
with O
refugees B-TER
who O
poured O
in O
from O
all O
surrounding O
cities O
, O
from O
nearby O
and O
faraway O
. O

Since O
everywhere O
it O
was O
overcrowded O
, O
they O
were O
crammed O
into O
the O
places O
of O
their O
acquaintances O
laying O
in O
the O
courtyards O
and O
flights O
of O
stairs O
. O

The O
city O
was O
continuously O
bombarded O
from O
the O
Germans B-TER
, O
every O
day O
a O
new O
quarter O
. O

Every O
time O
news O
arrived O
about O
destroyed O
buildings O
and O
streets O
. O

I O
was O
a O
O.P.L O
Uncertain O
. O

.-Commander O
of O
my O
block O
, O
and O
it O
amounted O
to O
a O
lot O
of O
work O
, O
both O
to O
protect O
the O
house O
from O
fires O
and O
from O
looting B-TER
and O
robberies B-TER
. O

I O
also O
had O
to O
care O
for O
keeping O
the O
emotional O
equilibrium O
of O
the O
residents O
who O
were O
very O
nervous O
, O
upset O
. O

And O
I O
had O
to O
prevent O
any O
outbreak O
of O
panic O
and O
distress O
. O

At O
first O
, O
in O
the O
days O
from O
September O
6 O
to O
7 O
, O
I O
had O
in O
mind O
to O
follow O
the O
great O
mass O
of O
the O
Jewish O
youth O
: O
to O
leave O
Warsaw B-LOC
. O

But O
when O
I O
came O
to O
my O
boss O
in O
order O
to O
say O
goodbye O
, O
he O
started O
to O
beg O
me O
not O
to O
leave O
and O
I O
decided O
to O
stay O
. O

Until O
Rosh O
Hashanah O
, O
as O
mentioned O
before O
, O
Warsaw B-LOC
was O
bombarded O
day O
in O
, O
day O
out O
. O

But O
we O
had O
not O
endured O
a O
hell O
- O
like O
day O
before O
like O
the O
eve O
of O
Rosh O
Hashanah O
. O

In O
the O
morning O
, O
it O
was O
relatively O
calm O
. O

I O
left O
with O
a O
wagon O
for O
Grochów B-LOC
to O
the O
tannery O
and O
from O
there O
, O
I O
brought O
a O
wagon O
with O
leather O
( O
I O
had O
a O
special O
permit O
from O
the O
city B-LOC
headquarters I-LOC
to O
drive O
it O
) O
. O

When O
I O
came O
to O
Muranow B-LOC
Square I-LOC
, O
I O
was O
already O
trapped O
in O
the O
bombardment O
. O

Houses O
started O
to O
catch O
fire O
, O
flames O
flashed O
over O
from O
neighboring O
buildings O
where O
I O
lived O
and O
where O
I O
worked O
as O
a O
O.P.L.-commander O
( O
Nalewki B-LOC
No I-LOC
. I-LOC

40 I-LOC
) O
. O

The O
women B-TER
and O
children B-TER
were O
in O
the O
basements O
of O
the O
house O
and O
we O
kept O
watch O
standing O
in O
the O
gate O
. O

At O
5 O
pm O
, O
we O
noticed O
how O
the O
fire O
from O
the O
German B-TER
incendiary O
bombs O
flashed O
over O
to O
Nalewki B-LOC
38 I-LOC
. O

The O
O.P.L.-headquarter B-LOC
decided O
that O
we O
had O
to O
prepare O
the O
crowd O
for O
a O
potential O
evacuation O
of O
the O
women B-TER
and O
children B-TER
from O
the O
yard O
. O

We O
entered O
the O
basements O
and O
said O
: O
the O
situation O
is O
very O
serious O
. O

We O
have O
to O
hang O
on O
, O
however O
. O

It O
is O
possible O
that O
we O
have O
to O
leave O
the O
yard O
. O

But O
everyone O
should O
be O
careful O
and O
calm O
. O

In O
the O
basement O
, O
we O
, O
the O
O.P.L. O
activists O
( O
just O
like O
others O
) O
, O
had O
prepared O
hand O
luggage O
with O
the O
most O
necessary O
things O
in O
order O
to O
take O
it O
if O
need O
be O
. O

We O
took O
the O
suitcases O
and O
exited O
. O

The O
crowd O
, O
noticing O
that O
we O
took O
the O
suitcases O
, O
understood O
that O
the O
situation O
is O
serious O
and O
all O
at O
once O
everyone O
ran O
out O
of O
the O
basement O
. O

Everyone O
chaotically O
ran O
into O
the O
streets O
. O

People O
came O
running O
from O
everywhere O
and O
erratically O
, O
without O
a O
direction O
. O

I O
left O
for O
Shvyentayerske B-LOC
Street I-LOC
. O

I O
went O
there O
because O
my O
boss O
lives O
there O
and O
this O
corner O
was O
not O
touched O
by O
the O
bombardments O
and O
fires O
yet O
. O

At O
my O
boss O
’s O
house O
, O
I O
lived O
for O
3 O
days O
. O

His O
family B-TER
came O
running O
to O
him O
, O
however O
. O

7 O
individuals O
from O
Ayzn B-LOC
Street I-LOC
89 I-LOC
( O
Yakubovitsh B-LOC
) O
. O

Their O
house O
was O
hit O
by O
a O
bomb O
and O
destroyed O
their O
apartment O
. O

So O
they O
came O
to O
Shvyentayerske B-LOC
Street I-LOC
and O
I O
consequently O
had O
to O
move O
on O
. O

I O
left O
for O
Hazshe B-LOC
treet I-LOC
54 I-LOC
. O

During O
the O
whole O
bombardment O
until O
the O
Germans B-TER
invaded O
, O
there O
were O
uncountable O
numbers O
of O
victims B-TER
, O
both O
those O
struck O
by O
shrapnels O
and O
those O
buried O
alive O
and O
heavily O
injured O
from O
bombs O
or O
burnt O
houses O
. O

On O
the O
first O
day O
of O
Rosh O
Hashanah O
, O
it O
was O
calm O
. O

So O
I O
went O
out O
to O
have O
a O
look O
at O
the O
destruction O
of O
last O
night O
’s O
fire O
. O

The O
streets O
were O
full O
with O
corpses B-TER
. O

Freight O
wagons O
were O
driving O
across O
the O
streets O
and O
the O
victims B-TER
were O
placed O
on O
top O
on O
them O
. O

At O
the O
passageway O
Valove B-LOC
Street I-LOC
8 I-LOC
– O
Frantshishker B-LOC
Street I-LOC
29 I-LOC
, O
I O
saw O
a O
great O
number O
of O
burnt O
people O
. O

On O
the O
streets O
Stawki B-LOC
and O
Niska B-LOC
freight O
cars O
with O
corpses B-TER
were O
standing O
. O

On O
Frantshishker B-LOC
Street I-LOC
29 I-LOC
, O
the O
number O
of O
corpses B-TER
was O
estimated O
in O
the O
hundreds O
. O

On O
Gensha B-LOC
Street I-LOC
25 I-LOC
, O
35 O
men B-TER
were O
buried O
in O
the O
basements O
– O
among O
them O
my O
friend O
Reyman B-PER
, O
a O
house O
painter O
who O
lived O
on O
Muranowski B-LOC
Street I-LOC
40 I-LOC
, O
he O
was O
26 O
years O
of O
age O
. O

It O
was O
the O
first O
year O
after O
the O
wedding O
, O
he O
was O
alone O
from O
Chełm B-LOC
. O

For O
three O
weeks O
, O
he O
was O
laying O
under O
the O
debris O
. O

The O
following O
happened O
to O
me O
: O
on O
a O
certain O
day O
, O
a O
certain O
acquainted O
girl B-TER
came O
to O
me O
from O
Grochów B-LOC
. O

On O
the O
same O
day O
, O
we O
learned O
that O
Grochów B-LOC
had O
been O
bombarded O
heavily O
. O

The O
girl B-TER
went O
to O
great O
length O
to O
get O
home O
. O

I O
accompanied O
her O
to O
the O
Kerbedzsh B-LOC
bridge I-LOC
but O
in O
that O
same O
moment O
German B-TER
airplanes O
approached O
and O
started O
to O
heavily O
bombard O
the O
bridge B-LOC
and O
the O
royal B-LOC
palace I-LOC
. O

It O
was O
at O
the O
moment O
when O
my O
acquaintance O
was O
on O
the O
bridge B-LOC
. O

In O
shock O
, O
I O
let O
the O
bombardment O
pass O
and O
only O
afterwards O
I O
went O
looking O
for O
her O
. O

The O
bridge B-LOC
was O
perforated O
. O

I O
needed O
to O
jump O
from O
one O
plank O
to O
the O
next O
. O

On O
the O
other O
side O
, O
the O
dom O
żołmierza O
( O
soldiers B-TER
’ I-TER
home O
) O
was O
destroyed O
where O
one O
goes O
to O
the O
zoological O
garden O
. O

Under O
the O
debris O
, O
masses O
of O
corpses B-TER
were O
laying O
. O

I O
did O
not O
find O
my O
acquaintance O
. O

Only O
later O
, O
I O
got O
through O
to O
Grochów B-LOC
by O
phone O
and O
learned O
that O
she O
is O
alive O
. O

Immediately O
when O
the O
Germans B-TER
invaded O
Warsaw B-LOC
, O
it O
become O
possible O
to O
exit O
the O
city B-LOC
the O
next O
day O
. O

I O
left O
for O
Pulav B-LOC
to O
see O
how O
my O
mother B-TER
is O
doing O
. O

I O
went O
by O
foot O
. O

The O
140 O
kilometres O
took O
us O
3 O
days O
. O

One O
could O
only O
go O
until O
nightfall O
. O

We O
went O
in O
groups O
of O
two O
– O
me O
and O
another O
one O
, O
someone O
from O
Pulav B-LOC
. O

On O
the O
way O
, O
we O
spent O
the O
first O
night O
in O
a O
village O
near O
Otwock B-LOC
at O
a O
peasant O
’s O
house O
, O
and O
the O
second O
night O
in O
Ryki B-LOC
. O

We O
passed O
through O
Garwolin B-LOC
. O

The O
entire O
city O
was O
burnt O
to O
the O
ground O
. O

Maybe O
a O
dozen O
houses O
remained O
intact O
. O

The O
Jewish O
population O
was O
not O
in O
the O
city B-LOC
. O

We O
met O
2 O
Jews O
who O
searched O
and O
rummaged O
in O
the O
rubble O
of O
their O
houses O
. O

In O
Ryki B-LOC
, O
we O
spent O
the O
night O
at O
the O
house O
of O
the O
Pulav B-LOC
rabbi B-TER
’s I-TER
son B-TER
( O
it O
was O
the O
second O
day O
of O
Sukkot O
) O
. O

More O
than O
60 O
percent O
of O
the O
city O
was O
burnt O
to O
the O
ground O
. O

The O
son B-TER
of O
the O
Pulav B-LOC
rabbi B-TER
told O
us O
that O
masses O
of O
Jews O
from O
Dęblin B-LOC
arrived O
in O
Ryki B-LOC
in O
the O
first O
week O
of O
the O
war B-TER
. O

They O
came O
to O
Ryki B-LOC
because O
in O
Dęblin B-LOC
there O
are O
great O
fortresses O
and O
airports B-LOC
. O

So O
Ryki B-LOC
’s O
population O
expected O
air O
strikes O
from O
the O
Germans B-TER
and O
ran O
away O
. O

Then O
the O
German B-TER
planes O
supposedly O
saw O
a O
big O
mob O
so O
they O
bombarded O
Ryki B-LOC
and O
that O
time O
400 O
residents O
of O
Dęblin B-LOC
and O
Ryki B-LOC
were O
killed B-TER
. O

In O
Pulav B-LOC
, O
more O
than O
half O
of O
the O
city O
was O
burnt O
to O
the O
ground O
as O
a O
result O
of O
German B-TER
incendiary O
bombs O
. O

The O
following O
were O
burnt O
down O
: O
the O
Pyaskove B-LOC
Street I-LOC
( O
where O
the O
butcher O
shops O
are O
) O
, O
the O
entire O
street O
was O
destroyed O
; O
the O
Rabbi B-LOC
’s I-LOC
street I-LOC
( O
partly O
destroyed O
) O
; O
Lubliner B-LOC
Street I-LOC
( O
partly O
destroyed O
) O
; O
Piłsudsky B-LOC
Street I-LOC
( O
partly O
destroyed O
) O
. O

Both O
bote O
- O
midroshim O
and O
the O
old O
synagogue B-TER
were O
burnt B-TER
to O
the O
ground O
. O

In O
the O
old O
synagogue B-TER
, O
a O
granate O
came O
in O
and O
did O
not O
explode O
so O
the O
Germans B-TER
later O
blew O
up O
the O
granate O
and O
the O
synagogue B-TER
crumbled O
. O

Beside O
the O
hotel O
Bristol O
( O
Piłsudsky B-LOC
Street I-LOC
) O
a O
bomb O
dropped O
and O
40 O
men B-TER
from O
Pulav B-LOC
, O
primarily O
Jews O
, O
were O
killed B-TER
. O

Among O
the O
victims O
were O
: O
1 O
) O
Gevirtsman B-PER
, O
a O
typesetter O
, O
he O
left O
behind O
a O
wife B-TER
with O
a O
child B-TER
; O
2 O
) O
Dorfman B-PER
, O
a O
student B-TER
in O
the O
Polish B-TER
secondary O
school O
, O
he O
lived O
on O
the O
Krantsover B-LOC
Street I-LOC
( O
his O
father B-TER
owns O
a O
grocery O
store O
) O
. O

I O
stayed O
in O
Pulav B-LOC
for O
3 O
days O
and O
when O
the O
Germans B-TER
started O
to O
catch O
Jews O
for O
work B-TER
, O
I O
left O
for O
Kuzmir B-LOC
. O

Kuzmir B-LOC
did O
not O
suffer O
from O
bombardments O
. O

The O
city O
as O
a O
whole O
stayed O
intact O
. O

When O
I O
was O
in O
Kuzmir B-LOC
, O
a O
rumor O
circulated O
that O
in O
the O
coming O
night O
the O
Germans B-TER
will O
set O
fire O
to O
the O
city O
. O

2 O
peasants O
from O
Opole[Lubelskie B-LOC
] I-LOC
told O
this O
story O
. O

The O
Jews O
came O
out O
of O
the O
houses O
and O
they O
were O
laying O
in O
the O
yards O
for O
the O
whole O
night O
. O

It O
ended O
in O
a O
shock O
since O
very O
likely O
the O
Christians B-TER
themselves O
circulated O
the O
rumor O
in O
order O
to O
loot B-TER
the O
city B-LOC
. O

In O
Kuzmir B-LOC
, O
I O
was O
for O
a O
week O
and O
after O
that O
I O
drove O
to O
Warsaw B-LOC
. O

I O
transported O
merchandise O
back O
and O
forth O
. O

Jews O
were O
not O
allowed O
to O
take O
the O
train B-TER
. O

But O
we O
put O
on O
matsheyuvkes O
caps O
with O
a O
visor O
( O
a O
kind O
of O
Polish B-TER
hat O
) O
, O
and O
the O
Germans B-TER
took O
us O
for O
Christians B-TER
. O

This O
way O
, O
we O
drove O
back O
and O
forth O
for O
3 O
weeks O
. O

In O
Pulav B-LOC
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
in O
the O
course O
of O
this O
time O
completely O
robbed B-TER
and O
ruined O
the O
Jews O
. O

At O
first O
, O
they O
took O
all O
Jewish O
stores O
and O
gave O
them O
to O
Poles B-TER
. O

After O
that O
, O
they O
drove O
out O
the O
Jews O
from O
all O
streets O
and O
permitted O
them O
to O
only O
live O
on O
Gdańsker B-LOC
Street I-LOC
, O
outside O
the O
city B-LOC
. O

Before O
the O
war B-TER
, O
Christians B-TER
were O
primarily O
living O
there O
. O

On O
houses O
, O
in O
which O
Jews O
were O
allowed O
to O
move O
in O
, O
they O
drew O
a O
Magen O
David O
through O
a O
stencil O
with O
red O
paint O
. O

Jews O
were O
allowed O
to O
appear O
on O
the O
other O
streets O
from O
10 O
am O
to O
12 O
at O
noon O
. O

In O
the O
ghetto B-LOC
, O
namely O
on O
Gdańsker B-LOC
Street I-LOC
, O
the O
Jews O
were O
allowed O
to O
walk O
around O
the O
whole O
day O
. O

In O
a O
basement O
of O
Honigsfeld B-PER
’s O
house O
( O
the O
Jewish O
bank O
was O
there O
) O
, O
the O
Jews O
hid B-TER
their O
belongings O
. O

The O
basement O
was O
fire O
- O
proved O
. O

The O
house O
even O
burnt O
down O
and O
the O
basement O
stayed O
intact O
. O

Then O
the O
Germans B-TER
found O
out O
[ O
about O
the O
belongings O
] O
and O
took O
out O
everything O
from O
the O
basement O
. O

They O
admittedly O
gave O
notice O
to O
come O
to O
the O
city B-LOC
hall I-LOC
in O
order O
to O
identify O
and O
reclaim O
the O
things O
, O
but O
when O
the O
Jews O
came O
in O
city B-LOC
hall I-LOC
, O
they O
did O
not O
find O
anything O
anymore O
: O
the O
Germans B-TER
had O
already O
taken O
everything O
for O
themselves O
or O
distributed O
it O
amongst O
the O
Christians B-TER
. O

I O
was O
in O
Pulav B-LOC
in O
the O
context O
of O
my O
business O
when O
the O
Jews O
were O
chased O
out O
of O
their O
homes O
. O

So O
I O
took O
my O
mother B-TER
and O
moved O
her O
to O
Nałęczów B-LOC
where O
an O
older O
sister B-TER
of O
mine O
is O
living O
. O

Nałęczów B-LOC
in O
general O
did O
not O
suffer O
from O
the O
war O
. O

Once O
the O
German B-TER
airplanes O
threw O
bombs O
which O
, O
however O
, O
did O
not O
hit O
the O
shtetl O
. O

In O
Nałęczów B-LOC
, O
a O
German B-TER
general O
staff O
was O
established O
. O

On O
a O
certain O
day O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
went O
from O
house O
to O
house O
and O
dragged O
out O
the O
Jews O
. O

They O
gathered O
around O
30 O
Jews O
( O
there O
were O
not O
more O
than O
30 O
Jewish O
families B-TER
in O
Nałęczów B-LOC
) O
. O

They O
ordered O
them O
to O
lay O
down O
in O
the O
middle O
of O
the O
street O
in O
a O
puddle O
and O
swim O
. O

At O
the O
same O
time O
, O
the O
Jews O
were O
beaten O
mercilessly O
. O

Also O
my O
brother B-TER
-in O
- O
law O
and O
a O
son B-TER
of O
his O
were O
among O
the O
swimmer O
. O

From O
the O
beating O
, O
they O
got O
ill B-TER
and O
laid O
down O
in O
bed O
. O

I O
was O
in O
the O
shtetl O
and O
hid B-TER
. O

At O
that O
moment O
, O
I O
decided O
to O
leave O
the O
German B-TER
- O
occupied B-TER
territory O
. O

Signed O
: O
Yitskhok O
R. O
