The O
popular O
Rumanian B-TER
reaction O
to O
the O
recent O
excesses B-TER
committed I-TER
against I-TER
the I-TER
Jews I-TER
is O
difficult O
of O
assessment O
. O

The O
Rumanians B-TER
have O
heretofore O
insisted O
upon O
being O
known O
as O
a O
tolerant O
people B-TER
, O
and O
I O
do O
not O
doubt O
that O
the O
majority O
of O
them O
learn O
of O
the O
massacres B-TER
and O
other O
atrocities B-TER
with O
, O
possibly O
, O
a O
slight O
feeling O
of O
satisfaction O
, O
mixed O
with O
a O
stronger O
sense O
of O
surprise O
, O
shock O
and O
misgiving O
. O

It O
is O
undoubtedly O
true O
that O
the O
anti B-TER
- I-TER
Semitic I-TER
campaign I-TER
of O
the O
Legionary B-ORG
régime I-ORG
, O
the O
continual O
attacks B-TER
of I-TER
the I-TER
press I-TER
, O
the O
present O
military B-TER
collaboration B-TER
with O
anti B-TER
- I-TER
Semitic I-TER
Germany B-TER
, O
and O
the O
attitude O
of O
the O
Government B-TER
during O
General B-PER
Antonescu I-PER
’s I-PER
absence O
at O
the O
front O
, O
during O
which O
time O
Mr. B-PER
Mihai I-PER
Antonescu I-PER
has O
been O
Acting O
Premier O
, O
have O
all O
had O
their O
effect O
on O
popular B-TER
opinion I-TER
, O
tending O
to O
make O
it O
especially O
anti B-TER
- I-TER
Semitic I-TER
, O
but O
I O
fail O
to O
believe O
that O
the O
country O
as O
a O
whole O
willingly O
countenances O
outright O
slaughter B-TER
and I-TER
brutality I-TER
in O
the O
handling O
of O
the O
Jewish B-TER
problem I-TER
. O

[ O
... O
] O
But O
the O
fact O
remains O
that O
there O
has O
been O
no O
popular O
uprising B-TER
or O
movement O
against O
all O
these O
cruelties B-TER
. O

It O
may O
well O
be O
that O
the O
ethical O
sense O
of O
the O
Rumanian B-TER
people B-TER
has O
been O
somewhat O
dulled O
by O
recent O
miseries O
and O
disasters O
[ O
... O
] O
, O
with O
the O
result O
that O
they O
are O
not O
fully O
conscious O
of O
the O
horrors B-TER
of I-TER
the I-TER
Jewish I-TER
phase I-TER
. O

Whatever O
the O
cause O
, O
1941 O
has O
thus O
far O
proved O
to O
be O
a O
black O
year O
for O
the O
Jews B-TER
in O
Rumania B-LOC
. O

My O
own O
experience O
is O
that O
the O
better O
class O
of O
Rumanians B-TER
thoroughly O
disapproves O
of O
the O
methods B-TER
resorted I-TER
to I-TER
from I-TER
time I-TER
to I-TER
time I-TER
against I-TER
the I-TER
Jews I-TER
, O
the O
cruelty B-TER
and O
the O
injustice O
. O

[ O
... O
] O
The O
fact O
remains O
, O
however O
, O
that O
the O
lower B-TER
- I-TER
class I-TER
Jew I-TER
who O
has O
filtered O
into O
Rumania B-LOC
since O
the O
War B-TER
from O
Galicia B-LOC
, O
Russia B-LOC
, O
Hungary B-LOC
, O
Czechoslovakia B-LOC
, O
or O
elsewhere O
, O
and O
fastened O
upon O
village O
and O
small O
- O
town O
life O
is O
, O
by O
and O
large O
, O
not O
assimilable O
. O

The O
Rumanian B-TER
resents O
his O
presence O
, O
although O
it O
is O
largely O
due O
to O
his O
own O
laissez O
faire O
that O
this O
type O
of O
Jew B-TER
is O
here O
, O
and O
, O
from O
time O
to O
time O
when O
things O
are O
not O
going O
well O
, O
sporadic O
examples O
of O
appalling O
cruelty B-TER
occur O
. O

The O
Jew B-TER
is O
always O
the O
convenient O
butt O
. O

Frank O
Rumanians B-LOC
will O
admit O
that O
robbery B-TER
is O
often O
the O
real O
leit O
motif O
. O

