Budapest B-LOC
, O
6th O
August O
1941 O
, O
Year O
XIX O
Re O
: O
Jews B-TER
against O
the O
Jews B-TER
in O
Hungary B-LOC
The O
military B-TER
action O
against O
Russia B-LOC
and O
the O
occupation O
by O
Hungarian B-LOC
troops O
of O
a O
considerable O
part O
of O
the O
territory O
of O
Galicia B-LOC
has O
offered O
Authorities O
here O
the O
opportunity O
to O
solve O
a O
problem O
that O
had O
arisen O
during O
and O
after O
the O
operations O
carried O
out O
by O
Germany B-LOC
in O
Poland B-LOC
. O

A O
large O
number O
of O
Jewish B-TER
elements O
had O
been O
able O
to O
filter O
in O
from O
Poland B-LOC
and O
in O
some O
cases O
also O
from O
Russian B-LOC
territory O
and O
, O
with O
the O
support O
of O
coreligionists O
living O
in O
Hungary B-LOC
, O
had O
managed O
to O
live O
here O
practically O
undisturbed O
until O
now O
. O

These O
past O
weeks O
the O
Hungarian B-LOC
police B-TER
has O
carried O
out O
raids O
against O
the O
said O
Semitic B-TER
elements O
who O
, O
in O
concert O
with O
Hungarian B-LOC
and O
German B-LOC
military B-TER
authorities O
, O
have O
then O
been O
conveyed O
to O
Galicia B-LOC
, O
particularly O
to O
the O
major O
towns O
such O
as O
Kolomea B-LOC
and O
Stanislau B-LOC
, O
where O
they O
are O
assigned O
to O
concentration B-TER
camps I-TER
and O
employed B-TER
in O
excavation O
work O
, O
demolitions O
, O
mine O
clearance O
etc O
. O

So O
far O
, O
according O
to O
official O
information O
, O
the O
number O
of O
these O
Jews B-TER
amounts O
to O
approx O
. O

12,000 O
, O
but O
this O
number O
will O
increase O
significantly O
as O
a O
recent O
decree O
has O
determined O
to O
extend O
the O
same O
measures O
to O
those O
Jews B-TER
having O
Polish B-LOC
or O
Soviet B-LOC
citizenship B-TER
who O
, O
although O
they O
live O
in O
Hungary B-LOC
with O
a O
proper O
residence O
permit O
, O
have O
not O
requested O
and O
obtained O
the O
Hungarian B-LOC
citizenship O
during O
the O
past O
ten O
years O
. O

The O
only O
difference O
between O
these O
latter O
and O
those O
who O
have O
entered O
Magyar B-LOC
territory O
illegally O
will O
be O
, O
it O
is O
said O
, O
that O
they O
will O
be O
allowed O
to O
take O
their O
personal O
property O
with O
them O
, O
whereas O
the O
Jews B-TER
transported O
to O
Galicia B-LOC
up O
to O
now O
have O
been O
allowed O
to O
transfer O
only O
the O
sum O
of O
not O
more O
than O
30 O
Pengö O
, O
equivalent O
to O
120 O
Italian O
Lira O
. O

Talamo B-PER
