My O
Dears O
, O
We O
are O
overjoyed O
that O
we O
are O
finally O
in O
written B-TER
touch I-TER
with O
you O
and O
that O
we O
can O
write O
to O
you O
in O
our O
mother O
tongue O
. O

We O
have O
so O
much O
to O
tell O
you O
that O
there O
is O
n’t O
enough O
paper O
in O
the O
world O
that O
could O
contain O
it O
all O
. O

Unfortunately O
, O
it O
’s O
mostly O
all O
bad O
news O
. O

So O
little O
of O
it O
is O
good O
. O

As O
you O
have O
perhaps O
already O
learned O
from O
Maruška O
, O
out O
of O
our O
whole O
family O
only O
Hanka B-PER
and O
I O
returned O
, O
but O
we O
are O
happy O
that O
at O
least O
the O
two O
of O
us O
were O
reunited O
. O

I O
must O
tell O
you O
all O
about O
our O
departure O
from O
Prague B-LOC
. O

As O
you O
know O
, O
Kurt B-PER
and O
I O
were O
transported O
to O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
in O
July O
1943 O
to O
be O
with O
our O
parents O
and O
Hanka B-PER
. O

We O
were O
together O
there O
for O
1 O
¼ O
years O
. O

We O
were O
doing O
rather O
well O
, O
all O
told O
. O

Kurt B-PER
and O
my O
parents O
worked O
in O
the O
office O
, O
Hanka B-PER
in O
the O
bakery O
, O
and O
I O
mostly O
did O
nothing O
because O
I O
was O
sick B-TER
. O

Then O
, O
in O
the O
fall O
of O
1944 O
, O
we O
were O
gradually O
transported B-TER
— O
father B-PER
left O
separately O
, O
mother B-PER
with O
Hanka B-PER
, O
and O
I O
with O
Kurt B-PER
. O

All O
of O
the O
transports B-TER
went O
to O
Auschwitz B-LOC
. O

You O
can O
not O
imagine O
what O
we O
suffered O
through O
. O

I O
do O
n’t O
want O
to O
describe O
our O
experiences O
and O
so O
it O
’s O
perhaps O
a O
little O
cruel O
of O
me O
to O
write O
and O
tell O
you O
so O
directly O
that O
our O
dear O
mother B-PER
died B-TER
there O
. O

Father B-PER
, O
who O
successfully O
made O
it O
past O
the O
selection B-TER
process O
, O
was O
shot B-TER
on O
the O
Czech B-LOC
border O
on O
May O
3rd O
, O
1945 O
, O
just O
5 O
days O
before O
the O
end O
of O
the O
war B-TER
, O
during O
the O
evacuation B-TER
of O
the O
labor B-TER
camp I-TER
where O
he O
was O
sent O
. O

Kurt B-PER
was O
separated O
from O
me O
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
near O
the O
train O
and O
it O
was O
only O
when O
I O
returned O
to O
Prague B-LOC
that O
I O
learned O
that O
he O
was O
held O
for O
about O
3 O
weeks O
in O
the O
Small B-LOC
Fortress I-LOC
and O
was O
supposedly O
shot B-TER
there O
. O

We O
are O
positive O
regarding O
father B-PER
since O
he O
was O
with O
Hanka B-PER
’s O
young O
man B-TER
, O
who O
returned O
. O

Jirka O
also O
returned O
and O
we O
’re O
living B-TER
together O
with O
him O
now O
. O

I O
ran O
into O
Hanka B-PER
by O
happy O
chance O
in O
Prague B-LOC
. O

She O
had O
come O
back O
one O
month O
earlier O
than O
I O
and O
she O
no O
longer O
believed O
that O
I O
would O
return O
. O

I O
’m O
sure O
you O
can O
imagine O
what O
our O
life B-TER
is O
like O
now O
. O

Our O
financial O
situation O
is O
miserable O
; O
we O
do O
n’t O
have O
enough O
clothes B-TER
to O
wear O
. O

I O
’ll O
likely O
find O
an O
office O
job O
. O

Hanka B-PER
is O
graduating O
in O
September O
and O
then O
she O
’ll O
probably O
make O
her O
living O
as O
an O
illustrator O
. O

In O
short O
, O
this O
is O
all O
that O
we O
wanted O
to O
tell O
you O
about O
what O
we O
went O
through O
. O

We O
do O
n’t O
know O
what O
the O
future O
holds O
. O

We O
are O
in O
touch O
with O
Maruška O
. O

Her O
little O
Jana O
is O
so O
adorable O
. O

We O
have O
visited O
them O
several O
times O
. O

Please O
write O
us O
soon O
and O
let O
us O
know O
if O
you O
are O
coming O
. O

We O
would O
love O
to O
see O
you O
, O
we O
have O
so O
much O
to O
tell O
. O

You O
ca O
n’t O
imagine O
how O
we O
are O
faring O
. O

But O
at O
least O
we O
are O
happy O
that O
you O
will O
come O
and O
see O
us O
. O

