EW O
4 O
3372 O
- O
3375 O
MASTER O
- O
INDEX O
( O
P O
- O
Scheme O
) O
1 O
. O

Index O
Number O
: O
P.III.e O
. O

No O
44 O
2 O
. O

Title O
of O
Document O
: O
EXPERIENCES O
OF O
A O
“ O
MISCHLING B-TER
” O
IN O
FRANKFURT B-LOC
/ I-LOC
MAIN I-LOC
. O

3 O
. O

Date O
: O
1939 O
- O
1945 O
4 O
. O

Number O
of O
Pages O
: O
4 O
Language O
: O
English B-LOC
5 O
. O

Author O
: O
Mrs. O
Johanna B-PER
Fraenkel I-PER
6 O
. O

Recorded O
by O
: O
Peter B-PER
Zadek I-PER
, O
April O
1955 O
7 O
. O

Form O
and O
Contents O
: O
Mrs. O
Fraenkel B-PER
, O
a O
non O
- O
Jewish O
lady B-TER
of O
part B-TER
- I-TER
Jewish I-TER
extraction O
was O
married B-TER
, O
first O
to O
a O
gentile O
, O
then O
to O
a O
Jewish O
husband O
. O

The O
latter O
was O
for O
a O
time O
in O
BUCHENWALD B-LOC
Concentration B-TER
Camp I-TER
, O
and O
emigrated B-TER
to O
England B-LOC
before O
the O
outbreak O
of O
the O
war B-TER
. O

Mrs. O
F. B-PER
stayed O
at O
FRANKFURT B-LOC
, O
where O
she O
was O
compelled O
to O
wear O
the O
yellow B-TER
star I-TER
. O

As O
regards O
work B-TER
, O
she O
was O
subject O
to O
the O
same O
regulations B-TER
as O
Jews O
. O

In O
1942 O
she O
was O
about O
to O
be O
deported B-TER
, O
but O
saved O
herself O
by O
starting O
divorce O
proceedings O
. O

After O
the O
war B-TER
she O
remarried B-TER
Mr. O
Fraenkel B-PER
in O
LONDON B-LOC
.{See O
report O
P.II.d O
. O

No.45 O
. O

} O
The O
Experiences O
of O
Mrs O
, O
Fraenkel B-PER
in O
FRANKFURT B-LOC
- I-LOC
am I-LOC
- I-LOC
MAIN I-LOC
, O
1939 O
- O
1945 O
. O

( O
Reported O
, O
15th O
April O
, O
1955 O
. O

Report O
by O
Peter B-PER
Zadek I-PER
) O
Mrs O
Fraenkel B-PER
was O
38 O
years O
of O
age O
in O
1939 O
. O

She O
was O
a O
gentile O
with O
some O
Jewish O
blood O
who O
had O
been O
married B-TER
to O
a O
gentile O
. O

This O
marriage B-TER
had O
been O
dissolved O
and O
, O
in O
April O
1939 O
, O
Mrs O
Fraenkel B-PER
married B-TER
Arnold B-PER
Fraenkel I-PER
, O
who O
had O
recently O
returned O
from O
Buchenwald B-LOC
Concentration B-TER
Camp I-TER
. O

Arnold B-PER
Fraenkel I-PER
managed O
to O
get O
to O
England B-LOC
before O
the O
outbreak O
of O
war B-TER
, O
but O
Mrs O
Fraenkel B-PER
was O
unable O
to O
get O
all O
the O
necessary O
papers B-TER
. O

At O
the O
outbreak O
of O
war B-TER
Mrs O
Fraenkel B-PER
was O
thus O
left O
in O
Frankfurt B-LOC
- I-LOC
am I-LOC
- I-LOC
Main I-LOC
, O
the O
( O
mainly O
) O
gentile O
wife B-TER
of O
a O
Jew O
, O
living O
with O
her O
19 O
year O
old O
gentile O
daughter O
from O
her O
previous O
marriage B-TER
. O

Mrs O
Fraenkel B-PER
had O
been O
employed O
by O
Voigt B-ORG
u. I-ORG
Heffner I-ORG
, O
Aktiengesellschaft B-TER
, O
Frankfurt B-LOC
- I-LOC
am I-LOC
- I-LOC
Main I-LOC
since O
1928 O
. O

She O
left O
the O
company B-TER
's I-TER
employ O
before O
her O
marriage B-TER
in O
April O
, O
preferring O
to O
leave O
before O
being O
thrown O
out O
. O

On O
the O
occasion O
of O
her O
leaving O
, O
her O
colleagues O
gave O
her O
a O
present O
. O

This O
was O
accompanied O
by O
a O
list O
of O
the O
subscribers O
to O
the O
present O
, O
with O
their O
signatures O
. O

Several O
Nazi B-TER
party I-TER
members O
were O
amongst O
the O
signatories O
. O

After O
it O
had O
been O
presented O
, O
Mrs O
Fraenkel B-PER
was O
visited O
by O
a O
representative O
of O
the O
employees O
and O
asked O
to O
return O
the O
list O
. O

However O
, O
she O
had O
it O
photocopied O
before O
returning O
it O
. O

In O
1940 O
Mrs O
Fraenkel B-PER
obtained O
employment O
with O
Geb O
. O

Roever O
, O
Aktiengesellschaft B-TER
. O

This O
gentile O
firm B-TER
employed O
many O
Jews O
in O
separate O
and O
inferior B-TER
departments O
to O
the O
gentile O
workers B-TER
. O

They O
also O
received O
smaller O
remuneration O
. O

Mrs O
Fraenkel B-PER
, O
as O
Mischling O
, O
was O
, O
at O
first O
, O
allowed O
to O
work B-TER
together O
with O
the O
gentiles O
. O

However O
, O
there O
was O
an O
SA B-ORG
control O
. O

Mrs O
Fraenkel B-PER
, O
who O
has O
presumably O
been O
denounced O
by O
one O
of O
her O
colleagues O
, O
was O
asked O
by O
an O
SA B-ORG
man I-ORG
how O
much O
she O
earned B-TER
. O

An O
unpleasant O
scene O
ensued O
and O
Mrs O
Fraenkel B-PER
was O
transferred O
to O
the O
sewing B-TER
department I-TER
with O
the O
full O
- O
Jews O
, O
where O
she O
earned B-TER
considerably O
less O
. O

When O
the O
regulation B-TER
first O
came O
into O
existence O
, O
according O
to O
which O
Jews O
were O
forced O
to O
wear O
a O
yellow B-TER
star I-TER
, O
Mrs O
Fraenkel B-PER
made O
an O
application O
through O
her O
lawyer B-TER
to O
the O
Ministry B-ORG
of I-ORG
the I-ORG
Interior I-ORG
, O
in O
which O
she O
maintained O
that O
she O
did O
not O
have O
to O
wear O
a O
star B-TER
, O
in O
spite O
of O
her O
re B-TER
- I-TER
marriage I-TER
. O

She O
based O
this O
on O
a O
clause O
in O
the O
regulation B-TER
which O
stated O
that O
Jews O
married O
to O
gentiles O
, O
whose O
children O
had O
a O
Christian O
up O
- O
bringing O
, O
need O
not O
wear O
the O
star O
, O
even O
if O
the O
marriage O
had O
been O
dissolved O
. O

There O
was O
a O
time O
- O
lapse O
of O
three O
months O
while O
her O
applicatiogestagestn O
was O
being O
considered O
. O

Meanwhile O
Mrs O
Fraenkel B-PER
did O
not O
wear O
the O
star B-TER
and O
therefore O
did O
not O
suffer O
the O
resulting O
loss O
of O
privilege O
( O
smaller O
rations B-TER
etc O
) O
. O

After O
three O
months O
, O
Mrs O
Fraenkel B-PER
was O
summoned O
to O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
H.Q. O
in O
Lindenstrasse O
. O

Here O
, O
after O
a O
two O
hour O
wait O
, O
during O
which O
a O
Gestapo B-ORG
official O
accosted O
and O
insulted O
her O
in O
the O
corridor O
, O
Mrs O
Fraenkel B-PER
was O
interviewed O
by O
a O
Gestapo B-ORG
official O
, O
Schmidt B-PER
who O
seemed O
to O
have O
more O
humanity O
than O
most O
of O
his O
colleagues O
. O

However O
, O
he O
told O
her O
that O
he O
had O
received O
orders B-TER
from O
the O
Ministry B-ORG
of I-ORG
the I-ORG
Interior I-ORG
that O
she O
had O
, O
in O
future O
, O
to O
wear O
the O
star B-TER
. O

During O
the O
interview O
, O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
Commissar O
entered O
, O
shouted O
at O
her O
and O
told O
her O
she O
would O
be O
sent O
to O
prison B-TER
and O
deported B-TER
. O

Mrs O
Fraenkel B-PER
answered O
very O
quietly O
and O
the O
Commissar O
left O
without O
taking O
any O
further O
action O
. O

Meanwhile O
, O
at O
another O
table O
in O
the O
same O
room O
, O
another O
Mischling O
was O
being O
interviewed O
. O

Her O
children B-TER
had O
had O
a O
Jewish B-TER
education I-TER
. O

Suddenly O
the O
doors O
were O
flung O
open O
and O
a O
Gestapo B-ORG
officer O
yelled O
: O
Any O
more O
for O
prison O
? O
and O
the O
woman B-TER
was O
dragged B-TER
away O
. O

Before O
allowing O
Mrs O
Fraenkel B-PER
to O
leave O
, O
Schmidt B-PER
asked O
her O
to O
send O
her O
father O
to O
his O
office O
, O
as O
he O
, O
too O
, O
now O
had O
to O
wear O
a O
star B-TER
. O

Mrs O
Fraenkel B-PER
asked O
whether O
anything O
would O
happen O
to O
him O
, O
and O
Schmidt B-PER
assured O
her O
that O
he O
would O
be O
sent O
back O
. O

Mrs O
Fraenkel B-PER
asked O
whether O
she O
could O
not O
simply O
give O
her O
father O
the O
message O
, O
and O
Schmidt B-PER
finally O
agreed O
to O
her O
request O
. O

Deportation B-TER
in O
Frankfurt B-LOC
- I-LOC
am I-LOC
- I-LOC
Main I-LOC
The O
first O
two O
transports B-TER
, O
consisting O
only O
of O
full O
Jews O
, O
had O
left O
Frankfurt B-LOC
for O
Poland B-LOC
and O
Minsk B-LOC
on O
October O
and O
November O
1941 O
, O
respectively O
. O

In O
May O
, O
1942 O
, O
Mrs O
Fraenkel B-PER
was O
leaving O
her O
home B-TER
when O
she O
met O
an O
officer O
from O
the O
Jewish B-TER
Community I-TER
of O
Frankfurt B-LOC
entering O
the O
house B-TER
. O

As O
the O
Community B-TER
had O
to O
compile O
the O
lists O
for O
the O
transports B-TER
and O
had O
to O
break O
the O
news O
to O
the O
deportees B-TER
, O
Mrs O
Fraenkel B-PER
feared B-TER
the O
worst O
. O

Indeed O
, O
she O
was O
on O
the O
list O
of O
the O
next O
transport B-TER
. O

She O
went O
immediately O
to O
see O
the O
lawyer O
, O
who O
represented O
the O
Jewish B-TER
Community I-TER
and O
who O
happened O
to O
be O
a O
relative O
of O
Mrs O
Fraenkel B-PER
. O

The O
lawyer O
suggested O
that O
the O
only O
way O
to O
escape B-TER
deportation B-TER
was O
to O
divorce B-TER
her I-TER
Jewish I-TER
husband I-TER
. O

Mrs O
Fraenkel B-PER
's I-PER
brother O
there O
upon O
went O
to O
Gestapo B-ORG
H.Q. O
where O
he O
was O
told O
that O
if O
divorce B-TER
proceedings O
had O
been O
started O
by O
that O
same O
afternoon O
, O
Mrs O
Fraenkel B-PER
would O
not O
be O
deported B-TER
. O

The O
rest O
of O
the O
day O
was O
spent O
in O
running O
from O
office O
to O
office O
( O
Jews O
were O
, O
of O
course O
, O
not B-TER
allowed I-TER
to O
use O
public O
transport O
) O
until O
a O
document O
was O
obtained O
stating O
officially O
that O
proceedings O
had O
been O
begun O
. O

Mrs O
Fraenkel B-PER
then O
took O
this O
to O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
who O
, O
at O
first O
refused O
to O
accept O
it O
and O
asked O
why O
she O
had O
waited O
until O
the O
last O
moment O
to O
begin O
proceedings O
and O
why O
she O
had O
married B-TER
a O
Jew O
in O
the O
first O
place O
. O

Mrs O
Fraenkel B-PER
answered O
that O
if O
they O
( O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
) O
had O
any O
humanity O
( O
Menschliches O
Verstaendnis O
) O
at O
all O
, O
they O
would O
understand O
that O
she O
wanted O
to O
give O
her O
daughter O
a O
home B-TER
and O
had O
married B-TER
for O
her O
sake O
. O

This O
evidently O
had O
some O
effect O
on O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
officers O
who O
passed O
Mrs O
Fraenkel B-PER
's I-PER
application O
not O
to O
be O
deported B-TER
, O
not O
because O
of O
the O
divorce O
, O
but O
because O
we O
do O
have O
humanity O
. O

The O
next O
morning O
, O
a O
Gestapo B-ORG
man O
came O
to O
collect O
her O
for O
the O
transport B-TER
. O

She O
told O
him O
that O
she O
was O
not O
to O
go O
. O

The O
Gestapo B-ORG
man B-TER
left O
to O
get O
in O
touch O
with O
H.Q. B-ORG
, O
telling O
Mrs O
Fraenkel B-PER
that O
if O
he O
did O
not O
return O
by O
12 O
a.m. O
, O
she O
would O
not O
be O
taken O
. O

He O
did O
not O
return O
, O
and O
so O
Mrs O
Fraenkel B-PER
escaped B-TER
almost O
certain O
death B-TER
. O

For O
nothing O
was O
ever O
heard O
again O
from O
anyone O
who O
left O
on O
this O
transport B-TER
. O

Amongst O
other O
of O
her O
acquaintances O
who O
were O
taken O
away O
on O
this O
transport B-TER
was O
an O
Eduard B-PER
Stern I-PER
, O
the O
Jewish O
hairdresser B-TER
, O
whose O
job B-TER
it O
had O
been O
to O
cut O
the O
hair O
of O
the O
deportees B-TER
at O
the O
collecting O
centre O
. O

With O
Stern B-PER
were O
his O
wife O
and O
his O
10 O
year O
- O
old O
daughter B-TER
. O

In O
August O
, O
1942 O
, O
Hermann B-PER
Fraenkel I-PER
, O
Mrs O
Fraenkel B-PER
's I-PER
father O
- O
in O
- O
law O
, O
was O
deported B-TER
to O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
. O

He O
had O
previously O
been O
sent O
to O
the O
Jewish O
Old B-TER
Age I-TER
Home I-TER
, O
Hermesweg O
. O

The O
home B-TER
was O
kept O
in O
existence O
after O
the O
dissolution O
of O
all O
the O
others O
. O

To O
be O
sent O
to O
the O
Hermesweg O
home O
meant O
certain O
deportation B-TER
. O

Hermann B-PER
Fraenkel I-PER
was O
67 O
years O
old O
at O
the O
time O
. O

In O
September O
, O
1942 O
, O
Arthur B-PER
Obst I-PER
, O
Mrs O
Fraenkel B-PER
's I-PER
uncle O
, O
was O
also O
sent O
to O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
. O

He O
was O
also O
67 O
years O
old O
. O

He O
wrote O
from O
the O
camp B-LOC
, O
telling O
Mrs O
Fraenkel B-PER
in O
veiled O
terms O
that O
Hermann B-PER
Fraenkel I-PER
was O
dead B-TER
. O

At O
this O
time O
the O
Jewish B-TER
Community I-TER
asked O
Mischlinge O
to O
help O
in O
feeding O
and O
caring O
for O
the O
deportees B-TER
at O
the O
collecting O
centre O
. O

Mrs O
Fraenkel B-PER
volunteered O
and O
continued O
to O
do O
this O
until O
the O
last O
transport B-TER
in O
1945 O
. O

The O
deportees B-TER
slept O
for O
one O
night O
at O
the O
centre O
. O

In O
the O
morning O
there O
was O
a O
luggage O
check O
, O
when O
Gestapo B-ORG
officers O
stole B-TER
what O
they O
happened O
to O
fancy O
from O
the O
luggage O
. O

Next O
, O
by O
lorry O
to O
the O
station O
, O
where O
they O
were O
herded O
into O
the O
train B-TER
like O
cattle O
. O

Finally O
, O
before O
the O
departure O
, O
minor O
Gestapo B-ORG
officials O
walked O
through O
the O
trains B-TER
and O
stole B-TER
such O
things O
as O
fountain O
- O
pens O
, O
cigarette O
lighters O
, O
hats B-TER
. O

Summary O
. O

In O
all O
, O
Mrs O
Fraenkel B-PER
was O
remarkably O
untouched O
throughout O
this O
period O
. O

She O
suffered O
the O
deprivations O
expected O
in O
war B-TER
- I-TER
time I-TER
, O
accentuated O
by O
her O
yellow B-TER
star I-TER
. O

Her O
main O
recollection O
is O
of O
constant O
nervous O
strain O
, O
of O
constant O
fear B-TER
for I-TER
her I-TER
friends I-TER
and I-TER
relatives I-TER
; O
of O
stories O
of O
terror O
and O
brutality O
, O
of O
constant O
attempts O
to O
humiliate B-TER
her O
and O
her O
Jewish O
friends O
and O
relatives O
. O

But O
apart O
from O
petty O
persecutions O
at O
work B-TER
and O
verbal O
insults O
from O
Nazis O
, O
Mrs O
Fraenkel B-PER
never O
once O
witnessed O
actual O
physical B-TER
brutality I-TER
, O
in O
spite O
of O
the O
fact O
that O
after O
1942 O
she O
spent O
a O
great O
deal O
of O
time O
with O
the O
deportees B-TER
and O
their O
Gestapo B-ORG
guards B-TER
. O

After O
the O
war B-TER
she O
joined O
her O
divorced O
husband O
in O
London B-LOC
where O
they O
re B-TER
- I-TER
married I-TER
again O
. O

