Unaccompanied O
child O
Registration O
No O
. O

G O
11368343 O
copy O
1 O
( O
✓ O
) O
2 O
3 O
M O
F(x O
) O
MARITAL O
STATUS O
Sing.(x O
) O
Mar. O
Wid O
. O

Div O
. O

SUPPLEMENTARY O
RECORD O
– O
FACE O
SHEET O
CHILD B-TER
Evidence O
of O
Verification O
Date O
Family O
or O
Surname O
HOLZ B-PER
Given O
or O
Christian O
Names O
Sonja B-PER
Other O
Names O
Used O
none O
Birthdate O
Day O
Month O
Year O
. O

As O
Verified O
: O
Day O
Month O
Year O
8 O
July O
1929 O
Birthplace O
Town O
Province O
Country O
Birthplace O
As O
Verified O
: O
Town O
Province O
Country O
Vilna B-LOC
Poland B-LOC
Nationality O
Claimed O
Polish B-TER
Jew O
Nationality O
Verified O
Adress O
in O
Country O
of O
Origin O
Prior O
to O
Displacement O
Vilna B-LOC
, O
Kalvariska B-LOC
Ul I-LOC
. I-LOC

26 I-LOC
/ I-LOC
II I-LOC
, O
Poland B-LOC
Date O
of O
Displacement O
June O
1942 O
Present O
location O
of O
Child B-TER
including O
Name O
of O
Family B-TER
, O
Center O
or O
institution O
, O
Person O
in O
Charge O
, O
Adtess O
, O
Date O
arrived O
at O
this O
location O
. O

D.P. B-TER
Camp I-TER
Wolfratshausen B-LOC
, O
Team O
106 O
. O

Dir O
. O

Mr. O
Cohen O
. O

November O
1945 O
. O

Language O
usually O
spoken O
Yiddish O
, O
Polish O
, O
Hebrew O
Other O
languages O
used O
Religion O
Jewish O
Occupation O
Dressmaker O
- O
apprentice O
FATHER B-TER
FAMILY B-TER
Family B-TER
Name O
HOLZ B-PER
First O
Middle O
Chona B-PER
Birthdate O
1906 O
Nationality O
Polish B-TER
Jewy O
Last O
known O
address O
same O
as O
child B-TER
. O

Date O
last O
heard O
fromy O
June O
1942 O
Permanent O
address O
same O
as O
child B-TER
. O

Occupation O
salesman O
Place O
of O
Employment O
Clothing B-TER
store O
, O
Vilna B-LOC
MOTHER B-TER
Maiden O
Name O
FISCHER B-PER
Family O
Name O
HOLZ B-PER
First O
Chana B-PER
Middle O
Birthdate O
1906 O
Nationality O
Polish B-TER
Jew O
Last O
known O
address O
same O
as O
child B-TER
Date O
last O
heard O
from O
June O
1942 O
. O

Permanent O
address O
same O
as O
child B-TER
. O

Occupation O
Dressmaker O
, O
own O
shop O
. O

Place O
of O
Employment O
Other O
members O
of O
the O
immediate O
family B-TER
and O
relatives O
. O

List O
for O
each O
the O
Name O
, O
Age O
, O
Relationship O
, O
Last O
known O
address O
, O
Former O
permanent O
address O
, O
Occupation O
and O
Employment O
, O
if O
known O
. O

( O
Continue O
on O
reverse O
side O
of O
page O
as O
necessary O
. O

) O
no O
relatives O
. O

Face O
Sheet O
prepared O
by O
: O
Victor B-PER
Roninson I-PER
Team O
: O
567 O
Date O
: O
24 O
April O
1946 O
. O

Information O
obtained O
from O
: O
Holz B-PER
, I-PER
Sonja I-PER
First O
displacement O
June O
1942 O
– O
brought O
with O
family B-TER
into O
Ghetto B-TER
. O

Separation O
from O
Family B-TER
Mother B-TER
and O
younger O
brother B-TER
( O
about O
six O
yrs O
. O

old O
) O
killed B-TER
in O
ghetto B-TER
. O

Older O
brother B-TER
( O
about O
eighteen O
yrs O
of O
age O
) O
shot B-TER
in O
ghetto B-TER
, O
because O
he O
did O
not O
wear O
the O
yellow B-TER
star I-TER
. O

Her O
father B-TER
has O
been O
taken B-TER
away I-TER
and O
she O
never O
saw O
him O
again O
. O

( O
All O
this O
happened O
in O
June O
1942 O
in O
the O
ghetto B-LOC
of I-LOC
Wolomin I-LOC
) O
. O

Moves O
and O
changes O
Summer O
1943 O
- O
Taken O
by O
Germans B-TER
to O
Riga B-LOC
( O
Latvia B-LOC
) O
; O
Worked O
there O
for O
a O
farmer O
, O
living O
in O
the O
camp B-LOC
of I-LOC
Kaiserwald I-LOC
( O
Latvia B-LOC
) O
, O
submitted O
to O
all O
atrocities O
of O
German B-ORG
SS I-ORG
- I-ORG
men I-ORG
and I-ORG
women I-ORG
. O

Then O
brought O
to O
Strassenhof B-LOC
( O
Latvia B-LOC
) O
, O
where O
she O
worked O
in O
an O
ammunition O
Factory B-TER
. O

Summer O
1944 O
- O
Stutthof B-LOC
( O
C. B-TER
C I-TER
. O

near O
Danzig B-LOC
) O
. O

Winter O
1944 O
- O
1945 O
- O
1945 O
- O
walking O
to O
Kalkau B-LOC
, O
as O
evacuated B-TER
from O
Stutthof B-LOC
. O

March O
1945 O
- O
liberated B-TER
by O
Russian B-ORG
troops I-ORG
. O

Sick O
with O
Typhus B-TER
, O
stays O
at O
the O
house O
of O
a O
farmer O
, O
being O
taken O
care O
of O
by O
a O
Russian B-TER
physician B-TER
. O

Then O
goes O
to O
Byalistok B-LOC
( O
Poland B-LOC
) O
seeking B-TER
family I-TER
, O
without O
success O
. O

12 O
June O
1945 O
- O
Bielsk B-LOC
( O
Poland B-LOC
) O
, O
Children B-TER
's O
home O
of O
the O
Jewish B-ORG
Central I-ORG
Committee I-ORG
at I-ORG
Warsaw I-ORG
. O

August O
1945 O
- O
Zabrza B-LOC
( I-LOC
Slonsk I-LOC
) I-LOC
, O
Poland B-LOC
: O
Kibutz B-LOC
Tel I-LOC
Iczhak I-LOC
. O

November O
1945 O
- O
D.P. B-TER
Camp I-TER
Föhrenwald B-LOC
, O
Wolfratshausen B-LOC
. O

Language O
Yiddish O
, O
Polish O
, O
Hebrew O
. O

Documents O
D.P. O
1 O
– O
Card O
( O
see O
reg O
. O

No O
. O

) O
. O

School B-TER
record O
Finished O
the O
fifth O
grade O
grammar O
school B-TER
. O

She O
is O
now O
a O
dressmaker O
apprentice O
in O
this O
camp B-TER
. O

She O
also O
attends O
grammar O
school B-TER
courses O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

Information O
re O
family B-TER
. I-TER

Her O
father B-TER
was O
a O
salesman O
in O
a O
clothing B-TER
store O
at O
Vilna B-LOC
. O

Her O
mother B-TER
was O
a O
dressmaker O
on O
her O
own O
. O

They O
were O
three O
children B-TER
at O
home O
. O

