Addressed O
to O
R. O
Ministry B-ORG
of I-ORG
Foreign I-ORG
Affairs I-ORG
, O
Rome B-LOC
R. O
Embassy O
of O
Italy O
, O
Berlin B-LOC
M O
Mussolini B-PER
Prague B-LOC
, O
23th O
March O
1942 O
. O

XX O
Re O
: O
Concentration B-TER
of I-TER
Jews I-TER
. O

I O
have O
the O
honour O
to O
inform O
that O
an O
important O
decree O
concerning O
the O
transfer B-TER
of O
Jews B-TER
to O
a O
location O
in O
the O
Protectorate B-LOC
( O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
) O
has O
been O
published O
in O
the O
Collection O
of O
Laws O
and O
Decrees O
of O
the O
Reichsprotektor O
. O

With O
this O
measure B-TER
the O
Jewish B-TER
element I-TER
will O
be O
definitively O
isolated O
from O
the O
remaining O
Aryan B-TER
population O
. O

Of O
course O
, O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
will O
have O
to O
be O
vacated O
by O
Aryan B-TER
citizens O
. O

The O
Reichsprotektor O
’s O
decree O
deals O
with O
this O
problem B-TER
and O
rules O
that O
no O
Aryan B-TER
person O
transferred O
elsewhere O
shall O
suffer O
any O
material B-TER
loss O
. O

All O
Aryans B-TER
living O
in O
the O
area O
chosen O
for O
the O
Protectorate B-LOC
’s I-LOC
Jewish B-TER
ghetto B-TER
will O
have O
their O
losses O
refunded O
and O
will O
be O
transferred B-TER
elsewhere O
in O
an O
appropriate O
manner O
. O

Clearly O
, O
despite O
this O
measure O
, O
those O
who O
are O
to O
be O
transferred O
will O
have O
to O
bear O
some O
sacrifices O
for O
the O
benefit O
of O
all O
. O

The O
local O
press B-TER
emphasizes O
that O
these O
sacrifices O
will O
in O
any O
case O
be O
largely O
offset O
by O
the O
huge O
advantages O
that O
cleansing O
the O
Protectorate B-LOC
of O
Jews B-TER
will O
provide O
to O
the O
entire O
Czech B-LOC
Aryan B-TER
population O
. O

I O
enclose O
a O
full O
translation O
of O
the O
Reichsprotektor O
’s O
decree O
. O

Caruso B-PER
