- O
1 O
- O
Poland B-TER
- I-TER
Action I-TER
1938 O
. O

- O
In O
the O
camp O
Sbonczyn B-LOC
handwritten O
addition O
Report O
of O
the O
couple O
Mrs. O
Rosa B-PER
Friedfertig I-PER
and O
Mr. O
Koppel B-PER
Friedfertig I-PER
from O
Hamburg B-LOC
. O

Tel B-LOC
Aviv I-LOC
, O
Feierbergstr O
. O

16 O
Stenographical O
record O
by O
Dr. B-PER
K. I-PER
Ball I-PER
, O
early O
November O
1944 O
. O

1 O
. O

) O
We O
were O
Polish B-LOC
citizens B-TER
and O
lived O
in O
Hamburg B-LOC
- O
Altona B-LOC
for O
over O
30 O
years O
. O

Our O
eldest O
daughter B-TER
studied O
in O
Frankfurt B-LOC
and O
already O
had O
a O
student B-TER
certificate I-TER
for O
Palestine B-LOC
. O

Her O
papers O
were O
in O
Frankfurt B-LOC
, O
she O
herself O
was O
just O
with O
us O
to O
say O
goodbye O
. O

Our O
second O
daughter B-TER
was O
in O
Berlin B-LOC
on O
Hachscharah B-TER
, O
the O
third O
went O
to O
school O
. O

We O
lived O
in O
Altona B-LOC
, O
Adolfstr B-LOC
. I-LOC

164 I-LOC
. O

Our O
eldest O
daughter B-TER
temporarily O
helped O
out O
as O
a O
guide O
in O
the O
Wilhelmshöhe B-LOC
preparation B-TER
camp I-TER
in O
Blankenese B-LOC
. O

In O
this O
camp B-TER
the O
Polish B-LOC
boys O
were O
picked O
up O
on O
October O
28 O
, O
1938 O
. O

Our O
daughter B-TER
came O
home O
in O
the O
afternoon O
instead O
of O
in O
the O
evening O
, O
was O
very O
excited O
, O
but O
told O
us O
nothing O
. O

2 O
. O

) O
In O
the O
night O
from O
28 O
to O
29 O
October O
between O
5 O
and O
½ O
6 O
, O
still O
in O
full O
darkness O
, O
I O
heard O
footsteps O
in O
the O
hallway O
, O
then O
it O
rang O
and O
2 O
police B-TER
officers I-TER
demanded O
entrance O
. O

They O
came O
with O
the O
order O
to O
pick O
us O
all O
up O
and O
called O
all O
by O
name O
. O

I O
said O
that O
the O
oldest O
daughter B-TER
was O
in O
Frankfurt B-LOC
and O
the O
second O
in O
Berlin B-LOC
. O

In O
the O
end O
, O
however O
, O
they O
only O
demanded O
that O
my O
husband B-TER
come O
with O
me O
. O

They O
also O
said O
that O
he O
should O
dress B-TER
warmly O
, O
have O
breakfast B-TER
and O
be O
allowed O
10 O
Marks O
. O

They O
took O
their O
time O
to O
dress B-TER
in O
peace O
, O
to O
pray B-TER
, O
and O
came O
back O
after O
10 O
minutes O
. O

They O
took O
the O
passport B-TER
, O
but O
they O
should O
have O
taken O
me O
with O
them O
, O
too O
, O
but O
they O
wanted O
to O
refrain O
from O
doing O
so O
. O

Then O
my O
husband B-TER
was O
picked O
up O
and O
taken O
to O
the O
police B-TER
headquarters I-TER
. O

We O
had O
asked O
what O
would O
happen O
to O
those O
arrested B-TER
, O
the O
officials B-TER
said O
we O
did O
n’t O
need O
to O
get O
upset O
, O
it O
was O
n’t O
something O
that O
affected O
my O
husband B-TER
personally O
, O
but O
a O
general O
action O
against O
the O
Polish B-TER
citizens I-TER
. O

At O
first O
he O
would O
come O
to O
the O
police B-TER
headquarters I-TER
, O
which O
would O
go O
on O
if O
they O
themselves O
did O
not O
know O
. O

3 O
. O

) O
Afterwards O
I O
brought O
my O
youngest O
daughter B-TER
to O
school B-TER
. O

When O
I O
came O
onto O
the O
street O
, O
a O
horrible O
picture O
appeared O
: O
everywhere O
policemen B-ORG
who O
led O
Jews B-TER
of O
all O
ages O
and O
sex O
away O
. O

They O
even O
went O
into O
the O
synagogue B-TER
and O
got O
the O
people O
out O
. O

Then O
I O
went O
to O
the O
congregation B-TER
, O
where O
mainly O
women B-TER
and O
children B-TER
flocked O
together O
, O
as O
well O
as O
stateless B-TER
men O
who O
had O
not O
been O
picked O
up O
. O

In O
the O
congregation B-TER
we O
were O
told O
that O
they O
were O
in O
negotiations O
with O
the O
Polish B-LOC
consulates B-TER
in O
Hamburg B-LOC
and O
Berlin B-LOC
, O
that O
we O
had O
to O
wait O
, O
that O
they O
could O
not O
say O
anything O
at O
the O
moment O
. O

From O
there O
I O
went O
to O
pick O
up O
my O
daughter B-TER
from O
school B-TER
and O
had O
the O
big O
daughter B-TER
try O
to O
call O
the O
daughter B-TER
in O
Berlin B-LOC
, O
so O
that O
she O
would O
come O
to O
Hamburg B-LOC
- I-LOC
Altona I-LOC
immediately O
and O
the O
family B-TER
would O
be O
together O
. O

Then O
I O
went O
to O
visit O
my O
husband B-TER
. O

I O
found O
him O
in O
a O
huge O
gymnasium O
where O
hundreds O
of O
people O
had O
already O
gathered O
, O
old O
people O
, O
men B-TER
, O
women B-TER
, O
babies B-TER
in O
prams O
, O
etc O
. O

, O
etc O
. O

The O
congregation B-TER
had O
some O
representatives O
there O
, O
they O
had O
sent O
food O
and O
took O
orders O
from O
the O
individuals O
, O
which O
perhaps O
could O
still O
be O
done O
. O

Miss O
Ellern B-PER
, O
who O
is O
now O
here O
in O
the O
country O
( O
note O
by O
Dr. B-PER
Ball I-PER
: O
working O
as O
a O
social O
worker O
in O
Bnei B-LOC
Brak I-LOC
) O
, O
worked O
there O
alongside O
various O
board O
members O
of O
the O
congregation B-TER
. O

After O
I O
had O
spoken O
to O
my O
husband B-TER
and O
wanted O
to O
leave O
again O
, O
the O
guard B-TER
did O
not O
let O
me O
through O
. O

I O
said O
I O
was O
not O
arrested B-TER
at O
all O
, O
but O
only O
visited O
my O
husband B-TER
. O

He O
replied O
that O
he O
did O
n’t O
think O
so O
, O
but O
if O
I O
had O
n’t O
been O
picked O
up O
, O
it O
had O
only O
happened O
by O
mistake O
, O
now O
I O
had O
to O
I O
'll O
stay O
here O
. O

I O
was O
very O
desperate O
because O
my O
children B-TER
did O
not O
know O
where O
I O
was O
, O
I O
turned O
to O
Miss O
Ellern B-PER
. O

She O
went O
straight O
to O
the O
door O
with O
me O
and O
said O
to O
me O
in O
a O
loud O
voice O
: O
Sheep O
, O
I O
told O
you O
to O
bring O
my O
files O
, O
they O
are O
in O
my O
desk O
in O
the O
study O
. O

Then O
the O
guard B-TER
let O
me O
pass O
. O

4 O
. O

) O
At O
home O
I O
cooked O
lunch B-TER
. O

There O
it O
knocked O
again O
and O
there O
appeared O
again O
- O
2 O
- O
two O
policemen B-TER
, O
this O
time O
to O
pick O
up O
me O
and O
the O
kids B-TER
. O

I O
concealed O
that O
my O
eldest O
daughter B-TER
was O
in O
the O
apartment O
, O
and O
went O
with O
the O
little B-TER
one I-TER
together O
. O

The O
officer B-TER
said O
I O
could O
take O
anything O
I O
could O
carry O
, O
and O
I O
packed O
as O
many O
suitcases O
as O
I O
had O
, O
far O
too O
many O
of O
course O
. O

But O
then O
the O
officer B-TER
let O
me O
go O
down O
the O
stairs O
several O
times O
with O
the O
suitcases O
, O
so O
that O
I O
could O
take O
them O
all O
. O

Downstairs O
, O
the O
Green O
Car O
was O
waiting O
, O
and O
we O
got O
up O
and O
were O
, O
too O
, O
were O
brought O
to O
the O
police B-TER
headquarters I-TER
and O
to O
the O
hall O
I O
already O
knew O
. O

5 O
. O

) O
From O
there O
we O
were O
taken O
by O
lorry O
to O
Altona B-LOC
station I-LOC
and O
to O
a O
train B-TER
waiting O
there O
. O

It O
was O
a O
real O
passenger O
train B-TER
, O
heated O
and O
illuminated O
. O

On O
the O
platform O
stood O
big O
tables O
and O
there O
were O
representatives O
of O
the O
Hamburg B-ORG
and O
Altona B-LOC
congregation B-TER
, O
on O
the O
tables O
food B-TER
packages O
etc O
. O

, O
which O
were O
given O
along O
, O
also O
money O
. O

In O
the O
train B-TER
were O
of O
Jews B-TER
of O
all O
ages O
, O
often O
still O
with O
prayer B-TER
shawls I-TER
and O
prayer B-TER
books I-TER
, O
since O
it O
was O
just O
Friday O
evening O
. O

At O
the O
last O
moment O
my O
daughter B-TER
came O
from O
Berlin B-LOC
, O
who O
had O
just O
left O
and O
was O
informed O
at O
home O
by O
some O
neighbours O
. O

In O
the O
police B-TER
headquarters I-TER
she O
was O
told O
that O
she O
did O
n’t O
handwritten O
addition O
have O
to O
join O
us O
, O
but O
she O
wanted O
to O
be O
with O
us O
and O
just O
reached O
the O
train B-TER
. O

My O
other O
daughter B-TER
stayed O
in O
Hamburg B-LOC
because O
she O
already O
had O
the O
certificate B-TER
. O

That O
same O
evening O
she O
flew O
to O
Frankfurt B-LOC
and O
was O
able O
to O
emigrate B-TER
immediately O
to O
Palestine B-LOC
. O

6 O
. O

) O
The O
train B-TER
left O
at O
about O
½ O
8 O
o'clock O
in O
the O
evening O
and O
at O
5 O
o'clock O
in O
the O
morning O
we O
arrived O
to O
Bentschen B-LOC
completed O
, O
not O
legible O
in O
original O
. O

There O
we O
all O
had O
to O
get O
off O
, O
then O
we O
were O
examined O
for O
money O
, O
where O
several O
people O
had O
to O
go O
through O
posts B-TER
next O
to O
each O
other O
. O

It O
was O
not O
examined O
however O
very O
exactly O
, O
I O
could O
e.g. O
keep O
several O
hundred O
Marks O
with O
me O
. O

Then O
a O
terrible O
march O
of O
about O
7 O
kilometers O
began O
, O
without O
consideration O
of O
the O
physical O
abilities O
of O
the O
individual O
. O

If O
somebody O
could O
not O
carry O
his O
luggage O
or O
fell O
behind O
, O
the O
luggage O
was O
taken O
from O
him O
and O
thrown O
away O
. O

If O
somebody O
could O
not O
keep O
pace O
, O
he O
was O
beaten O
. O

Finally O
we O
reached O
the O
border O
. O

There O
is O
about O
100 O
meters O
of O
no O
man O
’s O
land O
on O
both O
sides O
. O

On O
the O
Polish B-LOC
side O
there O
was O
a O
single O
guard B-TER
with O
a O
rusted O
rifle O
. O

Nobody O
wanted O
to O
let O
him O
through O
. O

But O
the O
Germans B-LOC
pushed O
from O
behind O
and O
pushed O
and O
said O
: O
You O
wo O
n’t O
let O
a O
single O
man O
stop O
you O
! O
Finally O
a O
few O
younger O
men O
formed O
a O
chain O
, O
went O
under O
the O
barrier O
and O
shouted O
to O
the O
Poles B-LOC
: O
Shoot O
us O
. O

The O
Polish B-LOC
side O
then O
shot O
into O
the O
air O
a O
few O
times O
, O
but O
since O
the O
crowd O
was O
pushing O
and O
the O
barrier O
was O
already O
raised O
, O
the O
whole O
procession O
finally O
reached O
Polish B-LOC
territory O
. O

7 O
. O

) O
In O
the O
meantime O
, O
negotiations O
were O
going O
on O
there O
somehow O
and O
everyone O
first O
came O
to O
a O
little O
wood O
on O
the O
Polish B-LOC
side O
, O
where O
they O
sat O
down O
tired O
to O
death O
, O
ate O
what O
they O
still O
had O
with O
them O
, O
and O
so O
on O
. O

From O
approx O
. O

10 O
- O
1 O
o'clock O
we O
were O
in O
the O
wood O
, O
in O
the O
pouring O
rain O
. O

Then O
the O
permission O
of O
the O
Polish B-LOC
government O
arrived O
to O
let O
us O
in O
to O
Sbonczyn B-LOC
. O

So O
we O
were O
able O
to O
leave O
again O
, O
and O
there O
were O
horde O
stables O
provided O
for O
us O
, O
which O
happened O
to O
be O
empty O
. O

We O
were O
accommodated B-TER
there O
, O
as O
good O
as O
it O
could O
be O
, O
and O
some O
people O
from O
other O
cities O
had O
already O
been O
there O
from O
the O
day O
before O
. O

The O
station B-LOC
Neu I-LOC
- I-LOC
Bentschen I-LOC
was O
already O
black O
from O
people O
who O
had O
been O
there O
from O
the O
day O
before O
, O
the O
first O
20 O
to O
30 O
had O
been O
able O
to O
continue O
, O
but O
then O
the O
onward O
journey O
was O
generally O
blocked O
. O

At O
the O
station B-LOC
there O
was O
no O
more O
space O
for O
anyone O
, O
because O
it O
was O
completely O
overcrowded O
. O

We O
spent O
the O
night O
in O
a O
horse O
stable O
, O
or O
more O
correctly O
, O
we O
started O
to O
spend O
the O
night O
there O
. O

My O
husband B-TER
stayed O
on O
the O
ground O
floor O
, O
I O
and O
my O
two O
daughters B-TER
went O
up O
to O
the O
hayloft O
because O
it O
seemed O
warmer O
to O
us O
there O
. O

But O
afterwards O
other O
people O
lit O
lights O
there O
, O
and O
it O
became O
too O
flammable O
for O
us O
to O
go O
down O
again O
. O

Meanwhile O
my O
youngest O
daughter B-TER
got O
very O
sick B-TER
and O
I O
went O
outside O
with O
both O
daughters B-TER
. O

There O
, O
my O
older O
daughter B-TER
also O
collapsed O
. O

- O
3 O
- O
Then O
, O
in O
the O
pitch O
blackness O
, O
I O
groped O
my O
way O
further O
for O
some O
help O
and O
accommodation B-TER
. O

I O
heard O
voices O
and O
saw O
a O
light O
and O
finally O
found O
an O
inn B-TER
. O

I O
came O
into O
a O
room B-TER
smoked O
with O
tobacco O
in O
which O
there O
were O
many O
refugees B-TER
. O

The O
children B-TER
, O
who O
were O
almost O
unconscious O
, O
were O
immediately O
put O
on O
two O
cane O
chairs O
and O
we O
got O
hot O
coffee B-TER
. O

Here O
I O
was O
discovered O
by O
chance O
by O
an O
acquaintance O
from O
Duisburg B-LOC
, O
who O
had O
got O
a O
room B-TER
in O
this O
hotel B-TER
only O
yesterday O
. O

He O
said O
there O
was O
unfortunately O
no O
space O
in O
his O
room B-TER
because O
he O
had O
his O
two O
children B-TER
there O
and O
his O
wife B-TER
was O
ill B-TER
. O

But O
there O
was O
another O
vacancy O
next O
to O
his O
room B-TER
, O
because O
the O
owner O
had O
gone O
on O
a O
night O
’s O
journey O
. O

I O
replied O
- O
still O
in O
old O
ideas O
- O
that O
I O
could O
not O
stay O
in O
a O
strange O
room B-TER
. O

But O
he O
said O
that O
that O
was O
not O
the O
point O
now O
. O

Then O
he O
opened O
the O
room B-TER
with O
a O
randomly O
matching O
key O
, O
and O
we O
found O
a O
wonderful O
room B-TER
with O
a O
tiled O
stove O
, O
electric O
light O
, O
two O
large O
beds O
, O
etc O
. O

, O
and O
so O
on O
. O

There O
I O
first O
put O
the O
children B-TER
in O
their O
beds O
, O
and O
then O
I O
went O
in O
search O
of O
milk B-TER
. O

Finally O
I O
found O
a O
farm O
and O
asked O
if O
I O
could O
get O
some O
milk B-TER
. O

They O
even O
warmed O
it O
up O
for O
me O
, O
and O
I O
brought O
the O
milk B-TER
to O
the O
inn B-TER
. O

When O
I O
came O
back O
, O
the O
children B-TER
had O
already O
recovered O
to O
some O
extent O
. O

8 O
. O

) O
The O
accommodation B-TER
was O
such O
that O
everyone O
had O
to O
put O
themselves O
in O
places O
and O
had O
to O
pay O
for O
them O
first O
. O

It O
was O
not O
a O
common O
camp B-TER
, O
but O
accommodation B-TER
with O
families B-TER
in O
the O
village O
, O
but O
the O
whole O
place O
was O
sealed O
off O
by O
the O
police B-TER
and O
none O
of O
us O
was O
allowed O
to O
leave O
it O
. O

Who O
had O
no O
money O
at O
all O
or O
in O
a O
collection B-TER
camp I-TER
, O
which O
was O
set O
up O
in O
two O
mills O
. O

On O
the O
second O
day O
, O
large O
lorries O
with O
food B-TER
came O
from O
the O
Jewish O
places O
in O
Poland B-LOC
, O
distributing O
bread B-TER
, O
butter B-TER
and O
eggs B-TER
. O

Gradually O
the O
whole O
thing O
was O
organized O
, O
committees O
were O
formed O
, O
delegates O
of O
the O
organizations B-TER
came O
from O
Warsaw B-LOC
, O
and O
the O
head O
was O
Prof. O
Ginsburg B-PER
. O

The O
committee O
then O
took O
over O
the O
payment O
of O
all O
rents O
, O
field B-TER
kitchens I-TER
were O
set O
up O
, O
clothing B-TER
for O
the O
winter O
came O
, O
etc O
. O

, O
etc O
. O

Of O
course O
it O
took O
a O
long O
time O
until O
the O
distribution O
was O
organized O
properly O
. O

We O
could O
n’t O
stomach O
the O
food B-TER
from O
the O
field B-TER
kitchen I-TER
, O
but O
since O
we O
still O
had O
some O
money O
, O
we O
were O
able O
to O
manage O
the O
necessities O
ourselves O
. O

9 O
. O

) O
There O
were O
some O
young O
people O
together O
who O
belonged O
to O
the O
Mizrahi B-ORG
. O

Their O
meeting O
room O
was O
our O
room O
, O
the O
largest O
and O
brightest O
. O

They O
thought O
of O
writing O
to O
the O
Palestine B-TER
Office I-TER
in O
Warsaw B-LOC
and O
asking O
for O
certificates B-TER
. O

After O
some O
consideration O
they O
changed O
the O
plan O
and O
asked O
for O
certificates B-TER
for O
the O
parents B-TER
. O

We O
adults O
considered O
this O
attempt O
to O
be O
ridiculous O
. O

The O
children B-TER
prepared O
15 O
applications O
and O
sent O
them O
to O
Warsaw B-LOC
. O

Already O
after O
3 O
days O
an O
emissary O
from O
Warsaw B-LOC
, O
Dr. O
Wilhelm B-PER
, O
came O
and O
recorded O
more O
detailed O
personal O
data O
. O

And O
after O
a O
very O
short O
time O
we O
were O
informed O
by O
telephone O
that O
our O
certificate B-TER
had O
been O
approved O
. O

We O
do O
n’t O
know O
why O
our O
certificate B-TER
was O
granted O
, O
maybe O
it O
was O
connected O
to O
the O
fact O
that O
we O
were O
known O
from O
Mizrahi B-ORG
work I-ORG
in O
Hamburg B-LOC
, O
maybe O
also O
with O
the O
fact O
that O
our O
eldest O
daughter B-TER
was O
already O
in O
Palestine B-LOC
and O
that O
we O
had O
two O
children B-TER
here O
. O

In O
total O
, O
however O
, O
only O
5 O
certificates B-TER
were O
given O
for O
the O
approximately O
6500 O
refugees B-TER
in O
Sbonczyn B-LOC
at O
that O
time O
. O

We O
got O
one O
of O
them O
. O

The O
passports B-TER
were O
immediately O
taken O
from O
us O
, O
sent O
to O
Warsaw B-LOC
and O
so O
on O
. O

At O
the O
last O
moment O
it O
turned O
out O
that O
our O
older O
daughter B-TER
, O
because O
already O
over O
18 O
, O
could O
not O
come O
with O
us O
. O

So O
at O
first O
I O
did O
n’t O
want O
to O
travel O
, O
but O
I O
was O
forced O
at O
gunpoint O
and O
my O
daughter B-TER
demanded O
that O
we O
should O
travel O
, O
she O
herself O
would O
somehow O
get O
through O
. O

In O
fact O
, O
about O
3 O
weeks O
later O
, O
she O
arrived O
with O
the O
so O
- O
called O
Aliya B-TER
Bet I-TER
, O
on O
the O
first O
Greek B-TER
ship I-TER
to O
dock O
in O
Nahariyya B-LOC
. O

We O
left O
Sbonczyn B-LOC
on O
December O
22nd O
, O
we O
did O
n’t O
have O
any O
money O
left O
at O
all O
, O
and O
the O
whole O
trip O
and O
equipment O
was O
paid O
for O
by O
the O
Jewish O
public O
authorities O
in O
Poland B-LOC
. O

I O
received O
the O
cheque O
- O
5000 O
zloty O
- O
myself O
. O

Ship B-TER
Konstanca I-TER
29 O
January O
. O

