The O
destruction O
of O
the O
Jews O
in O
the O
small O
Lithuanian B-TER
shtetl O
of O
Šaukenai B-LOC
Testimony O
given O
by O
Luba B-PER
Klor I-PER
, O
born O
1927 O
, O
February O
16 O
, O
in O
the O
shtetl O
of O
Šaukenai B-LOC
( O
Shukyan B-LOC
) O
. O

Until O
the O
outbreak O
of O
the O
war B-TER
Luba B-PER
Klor I-PER
studied O
in O
Šaukenai B-LOC
. O

Her O
father B-TER
’s I-TER
name O
– O
Shmuel B-PER
. O

Her O
mother B-TER
’s O
name O
– O
Tsivia B-PER
. I-PER

Née I-PER
Meltz I-PER
. O

Luba B-PER
completed O
six O
classes O
of O
the O
Folks B-TER
- I-TER
School I-TER
. O

By O
trade O
– O
a O
seamstress O
. O

Šaukenai B-LOC
is O
located O
thirty O
- O
two O
kilometers O
from O
Šiauliai B-LOC
( O
Shavl B-LOC
) O
, O
twenty O
- O
four O
kilometers O
from O
Kuršėnai B-LOC
, O
and O
twenty O
- O
four O
kilometers O
from O
Kelmė B-LOC
. O

Not O
far O
from O
the O
shtetl O
, O
one O
and O
a O
half O
kilometers O
away O
, O
the O
river B-LOC
[ O
Venta B-LOC
] O
begins O
to O
flow O
. O

Before O
the O
war B-TER
and O
during O
the O
outbreak O
of O
the O
war B-TER
, O
fifty O
( O
50 O
) O
Jewish O
families B-TER
lived O
in O
Šaukenai B-LOC
. O

Most O
were O
small O
traders O
, O
peddlers O
, O
craftsmen O
. O

Others O
worked B-TER
in O
agriculture O
. O

The O
Jews O
lived O
in O
peace O
with O
the O
local O
Lithuanian B-TER
population B-TER
. O

All O
the O
Jews O
in O
the O
shtetl O
had O
their O
own O
horses O
and O
other O
beasts O
. O

In O
the O
shtetl O
there O
was O
a O
Folks B-TER
- I-TER
School I-TER
, O
a O
library O
, O
and O
a O
large O
, O
old O
synagogue B-TER
with O
an O
ancient O
Holy O
Ark. O
The O
Holy O
Ark O
was O
decorated O
with O
old O
, O
antique O
wood O
carvings O
. O

Tourists O
visited O
to O
see O
the O
Holy O
Ark O
and O
the O
old O
synagogue B-TER
. O

Apart O
from O
that O
, O
there O
was O
a O
study O
house O
( O
Bet O
Midrash O
) O
in O
the O
shtetl O
. O

After O
finishing O
the O
Hebrew O
Folks B-TER
- I-TER
School I-TER
, O
Jewish O
children B-TER
studied O
in O
the O
Hebrew O
gymnasium B-TER
in O
Šiauliai B-LOC
. O

The O
German B-ORG
army I-ORG
entered O
the O
shtetl O
on O
Thursday O
, O
June O
26 O
, O
1941 O
. O

All O
Jewish O
families B-TER
fled B-TER
from O
the O
shtetl O
on O
Tuesday O
, O
June O
24 O
. O

The O
flight B-TER
from O
the O
shtetl O
was O
not O
difficult O
, O
because O
almost O
all O
owned O
their O
own O
horses O
and O
wagons O
. O

The O
Jews O
left O
their O
beasts O
, O
mainly O
the O
cows O
, O
with O
their O
Lithuanian B-TER
neighbors I-TER
. O

Obviously O
it O
was O
not O
possible O
to O
take O
everything O
with O
them O
and O
they O
left O
it O
behind O
. O

They O
locked O
the O
doors O
. O

Almost O
all O
Jews O
traveled O
to O
the O
village O
of O
Sviliaś B-LOC
[ O
Svilė B-LOC
] O
, O
three O
kilometers O
from O
the O
shtetl O
. O

The O
Jewish O
family B-TER
Levin B-PER
, O
three O
people B-TER
, O
lived O
in O
the O
village O
. O

Mr. O
Levin B-PER
was O
ordained O
as O
a O
Rabbi B-TER
but O
he O
did O
not O
work B-TER
as O
a O
Rabbi B-TER
. O

Levin B-PER
had O
his O
own O
mill O
, O
land O
, O
and O
beasts O
in O
the O
village O
. O

Almost O
all O
the O
Jews O
from O
the O
shtetl O
fled B-TER
to O
Levin B-PER
, O
although O
a O
number O
of O
families B-TER
stayed O
with O
peasant O
acquaintances O
. O

On O
Thursday O
, O
June O
26 O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
entered O
the O
village O
. O

On O
the O
same O
day O
, O
at O
night O
, O
the O
Jews O
returned O
near O
to O
the O
shtetl O
and O
spent O
the O
night O
with O
the O
Jewish O
landowner O
Yitzhok B-PER
Meltz I-PER
, O
half O
a O
kilometer O
from O
the O
shtetl O
. O

However O
, O
the O
Jews O
were O
frightened O
to O
enter O
the O
shtetl O
. O

Mrs. B-PER
Pare I-PER
Forman I-PER
went O
the O
next O
morning O
, O
Friday O
June O
27 O
, O
to O
the O
shtetl O
to O
discover O
the O
situation O
therein O
. O

When O
she O
returned O
, O
she O
reported O
that O
the O
shtetl O
was O
completely O
calm O
and O
they O
could O
go O
back O
home O
. O

Upon O
returning O
to O
the O
shtetl O
, O
the O
Jews O
found O
the O
locks O
of O
the O
doors O
torn O
off O
, O
the O
window O
panes O
broken O
, O
and O
their O
best O
possessions O
stolen O
by O
the O
local B-TER
inhabitants I-TER
. O

The O
best O
homes O
had O
been O
taken O
by O
the O
Germans B-TER
. O

Doctor B-PER
Girdrainys I-PER
immediately O
became O
the O
chief O
of O
the O
shtetl O
. O

The O
manager O
of O
a O
cooperative O
in O
the O
shtetl O
of O
Šaukenai B-LOC
under O
the O
Soviets B-TER
became O
an O
important O
figure O
in O
the O
newly O
created O
shtetl O
police B-TER
. O

His O
name O
– O
Berrotas B-PER
. O

The O
Joćas B-PER
brothers I-PER
also O
joined O
the O
police B-TER
straight O
away O
. O

One O
was O
a O
shoemaker O
; O
the O
other O
brother B-TER
had O
finished O
the O
shtetl O
’s O
Folks B-TER
- I-TER
School I-TER
. O

From O
the O
village O
of O
Paveniśies B-LOC
Pavainiškė O
– O
three O
kilometers O
from O
the O
shtetl O
– O
the O
landowner O
Delinninkaitis B-PER
and O
others O
. O

Dozens O
of O
peasants O
from O
the O
villages O
immediately O
began O
to O
sign O
up O
, O
voluntarily O
, O
to O
join O
the O
ranks O
of O
the O
partisans B-TER
. O

A O
headquarters O
for O
the O
partisans B-TER
was O
also O
directly O
established O
in O
the O
shtetl O
. O

The O
German B-ORG
military I-ORG
divisions I-ORG
remained O
in O
the O
shtetl O
only O
three O
to O
four O
days O
and O
then O
continued O
their O
advance O
towards O
the O
front O
. O

All O
authority O
remained O
in O
the O
hands O
of O
the O
Lithuanians B-TER
. O

The O
partisans B-TER
immediately O
began O
to O
arrest B-TER
young O
Jewish O
men B-TER
who O
had O
a O
link O
to O
the O
young O
communists B-TER
or O
party B-TER
or O
had O
held O
positions B-TER
under I-TER
the I-TER
Soviets I-TER
. O

After O
the O
Germans B-TER
left O
the O
area O
, O
they O
arrested B-TER
the O
Jews O
: O
Feivush B-PER
, O
Zak B-PER
Yitzhok I-PER
, O
Sheitl B-PER
Chaim I-PER
, O
Meltz B-PER
Yankev I-PER
, O
Izaak B-PER
Moyshe I-PER
, O
Shultziner B-PER
Efraim I-PER
, O
and O
Furman B-PER
Feyvel I-PER
, O
in O
total O
seven O
men B-TER
. O

The O
partisans B-TER
held O
these O
seven O
in O
the O
shtetl O
prison B-TER
for O
a O
few O
days O
, O
after O
which O
they O
took O
them O
away O
to O
the O
prison B-TER
in O
Šiauliai B-LOC
. O

In O
the O
prison B-TER
in O
Šiauliai B-LOC
, O
they O
tortured B-TER
them O
murderously O
, O
beat B-TER
them O
, O
and O
then O
shot B-TER
six O
of O
them O
. O

They O
freed O
Moyshe B-PER
Izak I-PER
from O
the O
Šiauliai B-LOC
prison B-TER
and O
he O
remained O
living O
in O
Šiauliai B-LOC
. O

Every O
day O
, O
the O
partisans B-TER
drove O
Jews O
from O
their O
homes O
to O
perform O
jobs B-TER
. O

The O
men B-TER
had O
to O
bury B-TER
the I-TER
corpses I-TER
of O
the O
dead B-TER
horses O
, O
put O
in O
order O
the O
destroyed O
roads O
, O
and O
so O
on O
. O

They O
forced O
the O
women B-TER
to O
clean O
the O
German B-TER
hospital B-TER
, O
wash O
the O
rooms O
and O
windows O
of O
the O
police B-TER
[ O
house O
] O
, O
and O
so O
on O
. O

There O
was O
no O
work B-TER
in O
the O
shtetl O
. O

However O
, O
for O
the O
Jews O
they O
dug O
out O
work B-TER
The O
word O
is O
missing O
in O
the O
text O
from O
under O
the O
earth O
. O

On O
Shabbat O
, O
in O
particular O
, O
the O
partisans B-TER
would O
take O
the O
Jews O
from O
the O
synagogue B-TER
and O
their O
homes O
, O
give O
them O
brooms O
, O
and O
order O
them O
to O
come O
to O
the O
market O
. O

The O
murderers B-TER
made O
a O
special O
effort O
to O
herd O
the O
religious O
Jews O
to O
work B-TER
on O
Shabbat O
. O

Some O
yeshiva O
students O
from O
the O
Kelme B-LOC
yeshiva O
had O
fled O
to O
the O
shtetl O
. O

They O
ordered O
the O
young O
Rabbi B-TER
, O
Rabbi B-PER
Feyvelzon I-PER
from O
Šaukenai B-LOC
, O
and O
another O
couple O
of O
Rabbis B-TER
from O
Kelme B-LOC
to O
sweep O
quickly O
, O
one O
after O
the O
other O
. O

I O
am O
not O
sure O
of O
the O
exact O
meaning O
here O
. O

This O
seems O
to O
be O
the O
intention O
. O

Farmers B-TER
from O
the O
village O
and O
from O
the O
shtetl O
would O
come O
to O
watch O
the O
Jews O
sweeping O
the O
market O
on O
Shabbat O
and O
laugh B-TER
. O

The O
partisans B-TER
shaved B-TER
off I-TER
half I-TER
the I-TER
beards I-TER
of O
one O
old O
Jew O
from O
the O
shtetl O
, O
Shimen B-PER
Laser I-PER
, O
seventy O
years O
old O
, O
and O
another O
Jew O
from O
Kelme B-LOC
. O

They O
borrowed O
from O
Luba B-PER
Klor I-PER
’s O
home O
shears O
. O

The O
partisans B-TER
herded O
both O
shorn O
Jews O
to O
a O
tavern O
and O
forced O
them O
to O
dance B-TER
and I-TER
sing I-TER
Soviet B-TER
and O
religious O
songs O
. O

Music B-TER
was O
playing O
in O
the O
tavern O
and O
the O
murderers O
made O
merry O
around O
the O
two O
unfortunate O
old O
Jews O
. O

During O
the O
third O
week O
of O
the O
war B-TER
, O
the O
partisans B-TER
announced O
to O
the O
Jews O
of O
the O
shtetl O
that O
they O
must O
raise O
a O
contribution B-TER
of O
fifty O
thousand O
rubles O
. O

The O
sum O
could O
be O
in O
money O
, O
gold O
, O
silver O
, O
and O
other O
valuable O
items O
. O

The O
contribution B-TER
must O
be O
raised O
in O
six O
hours O
. O

Three O
Jews O
, O
one O
of O
them O
Elye B-PER
Niselevitsh I-PER
– O
a O
textile O
merchant O
– O
raised O
the O
sum O
among O
the O
Jews O
of O
the O
shtetl O
. O

All O
Jews O
from O
the O
shtetl O
gathered O
together O
in O
the O
synagogue B-TER
for O
a O
discussion O
. O

Everyone O
gave O
however O
much O
he O
could O
. O

They O
raised O
thirty O
three O
thousand O
rubles O
in O
cash O
– O
the O
remainder O
in O
valuable O
items O
. O

The O
decree O
concerning O
raising O
a O
contribution B-TER
was O
given O
on O
Shabbat O
in O
the O
third O
week O
of O
the O
war B-TER
. O

The O
Sunday O
and O
Monday O
after O
raising O
the O
contribution B-TER
passed O
calmly O
. O

On O
Tuesday O
, O
at O
5 O
A.M. O
, O
Luba B-PER
heard O
a O
commotion O
in O
the O
street O
. O

Neighbors O
said O
that O
the O
partisans B-TER
were O
searching O
for O
communists B-TER
. O

They O
knocked O
on O
the O
door O
of O
the O
Klor O
home O
. O

Partisans B-TER
entered O
and O
ordered O
them O
to O
prepare O
themselves O
to O
leave O
the O
shtetl O
for O
work B-TER
. O

They O
warned O
them O
not O
to O
leave O
behind O
valuable O
items O
, O
to O
pack O
everything O
and O
take O
it O
with O
them O
. O

All O
families B-TER
from O
the O
shtetl O
– O
old O
, O
sick B-TER
, O
children B-TER
; O
everyone O
without O
exception O
– O
had O
to O
leave O
their O
homes O
and O
were O
forced O
to O
the O
synagogue B-TER
courtyard O
. O

At O
the O
entrance O
to O
the O
synagogue B-TER
stood O
partisans B-TER
with O
a O
small O
table O
. O

Family B-TER
by O
family B-TER
they O
herded O
them O
into O
the O
synagogue B-TER
. O

Before O
entering O
the O
synagogue B-TER
, O
the O
Jews O
had O
to O
give O
away O
all O
valuable O
items O
, O
for O
example O
watches O
, O
rings O
, O
earrings O
, O
and O
so O
on O
. O

At O
the O
table O
they O
registered O
every O
family B-TER
. O

Many O
of O
the O
Jews O
threw O
their O
valuable O
objects O
into O
nearby O
bushes O
and O
grass O
. O

For O
the O
past O
two O
weeks O
they O
had O
continuously O
registered B-TER
and I-TER
counted I-TER
the I-TER
Jews I-TER
in O
the O
shtetl O
. O

The O
partisans B-TER
constantly O
registered B-TER
separately O
, O
every O
day O
, O
women B-TER
, O
children B-TER
, O
the O
sick B-TER
, O
the O
old O
, O
and O
so O
on O
. O

The O
Jews O
now O
understood O
for O
what O
reason O
they O
had O
done O
so O
. O

During O
the O
registration B-TER
, O
Lithuanian B-TER
acquaintances I-TER
came O
to O
the O
Jews O
and O
asked O
for O
their O
possessions O
. O

While O
asking O
for O
the O
possessions O
, O
they O
assured O
the O
Jews O
, O
Anyway O
, O
they O
’ll O
soon O
be O
shooting O
you O
. O

The O
Jews O
did O
not O
believe O
it O
at O
that O
time O
. O

When O
they O
herded O
them O
into O
the O
synagogue B-TER
and O
placed O
them O
under O
strict O
guard O
, O
the O
Jews O
then O
understood O
that O
nothing O
good O
lay O
in O
store O
for O
them O
in O
the O
synagogue B-TER
. O

They O
kept O
the O
Jews O
in O
the O
synagogue B-TER
for O
a O
few O
hours O
and O
then O
they O
drove O
them O
out O
to O
the O
courtyard O
and O
lined O
them O
up O
in O
fours O
. O

Or O
fours O
They O
placed O
the O
sick B-TER
and O
the O
elderly O
on O
wagons O
. O

The O
remainder O
went O
on O
foot O
. O

They O
brought O
all O
of O
them O
to O
the O
courtyard O
of O
the O
Jew O
Rozental B-PER
, O
one O
kilometer O
from O
the O
shtetl O
, O
in O
the O
village O
of O
Šukiškiai B-LOC
. O

They O
forced O
the O
women B-TER
with O
children B-TER
into O
a O
room O
in O
the O
courtyard O
and O
the O
men B-TER
into O
a O
stable O
. O

They O
did O
not O
let O
anyone O
approach O
the O
Jews O
. O

The O
same O
day O
, O
Tuesday O
, O
the O
partisans B-TER
ordered O
them O
to O
take O
off O
their O
better O
clothes B-TER
and O
shoes B-TER
, O
both O
men B-TER
and O
women B-TER
and O
children B-TER
. O

The O
robbery O
and O
confiscation B-TER
of O
the O
better O
belongings O
continued O
throughout O
the O
entire O
day O
on O
Tuesday O
. O

At O
4 O
A.M. O
on O
Wednesday O
, O
they O
herded O
all O
the O
women B-TER
out O
of O
the O
room O
and O
arranged O
them O
in O
a O
line O
. O

After O
everyone O
had O
taken O
off O
their O
clothes B-TER
, O
the O
partisans B-TER
herded O
them O
back O
into O
the O
room O
. O

The O
murderers B-TER
immediately O
divided O
up O
the O
belongings O
among O
themselves O
. O

The O
women B-TER
without O
children B-TER
spent O
the O
night O
in O
a O
barn O
. O

From O
4 O
A.M. O
until O
9 O
A.M. O
on O
Wednesday O
morning O
, O
the O
partisans B-TER
forced O
other O
men B-TER
and O
women B-TER
to O
take O
off O
their O
better O
things O
. O

At O
10 O
A.M. O
they O
herded O
out O
the O
women B-TER
with O
the O
children B-TER
from O
the O
room O
into O
a O
separate O
barn O
. O

At O
11 O
A.M. O
, O
a O
light O
automobile O
drove O
up O
to O
the O
yard O
with O
Germans B-TER
in O
it O
. O

Immediately O
after O
this O
, O
a O
truck O
with O
drunk O
Lithuanians B-TER
inside O
drove O
up O
to O
the O
courtyard O
. O

They O
were O
all O
well O
- O
armed O
. O

They O
immediately O
opened O
the O
barn O
, O
and O
the O
partisans B-TER
from O
the O
shtetl O
called O
out O
from O
a O
list O
the O
names O
of O
all O
children B-TER
up O
to O
the O
age O
of O
twelve O
. O

All O
those O
whose O
names O
they O
called O
out O
, O
their O
mothers B-TER
had O
to O
take O
them O
from O
the O
barn O
and O
put O
them O
in O
the O
yard O
. O

The O
mothers B-TER
were O
then O
immediately O
driven O
back O
into O
the O
barn O
. O

The O
partisans B-TER
chose O
fifteen O
women B-TER
, O
among O
them O
Luba B-PER
’s O
mother B-TER
, O
Mrs. B-PER
Meltz I-PER
, O
Mrs. B-PER
Mikhl I-PER
, O
Mrs. B-PER
Kalmanovitsh I-PER
, O
Ms. B-PER
Ite I-PER
Broyz I-PER
, O
and O
Ms. B-PER
Meltz I-PER
Libe I-PER
and O
four O
men B-TER
– O
Leibe B-PER
Shneider I-PER
, O
Ore B-PER
- I-PER
Feifke I-PER
Leybovitsh I-PER
, O
Shmuel B-PER
Mikhl I-PER
, O
and O
Chaim B-PER
Shloyme I-PER
Kremer I-PER
. O

The O
partisans B-TER
herded O
the O
fifteen O
women B-TER
and O
four O
men B-TER
, O
together O
with O
the O
children B-TER
up O
to O
twelve O
years O
old O
, O
into O
the O
room O
and O
closed O
the O
shutters O
. O

Apart O
from O
the O
four O
men B-TER
they O
also O
left O
the O
shtetl O
’s O
tanner O
. O

They O
herded O
the O
women B-TER
and O
men B-TER
from O
the O
barn O
out O
to O
the O
farmyard O
and O
arranged O
them O
four O
in O
a O
row O
. O

All O
had O
to O
undress O
to O
their O
underwear B-TER
, O
and O
they O
were O
commanded O
to O
throw O
their O
belongings O
onto O
a O
pile O
in O
the O
farmyard O
. O

While O
the O
Jews O
were O
undressing O
, O
Luba B-PER
saw O
the O
known O
lawyer O
, O
the O
Lithuanian B-TER
Kolkhoz B-PER
, O
who O
was O
the O
leading O
murderer B-TER
. O

After O
undressing B-TER
, O
the O
old O
and O
sick B-TER
were O
put O
on O
the O
trucks O
and O
driven O
away O
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
took O
two O
young O
women B-TER
, O
Frida B-PER
Niselevitsh I-PER
and O
Basya B-PER
Yavner I-PER
, O
from O
the O
vehicle O
and O
ordered O
that O
they O
should O
be O
taken O
into O
the O
room O
with O
the O
children B-TER
. O

In O
that O
moment O
, O
Frida B-PER
lost O
her O
mind O
. O

They O
herded O
the O
remaining O
men B-TER
and O
women B-TER
on O
foot O
in O
the O
direction O
of O
Šiauliai B-LOC
, O
to O
the O
place O
of O
the O
White O
Cross O
. O

All O
walked O
only O
in O
their O
under B-TER
garments I-TER
. O

A O
grave B-TER
had O
already O
been O
dug O
beyond O
the O
White O
Cross O
. O

They O
led O
all O
the O
Jews O
next O
to O
a O
little O
hill O
, O
not O
far O
from O
the O
grave B-TER
, O
where O
they O
were O
forced O
to O
lie O
on O
the O
ground O
facing O
down O
. O

Talking O
was O
strongly O
forbidden O
; O
they O
threatened O
to O
shoot B-TER
anyone O
who O
did O
so O
. O

The O
murderers B-TER
began O
choosing O
groups O
of O
ten O
, O
which O
they O
then O
took O
them O
to O
the O
other O
side O
of O
the O
little O
hill O
, O
to O
the O
grave B-TER
. O

Each O
group O
included O
both O
men B-TER
and O
women B-TER
. O

Luba B-PER
was O
also O
amongst O
those O
Jews O
at O
the O
bottom O
of O
the O
little O
hill O
, O
a O
few O
dozen O
meters O
away O
from O
the O
grave B-TER
. O

She O
did O
not O
see O
the O
grave B-TER
, O
because O
it O
was O
among O
shrubs O
on O
the O
other O
side O
of O
the O
little O
hill O
. O

However O
, O
she O
knew O
that O
after O
taking O
away O
a O
group O
they O
would O
hear O
a O
command O
from O
the O
partisans B-TER
: O
Kaluplis O
Kneel O
! O
. O

They O
would O
hear O
screams O
and O
the O
crying O
of O
women B-TER
; O
straight O
afterwards O
a O
shot B-TER
. O

Luba B-PER
did O
not O
hear O
cries O
from O
the O
men B-TER
. O

After O
the O
shooting B-TER
, O
groans O
and O
the O
wheezing O
of O
the O
wounded O
could O
be O
heard O
. O

Germans B-TER
were O
also O
present O
at O
the O
shooting B-TER
, O
watching O
. O

Luba B-PER
’s I-PER
father B-TER
was O
driven O
to O
the O
grave B-TER
in O
the O
fifth O
group O
of O
ten O
. O

Luba B-PER
should O
have O
been O
among O
the O
next O
group O
of O
ten O
. O

She O
turned O
to O
a O
partisan B-TER
from O
her O
shtetl O
, O
who O
was O
making O
sure O
that O
the O
Jews O
lay O
on O
their O
stomachs O
and O
not O
speak O
, O
and O
said O
to O
him O
, O
What O
is O
going O
on O
here O
, O
they O
undressed O
us O
, O
left O
us O
naked O
, O
and O
shoot O
us O
for O
no O
reason O
, O
for O
nothing O
? O
The O
partisan B-TER
apparently O
was O
struck O
with O
sympathy O
for O
the O
young O
girl B-TER
and O
answered O
Run O
away O
! O
It O
ca O
n’t O
get O
any O
worse O
for O
you O
! O
He O
even O
showed O
Luba B-PER
in O
which O
direction O
she O
should O
Run O
. O

Luba B-PER
made O
a O
run O
for O
it O
and O
took O
off O
into O
the O
forest O
. O

The O
partisan B-TER
pretended O
to O
shoot O
into O
the O
air O
. O

His O
family B-TER
name O
: O
Bertnolos B-PER
from O
Šaukenai B-LOC
. O

Luba B-PER
ran O
into O
the O
forest O
and O
hid B-TER
for O
a O
few O
hours O
. O

Lying O
in O
the O
forest O
she O
heard O
a O
shot O
following O
the O
command O
. O

That O
Wednesday O
, O
in O
the O
fourth O
week O
of O
the O
war B-TER
, O
they O
shot B-TER
next O
to O
the O
White O
Cross O
one O
hundred O
and O
ninety O
- O
eight O
Jewish O
men B-TER
and O
women B-TER
( O
198 O
) O
. O

From O
the O
forest O
, O
Luba B-PER
fled O
to O
her O
mother B-TER
in O
Šukiškiai B-LOC
, O
where O
the O
fifteen O
women B-TER
and O
four O
men B-TER
were O
still O
confined O
. O

The O
children B-TER
were O
crying O
terribly O
and O
begging O
for O
their O
parents B-TER
. O

The O
women B-TER
could O
not O
calm O
them O
and O
were O
crying O
their O
eyes O
out O
themselves O
. O

The O
four O
men B-TER
lay O
about O
, O
stony O
and O
lost O
in O
thought O
. O

All O
believed O
everything O
that O
Luba B-PER
told O
them O
: O
furthermore O
, O
they O
themselves O
heard O
the O
shots O
from O
the O
direction O
in O
which O
they O
had O
herded O
the O
Jews O
. O

That O
Wednesday O
night O
was O
a O
terrible O
one O
for O
the O
children B-TER
and O
adults O
in O
the O
room O
. O

The O
entire O
night O
they O
all O
lamented O
and O
wept O
for O
their O
loved O
ones O
and O
relatives B-TER
who O
had O
been O
shot B-TER
. O

Thursday O
morning O
, O
the O
women B-TER
persuaded O
[ O
the O
guards O
] O
that O
they O
should O
let O
them O
and O
the O
children B-TER
out O
of O
the O
room O
. O

They O
took O
most O
of O
the O
Jews O
to O
the O
village O
of O
Svilė B-LOC
, O
to O
Levin B-PER
’s O
courtyard O
. O

Some O
they O
settled O
with O
peasants B-TER
. O

The O
women B-TER
received O
permission O
to O
go O
to O
the O
shtetl O
for O
three O
days O
and O
take O
possessions O
from O
their O
homes O
. O

The O
best O
things O
had O
already O
been O
stolen O
. O

Local B-TER
peasants I-TER
came O
to O
the O
courtyard O
, O
threatening O
and O
robbing O
the O
women B-TER
and O
children B-TER
; O
as O
a O
result O
the O
women B-TER
themselves O
asked O
that O
they O
should O
be O
guarded O
. O

Frida B-PER
Niselevitsh I-PER
was O
there O
with O
her O
little O
brother B-TER
, O
Chaim B-PER
. O

She O
walked O
around O
the O
entire O
day O
naked O
, O
crying O
out O
, O
Give O
me O
back O
my O
parents O
! O
She O
walked O
around O
naked O
in O
the O
shtetl O
and O
shattered O
the O
window O
panes O
of O
the O
partisans B-TER
. O

The O
Jews O
suffered O
a O
lot O
because O
of O
her O
. O

Luba B-PER
, O
her O
mother B-TER
with O
her O
three O
little O
sisters B-TER
and O
three O
other O
children B-TER
, O
as O
well O
as O
and O
Leib B-PER
- I-PER
Shneider I-PER
, O
left O
the O
courtyard O
and O
were O
accommodated O
in O
a O
room O
belonging O
to O
a O
farmer B-TER
near O
the O
shtetl O
of O
Naujieji O
Šaukėnai B-LOC
. O

They O
spent O
a O
few O
weeks O
there O
. O

They O
found O
out O
from O
the O
farmers B-TER
that O
the O
partisans B-TER
divided O
among O
themselves O
the O
possessions O
of O
those O
Jews O
who O
had O
been O
shot B-TER
. O

After O
two O
weeks O
, O
an O
order O
was O
issued O
that O
all O
Jews O
must O
prepare O
themselves O
, O
together O
with O
the O
children B-TER
, O
to O
leave O
for O
work B-TER
. O

The O
Jews O
learned O
from O
the O
shtetl O
priest B-TER
Staševičius B-PER
that O
they O
would O
all O
be O
taken B-TER
to O
Žagarė B-LOC
( O
Zhager B-LOC
) O
. O

The O
wagons B-TER
arrived O
on O
Friday O
. O

They O
allowed O
them O
to O
pack O
all O
their O
things O
and O
put O
them O
on O
the O
wagons B-TER
. O

The O
three O
old O
women B-TER
pleaded O
that O
they O
should O
not O
be O
taken O
to O
Žagarė B-LOC
and O
it O
would O
be O
better O
to O
shoot B-TER
them O
on O
the O
spot O
. O

The O
children B-TER
were O
put O
on O
the O
wagons B-TER
. O

As O
they O
passed O
the O
Jewish B-TER
cemetery I-TER
, O
the O
women B-TER
asked O
that O
they O
be O
allowed O
to O
visit O
the O
cemetery B-TER
and O
bid O
farewell O
to O
their O
deceased O
friends O
and O
parents B-TER
. O

They O
were O
allowed O
to O
do O
so O
. O

Luba B-PER
, O
together O
with O
another O
fourteen O
young O
people B-TER
, O
was O
taken O
by O
truck O
through O
Šiauliai B-LOC
. O

They O
were O
accompanied O
by O
Povilas B-PER
Jočas I-PER
and O
another O
partisan B-TER
. O

As O
they O
passed O
through O
Šiauliai B-LOC
, O
Luba B-PER
saw O
the O
Jews O
assembling O
in O
the O
ghetto B-TER
and O
wanted O
to O
stay O
there O
. O

The O
partisans B-TER
would O
not O
allow O
it O
. O

As O
they O
passed O
through O
Joniškis B-LOC
( O
Yaneshok B-LOC
) O
, O
[ O
they O
saw O
that O
] O
all O
the O
Jewish O
houses O
were O
closed O
, O
the O
locks O
bolted O
; O
the O
Jews O
of O
the O
shtetl O
had O
already O
been O
taken O
to O
Žagarė B-LOC
. O

The O
fifteen O
young O
people B-TER
were O
taken O
to O
Žagarė B-LOC
, O
to O
the O
synagogue B-TER
yard O
. O

There O
they O
found O
Jews O
who O
had O
been O
gathered O
from O
many O
surrounding O
shtetls O
. O

There O
was O
a O
great O
panic O
. O

Povilas B-PER
Jočys I-PER
asked O
the O
chief O
of O
the O
Žagarė B-LOC
police B-TER
, O
who O
had O
come O
to O
the O
courtyard O
, O
What O
will O
happen O
to O
all O
these O
Jews O
here O
? O
The O
chief O
answered O
: O
They O
will O
take O
all O
the O
Jews O
from O
the O
surrounding O
shtetls O
to O
Žagarė O
and O
here O
they O
will O
probably O
shoot O
them O
? O
As O
the O
fifteen O
young O
girls B-TER
were O
being O
taken O
away O
from O
Šaukenai B-LOC
, O
the O
old O
policeman B-TER
Bernotas B-PER
told O
Jočys B-PER
that O
he O
should O
find O
out O
what O
they O
intended O
to O
do O
with O
the O
Jews O
and O
, O
if O
they O
are O
intending O
to O
shoot B-TER
them O
, O
should O
make O
sure O
to O
bring O
back O
Luba B-PER
Meltz I-PER
, O
who O
had O
worked B-TER
with O
him O
under O
the O
Soviets B-TER
. O

Jočys B-PER
informed O
and O
warned O
Lob B-PER
Meltz I-PER
, O
who O
immediately O
told O
all O
the O
other O
young O
people B-TER
from O
Šaukenai B-LOC
. O

They O
then O
related O
it O
to O
all O
the O
Jews O
, O
and O
the O
panic O
in O
the O
synagogue B-TER
courtyard O
increased O
. O

Luba B-PER
Meltz I-PER
, O
Ita B-PER
Broyz I-PER
, O
and O
Shmuel B-PER
- I-PER
Michl I-PER
bribed B-TER
the O
partisan B-TER
Jočys B-PER
, O
who O
took O
all O
three O
back O
to O
the O
village O
of O
Šaukenai B-LOC
and O
set O
them O
free O
. O

Luba B-PER
Klor I-PER
could O
not O
run O
away O
, O
because O
she O
was O
waiting O
for O
her O
mother B-TER
and O
sisters B-TER
, O
who O
had O
travelled O
by O
wagon B-TER
. O

She O
discovered O
that O
on O
more O
than O
one O
occasion O
the O
partisans B-TER
, O
taking O
many O
Jews O
to O
Žagarė B-LOC
, O
shot B-TER
them O
on O
the O
way O
. O

So O
she O
wanted O
to O
know O
what O
had O
become O
of O
her O
mother B-TER
and O
sisters B-TER
, O
because O
they O
were O
late O
in O
arriving O
. O

She O
left O
the O
synagogue B-TER
yard O
and O
went O
in O
the O
direction O
of O
her O
mother B-TER
and O
sisters B-TER
. O

A O
farmer B-TER
noticed O
her O
and O
brought O
her O
to O
the O
police B-TER
. O

From O
there O
, O
they O
took O
her O
back O
to O
the O
courtyard O
. O

Luba B-PER
remembers O
well O
that O
they O
brought O
Jews O
from O
Radviliškis B-LOC
( O
Radvikishok B-LOC
) O
, O
Kuršėnai B-LOC
, O
Užventis B-LOC
, O
Vaiguva B-LOC
, O
and O
other O
shtetls O
. O

She O
then O
talked O
with O
Jews O
from O
Kuršėnai B-LOC
, O
who O
told O
her O
that O
some O
of O
the O
Jews O
were O
shot B-TER
in O
Kuršėnai B-LOC
on O
the O
spot O
. O

The O
Jews O
from O
all O
the O
shtetls O
were O
brought O
to O
the O
synagogue B-TER
courtyard O
and O
later O
locked O
in O
the O
synagogue B-TER
. O

On O
Shabbat B-TER
morning O
, O
they O
brought O
with O
wagons B-TER
Jews O
from O
Bazilionai B-LOC
( O
Bazelon B-LOC
) O
. O

Luba B-PER
talked O
with O
them O
. O

These O
included O
women B-TER
and O
children B-TER
but O
few O
men B-TER
. O

On O
Sunday O
, O
the O
wagons B-TER
with O
the O
women B-TER
and O
children B-TER
from O
Šaukenai B-LOC
arrived O
. O

Luba B-PER
immediately O
told O
her O
mother B-TER
everything O
, O
and O
the O
latter O
advised O
Luba B-PER
to O
run O
away O
immediately O
. O

She O
added O
: O
Perhaps O
you O
will O
be O
able O
to O
save O
me O
and O
the O
children O
. O

Go O
! O
They O
placed O
the O
children B-TER
and O
women B-TER
who O
had O
arrived O
in O
a O
synagogue B-TER
across O
the O
street O
. O

On O
Rosh B-TER
Hashana I-TER
, O
Luba B-PER
was O
still O
in O
the O
synagogue B-TER
. O

The O
Jews O
prayed O
and O
shed O
rivers O
of O
tears O
. O

The O
panic O
among O
the O
Jews O
in O
the O
synagogue B-TER
s O
was O
very O
great O
. O

They O
had O
already O
seen O
with O
their O
own O
eyes O
what O
the O
partisans B-TER
had O
done O
to O
some O
of O
the O
Jews O
from O
their O
shtetls O
. O

The O
Jews O
from O
the O
provinces O
believed O
everything O
that O
the O
young O
women B-TER
from O
Šaukenai B-LOC
said O
about O
the O
explanation O
given O
by O
the O
Žagarė B-LOC
police B-TER
chief O
. O

The O
Jews O
in O
the O
synagogue B-TER
s O
were O
not O
given O
food B-TER
or O
drink B-TER
. O

Every O
morning O
and O
every O
evening O
they O
herded O
all O
the O
Jews O
out O
of O
the O
synagogues B-TER
to O
the O
courtyard O
and O
count O
them O
. O

After O
counting O
them O
, O
they O
herded O
them O
back O
into O
the O
synagogues B-TER
. O

The O
women B-TER
of O
Žagarė B-LOC
, O
children B-TER
, O
and O
some O
of O
the O
men B-TER
were O
still O
living O
in O
their O
homes O
. O

On O
more O
than O
one O
occasion O
, O
their O
representative O
came O
to O
talk O
to O
the O
provincial O
Jews O
. O

He O
reassured O
them O
that O
they O
were O
intending O
to O
establish O
a O
ghetto B-TER
in O
Žagarė B-LOC
, O
where O
all O
the O
Jews O
would O
live O
and O
work B-TER
. O

The O
Šaukenai B-LOC
Jews O
, O
however O
, O
told O
him O
about O
what O
the O
police B-TER
chief O
had O
said O
to O
Jocys B-PER
. O

He O
did O
not O
believe O
them O
and O
calmed O
everyone O
. O

In O
general O
, O
the O
Žagarė B-LOC
Jews O
did O
not O
believe O
that O
they O
had O
shot B-TER
women B-TER
and O
children B-TER
in O
the O
provinces O
. O

They O
did O
not O
even O
want O
to O
hear O
about O
it O
and O
warned O
them O
[ O
the O
newcomers O
] O
not O
to O
make O
a O
panic O
. O

In O
the O
synagogues B-TER
the O
partisans B-TER
registered B-TER
all O
Jews O
a O
few O
times O
. O

Tuesday O
, O
exactly O
a O
week O
before O
the O
eve O
of O
Yom B-TER
Kippur I-TER
, O
they O
drove O
out O
all O
the O
Jews O
from O
the O
synagogues B-TER
for O
a O
roll B-TER
call I-TER
( O
appell B-TER
) O
, O
to O
count O
them O
. O

Following O
this O
, O
as O
always O
they O
herded O
them O
back O
into O
the O
synagogues B-TER
. O

Luba B-PER
went O
into O
a O
little O
room O
, O
from O
the O
synagogue B-TER
corridor O
and O
there O
directly O
hid B-TER
in O
a O
round O
, O
tin O
oven O
. O

She O
lay O
in O
the O
oven O
until O
Wednesday O
morning O
and O
then O
went O
out O
into O
the O
yard O
into O
the O
toilet O
. O

She O
looked O
around O
. O

No O
partisans B-TER
were O
to O
be O
seen O
. O

She O
went O
out O
from O
the O
toilet O
and O
left O
the O
shtetl O
, O
going O
in O
the O
direction O
of O
Šaukenai B-LOC
, O
going O
through O
the O
back O
small O
streets O
. O

She O
walked O
nineteen O
kilometers O
by O
foot O
and O
arrived O
in O
the O
village O
of O
Šaukenai B-LOC
. O

There O
she O
went O
into O
a O
stable O
full O
of O
hay O
, O
owned O
by O
a O
Christian B-TER
acquaintance I-TER
, O
and O
remained O
there O
three O
days O
. O

The O
farmer B-TER
woman B-TER
had O
mercy B-TER
on O
Luba B-PER
and O
gave O
her O
food B-TER
. O

The O
farmer B-TER
woman B-TER
was O
afraid O
to O
let O
her O
stay O
any O
longer O
. O

Luba B-PER
went O
to O
another O
farmer B-TER
, O
Jonas B-PER
Peleckis I-PER
, O
in O
the O
same O
village O
. O

The O
farmer B-TER
’s I-TER
wife B-TER
received O
Luba B-PER
well O
, O
gave O
her O
food B-TER
, O
and O
let B-TER
her I-TER
sleep I-TER
in O
the O
house O
. O

A O
few O
days O
later O
, O
Shmuel B-PER
Michl I-PER
, O
Ita B-PER
Broyz I-PER
, O
and O
Luba B-PER
Meltz I-PER
, O
who O
had O
also O
previously O
fled B-TER
from O
the O
synagogue B-TER
yard O
in O
Žagarė B-LOC
, O
came O
to O
the O
farmer B-TER
. O

All O
of O
them O
gave O
the O
farmer B-TER
money O
. O

He O
bought O
food B-TER
and O
took B-TER
it O
to O
all O
their O
families B-TER
in O
Žagarė B-LOC
. O

Returning O
from O
Žagarė B-LOC
, O
the O
farmer B-TER
told O
them O
about O
the O
situation O
of O
the O
Jews O
in O
the O
Žagarė B-LOC
synagogues B-TER
. O

He O
said O
: O
Oh O
, O
Jesus O
and O
Mary O
, O
what O
is O
going O
on O
in O
Žagarė O
! O
He O
told O
them O
that O
the O
Jews O
in O
the O
synagogues B-TER
were O
walking O
around O
with O
weeping O
eyes O
. O

All O
fell O
upon O
him O
and O
begged O
him O
to O
bring O
them O
food B-TER
and O
help O
save O
their O
lives O
. O

He O
met O
Luba B-PER
’s O
mother B-TER
in O
the O
ghetto B-TER
quarter O
. O

She O
lived O
in O
a O
small O
, O
old O
house O
with O
her O
three O
children B-TER
, O
together O
with O
a O
few O
other O
families B-TER
. O

With O
tears O
in O
her O
eyes O
, O
the O
mother B-TER
begged O
the O
farmer B-TER
to O
save O
her O
and O
her O
three O
children B-TER
, O
to O
take O
them O
with O
him O
to O
the O
village O
. O

The O
farmer B-TER
promised O
to O
come O
again O
and O
take O
them O
with O
him O
. O

He O
brought O
Luba B-PER
a O
little O
letter B-TER
from O
her O
mother B-TER
. O

Among O
other O
things O
, O
the O
letter B-TER
said O
: O
We O
will O
not O
stay O
for O
long O
in O
Žagarė O
. O

They O
are O
saying O
that O
soon O
they O
will O
kill O
all O
the O
Jews O
. O

A O
few O
days O
later O
, O
the O
farmer B-TER
was O
getting O
ready O
to O
go O
to O
take O
Luba B-PER
’s O
mother B-TER
and O
the O
children B-TER
from O
Žagarė B-LOC
. O

However O
, O
he O
discovered O
that O
all O
the O
Jews O
had O
been O
shot B-TER
on O
Thursday O
morning O
, O
the O
morning O
after O
Yom B-TER
Kippur I-TER
. O

On O
the O
Sunday O
after O
Yom B-TER
Kippur I-TER
, O
a O
young O
woman B-TER
from O
Šaukenai B-LOC
, O
Devoyra B-PER
Michl I-PER
, O
fled B-TER
to O
the O
same O
village O
. O

Together O
with O
her O
also O
escaped B-TER
a O
sixteen O
- O
year O
- O
old- O
boy B-TER
from O
Šaukenai B-LOC
, O
by O
the O
name O
of O
Berke O
. O

Luba B-PER
went O
to O
them O
straight O
away O
to O
find O
out O
what O
had O
happened O
to O
her O
mother B-TER
and O
sisters B-TER
. O

Devoyrale B-PER
and O
Berke O
told O
Luba B-PER
the O
following O
: O
On O
Wednesday O
, O
the O
day O
of O
Yom B-TER
Kippur I-TER
, O
for O
the O
first O
time O
since O
they O
had O
been O
there O
, O
the O
Jews O
were O
each O
given O
a O
loaf B-TER
of I-TER
bread I-TER
. O

An O
order O
was O
given O
that O
all O
Jews O
from O
the O
synagogue B-TER
and O
the O
shtetl O
must O
gather O
money O
, O
gold O
, O
silver O
and O
other O
valuable O
objects O
in O
an O
appointed O
place O
. O

The O
Jews O
themselves O
collected O
together O
three O
sacks O
and O
gave O
it O
to O
the O
partisans B-TER
. O

The O
same O
day O
, O
they O
ordered O
the O
Jews O
to O
choose O
ten O
Jews O
who O
would O
wake O
up O
all O
the O
Jews O
on O
the O
next O
morning O
, O
Thursday O
, O
at O
6 O
A.M. O
, O
order O
tell O
them O
to O
go O
to O
the O
market O
place O
. O

The O
next O
day O
, O
after O
Yom B-TER
Kippur I-TER
, O
these O
ten O
woke O
up O
the O
Jews O
in O
the O
shtetl O
and O
in O
the O
synagogue B-TER
, O
ordering O
them O
to O
come O
to O
the O
market O
place O
. O

All O
men B-TER
and O
women B-TER
capable O
of O
work B-TER
were O
required O
to O
come O
to O
the O
market O
place O
. O

They O
allowed O
everyone O
to O
enter O
the O
market O
place O
. O

No O
one O
could O
leave O
. O

A O
few O
partisans B-TER
kept O
watch O
and O
did O
not O
let O
anyone O
leave O
. O

Someone O
gave O
a O
speech O
from O
a O
balcony O
. O

After O
his O
speech O
, O
a O
whistle O
was O
sounded O
. O

From O
all O
sides O
partisans B-TER
with O
weapons O
appeared O
; O
they O
had O
been O
hiding B-TER
in O
courtyards O
the O
entire O
time O
. O

They O
were O
so O
many O
that O
they O
formed O
a O
fence O
around O
the O
market O
place O
. O

Escape B-TER
was O
already O
impossible O
. O

Suddenly O
, O
shooting B-TER
and O
cries O
were O
heard O
from O
all O
sides O
. O

Trucks O
, O
wagons B-TER
, O
and O
light O
vehicles O
began O
driving O
up O
from O
all O
sides O
. O

There O
was O
a O
terrible O
commotion O
. O

Devoyra B-PER
’s O
mother B-TER
and O
her O
children B-TER
and O
Luba B-PER
’s O
mother B-TER
and O
her O
three O
children B-TER
had O
been O
accommodated O
in O
an O
old O
house O
. O

Devoyra B-PER
and O
Luba B-PER
’s O
mother B-TER
s O
went O
off O
to O
the O
market O
place O
to O
see O
what O
will O
happen O
there O
and O
what O
they O
will O
say O
. O

They O
promised O
to O
come O
back O
soon O
. O

Time O
passed O
and O
the O
mother B-TER
s O
did O
not O
return O
. O

The O
children B-TER
were O
very O
agitated O
and O
sent O
a O
six O
- O
year O
- O
old O
boy B-TER
to O
the O
market O
place O
to O
look O
for O
their O
mother B-TER
s. O
He O
too O
did O
not O
come O
back O
. O

Devoyra B-PER
, O
the O
oldest O
of O
the O
children B-TER
, O
went O
up O
to O
the O
attic O
to O
try O
to O
see O
what O
was O
happening O
in O
the O
market O
place O
. O

Devoyra B-PER
told O
Luba B-PER
that O
the O
speech O
on O
the O
balcony O
was O
given O
by O
the O
Lithuanian B-TER
lawyer O
from O
the O
shtetl O
of O
Užventis B-LOC
, O
his O
surname O
is O
Kolkhoz B-PER
. O

Before O
the O
Soviet B-TER
years O
, O
Kolkhoz B-PER
was O
a O
lawyer B-TER
in O
the O
shtetl O
of O
Šaukenai B-LOC
. O

Loba B-PER
and O
Devoyra B-PER
knew O
him O
well O
. O

Devoyrale B-PER
also O
related O
that O
at O
2 O
P.M. O
on O
the O
same O
day O
they O
began O
taking O
away O
from O
the O
houses O
the O
old O
, O
sick B-TER
, O
and O
children B-TER
with O
trucks O
. O

Both O
young O
people B-TER
were O
lying O
in O
the O
attic O
and O
heard O
how O
they O
took O
the O
children B-TER
from O
the O
house O
. O

Their O
little O
siblings B-TER
gave O
heart O
rending O
cries O
, O
calling O
out O
, O
Mummy O
! O
Help O
! O
Shabbat B-TER
morning O
, O
the O
two O
left O
the O
attic O
and O
fled O
from O
Žagarė B-LOC
. O

By O
Shabbat B-TER
evening O
they O
were O
already O
in O
the O
village O
. O

Luba B-PER
went O
back O
to O
the O
farmer B-TER
with O
tears O
in O
her O
eyes O
. O

She O
had O
received O
a O
full O
report O
about O
her O
unfortunate O
dead O
mother B-TER
and O
sisters B-TER
. O

Berke O
’s O
father B-TER
had O
fled O
from O
Šaukenai B-LOC
when O
they O
took O
the O
Jews O
to O
Žagarė B-LOC
. O

He O
found O
out O
about O
his O
son B-TER
and O
took O
him O
to O
be O
with O
him O
. O

Luba B-PER
discovered O
a O
few O
days O
later O
that O
around O
Šaukenai B-LOC
were O
hiding B-TER
fifteen O
Jews O
. O

Four O
young O
people B-TER
came O
to O
her O
Christian B-TER
: O
Luba B-PER
Meltz I-PER
, O
Ita B-PER
Broyz I-PER
, O
Shmuel B-PER
Michl I-PER
and O
Soznye B-PER
Kaminetzky I-PER
. O

The O
first O
period O
passed O
well O
, O
because O
at O
this O
point O
no O
one O
found O
out O
about O
them O
. O

Ita B-PER
Broyz I-PER
’s O
belongings O
were O
with O
a O
farmer B-TER
woman B-TER
Word O
missing O
in O
the O
text O
in O
a O
village O
not O
far O
from O
Šaukenai B-LOC
. O

Ita B-PER
stayed O
with O
the O
farmer B-TER
for O
a O
certain O
time O
and O
it O
was O
not O
bad O
for O
her O
. O

After O
he O
was O
investigated O
concerning O
other O
Jews O
, O
they O
told O
her O
that O
they O
could O
not O
keep O
her O
any O
longer O
. O

Ita B-PER
came O
to O
Luba B-PER
’s O
farmer B-TER
, O
Jonas B-PER
Peleckis I-PER
. O

The O
farmer B-TER
woman B-TER
wanted O
to O
confirm O
that O
Ita B-PER
was O
with O
Peleckis B-PER
and O
ostensibly O
came O
to O
invite O
her O
to O
come O
to O
[ O
live O
with O
] O
her O
once O
again O
. O

The O
police B-TER
and O
partisans B-TER
discovered O
that O
Jews O
were O
hiding B-TER
in O
the O
villages O
and O
began O
to O
conduct O
searches O
. O

Peleckis B-PER
was O
afraid O
to O
keep B-TER
five I-TER
Jews I-TER
in O
his O
home O
any O
longer O
and O
advised O
them O
to O
approach O
the O
priest B-TER
Staševičius B-PER
for O
help O
. O

The O
priest B-TER
counseled O
the O
five O
young O
people B-TER
to O
become O
Christians B-TER
in O
order O
that O
it O
would O
be O
possible O
to O
find O
them O
places O
with O
farmers B-TER
, O
as O
Christians B-TER
. O

All O
five O
were O
baptized O
. O

Luba B-PER
remained O
living O
in O
a O
room O
in O
the O
priest B-TER
’s I-TER
home O
. O

The O
remaining O
four O
remained O
in O
hiding B-TER
with O
Peleckis B-PER
. O

However O
, O
Luba B-PER
could O
not O
remain O
for O
long O
with O
the O
priest B-TER
because O
he O
simply O
disgusted O
her O
with O
teaching O
her O
the O
laws O
of O
her O
new O
faith O
. O

She O
went O
back O
to O
the O
farmer B-TER
Jonas B-PER
Peleckis I-PER
. O

The O
five O
Jews O
were O
informed B-TER
upon I-TER
to O
the O
shtetl O
police B-TER
a O
few O
times O
. O

The O
priest B-TER
, O
however O
, O
had O
contacts O
with O
the O
police B-TER
. O

Every O
time O
that O
they O
came O
from O
the O
shtetl O
, O
ostensibly O
searching O
for O
Jews O
, O
they O
did O
not O
find O
them O
. O

For O
four O
to O
five O
months O
, O
the O
five O
Jews O
remained O
hiding B-TER
with O
the O
farmer B-TER
Peleckis B-PER
. O

They O
all O
slept O
in O
his O
home O
. O

Once O
, O
a O
Tuesday O
, O
a O
few O
weeks O
before O
New O
Year O
1942 O
, O
four O
Jews O
were O
sitting O
in O
the O
kitchen O
and O
talking O
. O

Suddenly O
, O
a O
partisan B-TER
from O
the O
shtetl O
came O
into O
the O
house O
, O
Juozas B-PER
Jocas I-PER
. O

He O
sat O
down O
and O
talked O
with O
the O
four O
Jews O
, O
whom O
he O
knew O
well O
from O
the O
shtetl O
. O

Luba B-PER
understand O
that O
he O
had O
come O
for O
a O
reason O
and O
there O
was O
a O
danger O
. O

She O
went O
to O
Soznye B-PER
Kaminetzky I-PER
in O
the O
room O
. O

At O
that O
moment O
, O
a O
farmer B-TER
woman B-TER
came O
running O
to O
the O
house O
and O
reported O
that O
partisans B-TER
were O
approaching O
the O
village O
. O

She O
told O
them O
that O
six O
Jews O
had O
already O
been O
caught O
in O
another O
place O
. O

Luba B-PER
and O
Sozna B-PER
fled B-TER
from O
the O
house O
. O

They O
heard O
shots B-TER
and O
cries O
. O

The O
arriving O
partisans B-TER
shot B-TER
at O
the O
three O
remaining O
Jews O
, O
who O
tried O
to O
flee B-TER
from O
Peleckis B-PER
’ O
house O
. O

However O
, O
they O
caught O
them O
, O
and O
together O
with O
the O
farmer B-TER
, O
arrested B-TER
them O
and O
took O
them O
to O
the O
shtetl O
’s O
prison B-TER
. O

Hearing O
the O
shots O
, O
Luba B-PER
and O
Sone B-PER
Soznye O
is O
referred O
to O
sometimes O
as O
Sone O
and O
sometimes O
as O
Sozne O
. O

The O
spellings O
in O
the O
original O
Yiddish O
vary O
. O

threw O
themselves O
into O
a O
valley O
. O

When O
the O
shots O
stopped O
, O
they O
stole O
into O
a O
nearby O
forest O
. O

From O
there O
they O
went O
together O
to O
the O
priest B-TER
. O

On O
this O
occasion O
, O
the O
priest B-TER
did O
not O
know O
that O
partisans B-TER
were O
coming O
to O
the O
village O
and O
could O
not O
protect O
the O
unfortunate O
Jews O
. O

This O
time O
, O
the O
lawyer B-TER
Kolkhoz B-PER
came O
to O
the O
village O
with O
his O
partisans B-TER
from O
the O
shtetl O
of O
Uzventis B-LOC
. O

The O
police B-TER
from O
Šaukenai B-LOC
did O
not O
even O
know O
about O
it O
and O
could O
not O
tell O
the O
priest B-TER
. O

The O
next O
day O
, O
Wednesday O
, O
the O
partisans B-TER
from O
Uzventis B-LOC
came O
to O
the O
priest B-TER
and O
, O
with O
revolvers O
in O
their O
hands O
, O
threatened O
to O
shoot B-TER
him O
if O
he O
would O
not O
tell O
them O
the O
location O
of O
the O
Jews O
whom O
he O
had O
converted B-TER
. O

The O
priest B-TER
answered O
that O
he O
had O
converted B-TER
the O
Jews O
, O
where O
they O
were O
now O
he O
did O
not O
know O
. O

At O
that O
time O
, O
the O
two O
girls B-TER
were O
lying O
under O
the O
priest B-TER
’s I-TER
bed O
and O
heard O
everything O
. O

They O
had O
threatened O
to O
shoot B-TER
the O
farmer B-TER
Peleckis B-PER
if O
he O
would O
not O
reveal O
the O
location O
of O
the O
remaining O
Jews O
. O

They O
assured O
him O
that O
so O
long O
as O
they O
did O
not O
find O
all O
fifteen O
Jews O
, O
they O
would O
not O
free O
him O
from O
the O
prison B-TER
and O
would O
subsequently O
shoot B-TER
him O
. O

Among O
the O
Jews O
they O
caught O
in O
another O
village O
were O
also O
three O
Jews O
from O
Kelme B-LOC
. O

The O
six O
Jews O
were O
: O
Devoyra B-PER
Mikhl I-PER
, O
Ore B-PER
- I-PER
Feifke I-PER
Leybovitsh I-PER
and O
his O
sister B-TER
Tzile B-PER
Leybovitsh I-PER
. O

The O
Kelme B-LOC
( O
female O
) O
dentist O
Gurevitsh B-PER
with O
her O
sister B-TER
and O
a O
third O
person O
. O

Together O
they O
gathered O
in O
the O
shtetl O
prison B-TER
nine O
Jewish O
souls O
( O
including O
those O
caught O
at O
Peleckis B-PER
’ O
home O
) O
. O

They O
took O
all O
nine O
from O
the O
prison B-TER
to O
the O
edge O
of O
the O
shtetl O
. O

The O
murderers B-TER
ordered O
all O
of O
them O
to O
undress O
and O
lie O
in O
the O
snow O
. O

The O
winter O
of O
1941 O
was O
terribly O
cold O
. O

Before O
getting O
undressed B-TER
and O
lying O
in O
the O
snow O
, O
the O
scum O
ostensibly O
promised O
to O
free O
all O
nine O
. O

Ita B-PER
Broyz I-PER
did O
not O
undress B-TER
. O

They O
beat O
her O
murderously O
with O
the O
butts O
of O
their O
rifles O
until O
she O
fell O
unconscious O
. O

The O
murderers B-TER
tore O
the O
clothes B-TER
from O
her O
unconscious O
body O
. O

They O
ordered O
the O
nine O
to O
lie O
in O
a O
circle O
, O
one O
head O
next O
to O
another O
. O

The O
lawyer B-TER
Kolkhoz B-PER
personally O
shot B-TER
all O
nine O
with O
a O
revolver O
. O

All O
the O
partisans B-TER
who O
carried O
out O
the O
execution B-TER
were O
from O
the O
small O
shtetl O
of O
Uzventis B-LOC
. O

The O
priest B-TER
related O
all O
this O
to O
both O
girls B-TER
. O

A O
few O
of O
the O
partisans B-TER
came O
to O
the O
priest B-TER
and O
reported O
that O
he O
should O
go O
to O
bury B-TER
the O
nine O
baptized B-TER
Jews O
. O

Captured B-TER
Red B-ORG
Army I-ORG
soldiers I-ORG
worked B-TER
for O
the O
priest B-TER
and O
they O
brought O
all O
nine O
who O
had O
been O
shot B-TER
to O
the O
priest B-TER
’s I-TER
yard O
. O

He O
interred O
all O
nine O
at O
the O
shtetl O
’s O
Lithuanian B-TER
cemetery B-TER
in O
two O
graves B-TER
. O

Luba B-PER
and O
Sone B-PER
saw O
with O
their O
own O
eyes O
how O
they O
took O
those O
who O
were O
shot B-TER
past O
the O
house O
. O

The O
priest B-TER
lived O
in O
the O
shtetl O
near O
the O
church O
. O

After O
this O
case O
, O
the O
priest B-TER
gave O
the O
girls B-TER
six O
hundred O
rubles O
and O
advised O
them O
to O
go O
to O
the O
Šiauliai B-LOC
ghetto B-TER
. O

Both O
girls B-TER
went O
to O
the O
village O
of O
Spaudžiai B-LOC
, O
four O
kilometers O
from O
the O
shtetl O
and O
hid B-TER
there O
in O
a O
field O
, O
in O
the O
farmer B-TER
’s I-TER
outhouse O
. O

The O
cold B-TER
was O
terrible O
and O
Sone B-PER
’s O
feet O
froze O
. O

She O
had O
already O
firmly O
decided O
to O
throw O
herself O
into O
the O
nearby O
lake O
and O
drown O
. O

Luba B-PER
however O
stopped O
her O
from O
committing O
suicide B-TER
. O

Two O
days O
later O
, O
the O
owner O
of O
the O
hut O
As O
above O
. O

came O
to O
make O
samagon B-TER
( O
brandy B-TER
) O
or O
moonshine B-TER
самогон O
and O
noticed O
the O
two O
frozen O
young O
girls B-TER
. O

He O
brought O
them O
food B-TER
and O
for O
Sone B-PER
a O
pair O
of O
fur O
boots B-TER
. O

However O
, O
he O
would O
not O
let O
them O
remain O
any O
longer O
in O
the O
hut O
. O

The O
girls B-TER
persuaded O
him O
to O
look O
for O
a O
farmer B-TER
who O
would O
hide B-TER
them O
in O
a O
wagon O
of O
straw O
and O
take O
them O
Šiauliai B-LOC
. O

For O
this O
he O
took O
six O
hundred O
rubles O
. O

Both O
girls B-TER
reached O
the O
ghetto B-TER
in O
Šiauliai B-LOC
with O
great O
difficulty O
. O

The O
good O
priest B-TER
did O
not O
forget O
them O
and O
very O
often O
sent O
them O
packages O
of O
food B-TER
. O

Luba B-PER
also O
suffered O
in O
the O
ghetto B-TER
. O

As O
a O
young O
, O
single O
girl B-TER
they O
sent O
her O
from O
the O
ghetto B-TER
to O
various O
camps B-TER
for O
the O
hardest O
labor B-TER
. O

So O
it O
was O
in O
the O
peat O
camp B-TER
at O
Bačiŭnai B-LOC
for O
five O
months O
, O
thereafter O
in O
a O
camp B-LOC
near I-LOC
Viduklė I-LOC
, O
together O
with O
another O
fifty O
women B-TER
and O
two O
men B-TER
. O

There O
they O
worked B-TER
in O
the O
yard O
of O
the O
SS B-ORG
, O
choosing O
potatoes B-TER
. O

From O
there O
again O
to O
a O
peat B-TER
camp I-TER
in O
Gaudučiai B-LOC
. O

After O
finishing O
the O
peat O
work B-TER
, O
Luba B-PER
was O
sent O
to O
Pavenćiai B-LOC
. O

In O
that O
camp B-TER
they O
worked B-TER
in O
the O
yard O
of O
the O
SS B-ORG
. O

The O
SS B-ORG
men B-TER
would O
beat O
and O
torture B-TER
the O
Jews O
. O

Luba B-PER
was O
there O
for O
one O
and O
half O
weeks O
and O
decided O
to O
flee B-TER
. O

Luba B-PER
informed O
the O
priest B-TER
about O
her O
decision O
via O
a O
letter B-TER
, O
and O
he O
sent O
a O
farmer B-TER
with O
a O
cart O
to O
collect O
her O
. O

The O
Jewish O
police B-TER
in O
the O
camp B-TER
found O
out O
that O
two O
girls B-TER
were O
intending O
to O
run B-TER
away I-TER
and O
guarded O
them O
closely O
, O
fearing O
the O
bad O
consequences O
that O
this O
would O
have O
for O
the O
rest O
of O
the O
Jews O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

The O
girls B-TER
went O
out O
to O
work B-TER
and O
labored B-TER
the O
entire O
day O
. O

In O
the O
evening O
, O
when O
the O
Jews O
were O
taken O
back O
from O
work B-TER
by O
cart O
, O
they O
both O
jumped B-TER
out I-TER
of O
the O
cart O
and O
hid B-TER
in O
a O
ditch O
on O
the O
side O
of O
the O
road O
. O

The O
farmer B-TER
knew O
where O
he O
must O
go O
to O
meet O
them O
with O
his O
cart O
. O

Half O
an O
hour O
after O
they O
jumped B-TER
out I-TER
of O
the O
cart O
, O
he O
drove O
up O
to O
them O
and O
took O
both O
girls B-TER
to O
his O
shtetl O
, O
Kursenai B-LOC
, O
and O
hid B-TER
them O
for O
a O
few O
weeks O
in O
his O
stable O
. O

Both O
girls B-TER
time O
died O
their O
hair O
during O
this O
time O
. O

A O
farmer B-TER
Fromas B-PER
, O
from O
Kursenai B-LOC
, O
made O
false B-TER
passes I-TER
for O
both O
girls B-TER
. O

Both O
girls B-TER
were O
taken O
in O
by O
a O
farmer B-TER
from O
the O
village O
of O
Nugarės B-LOC
, O
twelve O
kilometers O
from O
Kursenai B-LOC
. O

His O
family B-TER
name O
: O
Povilas B-PER
Hermanas I-PER
Both O
girls B-TER
lived O
freely O
, O
but O
they O
did O
not O
show O
themselves O
too O
much O
and O
as O
far O
as O
possible O
avoided O
strangers O
. O

For O
the O
farmer B-TER
, O
however O
, O
it O
was O
difficult O
to O
keep O
two O
serving O
girls B-TER
and O
he O
found O
a O
place O
for O
Basya B-PER
Yavner I-PER
with O
another O
farmer B-TER
. O

However O
, O
Basya B-PER
also O
did O
not O
stay O
with O
the O
second O
farmer B-TER
for O
long O
. O

She O
could O
not O
adapt O
to O
the O
farming O
, O
village O
lifestyle O
and O
found O
the O
work B-TER
hard O
. O

She O
went O
to O
the O
priest B-TER
and O
from O
there O
wandered O
around O
the O
villages O
for O
a O
few O
weeks O
. O

While O
in O
the O
village O
Aukštelkė B-LOC
Basia B-PER
by O
chance O
became O
acquainted O
with O
a O
Jewish O
young O
man B-TER
in O
hiding B-TER
, O
living O
on O
Aryan B-TER
papers I-TER
. O

They O
began O
to O
meet O
often O
. O

The O
young O
man B-TER
, O
however O
, O
had O
previously O
been O
spending O
time O
with O
a O
Lithuanian B-TER
girl B-TER
, O
who O
became O
jealous O
and O
informed O
on O
her O
beloved O
Jewish O
young O
man B-TER
together O
with O
Basya B-PER
. O

They O
were O
both O
arrested B-TER
and O
taken O
to O
the O
prison B-TER
in O
Šiauliai B-LOC
. O

The O
young O
man B-TER
was O
shot B-TER
. O

Basya B-PER
remained O
in O
prison B-TER
until O
the O
Red B-ORG
Army I-ORG
entered O
Šiauliai B-LOC
. O

She O
, O
together O
with O
two O
other O
Jewish O
women B-TER
who O
had O
been O
imprisoned B-TER
, O
fled B-TER
the O
prison B-TER
, O
along O
with O
other O
people B-TER
under O
arrest B-TER
. O

As O
she O
jumped B-TER
over I-TER
the I-TER
fence I-TER
, O
one O
old O
lady O
broke O
her O
foot O
and O
the O
partisans B-TER
shot B-TER
her O
. O

The O
rest O
fled B-TER
and O
survived B-TER
. O

Among O
them O
was O
also O
Basya B-PER
Yanver I-PER
. O

Luba B-PER
Klor I-PER
remained O
with O
the O
farmer B-TER
Hermanas B-PER
. O

She O
endeavored O
at O
every O
opportunity O
to O
learn O
all O
the O
tasks B-TER
involved O
in O
farming O
. O

She O
learned O
not O
only O
all O
the O
women B-TER
’s O
jobs B-TER
but O
also O
to O
plough O
. O

On O
more O
than O
one O
occasion O
, O
the O
householder O
reproached O
his O
own O
wife B-TER
for O
idleness O
and O
relying O
too O
much O
on O
the O
young O
woman B-TER
. O

She O
fed O
the O
pigs O
and O
animals O
, O
milked O
the O
cows O
, O
knitted O
, O
snowed O
, O
and O
did O
not O
rest O
all O
day O
long O
. O

When O
necessary O
, O
she O
also O
ploughed O
. O

The O
farmer B-TER
was O
very O
pleased O
with O
Luba B-PER
. O

There O
too O
, O
more O
than O
once O
she O
lived O
through O
threats O
to O
her O
life O
. O

During O
the O
last O
period O
before O
the O
arrival O
of O
the O
Red B-ORG
Army I-ORG
, O
the O
partisans B-TER
became O
wild O
and O
cruel O
. O

The O
search B-TER
for O
hidden B-TER
Jews O
intensified O
, O
due O
to O
the O
fear O
of O
leaving O
Jewish O
witnesses O
alive O
. O

Once O
they O
conducted O
an O
inspection O
in O
the O
village O
and O
looked B-TER
for I-TER
Jews I-TER
. O

Shots B-TER
were O
heard O
from O
all O
sides O
. O

In O
the O
middle O
of O
the O
night O
, O
they O
heard O
a O
banging O
on O
the O
door O
of O
Luba B-PER
’s O
house O
. O

The O
farmer B-TER
was O
very O
scared O
and O
quickly O
hid B-TER
himself O
. O

Everyone O
in O
the O
house O
was O
sure O
that O
the O
partisans B-TER
had O
discovered O
Luba B-PER
and O
were O
coming O
to O
arrest B-TER
her O
. O

The O
farmer O
’s O
wife B-TER
suggested O
that O
Luba B-PER
jump B-TER
out I-TER
of O
the O
window O
and O
flee B-TER
. O

However O
, O
Luba B-PER
refused O
, O
stating O
that O
it O
was O
already O
too O
late O
and O
that O
she O
must O
take O
the O
risk O
and O
remain O
in O
the O
house O
. O

The O
partisans B-TER
entered O
the O
house O
. O

The O
farmer B-TER
’s O
wife B-TER
was O
very O
scared O
and O
greeted O
them O
with O
a O
cry O
: O
My O
husband O
is O
not O
guilty O
. O

I O
am O
guilty O
of O
everything O
! O
The O
partisans B-TER
did O
not O
understand O
what O
she O
was O
saying O
and O
calmed O
her O
: O
they O
had O
just O
come O
to O
spend O
the O
night O
and O
would O
be O
leaving O
the O
next O
morning O
. O

The O
farmer B-TER
immediately O
came O
out O
of O
his O
hiding B-TER
place I-TER
and O
welcomed O
the O
partisans B-TER
. O

Sitting O
around O
the O
table O
and O
eating O
, O
the O
partisans B-TER
spoke O
angrily O
about O
the O
hidden B-TER
Jews O
, O
who O
could O
still O
, O
God O
forbid O
, O
remain O
as O
living O
witnesses O
against O
the O
Lithuanians B-TER
. O

When O
I O
catch O
a O
Jew O
, O
I O
will O
cut O
him O
into O
shreds O
! O
said O
one O
of O
them O
, O
gnashing O
his O
teeth O
. O

Luba B-PER
was O
lying O
in O
bed O
with O
blankets O
covering O
her O
head O
and O
heard O
everything O
. O

Early O
the O
next O
morning O
, O
the O
partisans B-TER
left O
and O
Luba B-PER
could O
breathe O
freely O
. O

Similar O
cases O
occurred O
on O
many O
occasions O
. O

The O
Red B-ORG
Army I-ORG
quickly O
approached O
the O
village O
in O
the O
summer O
of O
1944 O
. O

The O
front O
, O
however O
, O
came O
to O
a O
standstill O
and O
the O
village O
fell O
into O
the O
neutral O
zone O
. O

Patrols O
of O
both O
Germans B-TER
and O
Red B-ORG
Army I-ORG
soldiers B-TER
came O
to O
the O
village O
. O

The O
farmer B-TER
took O
Luba B-PER
with O
a O
cart O
from O
the O
neutral O
zone O
and O
brought O
her O
to O
the O
shtetl O
of O
Kuršėnai B-LOC
, O
to O
the O
Red B-ORG
Army I-ORG
. O

The O
village O
in O
which O
she O
had O
been O
hiding B-TER
was O
liberated B-TER
a O
full O
two O
months O
later O
. O

After O
the O
liberation B-TER
, O
Luba B-PER
went O
to O
the O
priest B-TER
and O
thanked O
him O
for O
his O
help O
in O
saving O
her O
life O
. O

The O
priest B-TER
asked O
her O
whether O
she O
remained O
a O
Christian B-TER
, O
went O
to O
church B-TER
etc O
. O

Luba B-PER
told O
him O
openly O
that O
she O
had O
returned O
to O
her O
people B-TER
. O

Itshe O
the O
shtetl O
tanner O
had O
fled B-TER
then O
when O
the O
children B-TER
and O
fifteen O
women B-TER
were O
taken O
to O
Žagarė B-LOC
. O

Later O
Devoyra B-PER
( O
sixteen O
years O
old O
) O
and O
his O
young O
son B-TER
Berke O
, O
aged O
fourteen O
/ O
fifteen O
, O
fled B-TER
to O
him O
in O
the O
village O
from O
Žagarė B-LOC
. O

The O
father B-TER
with O
his O
son B-TER
were O
staying O
with O
a O
farmer B-TER
in O
a O
village O
Traulėnai B-LOC
, O
ten O
- O
twelve O
kilometers O
from O
Šaukenai B-LOC
. O

The O
tanner O
produced O
raw O
animal O
hides O
for O
his O
savior O
. O

The O
farmer B-TER
made O
his O
own O
brandy B-TER
. O

The O
partisans B-TER
came O
to O
the O
farmer B-TER
looking O
for O
brandy B-TER
. O

Itshe O
and O
his O
son B-TER
noticed O
the O
partisans B-TER
coming O
and O
fled B-TER
from O
the O
house O
. O

The O
partisans B-TER
saw O
them O
and O
began O
shooting O
. O

They O
caught O
both O
and O
took O
them O
to O
a O
nearby O
forest O
where O
they O
shot B-TER
them I-TER
on O
the O
spot O
. O

Luba B-PER
does O
not O
know O
where O
they O
are O
buried B-TER
. O

While O
she O
was O
with O
the O
farmer B-TER
, O
Luba B-PER
had O
an O
opportunity O
to O
confirm O
that O
almost O
all O
the O
farmers B-TER
who O
came O
to O
visit O
talked O
about O
the O
Jews O
with O
bitterness O
: O
they O
blamed O
the O
Jews O
for O
helping O
the O
Soviets B-TER
take O
Lithuanians B-TER
to O
Siberia B-LOC
. O

The O
dirty O
Jews O
, O
the O
Zhids O
, O
they O
deserve O
to O
be O
shot O
! O
The O
farmers B-TER
in O
the O
villages O
more O
than O
once O
mentioned O
with O
fury O
the O
Jews O
, O
who O
had O
already O
for O
a O
long O
time O
lain O
decimated O
in O
all O
of O
Lithuania B-LOC
. O

Luba B-PER
can O
relate O
that O
in O
all O
the O
farmers B-TER
’ O
conversations O
concerning O
Jews O
which O
she O
heard O
, O
they O
all O
cried O
, O
Okay O
! O
It O
’s O
good O
that O
they O
have O
exterminated O
all O
the O
Jews O
! O
Apart O
from O
those O
that O
fled B-TER
to O
the O
Soviet B-LOC
Union I-LOC
( O
only O
one O
Rabinovitsh B-PER
) O
and O
apart O
from O
those O
who O
of O
the O
war O
settled O
in O
Šiauliai B-LOC
at O
the O
beginning O
( O
a O
few O
) O
– O
from O
Šaukenai B-LOC
only O
three O
people B-TER
survived B-TER
. O

Presumably O
in O
addition O
to O
Luba O
. O

The O
three O
who O
survived B-TER
from O
Šaukenai B-LOC
were O
: O
Luba B-PER
Klor I-PER
, O
Leibe B-PER
Shneider I-PER
, O
Kalman B-PER
and O
his O
brother B-TER
Khatze B-PER
Zak I-PER
, O
and O
a O
young O
girl B-TER
from O
Kelme B-LOC
, O
Basia B-PER
Yavner I-PER
. O

Leibe B-PER
fled B-TER
from O
the O
Žagarė B-LOC
synagogues B-TER
, O
wandered O
around O
the O
villages O
, O
and O
after O
that O
came O
to O
the O
Šiauliai B-LOC
ghetto B-LOC
. O

When O
the O
Šiauliai B-LOC
ghetto B-LOC
was O
liquidated B-TER
, O
Leibe B-PER
fled B-TER
to O
a O
village O
and O
was O
saved B-TER
. O

When O
the O
children B-TER
and O
women B-TER
were O
taken O
to O
Žagarė B-LOC
, O
the O
brothers B-TER
Khatze B-PER
and O
Kalman B-PER
Zak I-PER
fled B-TER
to O
a O
village O
. O

They O
wandered O
through O
the O
villages O
for O
half O
a O
year O
, O
then O
both O
came O
to O
the O
Šiauliai B-LOC
ghetto B-LOC
. O

They O
survived O
the O
Šiauliai B-LOC
ghetto I-LOC
, O
were O
later O
in O
concentration B-TER
camps I-TER
in O
Germany B-LOC
, O
and O
were O
liberated B-TER
there O
. O

Upon O
fleeing B-TER
from O
Šaukenai B-LOC
, O
they O
were O
both O
still O
children B-TER
of O
twelve O
to O
fourteen O
years O
old O
. O

Luba B-PER
Klor I-PER
remembers O
the O
following O
Lithuanian B-ORG
police I-ORG
and O
partisans B-TER
, O
who O
tortured O
, O
robbed O
, O
and O
later O
actively O
took O
part O
in O
shooting B-TER
the O
Jews O
of O
Šaukenai B-LOC
near O
Šaukenai B-LOC
and O
likewise O
later O
in O
Žagarė B-LOC
: O
The O
leader O
of O
the O
Šaukenai B-LOC
cooperative O
in O
the O
Soviet B-TER
years O
… O
.. O
Bernotas B-PER
The O
shoemaker O
… O
.. O
Povilas B-PER
Jočas I-PER
His O
brother B-TER
… O
.. O
Vladas B-PER
Jočas I-PER
The O
worst O
murderer B-TER
of O
the O
shtetl O
, O
the O
land O
- O
owner O
from O
the O
village O
of O
Paviniśkis O
…… O
Delininkaitis B-PER
The O
tailor O
…… O
Radžius B-PER
-II- O
… O
… O
. O

Arbatauskas B-PER
The O
land O
- O
owner O
…… O
Savickas B-PER
The O
land O
- O
owner O
…… O
Gričiunas B-PER
And O
the O
great O
murderer B-TER
, O
the O
leader O
, O
the O
lawyer O
… O
.. O
Kulokša B-PER
The O
small O
merchant O
of O
the O
shtetl O
…… O
Aleksandras B-PER
Žykas I-PER
The O
writer O
clerk O
at O
the O
urėdija O
( O
forestry O
) O
Jankus B-PER
… O
.. O
Raškauskas B-PER
… O
.. O
Turskis B-PER
The O
last O
two O
both O
landowners O
from O
the O
village O
of O
Paviniškis O
. O

Apart O
from O
all O
these O
, O
dozens O
of O
farmers B-TER
from O
the O
surrounding O
villages O
also O
took O
part O
in O
the O
extermination B-TER
of O
the O
Jews O
. O

Luba B-PER
Klor I-PER
does O
not O
remember O
their O
family B-TER
names O
. O

All O
facts O
, O
dates O
, O
names O
of O
people B-TER
and O
geographical O
places O
which O
I O
give O
here O
in O
my O
testimony O
about O
the O
destruction B-TER
of O
the O
Jews O
of O
Šaukenai B-LOC
near O
Šaukenai B-LOC
and O
in O
Žagarė B-LOC
, O
I O
myself O
lived O
through O
them O
and O
related O
it O
to O
[ O
… O
] O
Konaravsky B-PER
and O
confirm O
everything O
with O
my O
own O
signature O
on O
each O
page O
separately O
. O

Testimony O
given O
by O
: O
Luba B-PER
Klor I-PER
The O
protocol O
was O
taken O
by O
: O
Eng B-PER
. I-PER

L. I-PER
Konaravksy I-PER
. O

Feldading B-LOC
/ O
Bayem B-LOC
1947 O
- O
VIII-23 O
The O
president O
of O
the O
camp B-ORG
committee I-ORG
confirms O
that O
the O
signature O
is O
indeed O
that O
of O
Feldafing B-LOC
resident O
Luba B-PER
Klor I-PER
. O

E. B-PER
Reif I-PER
, O
Feldafing B-LOC
, O
23.8.1947 O
. O

