B. B-PER
Orenstein I-PER
They O
Were O
Five O
Very O
often O
there O
were O
moments O
in O
the O
Hasag B-LOC
Pelcery I-LOC
labor B-TER
camp I-TER
in O
Częstochowa B-LOC
when O
one O
thought O
that O
Jewish B-TER
life I-TER
had O
been O
completely O
extinguished O
. O

The O
tragic O
, O
daily O
events O
led O
to O
a O
depressing O
condition B-TER
among O
the B-TER
camp I-TER
inmates I-TER
. O

Despair O
, O
apathy O
, O
despondency O
unwillingly O
crept O
into O
the O
hearts O
of O
the O
people B-TER
The O
words O
is O
missing O
in O
the O
original O
. O

in O
Częstochowa B-LOC
. O

The O
political B-TER
news O
which O
reached O
the O
camp B-TER
were O
often O
painful O
and O
tragic O
. O

Every O
attempt O
at O
resistance B-TER
was O
put B-TER
down I-TER
, I-TER
suppressed I-TER
, I-TER
and I-TER
decimated I-TER
. O

The O
German B-ORG
military I-ORG
forces I-ORG
achieved O
successes O
on O
the O
Eastern O
Front O
. O

Some O
already O
lacked O
courage O
and O
patience O
for O
the O
long O
- O
enduring O
Jewish O
tragedy O
. O

In O
this O
situation O
, O
there O
were O
five O
people O
with O
a O
supernatural O
strength O
. O

They O
had O
the O
courage O
and O
daring O
to O
sing O
for O
their O
ill O
- O
fated O
brothers B-TER
and I-TER
sisters I-TER
, O
who O
numbered O
6,000 O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

They O
were O
two O
women B-TER
and O
three O
men B-TER
. O

With O
their O
singing B-TER
, O
they O
awoke O
a O
ray O
of O
hope O
for O
the O
future O
and O
a O
longing O
for O
the O
past O
. O

The O
songs B-TER
were O
for O
the O
most O
part O
sentimental O
and O
often O
called O
forth O
tears O
. O

The O
five O
were O
diverse O
in O
terms O
of O
repertoire O
and O
they O
sang B-TER
in O
three O
languages O
: O
Yiddish O
, O
Hebrew O
and O
Polish O
. O

Leon B-PER
Oberman I-PER
also O
sang B-TER
opera B-TER
arias O
in O
Italian O
. O

Roma B-PER
Nodelberg I-PER
was O
the O
most O
sentimental O
and O
often O
sang B-TER
My O
God O
, O
My O
God O
, O
Why O
Have O
You O
Forsaken O
Me O
Psalm O
22 O
and O
also O
, O
in O
Polish O
, O
Harmonia O
. O

Carola B-PER
Mardkavitsh I-PER
sang O
folk B-TER
songs I-TER
. O

Her O
most O
beloved O
song B-TER
was O
Frimorgen O
Dawn O
. O

Leon B-PER
Oberman I-PER
, O
with O
his O
Helden O
Baritone O
, O
quickly O
became O
known O
for O
his O
high O
C O
, O
singing B-TER
the O
arias B-TER
from O
Tosca O
, O
Manuela O
, O
Ravelo O
. O

He O
also O
sang B-TER
folk B-TER
songs I-TER
, O
Lekh O
- O
Lekha O
Go O
forth O
, O
Genesis O
12 O
, O
Rav O
Sender O
, O
and O
many O
others O
. O

Nehemiah B-PER
Tramkovsky I-PER
was O
known O
for O
his O
songs B-TER
Dos O
fishele O
The O
little O
fish O
, O
Goles O
- O
Lid O
S O
ong O
of O
the O
exile O
, O
Yidishe O
Mame O
Jewish O
mother O
, O
Dovidele O
little O
David O
, O
and O
, O
completely O
different O
, O
his O
song O
Matushka O
- O
Tsenstokhova O
Mother O
Częstochowa O
was O
a O
big O
hit O
, O
I O
long O
for O
the O
songs O
, O
for O
the O
brothers O
and O
sisters O
of O
Częstochowa O
. O

Borenstein B-PER
, O
the O
Częstochowa B-LOC
, O
Jewish O
Charlie B-PER
Chaplin I-PER
, O
who O
before O
the O
war B-TER
acted O
in O
films B-TER
, O
principally O
busied O
himself O
with O
monologues O
from O
Sholem B-PER
Aleichem I-PER
, O
Moshe B-PER
Nadir I-PER
, O
Tunkeler B-PER
[ I-PER
Yosef I-PER
Tunkel I-PER
] I-PER
, O
and O
others O
. O

His O
monologue O
Gornisht O
Nothing O
and O
Boy O
- O
material O
Building O
material O
, O
called O
forth O
great O
applause O
. O

The O
singing B-TER
concerts I-TER
were O
held O
in O
various O
places O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

The O
biggest O
and O
most O
popular O
hall O
was O
the O
Tzirk O
Circus O
. O

It O
received O
this O
name O
because O
this O
was O
where O
all O
those O
who O
did O
not O
have O
a O
place O
to O
sleep O
in O
the O
barracks B-TER
spent O
the O
night O
. O

There O
all O
the O
smuggling O
and O
trading O
occurred O
. O

The O
Tzirk O
was O
used O
for O
concerts B-TER
and O
as O
a O
synagogue B-TER
. O

The O
concerts B-TER
also O
took O
place O
in O
Hoffman O
’s O
shop O
and O
in O
barracks B-TER
seven O
and O
nine O
. O

The O
singing B-TER
was O
connected O
with O
prayers B-TER
. O

The O
singer B-TER
of O
Fishele O
, O
Nehemiah B-PER
Tramkovsky I-PER
, O
was O
in O
fact O
the O
cantor O
. O

Rosh B-TER
Hashana I-TER
and O
Yom B-TER
Kippur I-TER
he O
served O
as O
cantor O
. O

These O
were O
the O
most O
tragic O
years O
for O
the O
people B-TER
of O
Częstochowa B-LOC
in O
the O
camp B-TER
of O
Hasag B-LOC
Pelcery I-LOC
, O
1943 O
and O
1944 O
. O

Prayers B-TER
for O
the O
High O
Holy B-TER
Days I-TER
were O
held O
in O
such O
conditions B-TER
that O
they O
are O
unimaginable O
. O

It O
was O
more O
like O
fantasy O
, O
yet O
nevertheless O
it O
was O
a O
reality O
. O

The O
Tzirk O
was O
surrounded O
by O
guards B-TER
, O
who O
had O
to O
report O
if O
people B-TER
could O
pray B-TER
or O
not O
. O

Those O
praying B-TER
were O
the O
ones O
who O
left O
their O
work B-TER
places O
, O
left O
the O
machines O
, O
and O
came O
to O
pray B-TER
. O

According O
the O
German B-TER
conception O
, O
this O
was O
sabotage B-TER
and O
one O
would O
pay B-TER
for I-TER
it I-TER
with O
his O
life O
. O

The O
prayers B-TER
were O
accompanied O
by O
tragic O
crying O
from O
those O
present O
. O

It O
is O
noteworthy O
that O
in O
the O
same O
camp B-TER
a O
wedding B-TER
took O
place O
, O
and O
the O
cantor B-TER
, I-TER
singer I-TER
, O
Nehemiah B-PER
Tramkovsky I-PER
, O
conducted O
the O
wedding B-TER
ceremony I-TER
according O
to O
Jewish O
law O
. O

It O
took O
place O
in O
Barrack O
no O
. O

7 O
. O

They O
were O
five O
who O
sang B-TER
in O
the O
dark O
, O
tragic O
moments O
, O
singing B-TER
away O
the O
pain O
and O
suffering O
of O
the O
Jewish O
camp B-TER
inmates I-TER
and O
comforting O
them O
with O
the O
words O
of O
the O
song B-TER
: O
It O
will O
come O
once O
again O
, O
and O
Israel O
will O
be O
happy O
. O

Binyomin B-PER
Orenstein I-PER
Former O
inmate O
of O
Hasag B-LOC
Pelcery I-LOC
labor B-TER
camp I-TER
Born O
November O
9 O
, O
1910 O
, O
Warsaw B-LOC
Present O
address O
: O
Bamberg B-LOC
, O
Sophienst B-LOC
. I-LOC

12 I-LOC
