Estera B-PER
Stern I-PER
Testimony O
( O
doc O
. O

301/965 O
) O
Typescript O
, O
1 O
page O
, O
210 O
x O
295 O
mm O
, O
Polish O
language O
The O
Parschnitz B-LOC
Parschnitz O
- O
Pořiči(the O
Czech O
Lands O
) O
. O

In O
the O
text O
: O
Parssnitz O
. O

camp B-LOC
( O
the O
Sudeten B-LOC
) O
Estera B-PER
Stern I-PER
, O
born O
on O
November O
27 O
, O
1927 O
, O
in O
Sosnowiec B-LOC
; O
parents O
: O
Aron B-PER
and O
Majtla B-PER
née I-PER
Skóra I-PER
; O
before O
the O
war B-TER
: O
a O
student B-TER
. O

I O
was O
taken O
to O
the O
camp B-TER
from O
the O
Sosnowiec B-LOC
ghetto I-LOC
at O
Środula B-LOC
in O
February O
1943 O
. O

Thirty O
- O
three O
girls B-TER
, O
including O
myself O
, O
were O
taken O
to O
the O
camp B-TER
in O
Parschnitz B-LOC
( O
in O
the O
Sudeten B-LOC
) O
. O

When O
we O
arrived O
there O
we O
were O
barracked B-TER
in O
an O
old O
disused O
spinning O
factory B-TER
. O

250 O
other O
girls B-TER
had O
been O
quartered O
there O
already O
. O

There O
were O
three O
large O
halls O
changed O
into O
three O
large O
rooms O
there O
. O

They O
were O
equipped O
with O
wooden O
bunk O
beds O
, O
cupboards O
and O
benches O
. O

At O
the O
beginning O
there O
were O
300 O
of O
girls B-TER
there O
altogether O
, O
and O
we O
occupied O
the O
room O
on O
the O
ground O
floor O
and O
another O
one O
on O
the O
second O
floor O
. O

After O
some O
time O
, O
a O
year O
after O
my O
arrival O
, O
we O
were O
joined O
by O
a O
transport B-TER
of O
600 O
Hungarian B-TER
Jewish O
women B-TER
from O
Auschwitz B-LOC
and O
by O
about O
600 O
Polish B-TER
Jewish O
women B-TER
. O

They O
were O
given O
the O
room O
on O
the O
first O
floor O
, O
which O
had O
been O
empty O
before O
. O

At O
first O
our O
camp B-TER
was O
surrounded O
with O
a O
fence O
only O
. O

Then O
, O
after O
a O
year O
, O
when O
the O
camp B-TER
was O
taken O
over O
by O
the O
SS B-TER
command O
, O
it O
was O
surrounded O
with O
barbed O
wire O
. O

The O
Lagerführerin B-TER
was O
a O
German B-TER
woman O
named O
Hawlik B-PER
. O

At O
the O
beginning O
she O
treated O
us O
very O
decently O
and O
she O
took O
motherly O
care O
of O
us O
. O

But O
as O
it O
turned O
out O
later O
, O
her O
kindness O
was O
illusory O
and O
strictly O
calculated O
. O

She O
tried O
to O
convince O
us O
that O
as O
we O
were O
safe O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
under O
her O
care O
, O
we O
should O
write O
home O
and O
tell O
our O
people O
to O
send O
us O
valuables O
and O
jewellery O
which O
, O
as O
she O
argued O
, O
would O
be O
safer O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
than O
at O
home O
, O
from O
where O
our O
parents O
would O
be O
deported O
sooner O
or O
later O
. O

Most O
of O
the O
girls B-TER
followed O
her O
advice O
. O

As O
it O
turned O
out O
later O
, O
she O
took O
advantage O
of O
our O
trust O
and O
confiscated O
everything O
. O

As O
we O
also O
learnt O
later O
, O
she O
was O
a O
member O
of O
the O
SS B-TER
. O

Thus O
, O
after O
the O
camp B-TER
had O
been O
taken O
over O
by O
the O
SS B-TER
, O
Hawlik B-PER
revealed O
her O
real O
face O
. O

She O
set O
specially O
trained O
dogs O
on O
us O
for O
the O
slightest O
offence O
. O

She O
robbed O
us O
of O
our O
rations B-TER
, O
which O
shrank O
visibly O
because O
of O
that O
. O

We O
worked B-TER
in O
a O
textile O
factory B-TER
in O
Tratenau B-LOC
. O

Tratenau O
- O
Trutnov O
( O
the O
Czech O
Lands O
) O
. O

We O
had O
to O
cover O
6 O
kilometres O
’ O
distance O
on O
foot O
to O
get O
to O
our O
work B-TER
place O
. O

The O
way O
to O
work B-TER
was O
a O
hell O
, O
especially O
in O
winter O
. O

We O
left O
at O
5 O
o’clock O
in O
the O
morning O
, O
groping O
in O
the O
mountains O
, O
up O
to O
our O
knees O
in O
the O
snow O
. O

The O
girls B-TER
often O
took O
off O
their O
heavy O
wooden O
shoes O
, O
which O
were O
a O
burden O
on O
such O
a O
way O
, O
and O
they O
preferred O
to O
walk O
barefooted O
. O

They O
had O
to O
pay O
for O
their O
carelessness O
with O
pneumonia B-TER
, O
and O
sometimes O
with O
their O
life O
. O

The O
work B-TER
in O
the O
spinning O
factory B-TER
, O
where O
we O
operated O
the O
machines O
, O
required O
a O
lot O
of O
attention O
. O

A O
slightest O
mistake O
could O
end O
up O
in O
a O
disability O
. O

I O
worked B-TER
in O
the O
hardest O
unit O
, O
the O
so O
- O
called O
Feinsal O
. O

Feinsal O
may O
mean O
a O
room O
( O
Ger O
. O

: O
Saal O
) O
in O
which O
they O
spinned O
fine O
( O
Ger O
. O

: O
fein O
) O
yarn O
. O

My O
work B-TER
required O
special O
concentration O
. O

Our O
rations B-TER
were O
very O
scanty O
. O

One O
of O
the O
reasons O
was O
that O
Hawlik B-PER
, O
who O
stole O
our O
rations B-TER
. O

Thus O
, O
before O
leaving O
for O
work B-TER
, O
we O
were O
given O
½ O
litre O
of O
soup B-TER
which O
was O
supposed O
to O
be O
our O
dinner B-TER
in O
the O
factory B-TER
. O

Our O
breakfast B-TER
consisted O
of O
12 O
decagrams O
of O
bread B-TER
and O
bitter O
coffee B-TER
. O

For O
supper B-TER
, O
on O
the O
other O
hand O
, O
each O
of O
us O
got O
three O
potatoes B-TER
and O
a O
spoonful O
of O
sauce O
. O

We O
became O
witnesses O
of O
horrid O
events O
two O
weeks O
before O
the O
arrival O
of O
the O
Red B-ORG
Army I-ORG
. O

Transports B-TER
of O
Jews O
evacuated B-TER
from O
various O
camps B-TER
went O
past O
our O
camp B-TER
on O
their O
way O
to O
Germany B-LOC
. O

They O
had O
a O
few O
days O
’ O
break O
at O
the O
camp B-TER
, O
and O
that O
was O
followed O
by O
the O
selection B-TER
. O

Those O
were O
emaciated O
hungry B-TER
and O
miserable O
people O
. O

They O
were O
so O
changed O
that O
it O
happened O
that O
a O
sister O
failed O
to O
recognise O
her O
brother O
. O

Those O
unfit O
to O
physical O
effort O
were O
finished O
off O
at O
our O
camp B-TER
in O
front O
of O
our O
very O
eyes O
. O

The O
German B-TER
Aufseherinen O
found O
the O
spectacle O
funny O
: O
they O
looked O
and O
smiled O
. O

The O
Red B-ORG
Army I-ORG
liberated B-TER
us O
on O
May O
8 O
at O
4 O
pm O
. O

Recorded O
by O
H. B-PER
Landau I-PER
. O

