My O
Experiences O
and O
Impressions O
in O
Budapest B-LOC
in O
the O
Period O
of O
the O
first O
Jewish B-TER
Laws I-TER
in O
Hungary B-LOC
( O
1939 O
- O
1940 O
) O
By O
Alexander B-PER
Szanto I-PER
( O
London B-LOC
) O
I O
left O
Berlin B-LOC
on O
10 O
December O
1939 O
and O
arrived O
in O
Budapest B-LOC
after O
an O
uneventful O
18 O
- O
hour O
train B-TER
journey O
. O

In O
my O
jacket B-TER
pocket O
, O
together O
with O
other O
papers O
and O
documents O
, O
I O
had O
the O
official O
notification O
, O
stamped O
with O
a O
swastika B-TER
, O
withdrawing O
my O
residence O
and O
work B-TER
permits O
after O
over O
30 O
years O
of O
hard O
work B-TER
living O
in O
Germany B-LOC
without O
reproach O
. O

I O
also O
had O
a O
certificate O
from O
the O
Berlin B-ORG
Jewish I-ORG
congregation I-ORG
confirming O
my O
active O
role O
with O
them O
over O
a O
long O
period O
, O
plus O
a O
personal O
letter B-TER
of O
recommendation O
to O
the O
general O
secretary O
of O
the O
Budapest B-LOC
congregation B-TER
from O
our O
director O
Heinrich B-PER
Stahl I-PER
, O
the O
chairman O
of O
the O
Berlin B-LOC
congregation B-ORG
. O

I O
heard O
my O
last O
official O
German B-LOC
words O
at O
the O
border O
crossing O
from O
the O
mouth O
of O
a O
customs O
officer B-TER
who O
glared O
at O
me O
martially O
. O

Having O
inspected O
my O
passport B-TER
he O
asked O
with O
a O
snarl O
: O
You O
’re O
Jewish O
? O
I O
agreed O
and O
added O
: O
I O
’m O
emigrating O
. O

Huh O
, O
and O
about O
time O
too O
, O
he O
answered O
. O

Those O
were O
the O
last O
German B-LOC
words O
which O
set O
me O
on O
my O
way O
. O

In O
the O
first O
days O
of O
my O
stay O
in O
Budapest B-LOC
as O
I O
wandered O
the O
streets O
I O
was O
struck O
initially O
by O
the O
great O
difference O
between O
the O
everyday O
life O
of O
Germany B-LOC
at O
war B-TER
and O
that O
of O
Hungary B-LOC
which O
was O
still O
neutral B-TER
. O

In O
Germany B-LOC
there O
was O
already O
food B-TER
rationing I-TER
, O
with O
shortages O
in O
the O
shops O
and O
restrictions B-TER
, O
while O
here O
everything O
was O
still O
available O
and O
plentiful O
. O

Shop O
windows O
everywhere O
were O
full O
to O
bursting O
and O
there O
was O
no O
trace O
of O
shortage O
. O

But O
I O
soon O
discovered O
the O
other O
side O
of O
the O
coin O
, O
through O
conversations O
with O
relatives O
and O
friends O
as O
well O
by O
personal O
experience O
. O

Everything O
had O
got O
a O
lot O
dearer O
, O
prices O
were O
wildly O
disproportionate O
to O
wages O
. O

Many O
economic B-TER
sectors O
were O
in O
decline O
, O
state O
unemployment O
benefit O
did O
not O
exist O
, O
broad O
sections O
of O
the O
population O
were O
living O
in O
great O
misery B-TER
. O

The O
Jews O
were O
hardest O
hit O
. O

Following O
the O
absorption O
of O
Austria B-LOC
into O
the O
Third B-TER
Reich I-TER
in O
March O
1938 O
, O
Hungary B-LOC
had O
become O
directly O
adjacent O
to O
Nazi B-TER
Germany B-LOC
and O
the O
Hungarian B-LOC
government B-TER
could O
no O
longer O
evade O
the O
growing O
influence O
of O
Hitler B-PER
. O

It O
enacted O
a O
rapid O
succession O
of O
so O
- O
called O
Jewish B-TER
Laws I-TER
, O
which O
in O
the O
economic B-TER
sphere O
gravely O
damaged O
Jewish O
interests O
. O

The O
proportion B-TER
of I-TER
Jews I-TER
in O
individual O
trades O
was O
limited O
to O
a O
fixed O
percentage O
. O

Where O
the O
proportion B-TER
of I-TER
Jewish I-TER
employees O
exceeded O
this O
percentage O
, O
there O
had O
to O
be O
dismissals B-TER
. O

Similarly O
, O
the O
total O
of O
wages O
paid O
to O
Jews O
could O
not O
exceed O
this O
percentage O
. O

Public O
contracts O
were O
no O
longer O
awarded O
to O
Jewish O
firms B-TER
. O

Jews O
could O
no O
longer O
work B-TER
in O
state O
monopoly O
sectors O
, O
for O
example O
the O
tobacco O
trade O
. O

The O
number O
of O
Jewish O
doctors B-TER
and O
lawyers B-TER
was O
drastically O
reduced O
, O
other O
free O
professions O
were O
affected O
too O
. O

Jewish O
theatre B-TER
and O
cinema O
proprietors O
lost O
their O
licences O
. O

The O
press B-TER
was O
de O
- O
jewified O
. O

All O
of O
these O
legal B-TER
measures I-TER
, O
which O
in O
their O
detail O
were O
full O
of O
multiple O
clauses O
and O
in O
their O
complexity O
gave O
great O
scope O
to O
the O
most O
devious O
administrative O
interpretations O
and O
applications O
, O
resulted O
in O
great O
unemployment O
among O
Jews O
. O

Although O
the O
wording O
of O
the O
Law B-TER
provided O
for O
a O
stage O
- O
by O
- O
stage O
implementation O
lasting O
over O
several O
years O
, O
31 O
December O
1939 O
did O
constitute O
an O
important O
marker O
date O
for O
dismissals B-TER
, O
and O
so O
I O
was O
a O
witness O
shortly O
after O
my O
arrival O
to O
thousands O
and O
thousands O
of O
Jewish O
employees O
losing O
their O
livelihood O
. O

Everybody O
to O
whom O
I O
had O
the O
chance O
to O
speak O
– O
which O
later O
on O
included O
not O
only O
the O
man O
in O
the O
street O
but O
also O
circles O
of O
people O
with O
inside O
knowledge O
– O
was O
unanimously O
and O
firmly O
convinced O
that O
the O
anti B-TER
- I-TER
Jewish I-TER
economic I-TER
policies I-TER
of O
the O
government B-TER
were O
due O
to O
external O
pressure O
. O

The O
Nazis O
were O
at O
the O
borders O
, O
the O
Nazis O
had O
helped O
the O
Hungarians B-LOC
to O
territorial O
gains O
– O
following O
the O
Munich B-LOC
agreement O
and O
the O
collapse O
of O
Czechoslovakia B-LOC
, O
Carpathian B-LOC
Ruthenia I-LOC
and O
some O
Slovak B-LOC
areas O
were O
ceded O
to O
Hungary B-LOC
– O
and O
now O
the O
Hungarian B-LOC
government B-TER
had O
to O
pay O
the O
price O
. O

They O
also O
had O
to O
bear O
in O
mind O
that O
internally O
there O
was O
a O
powerful O
German B-LOC
minority B-TER
, O
the O
so O
- O
called O
Swabians B-LOC
, O
who O
were O
vociferously O
making O
pro B-TER
- I-TER
Nazi I-TER
propaganda I-TER
, O
as O
well O
as O
a O
far O
- O
right O
Fascist B-TER
party I-TER
, O
the O
so O
- O
called O
Arrow B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
, O
and O
the O
government B-TER
’s I-TER
Jewish O
policy B-TER
had O
to O
take O
the O
wind O
out O
of O
their O
sails O
. O

The O
Jewish B-TER
organisations I-TER
in O
Hungary B-LOC
for O
their O
part O
took O
measures O
to O
help O
economically B-TER
victimised I-TER
Jews I-TER
, O
supporting O
those O
dismissed B-TER
, O
moving O
the O
unemployed O
into O
other O
occupations O
, O
and O
so O
on O
. O

Since O
I O
had O
experience O
of O
working B-TER
in O
just O
this O
area O
of O
economic B-TER
policy I-TER
, O
I O
was O
asked O
by O
the O
leaders B-TER
of O
the O
Budapest B-LOC
congregation B-TER
, O
the O
chairman O
Samuel B-PER
Stern I-PER
and O
the O
general O
secretary O
Mr O
Eppler B-PER
, O
to O
contribute O
to O
the O
work B-TER
of O
the O
newly O
established O
agencies O
. O

On O
taking O
up O
this O
work B-TER
I O
found O
a O
mood O
among O
the O
members O
of O
the O
congregation B-TER
similar O
to O
that O
which O
had O
prevailed O
in O
April O
1933 O
in O
Berlin B-LOC
. O

Many O
thousands O
of O
our O
fellow O
Jews O
sought O
advice O
and O
assistance O
from O
the O
congregation B-TER
, O
our O
offices O
were O
as O
good O
as O
besieged O
by O
them O
daily O
. O

The O
large O
congregation B-TER
building O
located O
in O
Sip B-LOC
utca I-LOC
was O
insufficient O
, O
and O
so O
new O
headquarters O
was O
set O
up O
on O
Bethlen B-LOC
ter I-LOC
. O

The O
offices O
in O
this O
building O
, O
which O
had O
previously O
been O
used O
for O
school B-TER
purposes O
, O
were O
under O
construction O
when O
I O
began O
working O
there O
in O
January O
1940 O
. O

The O
work O
took O
place O
under O
the O
auspices O
of O
the O
Budapest B-LOC
congregation B-TER
, O
but O
it O
ranged O
over O
the O
whole O
country O
. O

It O
was O
decided O
to O
have O
the O
work B-TER
carried O
out O
by O
two O
parallel O
organisations B-TER
, O
both O
of O
which O
were O
based O
in O
the O
building O
on O
Bethlen B-LOC
ter I-LOC
. O

One O
of O
them O
was O
OMZSA B-ORG
( O
short O
for O
Orszagos B-ORG
Magyar I-ORG
Zaido I-ORG
Segitoe I-ORG
Akcio I-ORG
) O
, O
which O
was O
tasked O
with O
procuring O
the O
resources O
for O
the O
aid B-TER
programme I-TER
through O
large O
collections O
across O
the O
whole O
country O
. O

The O
other O
was O
Partfogo B-ORG
- I-ORG
Iroda I-ORG
( O
support B-TER
office I-TER
) O
, O
which O
was O
responsible O
for O
distributing O
the O
support O
and O
providing O
practical O
economic B-TER
assistance I-TER
. O

Its O
main O
departments O
were O
: O
welfare B-TER
, O
arranging O
employment B-TER
, O
changes B-TER
of I-TER
occupation I-TER
, O
emigration B-TER
, O
refugee B-TER
care O
, O
legal B-TER
advice O
, O
loans B-TER
. O

Among O
the O
many O
hundreds O
and O
thousands O
who O
found O
their O
way O
every O
day O
to O
the O
offices O
on O
Bethlen B-LOC
ter I-LOC
the O
main O
contingent O
was O
made O
up O
of O
unemployed O
workers B-TER
who O
had O
been O
thrown B-TER
out I-TER
of I-TER
their I-TER
jobs I-TER
by O
the O
Jewish B-TER
Laws I-TER
. O

There O
were O
two O
ways O
in O
which O
they O
could O
be O
helped O
. O

The O
first O
was O
by O
arranging O
employment B-TER
directly O
. O

There O
were O
still O
a O
large O
number O
of O
Jewish O
employers O
in O
whose O
business B-TER
or O
trade B-TER
the O
percentage O
of O
Jewish O
employees O
laid O
down O
had O
not O
been O
exceeded O
or O
had O
not O
yet O
been O
reached O
, O
so O
that O
they O
were O
in O
a O
position O
to O
engage O
additional O
Jewish O
workers B-TER
. O

Tracking O
down O
these O
possibilities O
and O
getting O
the O
employers O
concerned O
to O
do O
their O
duty O
by O
their O
jobless O
fellow O
Jews O
, O
even O
at O
the O
cost O
of O
material O
sacrifices O
, O
was O
hard O
and O
difficult O
work B-TER
, O
which O
however O
in O
many O
cases O
we O
did O
successfully O
carry O
out O
. O

The O
second O
way O
was O
by O
redeployment B-TER
in O
manual O
occupations O
in O
which O
there O
was O
still O
room O
for O
Jews O
. O

To O
this O
end O
we O
arranged O
a O
number O
of O
redeployment B-TER
courses I-TER
and O
training B-TER
programmes I-TER
. O

I O
was O
able O
to O
make O
use O
of O
a O
great O
deal O
of O
the O
experience O
I O
had O
gained O
in O
Berlin B-LOC
in O
the O
previous O
years O
and O
to O
give O
much O
advice O
, O
although O
in O
many O
respects O
the O
problems O
faced O
were O
different O
. O

Difficulties O
came O
from O
two O
quarters O
. O

First O
, O
the O
authorities B-TER
. O

In O
their O
individual O
offices O
there O
was O
no O
consistent O
line O
about O
their O
attitude O
to O
the O
social O
work B-TER
of O
the O
Jewish B-TER
organisations I-TER
. O

The O
general O
framework O
was O
laid O
down O
by O
the O
Jewish B-TER
Laws I-TER
, O
but O
the O
implementation O
of O
them O
in O
concrete O
individual O
cases O
varied O
according O
to O
the O
workings O
of O
the O
lower O
levels O
of O
bureaucracy O
. O

But O
that O
depended O
in O
turn O
on O
quite O
uncontrollable O
and O
unpredictable O
influences O
. O

For O
instance O
, O
on O
whether O
there O
was O
an O
official O
sympathetic O
to O
the O
Arrow B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
in O
the O
appropriate O
department O
or O
someone O
open O
to O
humane O
arguments O
. O

It O
depended O
very O
often O
on O
the O
general O
mood O
in O
the O
country O
, O
which O
changed O
according O
to O
the O
progress O
of O
the O
war B-TER
. O

If O
there O
were O
reports O
from O
the O
front B-TER
which O
were O
unfavourable O
for O
the O
Germans B-LOC
, O
it O
had O
an O
impact O
on O
the O
mood O
right O
down O
to O
the O
smallest O
administrative O
office O
in O
some O
godforsaken O
Hungarian B-LOC
one O
- O
horse O
town O
, O
the O
most O
dyed O
- O
in O
- O
the O
wool O
antisemites B-TER
fell O
silent O
, O
and O
on O
such O
days O
the O
Jews O
could O
to O
some O
extent O
feel O
safe O
from O
any O
dirty O
tricks O
by O
the O
authorities B-TER
. O

But O
if O
things O
were O
going O
the O
other O
way O
– O
and O
unfortunately O
in O
that O
first O
period O
of O
the O
war B-TER
they O
usually O
were O
– O
if O
the O
Germans B-LOC
landed O
in O
Norway B-LOC
or O
broke O
through O
the O
Maginot O
line O
in O
France B-LOC
or O
dropped O
parachute O
troops O
in O
Crete B-LOC
, O
then O
the O
Jews O
all O
round O
the O
Sip B-LOC
utca I-LOC
had O
a O
bad O
day O
. O

Hungary B-LOC
was O
still O
neutral B-TER
, O
but O
the O
populace O
followed O
events O
in O
the O
war B-TER
feverishly O
and O
despite O
all O
the O
complexity O
of O
internal B-TER
politics I-TER
fell O
broadly O
speaking O
into O
only O
two O
camps O
: O
on O
the O
one O
hand O
the O
pro- O
Germans B-LOC
, O
who O
were O
also O
Jew B-TER
- I-TER
haters I-TER
, O
and O
on O
the O
other O
the O
anti- O
Germans B-LOC
, O
whose O
attitude O
to O
the O
Jews O
was O
in O
some O
measure O
benign O
. O

The O
varying O
but O
generally O
nasty O
attitude O
of O
the O
administrative O
authorities O
made O
our O
work O
hugely O
more O
difficult O
. O

Thus O
for O
example O
every O
redeployment B-TER
course I-TER
was O
subject O
to O
authorisation O
. O

And O
this O
authorisation O
was O
very O
often O
denied O
or O
– O
what O
was O
worse O
– O
simply O
revoked O
after O
the O
course B-TER
had O
already O
started O
and O
considerable O
funds O
and O
effort O
had O
been O
put O
into O
it O
. O

I O
recall O
the O
huge O
amount O
of O
inconvenience O
and O
running O
around O
caused O
by O
every O
single O
case O
, O
how O
often O
one O
ministry O
negated O
what O
the O
other O
had O
approved O
after O
long O
official O
processes O
, O
how O
in O
any O
number O
of O
cases O
at O
the O
end O
a O
subordinate O
police B-TER
officer I-TER
wrecked O
the O
work B-TER
of O
many O
months O
by O
some O
trick O
or O
other O
. O

Every O
junior O
official O
and O
bureaucrat O
acted O
like O
a O
dictator O
towards O
the O
Jews O
, O
the O
fate O
of O
hundreds O
of O
human O
beings O
depended O
on O
his O
good O
or O
bad O
humour B-TER
. O

On O
the O
other O
hand O
it O
was O
sometimes O
possible O
by O
means O
of O
greasing O
a O
palm O
to O
achieve O
instantly O
what O
otherwise O
would O
have O
been O
pursued O
in O
vain O
for O
months O
. O

The O
other O
difficulty O
arose O
from O
the O
mentality O
of O
our O
own O
people O
. O

It O
is O
true O
that O
the O
Hungarian B-LOC
Jews O
– O
if O
something O
hit O
them O
hard O
– O
could O
easily O
get O
into O
a O
mood O
of O
panic O
, O
but O
usually O
that O
subsided O
and O
gave O
way O
to O
the O
general O
nonchalance O
which O
is O
a O
fundamental O
trait O
not O
only O
of O
the O
Hungarian B-LOC
Jews O
but O
of O
Hungarian B-LOC
people O
as O
a O
whole O
, O
above O
all O
in O
Budapest B-LOC
. O

Despite O
all O
the O
hardships O
of O
the O
situation O
, O
everyone O
to O
whom O
I O
spoke O
at O
that O
time O
was O
optimistic O
, O
and O
nobody O
had O
the O
slightest O
idea O
of O
what O
was O
to O
come O
. O

The O
general O
view O
was O
: O
the O
war B-TER
wo O
n’t O
last O
long O
; O
the O
Nazis O
will O
collapse O
in O
the O
near O
future O
; O
the O
Hungarian B-LOC
Jews O
will O
get O
off O
with O
a O
black O
eye O
; O
so O
it O
’s O
only O
a O
matter O
of O
surviving O
this O
short O
time O
as O
easily O
as O
possible O
. O

With O
this O
attitude O
it O
was O
no O
surprise O
that O
individuals O
turned O
to O
the O
congregation B-TER
when O
they O
needed O
support B-TER
, O
that O
wealthier O
people O
were O
inclined O
to O
give O
money B-TER
– O
but O
nobody O
thought O
it O
necessary O
to O
put O
in O
any O
very O
great O
trouble O
or O
effort O
. O

Thus O
for O
example O
most O
people O
considered O
it O
a O
waste O
of O
time O
to O
take O
a O
redeployment B-TER
course I-TER
, O
as O
they O
were O
absolutely O
convinced O
that O
the O
whole O
Nazi O
madness O
would O
be O
over O
in O
a O
short O
time O
and O
they O
could O
then O
return O
to O
their O
old O
professions O
. O

This O
is O
the O
reason O
why O
relatively O
few O
people O
expressed O
an O
interest O
in O
the O
redeployment B-TER
courses I-TER
and O
why O
, O
when O
after O
countless O
difficulties O
we O
finally O
succeeded O
in O
starting O
such O
a O
course B-TER
, O
the O
numbers O
attending O
soon O
crumbled O
away O
. O

Under O
these O
circumstances O
the O
work B-TER
of O
redeployment B-TER
in O
Hungary B-LOC
at O
that O
time O
was O
no O
great O
success O
. O

In O
Germany B-LOC
it O
had O
mainly O
been O
the O
emigrants B-TER
who O
wanted O
to O
learn O
a O
new B-TER
profession I-TER
before O
their O
departure B-TER
. O

In O
Hungary B-LOC
this O
motive O
did O
not O
apply O
either O
, O
since O
emigration B-TER
was O
no O
longer O
possible O
after O
autumn O
1939 O
. O

One O
small O
exception O
was O
the O
illegal B-TER
Aliyah O
, O
which O
since O
1940 O
went O
via O
Romania B-LOC
and O
the O
Black B-LOC
Sea I-LOC
, O
but O
was O
insignificant O
in O
terms O
of O
numbers O
. O

At O
the O
end O
of O
March O
or O
beginning O
of O
April O
1940 O
– O
the O
country O
was O
still O
neutral B-TER
and O
therefore O
connections O
with O
the O
West O
had O
not O
been O
entirely O
broken O
off O
– O
a O
representative O
of O
the O
headquarters O
in O
Paris B-LOC
of O
the O
ORT B-ORG
organisation I-ORG
came O
to O
Budapest B-LOC
to O
discuss O
an O
expansion O
of O
the O
redeployment B-TER
work B-TER
. O

As O
a O
result O
of O
negotiations O
with O
him O
a O
local O
ORT B-ORG
group O
was O
formed O
, O
which O
took O
over O
the O
direction O
of O
the O
redeployment B-TER
schemes O
and O
also O
continued O
the O
training B-TER
courses I-TER
which O
were O
already O
in O
place O
. O

The O
congregation B-TER
in O
Budapest B-LOC
of O
course B-TER
welcomed O
this O
warmly O
, O
since O
it O
represented O
a O
financial B-TER
relief O
. O

The O
ORT B-ORG
group O
ran O
an O
office O
of O
its O
own O
on O
the O
Ringstrasse O
, O
but O
its O
work B-TER
ground O
to O
a O
halt O
completely O
after O
Hungary B-LOC
entered O
the O
war B-TER
. O

As O
well O
as O
arranging O
employment B-TER
and O
redeployment B-TER
I O
was O
interested O
above O
all O
in O
another O
part O
of O
the O
work B-TER
, O
which O
at O
precisely O
that O
time O
– O
the O
beginning O
of O
1940 O
– O
was O
growing O
in O
importance O
, O
namely O
caring B-TER
for O
refugees B-TER
. O

In O
the O
previous O
year O
many O
Jews O
from O
Poland B-LOC
had O
fled O
from O
the O
German B-TER
invasion I-TER
across O
the O
Carpathians B-LOC
into O
Hungary B-LOC
, O
but O
many O
also O
came O
with O
or O
without O
passports B-TER
to O
Hungary B-LOC
from O
Austria B-LOC
and O
other O
Nazi B-TER
- I-TER
controlled I-TER
areas I-TER
. O

Initially O
the O
Hungarian B-LOC
government B-TER
treated O
them O
humanely O
and O
for O
the O
time O
being O
made O
no O
distinction O
between O
Jewish B-TER
and O
non O
- O
Jewish O
refugees B-TER
from O
Poland B-LOC
. O

It O
must O
be O
noted O
that O
after O
the O
collapse O
of O
the O
Polish B-ORG
army I-ORG
in O
September O
1939 O
many O
thousands O
of O
Poles B-LOC
fled O
, O
partly O
from O
the O
Nazis O
advancing O
from O
the O
west O
and O
partly O
from O
the O
Bolsheviks O
approaching O
from O
the O
east O
, O
and O
crossed O
the O
passes O
in O
the O
Carpathians B-LOC
to O
seek O
refuge O
in O
Hungary B-LOC
and O
Romania B-LOC
. O

Even O
small O
military B-TER
units I-TER
up O
to O
battalion O
strength O
crossed O
the O
border O
as O
a O
body O
and O
allowed O
themselves O
to O
be O
disarmed O
here O
. O

The O
Hungarian B-LOC
authorities O
interned O
them O
at O
first O
, O
but O
then O
allowed O
them O
greater O
freedom O
of O
movement O
and O
turned O
a O
blind O
eye O
when O
they O
continued O
on O
to O
Yugoslav B-LOC
territory O
, O
pushing O
on O
from O
there O
by O
detours O
into O
the O
camp B-TER
of O
the O
Western O
powers O
. O

At O
the O
start O
of O
1940 O
, O
however O
, O
the O
authorities B-TER
began O
to O
change O
their O
attitude O
towards O
the O
refugees B-TER
. O

A O
practice O
developed O
of O
placing O
those O
refugees B-TER
remaining O
in O
Hungary B-LOC
under O
police O
supervision O
but O
otherwise O
leaving O
them O
free O
, O
while O
those O
among O
them O
who O
were O
Jewish O
were O
locked O
up O
in O
internment B-TER
camps I-TER
. O

Within O
the O
Ministry B-ORG
of I-ORG
the I-ORG
Interior I-ORG
a O
special O
unit O
was O
created O
, O
called O
KHECK O
, O
which O
gradually O
showed O
a O
tendency O
to O
round O
up O
and O
intern O
all O
anti- O
Hungarian B-LOC
Jews O
who O
had O
entered O
the O
country O
after O
the O
outbreak O
of O
the O
war B-TER
, O
i.e. O
stateless B-TER
Jews O
and O
those O
of O
uncertain O
nationality O
. O

The O
intensification O
of O
this O
course O
of O
action O
, O
and O
the O
arbitrary O
interpretation O
of O
its O
provisions O
were O
later O
to O
become O
fateful O
for O
me O
and O
my O
family O
too O
, O
though O
at O
this O
point O
I O
did O
not O
foresee O
any O
of O
it O
, O
but O
felt O
comfortable O
and O
secure O
, O
as O
I O
had O
after O
all O
entered O
the O
country O
with O
a O
legal O
and O
valid O
passport B-TER
issued O
in O
Berlin B-LOC
by O
the O
Hungarian B-LOC
consulate B-TER
. O

In O
the O
winter O
of O
1939 O
- O
1940 O
the O
Jews O
placed O
in O
the O
internment B-TER
camps I-TER
were O
accommodated B-TER
under O
very O
unfavourable O
conditions O
from O
a O
hygienic B-TER
point O
of O
view O
. O

With O
a O
view O
to O
alleviating O
their O
situation O
the O
agencies B-TER
of O
the O
Jewish O
congregation B-TER
approached O
the O
Ministry B-ORG
of I-ORG
the I-ORG
Interior I-ORG
, O
and O
these O
negotiations O
met O
with O
some O
success O
. O

Although O
the O
request O
for O
release B-TER
of O
the O
interned B-TER
Jews O
was O
rejected O
, O
the O
Ministry B-ORG
did O
agree O
to O
assemble O
the O
Jews O
in O
special O
camps B-TER
in O
the O
area O
of O
the O
capital B-LOC
, O
provided O
the O
Jewish O
congregation B-TER
agreed O
to O
find O
the O
financial B-TER
resources O
for O
the O
maintenance O
of O
these O
camps B-TER
. O

The O
congregation B-TER
proceeded O
in O
the O
following O
months O
to O
construct O
and O
make O
available O
temporary O
buildings B-TER
on O
their O
own O
plots O
of O
land O
in O
various O
parts O
of O
the O
city O
. O

The O
resources O
to O
do O
so O
were O
found O
by O
longstanding O
and O
wealthy O
Jewish O
families O
; O
Baroness O
Alice B-PER
Weiss I-PER
, O
a O
member O
of O
an O
extremely O
rich O
family O
of O
industrialists B-TER
, O
made O
an O
outstanding O
contribution O
, O
not O
only O
by O
donating O
large O
amounts O
of O
money O
but O
also O
by O
personally O
concerning O
herself O
with O
hygiene B-TER
arrangements O
in O
the O
camps B-TER
and O
becoming O
involved O
in O
particular O
in O
providing O
for O
the O
interned O
women B-TER
and O
children B-TER
. O

Some O
of O
the O
camps B-TER
were O
given O
their O
own O
kosher B-TER
kitchens I-TER
; O
where O
that O
was O
not O
possible O
, O
deliveries O
of O
food B-TER
were O
made O
to O
them O
from O
central O
places O
run O
by O
the O
congregation B-TER
. O

The O
internees B-TER
received O
numerous O
benefits O
through O
us O
, O
with O
the O
consent O
of O
the O
authorities B-TER
, O
and O
were O
provided O
with O
warm B-TER
clothing I-TER
, O
linen O
, O
pocket O
money O
and O
medications B-TER
. O

Visiting O
days O
were O
introduced O
, O
and O
in O
many O
cases O
permission O
was O
also O
given O
for O
them O
to O
go O
out O
in O
the O
city O
. O

If O
internees B-TER
fell O
ill B-TER
, O
they O
could O
be O
transported O
to O
the O
Jewish B-TER
hospital I-TER
. O

I O
inspected O
these O
camps B-TER
frequently O
and O
took O
an O
active O
interest O
in O
the O
welfare B-TER
of O
the O
inmates B-TER
– O
without O
suspecting O
that O
one O
year O
later O
I O
would O
be O
one O
of O
them O
. O

My O
role O
in O
the O
congregation B-TER
agencies O
came O
to O
a O
temporary O
end O
in O
the O
summer O
of O
1940 O
when O
I O
– O
together O
with O
many O
fellow O
Jews O
of O
my O
age O
– O
was O
called O
up O
for O
work B-TER
service I-TER
. O

This O
work O
service O
( O
called O
munkaszolgalat O
in O
Hungarian B-LOC
) O
was O
a O
nasty O
trick O
and O
an O
act O
of O
discrimination B-TER
specially O
devised O
and O
set O
up O
for O
the O
Jews O
. O

The O
view O
of O
the O
Ministry B-TER
of O
War O
was O
that O
Jews O
were O
not O
suitable O
for O
military B-TER
service I-TER
, O
because O
they O
were O
unreliable O
. O

On O
the O
other O
hand O
it O
was O
felt O
inappropriate O
to O
leave O
the O
Jews O
at O
home B-TER
at O
a O
time O
when O
many O
generations O
of O
the O
rest O
of O
the O
population O
were O
being O
called O
up O
. O

Special O
work O
companies O
were O
therefore O
set O
up O
, O
in O
which O
Jews O
as O
well O
as O
members O
of O
unreliable O
national O
minorities B-TER
( O
Romanians B-LOC
, O
Slovaks B-LOC
etc O
. O

) O
were O
enrolled O
. O

It O
was O
doubtless O
no O
pleasure O
at O
that O
time O
to O
serve O
in O
the O
Hungarian B-ORG
army I-ORG
. O

As O
far O
as O
the O
work O
companies O
were O
concerned O
, O
however O
, O
it O
was O
pure O
hell O
. O

For O
reasons O
which O
have O
never O
become O
entirely O
clear O
, O
it O
was O
predominantly O
men B-TER
who O
were O
not O
particularly O
young O
who O
were O
called O
up O
. O

For O
them O
the O
unaccustomed O
work B-TER
( O
road O
mending O
, O
cleaning O
barracks O
etc O
. O

) O
was O
especially O
hard O
. O

Our O
lodgings O
and O
food B-TER
as O
well O
as O
our O
treatment O
by O
the O
( O
usually O
anti B-TER
- I-TER
semitic I-TER
- I-TER
minded I-TER
) O
superior O
officers O
were O
extremely O
bad O
. O

But O
fortunately O
the O
work B-TER
companies O
in O
this O
first O
period O
were O
only O
used O
within O
Hungary B-LOC
and O
were O
dissolved O
again O
after O
a O
few O
weeks O
or O
months O
. O

In O
the O
late O
summer O
and O
autumn O
people O
returned O
to O
their O
homes B-TER
. O

Soon O
the O
hardships O
suffered O
were O
forgotten O
and O
, O
as O
at O
the O
same O
time O
the O
economic B-TER
situation I-TER
improved O
somewhat O
and O
it O
was O
possible O
to O
place O
many O
of O
the O
unemployed B-TER
, O
at O
the O
end O
of O
the O
year O
in O
1940 O
the O
prevalent O
feeling O
among O
Hungarian B-LOC
Jews O
was O
again O
that O
they O
had O
got O
off O
with O
a O
black O
eye O
. O

But O
the O
hard O
persecutions O
had O
not O
yet O
begun O
. O

