On O
July O
24th O
I O
called O
on O
the O
Prime B-TER
Minister I-TER
and O
left O
with O
him O
some O
statements O
on O
the O
subject O
of O
the O
ill B-TER
treatment I-TER
to O
which O
certain O
Jews B-TER
are O
alleged O
to O
have O
been O
subjected O
. O

I O
did O
not O
ask O
him O
for O
an O
immediate O
answer O
, O
but O
requested O
an O
examination O
into O
the O
matter O
. O

[ O
... O
] O
In O
my O
opinion O
this O
ex O
parte O
statement O
puts O
the O
case O
for O
the O
Hungarian B-ORG
Government I-ORG
in O
an O
unduly O
favorable O
light O
, O
but O
I O
also O
believe O
that O
the O
dispatches O
sent O
by O
the O
American B-ORG
Joint I-ORG
Relief I-ORG
Association I-ORG
are O
at O
least O
equally O
prejudiced O
. O

Although O
the O
treatment B-TER
meted O
out O
to O
many O
of O
these O
unfortunates O
has O
been O
unnecessarily O
severe O
and O
in O
some O
cases O
flagrantly O
unjust O
, O
roughness O
on O
the O
part O
of O
those O
in O
authority O
, O
and O
hardship O
do O
not O
shock O
the O
susceptibilities O
of O
people O
accustomed O
to O
the O
habits O
and O
standard B-TER
of I-TER
living I-TER
that O
prevail O
in O
eastern B-LOC
Europe I-LOC
, O
as O
they O
would O
Americans B-TER
. O

