Gestapo B-ORG
Insists O
on O
Divorce O
of O
a O
Mixed B-TER
Marriage I-TER
Helene B-PER
Hirsch I-PER
, O
born O
Meyer B-PER
. O

Born O
: O
7 O
November O
1905 O
in O
Teplice B-LOC
. O

She O
remained O
an O
only O
child B-TER
. O

Father O
: O
Ship B-TER
’s I-TER
captain O
on O
a O
trade O
ship B-TER
. O

Of O
German B-LOC
nationality B-TER
, O
living O
in O
Hamburg B-LOC
. O

He O
died B-TER
in O
1908 O
. O

He O
and O
Helene B-PER
’s I-PER
mother O
were O
divorced O
shortly O
before O
his O
death B-TER
. O

Mother O
: O
Ella B-PER
Meyer I-PER
, O
born O
Kerl B-PER
, O
married B-TER
in O
1904 O
. O

Married B-TER
for O
a O
second O
time O
in O
1922 O
to O
a O
banker B-TER
named O
Perutz B-PER
in O
Teplice B-LOC
. O

Helene B-PER
’s I-PER
mother O
continued O
to O
run O
the O
boarding B-TER
house I-TER
founded O
by O
the O
grandmother O
, O
Mrs O
Marie B-PER
Kerl I-PER
, O
after O
her O
death B-TER
. O

Helene B-PER
spent O
her O
childhood O
and O
youth O
here O
until O
her O
marriage B-TER
. O

Helene B-PER
's I-PER
mother O
died B-TER
from O
suicide B-TER
on O
6 O
June O
1945 O
in O
Teplice B-LOC
. O

Native O
country O
: O
Through O
her O
father O
’s O
nationality B-TER
: O
Germany B-LOC
. O

Religion B-TER
: O
Evangelical B-TER
. O

Her O
mother O
was O
Catholic B-TER
. O

Due O
to O
her O
mother O
’s O
contact O
with O
Jewish O
people B-TER
, O
as O
a O
child B-TER
Helene B-PER
mainly O
had O
Jewish O
friends O
throughout O
her O
school B-TER
years O
. O

The O
other O
Christian B-TER
schoolgirls B-TER
resented O
her O
for O
this O
, O
which O
later O
led O
to O
a O
strong O
sense O
of O
isolation O
, O
especially O
in O
the O
dance O
classes B-TER
. O

One O
lifelong O
friendship O
with O
a O
Jewish O
girl O
began O
in O
the O
pram O
. O

It O
was O
not O
unusual O
in O
Teplice B-LOC
for O
Jews O
and O
Christians B-TER
to O
meet O
, O
since O
the O
well O
- O
off O
Jewish B-TER
population I-TER
held O
a O
fairly O
dominant O
position O
. O

Furthermore O
, O
many O
Jewish O
boarders O
were O
living O
in O
Helene B-PER
's I-PER
grandmother O
’s O
house B-TER
( O
later O
her O
mother O
’s O
) O
, O
so O
friendly O
relations O
began O
quite O
naturally.chr O
As O
a O
young O
woman B-TER
, O
through O
her O
interest O
in O
sport B-TER
Helene B-PER
mostly O
socialised O
with O
Christian B-TER
groups O
. O

She O
was O
well O
- O
known O
as O
a O
tennis B-TER
player I-TER
. O

A O
close O
friendship O
with O
a O
man B-TER
built O
up O
on O
this O
basis O
. O

With O
time O
however O
, O
this O
changed O
and O
at O
the O
age O
of O
25 O
Helene B-PER
married B-TER
a O
Jewish O
man B-TER
who O
was O
born O
in O
Teplice B-LOC
. O

When O
the O
engagement O
was O
announced O
, O
Helene B-PER
was O
annoyed O
by O
the O
Christian B-TER
and O
the O
Jewish O
families B-TER
alike O
in O
that O
the O
Christians B-TER
found O
it O
wrong O
that O
she O
should O
marry B-TER
a O
Jew O
, O
and O
the O
Jews O
found O
this O
Jew O
socially O
beneath O
her O
. O

The O
marriage B-TER
was O
however O
especially O
good O
– O
until O
Hitler B-PER
and O
the O
circumstances O
created O
by O
him O
interfered O
. O

The O
husband O
, O
Egon B-PER
Hirsch I-PER
, O
was O
a O
top O
insurance B-TER
agent B-TER
at O
the O
Viktoria O
company B-TER
. O

He O
got O
a O
job B-TER
in O
Bodenbach B-LOC
, O
where O
the O
young O
couple O
relocated O
( O
1930 O
) O
. O

There O
they O
only O
had O
contact O
with O
Jewish O
people B-TER
, O
the O
Jews O
and O
the O
Christians B-TER
did O
not O
socialise O
. O

They O
did O
have O
one O
non O
- O
Jewish O
acquaintance O
, O
a O
colleague O
of O
Egon B-PER
’s I-PER
who O
often O
came O
to O
their O
house B-TER
. O

He O
was O
resented O
for O
this O
by O
the O
Christian B-TER
side O
. O

In O
1933 O
Egon B-PER
was O
moved O
to O
Karlsbad B-LOC
, O
which O
was O
an O
improvement O
in O
every O
way O
. O

They O
felt O
so O
happy O
there O
that O
Egon B-PER
did O
not O
want O
to O
leave O
the O
place O
when O
in O
1938 O
Hitler B-PER
annexed B-TER
the O
Sudentenland B-LOC
and O
almost O
all O
Jews O
fled O
to O
( O
at O
that O
time O
still O
safe O
) O
Prague B-LOC
. O

But O
Helene B-PER
finally O
managed O
to O
persuade O
him O
, O
so O
they O
both O
went O
to O
Prague B-LOC
leaving O
everything O
behind O
in O
Karlsbad B-LOC
. O

The O
atmosphere O
there O
in O
the O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
was O
extremely O
depressing O
and O
Egon B-PER
and O
Helene B-PER
felt O
altogether O
so O
unhappy O
that O
they O
returned O
to O
Karlsbad B-LOC
. O

But O
not O
for O
long O
! O
After O
a O
week O
the O
situation O
in O
the O
Sudentenland B-LOC
got O
so O
much O
worse O
that O
they O
again O
fled B-TER
to O
Prague B-LOC
, O
this O
time O
for O
good O
. O

In O
1939 O
however O
, O
Hitler B-PER
also O
occupied B-TER
Prague B-LOC
. O

Helene B-PER
assessed O
the O
situation O
more O
accurately O
than O
her O
husband O
and O
she O
pulled O
out O
all O
the O
stops O
to O
make O
it O
possible O
for O
them O
both O
to O
emigrate B-TER
. O

In O
her O
spirited O
manner O
she O
went O
directly O
with O
Egon B-PER
’s I-PER
passport B-TER
to O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
and O
in O
order O
to O
get O
him O
a O
permit B-TER
to O
leave B-TER
the I-TER
country I-TER
, O
she O
came O
up O
with O
the O
excuse O
that O
he O
wanted O
to O
visit O
his O
sick O
mother O
- O
in O
- O
law O
. O

She O
also O
managed O
to O
get O
him O
a O
ticket O
, O
and O
so O
he O
was O
able O
to O
make O
the O
journey O
to O
England B-LOC
. O

Helene B-PER
herself O
was O
not O
granted O
permission B-TER
to O
leave B-TER
, O
since O
as O
a O
Christian B-TER
she O
was O
not O
allowed O
to O
leave B-TER
the I-TER
country I-TER
. O

Her O
passport B-TER
was O
even O
taken O
away O
and O
she O
only O
got O
it O
back O
two O
months O
later O
. O

She O
kept O
trying O
, O
but O
when O
she O
finally O
was O
allowed O
to O
leave B-TER
the I-TER
country I-TER
, O
she O
did O
not O
get O
the O
visa B-TER
for O
England B-LOC
, O
so O
had O
to O
stay O
in O
Prague B-LOC
. O

Until O
he O
left O
in O
March O
1939 O
, O
Egon B-PER
was O
able O
to O
continue O
working B-TER
for O
his O
insurance B-TER
company I-TER
Viktoria B-ORG
in O
Prague B-LOC
. O

The O
marriage B-TER
was O
dissolved B-TER
upon O
the O
orders O
of O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
once O
Egon B-PER
’s I-PER
passport B-TER
had O
arrived O
from O
England B-LOC
. O

Until O
1946 O
when O
Helene B-PER
was O
finally O
able O
to O
join O
her O
husband O
living O
in O
London B-LOC
, O
her O
life O
went O
by O
as O
follows O
: O
Since O
in O
Czechoslovakia B-LOC
there O
was O
labour O
conscription O
, O
she O
looked O
for O
work B-TER
although O
she O
did O
not O
have O
the O
financial B-TER
need O
to O
. O

She O
joined O
a O
Czech B-LOC
lawyer O
who O
needed O
to O
take O
on O
someone O
who O
could O
speak O
German B-LOC
, O
where O
she O
worked B-TER
in O
office O
service O
. O

After O
she O
had O
been O
working B-TER
there O
about O
a O
year O
, O
she O
gave O
up O
the O
job B-TER
and O
, O
as O
she O
was O
used O
to O
doing O
, O
went O
for O
a O
few O
weeks O
to O
do O
winter O
sports B-TER
in O
the O
mountains O
. O

This O
surprising O
fact O
was O
brought O
about O
by O
a O
doctor B-TER
’s I-TER
certificate O
stating O
that O
she O
had O
TB B-TER
. O

The O
reasoning O
given O
was O
that O
the O
X O
- O
ray O
image O
showed O
a O
healed O
over O
shadow O
and O
the O
longstanding O
slightly O
raised B-TER
temperatures I-TER
were O
indicative O
of O
TB B-TER
. O

The O
lung B-TER
disease I-TER
of O
an O
aunt O
who O
had O
died B-TER
early O
was O
also O
put O
to O
use O
for O
this O
purpose O
. O

In O
fact O
Helene B-PER
Hirsch I-PER
never O
had O
any O
such O
disease B-TER
, O
but O
the O
employment B-TER
office I-TER
never O
made O
any O
difficulties O
for O
her O
, O
neither O
this O
first O
time O
, O
nor O
over O
any O
of O
the O
other O
various O
later O
medical B-TER
certificates O
. O

Also O
, O
at O
a O
time O
when O
she O
was O
supposed O
to O
go O
to O
the O
ammunitions O
factory B-TER
, O
she O
was O
exempted O
. O

She O
worked B-TER
in O
various O
roles O
, O
either O
where O
the O
employment O
of O
a O
German B-LOC
was O
required O
, O
or O
else O
, O
as O
in O
the O
case O
of O
Viktoria B-ORG
, O
where O
in O
view O
of O
Egon B-PER
’s I-PER
work B-TER
there O
, O
they O
wanted O
to O
help O
her O
. O

On O
one O
occasion O
she O
found O
employment O
through O
a O
Christian B-TER
manager O
who O
had O
declared O
his O
Jewish O
wife O
as O
a O
half B-TER
Jew I-TER
, O
felt O
insecure O
and O
wanted O
to O
hire O
anyone O
who O
he O
knew O
to O
have O
an O
anti B-TER
- I-TER
Nazi I-TER
stance O
. O

Helene B-PER
used O
these O
various O
jobs B-TER
, O
where O
opportunities O
always O
arose O
, O
to O
sabotage B-TER
the O
work B-TER
of O
the O
Germans B-LOC
. O

She O
also O
sheltered B-TER
a O
Jewish O
acquaintance O
in O
her O
place O
of O
living O
for O
a O
while O
. O

He O
had O
come O
to O
Prague B-LOC
after O
his O
Christian B-TER
wife O
had O
driven O
him O
out O
of O
Vienna B-LOC
. O

He O
was O
eventually O
discovered O
and O
sent O
to O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
concentration B-TER
camp I-TER
where O
he O
took B-TER
his I-TER
own I-TER
life I-TER
by O
touching O
electrically O
charged O
barbed O
wire O
. O

A O
month O
and O
a O
half O
before O
the O
end O
of O
the O
war B-TER
Helene B-PER
was O
able O
to O
go O
to O
Teplice B-LOC
to O
see O
her O
mother O
with O
a O
certificate B-TER
from O
the O
employment B-TER
office O
, O
again O
acknowledging O
her O
tuberculosis B-TER
. O

She O
had O
to O
attend O
a O
doctor B-TER
in O
Teplice B-LOC
, O
who O
gave O
her O
very O
painful O
injections O
against O
the O
supposed O
disease B-TER
, O
but O
she O
wanted O
to O
stay O
in O
Teplice B-LOC
so O
she O
had O
to O
put O
herself O
through O
that O
. O

Two O
months O
after O
the O
peace O
agreement O
, O
when O
the O
Russians B-LOC
occupied B-TER
Teplice B-LOC
, O
the O
two O
women B-TER
( O
the O
mother O
was O
still O
alive O
) O
took O
French B-LOC
prisoners B-TER
of I-TER
war I-TER
under O
their O
protection O
in O
their O
house B-TER
. O

Apart O
from O
the O
fear B-TER
of O
the O
Russians B-LOC
, O
they O
were O
also O
troubled O
by O
the O
possibility O
of O
deportation B-TER
, O
and O
this O
drove O
the O
mother O
to O
suicide B-TER
. O

Helene B-PER
was O
one O
of O
the O
first O
to O
be O
able O
to O
go O
to O
England B-LOC
. O

She O
profusely O
thanked O
an O
English B-LOC
lady B-TER
, O
a O
Christian B-TER
, O
who O
had O
readily O
accepted O
Egon B-PER
, O
for O
her O
tireless O
efforts O
. O

Since O
Egon B-PER
had O
always O
declared O
himself O
to O
the O
authorities O
in O
England B-LOC
as O
married B-TER
, O
it O
was O
soon O
possible O
to O
get O
the O
marriage B-TER
, O
which O
had O
only O
been O
dissolved B-TER
under O
the O
Nazi B-TER
regime I-TER
, O
legally O
valid O
again O
. O

As O
it O
turned O
out O
however O
, O
due O
to O
the O
fact O
that O
their O
experiences O
over O
the O
seven O
years O
of O
their O
separation O
had O
estranged O
them O
so O
much O
from O
one O
another O
, O
after O
three O
years O
together O
, O
Helene B-PER
and O
Egon B-PER
again O
divorced O
. O

Afterwards O
, O
like O
almost O
all O
refugees B-TER
, O
Helene B-PER
tried O
a O
wide O
variety O
of O
types O
of O
work B-TER
. O

In O
1947 O
she O
eventually O
got O
a O
job B-TER
as O
a O
secretary O
for O
the O
European O
Service O
of O
the O
BBC B-ORG
, O
where O
she O
still O
works B-TER
today O
. O

Helene B-PER
's I-PER
possessions O
and O
the O
large O
house B-TER
in O
Teplice B-LOC
were O
lost O
through O
the O
circumstances O
without O
any O
prospect O
of O
proportionate O
refunding B-TER
. O

Helen B-PER
Hirsch I-PER
3 O
. O

Juli O
1958 O
