The O
person O
in O
question O
has O
given O
us O
the O
following O
information O
: O
Jewish B-TER
laws I-TER
concerned O
me O
only O
in O
as O
much O
as O
my O
application O
was O
accepted O
only O
by O
the O
University B-TER
of O
Pécs B-LOC
, O
and O
even O
there O
I O
needed O
the O
support O
of O
someone O
to O
get O
in O
. O

At O
the O
university B-TER
, O
I O
witnessed O
some O
harassment O
, O
beatings B-TER
and O
things O
like O
that O
. O

Antisemitism B-TER
was O
intense O
at O
that O
time O
and O
in O
some O
cases O
I O
also O
received O
some O
beatings O
. O

Having O
done O
some O
lawyer B-TER
’s I-TER
practice I-TER
in O
Mohács B-LOC
and O
Pécs B-LOC
I O
came O
to O
Pest B-LOC
and O
found O
a O
job O
. O

Later O
, O
however O
, O
I O
obtained O
new O
training O
and O
worked O
for O
the O
weaving O
factory B-TER
Star O
. O

I O
had O
no O
problems O
here O
since O
I O
worked O
as O
a O
physical O
labourer O
. O

The O
15th O
of O
March O
, O
1943 O
, O
I O
left O
the O
factory B-TER
and O
was O
drafted O
for O
labour B-TER
service I-TER
in O
Mohács B-LOC
. O

Later O
, O
I O
was O
resent O
to O
Pest B-LOC
to O
work O
in O
the O
package O
selection O
department O
of O
the O
post O
office O
No O
. O

70 O
. O

, O
and O
later O
I O
worked O
as O
a O
draftsman O
for O
the O
boss O
. O

Here O
I O
had O
a O
good O
life O
till O
I O
was O
sent O
into O
Transylvania B-LOC
. O

In O
Dés B-LOC
, O
in O
Désakna B-LOC
we O
had O
a O
malevolent O
commander B-TER
, O
a O
criminal O
, O
2nd O
Lieutenant O
Ferenc B-PER
Fehér I-PER
, O
who O
came O
from O
Vízvár B-LOC
in O
Somogy O
. O

There O
was O
also O
Ferenc B-PER
Kökönyei I-PER
who O
stole B-TER
my O
watch O
and O
wore O
it O
. O

The O
19th O
of O
February O
, O
1944 O
, O
at O
10 O
pm O
Béla B-PER
Steckel I-PER
, O
who O
was O
on O
night O
patrol O
, O
took O
me O
and O
11 O
of O
my O
companions O
to O
the O
headquarters O
from O
the O
Jewish O
Casino O
although O
I O
had O
a O
regular O
permission O
for O
a O
leave O
. O

Here O
I O
had O
to O
stand O
40 O
minutes O
and O
he O
slapped O
me O
and O
broke O
my O
eardrum O
. O

I O
made O
a O
great O
fuss O
about O
it O
, O
I O
went O
to O
the O
army B-TER
corps I-TER
headquarters I-TER
but O
in O
the O
meanwhile O
Germans B-TER
entered I-TER
the O
country O
and O
I O
had O
to O
withdraw O
the O
denunciation B-TER
. O

First O
, O
we O
worked B-TER
on O
railway O
construction O
for O
the O
railway O
co. O
, O
later O
we O
lay O
military O
cables O
in O
the O
ground O
between O
Óradna B-LOC
and O
Újradna B-LOC
. O

We O
had O
to O
walk O
28 O
kilometres O
a O
day O
back O
and O
forth O
to O
the O
workplace B-TER
. O

We O
worked B-TER
only O
during O
the O
time O
that O
remained O
. O

Our O
correspondence O
( O
both O
incoming O
and O
outgoing O
) O
was O
destroyed O
by O
the O
captain O
of O
the O
troop B-TER
, O
so O
we O
gathered O
torn O
pieces O
of O
letters B-TER
from O
the O
toilet O
. O

I O
had O
another O
incident O
with O
Cadet B-TER
Sergeant I-TER
Károly B-PER
Fejs I-PER
( O
from O
Szekszárd B-LOC
) O
who O
beat B-TER
me I-TER
and O
kicked O
my O
bottom O
because O
I O
went O
to O
get O
hold O
of O
food B-TER
. O

During O
the O
withdrawal O
from O
Transylvania B-LOC
we O
walked O
on O
foot O
from O
Újradna B-LOC
till O
Kassa B-LOC
without O
any O
food B-TER
. O

We O
got O
to O
Kassa B-LOC
the O
20th O
of O
December O
. O

We O
were O
terribly O
crammed O
in O
the O
brick O
factory B-TER
of O
Kassa B-LOC
. O

It O
was O
cold O
, O
we O
had O
no B-TER
food I-TER
and O
suffered O
greatly O
. O

We O
were O
nearly O
frozen B-TER
. O

The O
brick O
factory B-TER
of O
Kassa B-LOC
had O
a O
very O
bad O
reputation O
. O

7,000 O
people O
were O
kept O
there O
, O
out O
of O
whom O
many O
were O
frozen B-TER
and O
remained O
without O
food B-TER
. O

In O
December O
, O
they O
entrained B-TER
us O
, O
75 O
of O
us O
in O
a O
freight O
car O
, O
not O
more O
. O

We O
got O
food B-TER
once O
a O
day O
. O

One O
day O
we O
got O
lunch B-TER
, O
the O
other O
day O
dinner B-TER
, O
the O
next O
day O
breakfast B-TER
. O

We O
got O
no B-TER
water I-TER
at O
all O
and O
could O
not O
buy O
it O
either O
because O
the O
freight O
car O
was O
locked O
. O

It O
was O
full B-TER
of I-TER
lice I-TER
and O
people O
got O
sick B-TER
one O
after O
the O
other O
. O

We O
had O
to O
use O
for O
the O
toilet O
either O
a O
great O
teapot O
or O
other O
pots O
. O

Signs O
of O
spotted B-TER
fever I-TER
could O
be O
noticed O
already O
on O
the O
train B-TER
. O

When O
we O
arrived O
there O
was O
a O
dead B-TER
person O
, O
the O
boy O
next O
to O
me O
. O

The O
journey O
lasted O
9 O
days O
till O
Donnerskirchen B-LOC
. O

We O
arrived O
at O
2 O
am O
after O
9 O
days O
of O
travel O
and O
the O
Germans B-TER
ordered O
us O
to O
work O
already O
at O
6 O
am O
. O

We O
had O
to O
make B-TER
trenches I-TER
and O
bunkers O
, O
and O
had O
no O
opportunity O
to O
wash O
. O

We O
had O
no O
clothes B-TER
and O
some O
had O
to O
go O
to O
work B-TER
barefoot O
. O

Here O
a O
sergeant O
forced O
me O
to O
get O
out O
into O
the O
snow O
having O
a O
temperature O
of O
40 O
degrees O
and O
he O
also O
broke B-TER
my O
cheek O
- O
bone O
with O
a O
club O
. O

I O
stayed O
here O
9 O
days O
before O
I O
escaped B-TER
with O
four O
of O
my O
friends O
in O
the O
possession O
of O
a O
service O
ticket O
which O
was O
forged O
. O

The O
7th O
of O
January O
, O
we O
crossed O
the O
German O
- O
Hungarian O
border O
and O
arrived O
in O
Sopron B-LOC
. O

From O
Sopron B-LOC
we O
went O
to O
Győr B-LOC
, O
where O
luckily O
we O
contracted O
typhus B-TER
, O
which O
meant O
5 O
weeks O
stay O
in O
hospital B-TER
, O
till O
the O
1st O
of O
March O
. O

The O
winter O
was O
then O
over O
and O
we O
had O
a O
good O
life O
in O
the O
public O
hospital B-TER
of O
Győr B-LOC
. O

Later O
, O
the O
1st O
of O
March O
, O
a O
1st O
lieutenant O
of O
the O
Arrow B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
ordered O
us O
to O
leave O
the O
hospital B-TER
and O
put O
us O
into O
the O
collecting O
place O
, O
the O
prisoner B-TER
s O
’ O
camp B-TER
of O
Győr B-LOC
, O
from O
where O
we O
were O
taken O
to O
Schandorf B-LOC
. O

The O
sergeant O
who O
received O
us O
seized O
all O
the O
few O
things O
we O
had O
, O
he O
took O
even O
razors O
and O
soaps O
, O
etc O
. O

The O
20th O
of O
March O
, O
they O
took O
us O
to O
Szombathely B-LOC
, O
once O
again O
searched O
our O
luggage O
and O
robbed B-TER
us O
anew O
, O
leaving O
only O
a O
blanket O
. O

We O
then O
went O
to O
Schandorf B-LOC
on O
foot O
. O

Here O
we O
were O
crammed O
, O
750 O
of O
us O
, O
in O
a O
single O
cellar O
. O

In O
Schandorf B-LOC
we O
dug O
trenches O
and O
bunkers O
. O

We O
worked B-TER
from O
7 O
am O
till O
4 O
pm O
. O

In O
the O
meantime O
we O
were O
maltreated O
, O
beaten B-TER
, O
and O
struck O
. O

I O
left O
this O
camp B-TER
, O
but O
later O
I O
heard O
it O
became O
an O
unbearable O
place O
where O
they O
shot B-TER
people O
. O

Out O
of O
750 O
people O
, O
250 O
survived O
this O
camp B-TER
. O

Out O
of O
my O
team O
of O
40 O
people O
only O
8 O
survived O
. O

The O
rest O
all O
died B-TER
from O
typhus B-TER
. O

There O
were O
no O
doctors B-TER
at O
all O
. O

They O
kept O
these O
people O
in O
a O
special O
ward O
of O
a O
hospital B-TER
but O
it O
practically O
meant O
a O
death B-TER
sentence O
. O

A O
veterinarian B-TER
treated O
them O
but O
had O
no O
medicine O
, O
and O
people O
died B-TER
of O
starvation B-TER
. O

Food B-TER
was O
anyway O
extremely O
scarce O
. O

We O
set O
off O
from O
Schandorf B-LOC
because O
of O
the O
Russian B-ORG
approach O
and O
walked B-TER
for O
16 O
days O
. O

We O
got O
food O
6 O
times O
during O
these O
16 O
days O
. O

The O
person O
who O
got O
tired O
or O
was O
out O
of O
step O
was O
shot B-TER
. O

They O
treated O
us O
in O
an O
incredible O
way O
. O

An O
average O
of O
40 O
people O
died B-TER
per O
day O
. O

The O
7th O
of O
April O
, O
in O
the O
forest O
at O
Eisenerz B-LOC
, O
which O
was O
one O
of O
the O
greatest O
metallurgical O
towns O
, O
the O
SS B-TER
killed B-TER
150 O
Jews O
with O
machine O
guns O
without O
any O
reason O
. O

About O
10 O
centimetres O
behind O
my O
back O
my O
friend O
was O
shot B-TER
, O
too O
, O
but O
we O
had O
to O
proceed O
, O
we O
could O
not O
stop O
. O

This O
is O
how O
we O
got O
to O
Mauthausen B-LOC
. O

In O
Mauthausen B-LOC
we O
lived O
in O
tents B-TER
. O

After O
an O
air B-TER
raid I-TER
at O
night O
9 O
people O
remained O
dead B-TER
and O
20 O
were O
wounded O
. O

There O
was O
also O
another O
tragic O
event O
that O
affected O
my O
spirit O
a O
great O
deal O
. O

One O
of O
the O
supervisors B-TER
was O
beating O
a O
50 O
- O
year O
- O
old O
friend O
of O
mine O
badly O
when O
I O
jumped O
on O
him O
. O

He O
went O
to O
the O
SS B-TER
to O
complain O
about O
me O
. O

The O
SS B-TER
beat B-TER
me O
up O
so O
much O
that O
they O
broke O
my O
ribs O
and O
the O
bone O
of O
my O
little O
finger O
. O

Food B-TER
was O
terribly O
poor O
. O

For O
breakfast O
we O
got O
0.2 O
litre O
of O
bitter O
black O
coffee B-TER
, O
at O
noon O
some O
turnip O
soup B-TER
, O
and O
in O
the O
evening O
100 O
grams O
of O
bread B-TER
. O

That O
was O
all O
for O
a O
day O
. O

It O
was O
only O
natural O
that O
we O
became O
feeble O
and O
many O
died B-TER
. O

Death B-TER
was O
caused O
by O
typhus B-TER
, O
by O
starvation B-TER
and O
beating B-TER
. O

From O
Mauthausen B-LOC
we O
went O
to O
Gunskirchen B-LOC
walking B-TER
for O
four O
days O
. O

We O
were O
starving B-TER
a O
lot O
on O
the O
way O
; O
we O
ate O
grass O
, O
nettles O
, O
and O
leaves O
. O

If O
they O
noticed O
that O
someone O
was O
out O
of O
step O
they O
shot B-TER
him O
, O
they O
shot B-TER
also O
those O
weak O
people O
who O
could O
not O
carry O
on O
walking B-TER
, O
so O
there O
were O
a O
great O
number O
of O
dead B-TER
bodies I-TER
lying O
on O
the O
road O
. O

50 O
men O
were O
sent O
ahead O
to O
dig O
graves B-TER
. O

Once O
, O
an O
SS B-TER
soldier O
disliked O
the O
work O
of O
a O
gravedigger O
. O

He O
made O
him O
stand O
in O
the O
grave O
and O
beat O
him O
till O
he O
died B-TER
. O

One O
could O
see O
the O
inner O
parts O
of O
his O
skull O
, O
that O
is O
how O
much O
he O
beat O
him O
. O

It O
was O
a O
terrible O
view O
. O

The O
others O
then O
covered O
him O
with O
soil O
. O

When O
we O
arrived O
in O
Gunskirchen B-LOC
we O
were O
put O
up O
in O
wooden O
huts O
. O

They O
crammed B-TER
2,000 O
people O
in O
a O
barrack B-TER
for O
500 O
. O

We O
were O
terribly O
cramped O
, O
could O
not O
lie O
down O
, O
and O
slept O
sitting O
on O
the O
rucksacks O
. O

Later O
, O
I O
learnt O
from O
the O
Americans B-ORG
that O
they O
found O
arsenic O
in O
dissected O
dead B-TER
bodies I-TER
. O

They O
put O
little O
portions O
into O
the O
food B-TER
that O
caused O
the O
general O
diarrhoea B-TER
. O

If O
someone O
went O
to O
the O
toilet O
he O
could O
not O
get O
there O
because O
he O
was O
shot B-TER
by O
the O
SS B-TER
. O

We O
were O
very O
much O
full B-TER
of I-TER
lice I-TER
; O
there O
was O
no O
water O
to O
wash B-TER
, O
not O
even O
for O
drinking B-TER
. O

Sometimes O
we O
got O
a O
decilitre O
of O
water B-TER
and O
could O
decide O
to O
use O
it O
for O
drinking O
or O
for O
washing O
. O

Food B-TER
was O
turnip O
soup B-TER
all O
the O
time O
, O
and O
ca O
. O

70 O
grams O
of O
bread B-TER
. O

Here O
they O
did O
not O
beat O
us O
, O
they O
just O
simply O
shot B-TER
the O
people O
they O
disliked O
or O
against O
whom O
there O
were O
complaints O
. O

One O
day O
we O
were O
carrying O
the O
dead B-TER
. O

One O
of O
the O
boys O
ran O
out O
of O
energy O
and O
put O
the O
body O
down O
before O
it O
was O
allowed O
. O

He O
was O
shot B-TER
. O

Around O
150 O
- O
200 O
of O
us O
died B-TER
daily O
, O
completely O
feeble O
people O
who O
either O
died B-TER
of O
exhaustion O
or O
of O
typhus B-TER
. O

We O
had O
to O
bury O
them O
in O
a O
pit B-TER
. O

The O
Americans B-ORG
found O
this O
pit B-TER
; O
that O
was O
when O
they O
found O
out O
about O
arsenic O
poisoning O
. O

The O
Americans B-ORG
liberated B-TER
us O
the O
4th O
of O
May O
, O
1945 O
, O
and O
we O
started O
to O
do O
better O
. O

These O
were O
my O
own O
experiences O
. O

