Address O
: O
R. O
Ministry B-ORG
of I-ORG
Foreign I-ORG
Affairs I-ORG
, O
Rome B-LOC
Bucharest B-LOC
, O
23th O
September O
1942 O
– O
XX O
Re O
: O
New O
measures B-TER
against O
the O
Jews B-TER
in O
Romania B-LOC
Romanian B-LOC
authorities O
seem O
determined O
to O
solve O
the O
Jewish B-TER
problem I-TER
with O
drastic O
measures B-TER
, O
sending B-TER
a O
great O
number O
of O
Semtic B-TER
elements O
to O
the O
occupied B-TER
Russian B-LOC
territories O
. O

These O
deportations B-TER
had O
already O
started O
during O
last O
winter O
and O
involved O
the O
Jews B-TER
living O
in O
Bessarabia B-LOC
and O
Bukovina B-LOC
, O
who O
were O
accused O
of O
having O
welcomed O
the O
Bolshevik B-TER
occupation I-TER
, O
and O
those O
in O
Moldavia B-LOC
, O
who O
during O
the O
first O
days O
of O
the O
war B-TER
had O
stirred O
up O
Communist B-TER
riots O
in O
Jassy B-LOC
and O
in O
Galatz B-LOC
that O
were O
immediately O
suppressed O
. O

The O
system O
now O
has O
been O
extended O
to O
other O
regions O
and O
towns O
, O
including O
the O
capital B-LOC
, O
where O
in O
the O
last O
few O
days O
the O
police B-TER
have O
carried O
out O
vast O
round O
- O
ups O
among O
the O
Jewish O
element O
and O
have O
sent O
the O
people O
arrested O
beyond O
the O
Dnestr B-LOC
and O
beyond O
the O
Bug B-LOC
. O

There O
they O
are O
employed B-TER
in O
public O
works O
, O
mainly O
road O
works O
, O
but O
reportedly O
last O
winter O
many O
, O
due O
also O
to O
lack O
of O
equipment O
and O
of O
suitable O
lodgings O
, O
did O
not O
survive O
the O
long O
marches B-TER
from O
one O
place O
to O
the O
other O
and O
the O
rigours O
of O
the O
Russian B-LOC
winter O
. O

News O
of O
these O
measures B-TER
spread O
rapidly O
even O
abroad O
, O
causing O
the O
United B-LOC
States I-LOC
to O
send O
a O
protest B-TER
note I-TER
through O
the O
Swiss B-ORG
Legation I-ORG
which O
here O
protects O
their O
interests O
. O

However O
, O
the O
Romanian B-LOC
government B-TER
, O
during O
the O
last O
meeting O
of O
the O
Council O
of O
Ministers O
, O
decided O
to O
ignore O
the O
American O
démarche O
and O
to O
carry O
on O
with O
the O
deportations B-TER
. O

To O
this O
end O
, O
the O
Jews B-TER
to O
be O
sent O
beyond O
the O
Dniestr B-LOC
have O
been O
classed O
– O
according O
to O
a O
list O
that O
Romanian B-LOC
authorities O
have O
handed O
to O
German B-ORG
authorities I-ORG
on O
their O
request O
– O
in O
thirteen O
categories O
, O
namely O
: O
1 O
) O
those O
who O
when O
the O
Bolshevik O
invasion O
took O
place O
submitted O
an O
application O
to O
the O
local O
Soviet O
Legation O
to O
be O
allowed O
to O
move O
to O
the O
U.R.S.S B-LOC
. O

( O
the O
relevant O
lists O
were O
found O
by O
the O
Romanians B-LOC
in O
the O
archives O
of O
the O
Russian B-LOC
Legation O
) O
; O
2 O
) O
people O
who O
are O
in O
jail O
for O
being O
Communists B-TER
; O
3 O
) O
those O
who O
already O
are O
in O
concentration B-TER
camps I-TER
; O
4 O
) O
those O
engaged O
in O
illegal B-TER
activities I-TER
; O
5 O
) O
owners O
of O
gambling O
houses O
, O
gamblers O
, O
cardsharpers O
; O
6 O
) O
saboteurs B-TER
of O
the O
economy B-TER
, O
that O
is O
those O
guilty O
of O
speculating O
and O
hoarding O
, O
according O
to O
information O
acquired O
by O
the O
Prefecture O
of O
Police B-TER
; O
7 O
) O
those O
who O
are O
in O
favour O
of O
the O
Americans O
; O
8) O
Russophiles O
, O
who O
oppose O
the O
war O
against O
the O
Soviet B-LOC
Union I-LOC
; O
9 O
) O
alarmists O
; O
10 O
) O
Hungarophiles O
in O
Transylvania B-LOC
, O
particularly O
in O
the O
Deva B-LOC
and O
Arad B-LOC
areas O
, O
and O
those O
who O
have O
tried O
to O
emigrate O
to O
Hungary B-LOC
; O
12 O
) O
those O
guilty O
of O
fraudulent O
bankruptcy O
; O
13 O
) O
former O
journalists B-TER
who O
were O
employed O
by O
the O
Anglo O
- O
American O
news O
organization O
. O

The O
said O
measures O
are O
in O
my O
opinion O
further O
proof O
of O
the O
resolve O
with O
which O
the O
Conducator B-PER
’s I-PER
regime O
has O
embraced O
the O
cause O
of O
totalitarian O
Nations O
. O

They O
will O
no O
doubt O
please O
Germany B-LOC
, O
which O
never O
tires O
to O
urge O
Romanians B-LOC
to O
use O
forcefulness O
in O
eliminating B-TER
Jewry O
, O
but O
at O
the O
same O
time O
will O
deepen O
the O
chasm O
separating O
Antonescu B-PER
’s I-PER
Romania O
from O
the O
democratic O
countries O
. O

In O
the O
country O
itself O
the O
anti B-TER
- I-TER
Semitic I-TER
measures I-TER
are O
designed O
instead O
to O
do O
away O
with O
the O
most O
dangerous O
hotbeds O
of O
opposition O
and O
to O
“ O
romanize O
” O
the O
vast O
Jewish O
assets O
, O
while O
the O
deportation O
of O
Transylvanian O
Jews O
, O
who O
are O
all O
Hungarophiles O
, O
is O
aimed O
at O
strengthening O
the O
Romanian O
make O
- O
up O
of O
those O
contested O
regions O
. O

I O
enclose O
on O
this O
point O
the O
copy O
of O
a O
report O
by O
the O
R.Vice O
Consulate O
in O
Timisoara B-LOC
. O

R. O
Bova B-PER
Scoppa I-PER
