Ignalina B-LOC
( O
Švenčionys B-LOC
district I-LOC
) O
. O

A O
work B-TER
camp I-TER
of O
the O
organization B-ORG
Dat I-ORG
( O
or O
Todt B-ORG
) O
was O
located O
there O
from O
the O
month O
of O
April O
1942 O
until O
March O
30 O
, O
1943 O
. O

The O
work B-TER
was O
comprised O
of O
chopping O
[ O
wood O
in O
the O
] O
forest O
near O
Ignalina B-LOC
and O
also O
[ O
working O
] O
on O
the O
railway O
line O
. O

In O
the O
year O
1942 O
, O
around O
150 O
people O
from O
Vilna B-LOC
as O
well O
as O
Smarhoń B-LOC
( O
Smorgon B-LOC
) O
and O
Ashmyana B-LOC
( O
Oshmene B-LOC
) O
worked O
there O
. O

At O
the O
end O
of O
1942 O
, O
a O
great O
number O
became O
sick B-TER
with O
typhus B-TER
, O
they O
succeeded O
in O
transporting B-TER
the O
sick B-TER
to O
Švenčionys B-LOC
to O
the O
ghetto B-TER
and O
they O
never O
returned O
. O

In O
their O
stead O
workers O
were O
sent O
from O
the O
shtetls O
of O
Vidzy B-LOC
, O
Druysk B-LOC
, O
Dubina B-LOC
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
did O
not O
treat O
the O
Jewish O
workers B-TER
badly O
, O
most O
of O
all O
the O
camp B-TER
director I-TER
, O
a O
lieutenant O
form O
Danzig B-LOC
( O
I O
have O
forgotten O
his O
name O
) O
, O
distinguished O
himself O
. O

He O
would O
allow O
the O
Jews O
to O
go O
begging O
in O
the O
villages O
and O
to O
work B-TER
for O
Christians O
three O
to O
four O
days O
per O
month O
, O
but O
no O
one O
should O
say O
that O
he O
had O
allowed O
them O
to O
do O
so O
. O

At O
the O
end O
of O
March O
1943 O
, O
all O
the O
workers B-TER
had O
to O
be O
sent O
to O
the O
ghetto B-LOC
in I-LOC
Švenčionys I-LOC
. O

The O
workers B-TER
cried O
when O
they O
parted O
with O
the O
Germans B-TER
. O

The O
lieutenant O
and O
another O
two O
of O
the O
watchmen B-TER
cried O
. O

Of O
all O
the O
workers B-TER
only O
two O
remain O
alive O
, O
one O
from O
Vidzy B-LOC
, O
Leib B-PER
Tvaretsky I-PER
, O
and O
a O
young O
woman B-TER
from O
Dryusk B-LOC
, O
Sheyne B-PER
Feygin I-PER
. O

They O
must O
be O
in O
Germany B-LOC
, O
In O
the O
year O
1945 O
, O
I O
found O
in O
the O
home O
of O
a O
Christian B-TER
in O
Ignalina B-LOC
a O
photograph B-TER
of O
a O
group O
of O
workers B-TER
from O
the O
Ignalina B-LOC
camp I-LOC
. O

I O
gave O
the O
photo B-TER
to O
the O
Historical O
Museum B-TER
in O
Lodz B-LOC
, O
to O
Mr. O
Sh B-PER
. I-PER

Kaczerginski I-PER
. O

Munich B-LOC
, O
7/7/46 O
Yerachmiel B-PER
Korb I-PER
from O
Ignalina B-LOC
, O
Švenčionys B-LOC
district I-LOC
, O
Vilna B-LOC
region O
