Efroim B-PER
Münzer I-PER
Testimony O
( O
doc O
. O

301/203 O
) O
Original O
, O
manuscript O
, O
4 O
pages O
, O
150 O
x O
210 O
mm O
, O
Polish O
language O
Efroim B-PER
Münzer I-PER
, O
born O
1 O
. O

1 O
. O

1928 O
in O
Gdów B-LOC
, O
a O
town O
in O
Wieliczka B-LOC
district O
Occupation O
: O
baker O
Residence O
: O
66/17 B-LOC
Starowiślna I-LOC
[ I-LOC
Street I-LOC
] I-LOC
in O
Cracow B-LOC
Description O
of O
the O
camp B-TER
and O
life B-TER
in O
Stalowa B-LOC
Wola I-LOC
He O
stayed O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
from O
1942 O
to O
1944 O
. O

In O
August O
1942 O
, O
during O
a O
deportation B-TER
in O
Wieliczka B-LOC
, O
they O
were O
loaded O
onto O
cattle B-TER
cars I-TER
, O
100 O
people O
in O
each O
. O

He O
rode O
on O
a O
train B-TER
for O
24 O
hours O
during O
a O
very O
hot O
period O
and O
nobody O
was O
allowed O
to O
approach O
them O
with O
something O
to O
drink O
. O

Only O
in O
Dębica B-LOC
a O
Pole B-TER
gave O
them O
a O
bucket O
of O
water O
at O
the O
charge B-TER
of O
100 O
złotys O
. O

On O
the O
arrival O
in O
camp B-TER
, O
they O
were O
received O
by O
the O
camp B-TER
guards I-TER
consisting O
of O
Belorussians B-TER
with O
whips B-TER
. O

There O
were O
3 O
barracks B-TER
for O
the O
laborers B-TER
. O

In O
August O
1942 O
there O
were O
80 O
Jews O
from O
Sieniawa B-LOC
there O
. O

Since O
August O
, O
there O
were O
already O
680 O
( O
600 O
from O
Wieliczka B-LOC
) O
. O

The O
bunks O
in O
the O
barrack B-TER
had O
no O
paillasses O
, O
so O
that O
the O
laborers B-TER
slept O
on O
the O
boards O
. O

On O
the O
first O
day O
the O
workers B-TER
stood B-TER
in O
front O
of O
the O
barrack B-TER
from O
five O
in O
the O
morning O
till O
the O
evening O
. O

During O
that O
time O
they O
were O
thoroughly O
searched O
and O
deprived O
of O
everything O
, O
from O
money B-TER
and O
valuables O
down O
to O
a O
simple O
leather O
belt O
. O

In O
the O
evening O
the O
SS B-TER
Scharführer O
Schwamberg B-PER
( O
known O
as O
the O
liquidator B-TER
of O
the O
Przemyśl B-LOC
ghetto B-TER
) O
and O
the O
Unterscharführer O
Brzdok B-PER
( O
probably O
Bardok B-PER
) O
came O
to O
them O
. O

Schwamberg B-PER
gave O
a O
speech O
: O
They O
have O
to O
give O
away O
all O
the O
valuables O
. O

Whoever O
should O
go O
near O
the O
fence O
will O
automatically O
be O
shot B-TER
. O

Whichever O
of O
the O
Jews O
talks O
to O
a O
civilian O
during O
work O
, O
be O
it O
about O
the O
sale O
of O
bread B-TER
or O
anything O
else O
, O
will O
be O
shot B-TER
. O

Whoever O
pauses O
at O
work O
, O
will O
be O
shot B-TER
. O

Directly O
after O
this O
speech O
, O
the O
majority O
threw O
away O
the O
money O
or O
valuables B-TER
they O
were O
hiding O
. O

In O
the O
meantime O
, O
as O
a O
warning O
, O
they O
beat B-TER
several O
people O
till O
blood O
was O
drawn O
, O
supposedly O
because O
they O
had O
n’t O
given O
away O
everything O
. O

There O
was O
a O
reveille B-TER
at O
two O
in O
the O
night O
. O

They O
marched O
out O
to O
work B-TER
at O
6 O
; O
till O
then O
they O
were O
kept O
standing O
. O

They O
were O
taken O
away O
their O
caps O
and O
jackets O
to O
prevent O
them O
from O
escaping B-TER
. O

On O
the O
way O
to O
work B-TER
in O
a O
factory B-TER
distant O
by O
4 O
km O
they O
were O
driven O
with O
whips B-TER
. O

They O
had O
to O
run O
all O
the O
way O
. O

They O
worked B-TER
from O
7 O
am O
to O
6 O
pm O
with O
one O
20 O
- O
minute O
break O
at O
3 O
pm O
for O
a O
soup B-TER
. O

They O
worked B-TER
in O
a O
steelworks O
. O

Vorarbeiters O
Vorarbeiter O
( O
German O
) O
– O
foreman O
. O

at O
work B-TER
were O
Volksdeutsche B-TER
. O

The O
greatest O
sadist O
among O
them O
was O
Piosik B-PER
( O
rumored O
to O
come O
from O
Poznań B-LOC
) O
. O

He O
murdered B-TER
the O
Jews O
with O
a O
piece B-TER
of O
iron O
. O

He O
once O
burned B-TER
a O
Jew O
alive O
. O

Most O
Jews O
died B-TER
because O
of O
the O
said O
Piosik B-PER
. O

Almost O
8 O
- O
10 O
Jews O
escaped B-TER
everyday O
from O
the O
workplace O
. O

Because O
of O
that O
almost O
every O
day O
they O
had O
to O
stand B-TER
2 O
- O
3 O
hours O
at O
roll B-TER
call I-TER
. O

In O
the O
evening O
they O
were O
given O
ab[out O
] O
20dkg B-TER
of O
bread B-TER
and O
a O
soup B-TER
, O
in O
which O
there O
were O
dirty B-TER
and O
unpeeled O
potatoes B-TER
. O

At O
the O
head O
of O
a O
barrack B-TER
stood O
an O
Ordnungsdienstmann O
. O

Ordnungsdienstmann O
( O
German O
) O
– O
member O
of O
the O
Ordnungsdienst O
( O
Order O
Service O
) O
Almost O
everyday O
10 O
- O
15 O
of O
the O
sick B-TER
, O
who O
lay O
in O
the O
so O
called O
Krankenstube O
, O
Krankenstube O
( O
German O
) O
- O
sickroom O
were O
shot B-TER
. O

These O
murders B-TER
were O
committed O
by O
an O
SS B-TER
- O
Sturmmann O
. O

In O
December O
1942 O
, O
121 O
or O
123 O
Jews O
were O
shot B-TER
as O
unfit O
for O
work B-TER
. O

Apart O
from O
that O
, O
10 O
- O
15 O
people B-TER
died B-TER
every O
day O
( O
dysentery B-TER
and O
the O
like O
) O
. O

( O
Since O
September O
there O
were O
already O
1100 B-TER
Jews O
) O
. O

At O
the O
head O
of O
the O
OD B-TER
OD O
- O
Ordnungsdienst O
there O
stood O
a O
German B-TER
Jew O
, O
Goldstein B-PER
- I-PER
Lindenmann I-PER
, O
a O
pervert B-TER
, O
an O
SS B-TER
- O
Sturmmann O
’s O
favorite O
( O
He O
is O
rumored O
to O
be O
under O
arrest B-TER
now O
) O
. O

At O
the O
end O
of O
1942 O
only O
300 O
Jews O
remained O
, O
who O
worked B-TER
already O
under O
the O
Wehrmacht B-ORG
’s I-ORG
supervision O
. O

After O
80 O
Jews O
from O
Przemyśl B-LOC
arrived B-TER
( O
in O
December O
1942 O
) O
, O
there O
were O
already O
380 O
Jews O
. O

This O
situation O
did O
n’t O
change O
until O
the B-TER
end I-TER
. O

Once O
, O
when O
two O
Jews O
accused O
the O
said O
Goldstein B-PER
- I-PER
Lindenmann I-PER
of O
beating B-TER
the O
Jews O
, O
he O
denounced B-TER
their O
supposed O
intention O
of O
escape B-TER
. O

They O
were O
shot B-TER
. O

In O
March O
1943 O
he O
prepared O
a O
list O
of O
56 O
Jews O
who O
, O
as O
he O
claimed O
, O
were O
unable O
to O
work B-TER
. O

They O
were O
shot B-TER
. O

In O
July O
1944 O
, O
during O
the O
Soviet B-ORG
offensive I-ORG
, O
most O
people O
wanted O
to O
escape B-TER
, O
but O
were O
prevented O
by O
Goldstein B-PER
. O

And O
yet O
85 O
Jews O
pulled O
out O
the O
fences O
, O
cut O
the O
barbed O
wire O
with O
scissors O
and O
ran B-TER
away I-TER
into O
the O
forest B-TER
. O

They O
stayed B-TER
there O
for O
2 O
weeks O
( O
until O
August O
2 O
) O
. O

They O
were O
liberated B-TER
by O
the O
Soviets B-ORG
. O

