Fischer B-PER
Schaechter I-PER
Testimony O
( O
doc O
. O

301/201 O
) O
Typescript O
, O
1 O
page O
, O
210 O
x O
295 O
mm O
, O
Polish O
language O
Fischer B-PER
Schaechter I-PER
, O
son B-TER
of O
Eliasz B-PER
. O

Born O
on O
May O
22 O
, O
1933 O
in O
Beregsas B-LOC
( O
Hungary B-LOC
) O
. O

Beregszasz O
, O
today O
Berehovo O
( O
Ukraine O
) O
In O
1942 O
, O
he O
was O
deported B-TER
with O
his O
family B-TER
to O
Polish O
Ukraine B-LOC
. O

He O
survived O
the O
shootings B-TER
of O
Jews O
in O
Halicz B-LOC
, O
a O
pogrom B-TER
in O
Stanisławów B-LOC
. O

Then O
, O
for O
a O
year O
or O
so O
, O
he O
wandered O
with O
his O
family B-TER
from O
one O
place O
to O
another O
, O
as O
Ukrainians B-TER
. O

In O
mid- O
1943 O
they O
arrived O
in O
Nagymzolos B-LOC
. O

Nagyszöllos O
, O
today O
Vinohradiv O
( O
Ukraine O
) O
. O

They O
lived O
there O
as O
Aryans B-TER
until O
the O
ghetto B-TER
was O
created O
one O
day O
after O
the O
Germans B-TER
arrived O
in O
the O
town O
. O

In O
May O
1944 O
he O
arrived O
at O
Oświęcim B-LOC
[ I-LOC
Auschwitz I-LOC
] I-LOC
( I-LOC
Brzezinka I-LOC
) I-LOC
. O

A O
tattooed O
number B-TER
A O
5107 O
. O

Right O
after O
he O
arrived O
there O
with O
his O
brother B-TER
, O
as O
twins O
they O
were O
sent O
aside O
, O
to O
the O
hospital B-TER
( I-TER
Krankenbau I-TER
) I-TER
. O

Nine O
times O
his O
blood O
was O
drawn B-TER
, O
his O
nails O
were O
measured B-TER
, O
all O
parts O
of O
his O
body O
were O
measured O
under O
the O
supervision O
of O
Obersturmführer O
– O
Lagerarzt O
Oberstürmführer O
– O
SS O
rank O
equal O
to O
Oberleutnant O
( O
lieutenant O
) O
. O

Lagerarzt O
( O
German O
) O
– O
camp O
doctor O
. O

Research O
on O
twins O
was O
made O
by O
infamous O
doctor O
Josef O
Mengele O
, O
having O
the O
rank O
of O
Hauptstürmführer O
( O
captain O
) O
. O

Many O
twins B-TER
, O
( O
mostly O
girls O
) O
died O
after O
these O
experiments B-TER
. O

The O
twin B-TER
brothers I-TER
did O
not O
even O
receive O
regular O
food B-TER
rations I-TER
and O
had O
to O
work B-TER
hard O
[ O
moving O
] O
stones O
. O

