Adressed O
to O
: O
R. O
Representation O
of O
Italy B-LOC
for O
Greece B-LOC
, O
Athens B-LOC
c.c O
. O

R. O
Ministry B-ORG
of I-ORG
Foreign I-ORG
Affairs I-ORG
, O
Rome B-LOC
Position O
: O
class O
. O

Thessaloniki B-LOC
, O
20th O
March O
1943 O
, O
XXI O
Measures B-TER
against O
the O
Jews B-TER
of O
Thessaloniki B-LOC
. O

On O
the O
12th O
inst O
. O

the O
Jews O
’ O
departure B-TER
for O
Poland B-LOC
has O
begun O
. O

Four O
trains B-TER
are O
planned O
each O
week O
, O
and O
each O
train O
will O
hold O
approx O
. O

2,500 O
people O
. O

At O
this O
rate O
, O
within O
5 O
or O
6 O
weeks O
all O
Jews B-TER
will O
have O
left O
town O
. O

The O
beginning O
of O
the O
transfer B-TER
and O
the O
way O
in O
which O
it O
is O
carried O
out O
, O
i.e. O
more O
than O
60 O
people O
in O
each O
freight O
car O
, O
with O
very O
few O
clothes O
and O
little O
food O
and O
with O
no B-TER
money I-TER
and I-TER
valuables I-TER
, O
has O
caused O
deep O
dismay O
among O
the O
Jews B-TER
, O
who O
in O
their O
great O
majority O
deluded O
themselves O
that O
they O
would O
escape O
such O
a O
measure O
. O

The O
Greek B-LOC
population O
, O
in O
general O
, O
disapproves B-TER
of O
the O
severity O
with O
which O
the O
measures O
are O
carried O
out O
and O
is O
touched O
by O
what O
they O
see O
happening O
. O

Among O
the O
Jews B-TER
there O
is O
resentment B-TER
against O
the O
Greeks B-LOC
, O
because O
a O
rumour B-TER
has O
spread O
that O
the O
Germans B-TER
have O
acted O
at O
the O
request O
of O
a O
Greek B-LOC
committee O
that O
is O
said O
to O
have O
travelled O
to O
Nurnberg B-LOC
for O
this O
purpose O
, O
some O
time O
ago O
. O

During O
the O
departure O
operations O
, O
which O
have O
to O
be O
completed O
within O
a O
very O
short O
time O
, O
acts B-TER
of I-TER
violence I-TER
have O
occurred O
that O
have O
left O
an O
unfavourable O
impression O
. O

There O
have O
been O
several O
demises O
on O
the O
way O
from O
the O
ghetto B-TER
to O
the O
railway O
station O
. O

As O
soon O
as O
the O
Jews O
left O
their O
neighbourhood O
, O
gangs O
of O
Greek B-LOC
criminals B-TER
broke O
into O
their O
homes O
in O
order O
to O
plunder O
them O
. O

The O
Greek O
gendarmerie B-TER
had O
to O
step O
in O
and O
resorted O
to O
firearms O
. O

Four O
thieves O
were O
killed O
, O
four O
more O
were O
fatally O
wounded O
, O
approx O
. O

35 O
were O
wounded O
and O
about O
a O
hundred O
were O
arrested O
. O

German B-TER
authorities I-TER
have O
issued O
very O
harsh O
orders B-TER
whereby O
anyone O
entering O
a O
deserted O
Jewish B-TER
home O
will O
be O
shot O
on O
the O
spot O
. O

The B-TER
rebels I-TER
have O
sent O
agents O
into O
the O
ghetto B-TER
, O
to O
make O
propaganda B-TER
and O
to O
recruit O
more O
easily O
people O
for O
their O
bands O
. O

They O
do O
this O
very O
prudently O
, O
for O
fear O
of O
being O
found O
out O
, O
Some O
people O
have O
indeed O
fled O
, O
either O
to B-TER
join I-TER
the I-TER
rebels I-TER
or O
to O
reach O
our O
zone O
, O
but O
their O
number O
is O
as O
yet O
unknown O
. O

Town O
life O
continues O
to O
be O
overshadowed O
by O
this O
event O
, O
which O
has O
engendered O
situations O
that O
will O
find O
their O
solution O
only O
in O
the O
course O
of O
time O
. O

Guelfo B-PER
Zamboni I-PER
