B. O
310 O
- O
English O
Translation O
The O
experiences O
of O
a O
twelve O
- O
year O
- O
old O
Jewish O
child B-TER
in O
Vienna B-LOC
in O
the O
winter O
of O
1938 O
/ O
39 O
emerge O
from O
the O
following O
extracts O
of O
a O
series O
of O
letters B-TER
. O

February O
1939 O
Dear O
Sister O
, O
I O
have O
another O
big O
favour O
to O
ask O
you O
. O

I O
have O
received O
the O
following O
sad O
, O
deeply O
sad O
letters B-TER
from O
Vienna B-LOC
. O

C. O
ten O
days O
ago O
I O
got O
one O
from O
a O
little O
girl B-TER
who O
is O
almost O
twelve O
. O

I O
have O
told O
you O
about O
her O
already O
, O
she O
had O
come O
to O
England B-LOC
with O
her O
sister O
and O
was O
called O
back O
by O
a O
relative O
because O
the O
children B-TER
of O
Martha B-PER
( O
a O
cousin O
of O
her O
father O
) O
were O
very O
seriously O
ill B-TER
. O

The O
little O
boy B-TER
recovered O
, O
but O
the O
little O
girl B-TER
of O
four O
, O
whose O
picture O
I O
once O
showed O
you O
, O
died B-TER
. O

Leni B-PER
has O
now O
written O
to O
tell O
me O
that O
the O
child B-TER
has O
died B-TER
and O
that O
Martha B-PER
is O
refusing O
to O
eat B-TER
and O
does O
n’t O
want O
to O
see O
anyone O
, O
not O
even O
her O
little O
boy B-TER
. O

I O
wrote O
her O
a O
consoling O
letter B-TER
and O
then O
yesterday O
received O
an O
even O
sadder O
one O
, O
also O
written O
by O
the O
girl B-TER
. O

Martha B-PER
is O
in O
hospital B-TER
and O
has O
had O
a O
nervous B-TER
breakdown I-TER
, O
but O
not O
just O
as O
a O
result O
of O
the O
death B-TER
of O
her O
little O
girl B-TER
. O

She O
wrote O
the O
following O
: O
It O
has O
been O
very O
hot O
here O
in O
the O
last O
few O
days O
and O
in O
order O
to O
cool O
down O
we O
had O
to O
spend O
a O
day O
and O
a O
night O
in O
the O
cellar O
. O

When O
we O
came O
back O
up O
again O
burglars O
had O
been O
there O
and O
stolen O
everything O
– O
money O
, O
linen O
, O
clothes O
, O
jewellery O
, O
even O
things O
belonging O
to O
the O
little O
boy O
– O
and O
that O
’s O
when O
TanteMartha O
had O
her O
nervous O
breakdown O
. O

They O
only O
have O
what O
they O
were O
wearing B-TER
at O
the O
time O
. O

So O
to O
my O
request O
. O

If O
you O
have O
anything O
your O
daughter O
really O
ca O
n’t O
wear B-TER
any O
longer O
and O
anything O
you O
yourself O
do O
n’t O
use O
then O
I O
can O
send O
it O
to O
Martha B-PER
. O

It O
would O
be O
a O
big O
mitzvah O
[ O
good O
deed O
] O
and O
I O
am O
sure O
your O
husband O
will O
agree O
. O

The O
girl B-TER
now O
has O
to O
look O
after O
the O
little O
boy B-TER
. O

She O
spends O
the O
day O
with O
friends O
and O
at O
night O
sleeps O
alone O
with O
the O
boy B-TER
in O
the O
flat B-TER
. O

Is O
n’t O
this O
a O
terrible O
tragedy O
? O
... O
Vienna B-LOC
, O
February O
1939 O
Dear O
Frau O
Z. O
, O
I O
take O
the O
liberty O
of O
thanking O
you O
very O
sincerely O
in O
the O
name O
of O
my O
Tante O
Martha B-PER
for O
the O
parcel B-TER
. O

My O
Tante O
is O
very O
ill B-TER
and O
is O
in O
hospital B-TER
. O

But O
first O
I O
would O
like O
to O
introduce O
myself O
to O
you O
so O
you O
know O
who O
I O
am O
. O

My O
late O
father O
and O
Tante O
Martha B-PER
were O
cousins O
. O

I O
am O
eleven O
and O
a O
half O
and O
my O
name O
is O
Leni B-PER
and O
am O
now O
always O
going O
to O
stay O
with O
my O
Tante O
because O
my O
Mama O
also O
died B-TER
a O
few O
weeks O
ago O
. O

I O
will O
keep O
the O
parcel B-TER
safely O
until O
Tante O
Martha B-PER
comes O
home B-TER
. O

Then O
she O
will O
write O
to O
you O
herself O
. O

She O
got O
sick B-TER
because O
she O
was O
very O
agitated O
. O

In O
October O
my O
Papi O
died B-TER
, O
six O
weeks O
later O
my O
Mami O
. O

Onkel O
Jacob B-PER
disappeared O
last O
May O
and O
I O
ca O
n’t O
tell O
you O
where O
he O
is O
because O
I O
do O
n’t O
know O
. O

In O
January O
Sonja B-PER
died B-TER
, O
Martha B-PER
's I-PER
little O
girl B-TER
. O

She O
was O
four O
years O
old O
. O

But O
Tante O
Martha B-PER
has O
another O
child B-TER
. O

He O
's O
called O
Hans B-PER
and O
is O
one O
and O
a O
half O
years O
old O
. O

Now O
something O
else O
has O
happened O
, O
I O
ca O
n’t O
tell O
you O
everything O
, O
it O
was O
all O
too O
much O
for O
my O
Tante O
. O

She O
has O
often O
told O
me O
about O
you O
and O
is O
very O
fond O
of O
you O
. O

She O
always O
spoke O
so O
warmly O
about O
you O
. O

And O
she O
showed O
me O
pictures O
of O
tantet O
you O
and O
your O
little O
daughter B-TER
. O

So O
once O
again O
many O
thanks O
and O
warmest O
greetings O
from O
Leni B-PER
and O
Hansi B-PER
. O

I O
am O
going O
to O
the O
hospital B-TER
tomorrow O
, O
I O
hope O
my O
Tante O
will O
be O
able O
to O
write O
to O
you O
herself O
. O

Vienna B-LOC
, O
10th O
March O
1939 O
My O
dear O
good O
Tante O
I O
received O
your O
kind O
letter B-TER
. O

And O
thank O
you O
very O
much O
for O
letting O
me O
call O
you O
Tante O
. O

I O
am O
very O
fond O
of O
you O
and O
Tante O
Anna O
because O
Tante O
Martha B-PER
likes O
you O
so O
much O
. O

Unfortunately O
she O
is O
still O
very O
ill B-TER
and O
ca O
n’t O
write O
to O
you O
herself O
. O

Hansi B-PER
and O
I O
are O
staying O
with O
a O
woman B-TER
in O
the O
same O
building B-TER
. O

I O
do O
n’t O
want O
to O
look O
after O
Hansi B-PER
any O
more O
. O

He O
's O
very O
naughty O
. O

He O
wo O
n’t O
let O
me O
wash O
and O
dress O
him O
. O

He O
bites O
me O
and O
scratches O
me O
all O
the O
time O
and O
cries O
for O
his O
Mama O
. O

I O
go O
to O
school B-TER
. O

The O
teacher O
likes O
me O
a O
lot O
. O

The O
things O
you O
sent O
will O
fit O
Tante O
Martha B-PER
because O
she O
has O
got O
very O
thin O
. O

They O
are O
too O
big O
for O
me O
, O
but O
Tante O
Martha B-PER
will O
sort O
everything O
out O
for O
me O
when O
she O
's O
well O
again O
... O
Vienna B-LOC
, O
March O
1939 O
Dear O
good O
Tanterle O
[ O
little O
aunt O
] O
Your O
card B-TER
arrived O
yesterday O
. O

I O
ca O
n’t O
give O
you O
the O
address O
of O
the O
hospital B-TER
. O

Dear O
Tante O
, O
I O
will O
tell O
you O
the O
truth O
, O
although O
Tante O
Martha B-PER
has O
told O
me O
not O
to O
. O

She O
was O
in O
the O
District O
Court O
in O
January O
. O

What O
Tante O
Berta O
wrote O
is O
true O
, O
that O
burglars O
were O
here O
and O
stole B-TER
everything O
. O

In O
the O
heat O
of O
the O
moment O
my O
Tante O
said O
some O
unfortunate O
things O
, O
which O
is O
why O
she O
has O
had O
this O
misfortune O
. O

I O
ca O
n’t O
describe O
everything O
to O
you O
as O
it O
happened O
, O
you O
would O
have O
to O
see O
it O
with O
your O
own O
eyes O
to O
understand O
it O
. O

I O
would O
n’t O
have O
written O
to O
you O
about O
all O
this O
if O
you O
had O
n’t O
asked O
me O
for O
the O
address O
of O
the O
hospital B-TER
. O

Tante O
Martha B-PER
must O
n’t O
know O
that O
I O
have O
told O
you O
the O
truth O
and O
Tante O
Berta O
also O
. O

I O
visit O
her O
every O
Wednesday O
. O

I O
am O
sending O
you O
a O
note O
which O
she O
slipped O
me O
. O

Once O
more O
, O
please O
do O
n’t O
tell O
anyone O
that O
you O
know O
everything O
. O

Lots O
of O
kisses O
Leni B-PER
. O

Please O
do O
n’t O
send O
me O
any O
more O
cards B-TER
because O
the O
lady B-TER
I O
live O
with O
reads O
everything O
. O

Thank O
you O
very O
much O
for O
the O
beautiful O
things O
. O

Best O
wishes O
and O
kisses O
Martha O
. O

I O
am O
in O
hospital O
and O
ca O
n’t O
write O
anything O
else O
. O

Vienna B-LOC
, O
March O
1939 O
Dear O
Tante O
I O
am O
sending O
you O
a O
letter B-TER
from O
my O
Tante O
. O

Hansi B-PER
is O
now O
spending O
his O
time O
with O
Frau B-TER
F. O
until O
my O
Tante O
comes O
home B-TER
again O
. O

Lots O
of O
kisses O
from O
Leni B-PER
. O

From O
prison B-TER
, O
March O
1939 O
My O
dear O
good O
Täntchen O
[ O
little O
aunt O
] O
Yesterday O
my O
little O
Leni B-PER
was O
here O
with O
me O
and O
admitted O
to O
me O
that O
she O
has O
told O
you O
the O
whole O
truth O
. O

Dear O
Tante O
, O
will O
you O
now O
think O
ill O
of O
me O
? O
I O
do O
n’t O
know O
if O
Leni B-PER
told O
you O
everything O
in O
detail O
, O
I O
ca O
n’t O
talk O
much O
to O
her O
here O
. O

They O
took O
everything O
away O
from O
us O
and O
we O
just O
stood O
there O
with O
nothing O
more O
than O
clothes B-TER
we O
were O
wearing O
. O

In O
the O
heat O
of O
the O
moment O
I O
said O
some O
words O
I O
should O
n’t O
have O
and O
that O
’s O
why O
I O
've O
been O
here O
for O
the O
last O
three O
months O
. O

Please O
do O
n’t O
think O
ill O
of O
me O
as O
a O
result O
. O

After O
all O
, O
dear O
Tante O
, O
your O
brother O
was O
also O
here O
for O
13 O
weeks O
last O
year O
, O
as O
you O
know O
, O
and O
that O
did O
n’t O
make O
him O
a O
bad O
person O
. O

Thank O
you O
thousands O
of O
times O
for O
the O
lovely O
things O
. O

If O
I O
did O
n’t O
have O
them O
I O
would O
have O
to O
wear O
the O
same O
dress B-TER
all O
the O
time O
. O

They O
fit O
very O
well O
, O
although O
the O
shoes B-TER
are O
rather O
large O
, O
but O
I O
can O
still O
wear O
them O
. O

You O
ca O
n’t O
imagine O
how O
happy O
I O
was O
about O
everything O
you O
sent O
and O
above O
all O
because O
they O
came O
from O
you O
. O

I O
am O
always O
thinking O
of O
you O
. O

Please O
do O
n’t O
be O
angry O
that O
Leni B-PER
told O
you O
I O
was O
in O
hospital B-TER
, O
I O
was O
too O
embarrassed O
to O
tell O
you O
the O
truth O
. O

Please O
do O
n’t O
tell O
Tante O
Berta O
anything O
about O
this O
. O

Even O
though O
I O
'm O
here O
I O
'm O
not O
despondent O
and O
I O
hope O
that O
I O
will O
soon O
be O
able O
to O
be O
with O
my O
little O
boy B-TER
again O
. O

Leni B-PER
is O
a O
good O
child B-TER
and O
if O
I O
did O
n’t O
have O
her O
I O
would O
be O
completely O
alone O
. O

For O
this O
reason O
I O
will O
always O
keep O
her O
close O
to O
me O
. O

I O
would O
be O
very O
happy O
if O
Leni B-PER
could O
bring O
a O
letter B-TER
from O
you O
on O
Wednesday O
. O

She O
comes O
and O
visits O
me O
every O
Wednesday O
. O

A O
thousand O
greetings O
and O
kisses O
Your O
Martha B-PER
. O

Very O
best O
wishes O
to O
your O
husband O
, O
daughter O
and O
to O
Tante O
Anna O
. O

I O
am O
sending O
you O
a O
picture O
of O
me O
. O

It O
was O
taken O
here O
and O
is O
n’t O
very O
good O
. O

I O
'll O
give O
the O
letter B-TER
to O
Leni B-PER
. O

I O
hope O
it O
arrives O
safely O
. O

Once O
again O
, O
please O
do O
n’t O
tell O
Berta O
anything O
about O
this O
. O

Vienna B-LOC
, O
April O
1939 O
Dear O
good O
Tanterle O
I O
received O
your O
letter B-TER
. O

I O
have O
n’t O
got O
the O
parcel B-TER
yet O
, O
but O
they O
always O
take O
longer O
. O

I O
will O
write O
to O
you O
as O
soon O
as O
it O
arrives O
. O

This O
time O
it O
was O
n’t O
possible O
to O
include O
a O
letter B-TER
from O
Tante O
Martha B-PER
. O

Onkel O
was O
watching O
too O
carefully O
. O

She O
is O
n’t O
allowed O
to O
write O
or O
receive O
letters B-TER
. O

Dear O
Tante O
, O
you O
say O
we O
should O
put O
our O
faith B-TER
in O
God B-TER
. O

I O
do O
n’t O
believe B-TER
in O
God B-TER
. O

Why O
has O
he O
punished O
us O
so O
harshly O
? O
I O
ca O
n’t O
begin O
to O
describe O
what O
we O
've O
been O
through O
. O

God B-TER
has O
taken O
my O
beloved O
parents O
. O

My O
brother O
was O
in O
the O
same O
rest O
home O
as O
your O
brother O
last O
year O
and O
died B-TER
there O
. O

It O
’s O
the O
same O
home B-TER
that O
our O
Tante O
is O
in O
now O
. O

The O
most O
terrible O
thing O
was O
that O
the O
burglars O
were O
here O
and O
took B-TER
everything O
away B-TER
from O
us O
. O

At O
the O
time O
we O
[ O
were O
] O
hidden O
in O
the O
cellar O
for O
three O
days O
and O
did O
n’t O
dare O
come O
out O
. O

Can O
one O
still O
believe B-TER
in O
God B-TER
in O
these O
circumstances O
? O
Just O
look O
, O
dear O
Tante O
, O
at O
how O
badly O
Onkel O
treats O
us O
– O
I O
'm O
not B-TER
allowed I-TER
to I-TER
go I-TER
to O
the O
cinema O
, O
to O
the O
theatre B-TER
, O
I O
'm O
not B-TER
allowed I-TER
to I-TER
go I-TER
to O
the O
park O
, O
some O
days O
I O
'm O
not B-TER
allowed I-TER
to I-TER
show O
my O
face O
on O
the O
street O
. O

Is O
n’t O
that O
enough O
? O
I O
'm O
not O
quite O
twelve O
years O
old O
but O
sometimes O
I O
feel O
as O
if O
I O
'm O
100 O
years O
old O
. O

But O
I O
'll O
stop O
now O
or O
you O
'll O
get O
angry O
. O

Hansi B-PER
now O
spends O
all O
his O
time O
with O
Frau B-TER
F. O
, O
she O
gets O
15 O
Marks O
a O
month O
for O
him O
from O
the O
Gemeinde O
[ O
community O
] O
and O
I O
eat B-TER
in O
the O
girl O
’s O
refuge B-TER
. O

Hansi B-PER
is O
very O
naughty O
but O
a O
cute O
little O
scallywag O
. O

I O
'm O
sending O
you O
a O
picture O
of O
him O
. O

He O
did O
n’t O
want O
to O
stand O
still O
so O
we O
tied O
his O
hands O
to O
the O
railing O
. O

I O
photographed O
him O
. O

In O
the O
next O
letter B-TER
I O
'll O
send O
you O
a O
photograph O
of O
me O
. O

My O
Tante O
has O
a O
lawyer B-TER
. O

I O
do O
n’t O
know O
what O
else O
I O
can O
write O
to O
you O
. O

Your O
Leni B-PER
. O

Vienna B-LOC
, O
May O
1939 O
Dear O
, O
dear O
Tanterle O
I O
received O
your O
kind O
letter B-TER
and O
read O
it O
with O
great O
pleasure O
. O

I O
am O
always O
so O
happy O
when O
you O
write O
to O
me O
. O

As O
far O
as O
the O
subject O
of O
God B-TER
is O
concerned O
I O
want O
to O
ask O
you O
some O
time O
what O
you O
imagine O
him O
to O
be O
like O
. O

I O
know O
you O
'll O
tell O
me O
that O
God B-TER
is O
an O
invisible O
force O
, O
but O
you O
have O
to O
believe B-TER
in O
him O
all O
the O
same O
. O

Let O
me O
now O
give O
you O
a O
little O
example O
. O

If O
I O
wrote O
to O
you O
telling O
you O
that O
I O
have O
sent O
you O
1,000 O
Marks O
, O
but O
you O
'd O
never O
receive O
it O
because O
the O
money O
remains O
invisible O
, O
would O
you O
still O
believe O
me O
? O
You O
'd O
tell O
me O
that O
you O
'd O
believe O
it O
when O
you O
see O
it O
. O

That O
’s O
what O
I O
say O
too O
. O

I O
only O
believe O
what O
I O
see O
. O

And O
you O
also O
say O
that O
you O
could O
tell O
me O
about O
many O
things O
you O
have O
seen O
. O

Dear O
Tante O
, O
you O
certainly O
have O
n’t O
seen O
the O
kind O
of O
things O
I O
've O
seen O
. O

But O
I O
'm O
going O
to O
change O
the O
subject O
or O
you O
'll O
get O
angry O
. O

I O
think O
a O
lot O
about O
everything O
and O
say O
what O
I O
think O
. O

I O
'm O
sorry O
you O
've O
got O
such O
a O
weak O
heart B-TER
. O

If O
I O
was O
there O
I O
could O
have O
taken O
the O
workload O
off O
you O
. O

I O
can O
already O
cook O
a O
bit O
. O

I O
can O
make O
coffee B-TER
and O
I O
've O
also O
made O
Powidlknödel O
[ O
plum O
jam O
dumplings O
] O
. O

I O
am O
sending O
you O
a O
picture O
of O
me O
. O

I O
'm O
wearing O
everything O
you O
sent O
me O
. O

You O
'll O
laugh O
because O
I O
was O
photographed O
with O
the O
doll O
. O

I O
still O
like O
to O
play O
sometimes O
. O

Please O
do O
n’t O
laugh O
at O
me O
or O
get O
angry O
with O
me O
. O

I O
'm O
pleased O
you O
're O
going O
to O
the O
Comité O
. O

Perhaps O
you O
can O
sort O
something O
out O
. O

I O
'd O
be O
very O
grateful O
if O
you O
could O
... O
Please O
write O
to O
me O
again O
soon O
. O

Your O
letters B-TER
are O
a O
real O
comfort O
to O
me O
. O

For O
today O
best O
wishes O
and O
a O
million O
kisses O
Your O
Leni B-PER
and O
Hansi B-PER
. O

Vienna B-LOC
, O
15 O
June O
1939 O
My O
dear O
good O
Tanti O
[ O
auntie O
] O
Today O
a O
man B-TER
came O
to O
visit O
and O
said O
you O
had O
written O
to O
the O
Kultusgemeinde O
[ O
Jewish O
community O
] O
that O
you O
had O
n’t O
had O
any O
post O
from O
us O
since O
January O
. O

He O
also O
gave O
me O
a O
note O
for O
Tante O
Martha B-PER
which O
I O
am O
sending O
you O
. O

I O
do O
n’t O
understand O
why O
you O
have O
n’t O
received O
any O
post B-TER
. O

I O
have O
written O
to O
you O
and O
I O
also O
sent O
you O
a O
picture O
of O
me O
. O

The O
man B-TER
was O
very O
angry O
and O
said O
I O
was O
a O
stupid O
creature O
and O
that O
the O
Kultusgemeinde O
had O
better O
things O
to O
do O
than O
be O
pestered O
about O
things O
like O
this O
. O

Why O
have O
n’t O
you O
written O
to O
me O
? O
do O
n’t O
you O
believe O
what O
I O
told O
you O
about O
Tante O
Martha B-PER
? O
I O
will O
try O
to O
get O
a O
confirmation O
from O
them O
and O
then O
send O
it O
to O
you O
. O

But O
please O
do O
n’t O
write O
to O
the O
Kultusgemeinde O
again O
. O

Please O
reply O
immediately O
so O
I O
know O
that O
you O
've O
got O
my O
letter B-TER
and O
please O
also O
tell O
me O
whether O
you O
got O
my O
picture O
in O
the O
last O
letter B-TER
. O

The O
one O
in O
which O
I O
am O
wearing O
the O
dress B-TER
, O
pullover B-TER
and O
cap B-TER
which O
you O
sent O
me O
. O

Have O
you O
been O
able O
to O
make O
any O
enquiries O
in O
the O
emigration B-TER
office O
about O
Tante O
Martha B-PER
? O
Do O
émigrés B-TER
get O
an O
Arbeitsbewilligung O
[ O
work O
permit O
] O
? O
Tante O
Martha B-PER
is O
a O
qualified O
book B-TER
binder O
. O

I O
will O
travel O
to O
New B-LOC
York I-LOC
and O
Tante O
Martha B-PER
would O
leave O
Hansi B-PER
here O
for O
the O
time O
being O
so O
she O
can O
work O
there O
. O

Please O
, O
please O
reply O
. O

I O
send O
a O
hundred O
thousand O
kisses O
. O

Your O
Leni B-PER
. O

Please O
reply O
. O

( O
The O
inquiry O
directed O
to O
the O
Vienna B-LOC
Kultusgemeinde O
by O
relatives B-TER
in O
Holland B-LOC
was O
intended O
to O
ascertain O
whether O
the O
Kultusgemeinde O
knew O
about O
the O
fate O
of O
the O
family B-TER
. O

Clearly O
they O
were O
not O
informed O
about O
it O
as O
demonstrated O
by O
the O
behaviour O
of O
the O
investigator O
and O
the O
note O
he O
handed O
over O
. O

) O
To O
Martha B-PER
X I-PER
. O

Your O
Tante O
, O
Frau O
Z. O
in O
A. O
, O
requests O
that O
you O
write O
to O
her O
as O
she O
has O
n’t O
heard O
from O
you O
since O
January O
of O
this O
year O
. O

She O
has O
turned O
to O
us O
, O
the O
Vienna B-LOC
Kultusgemeinde O
. O

15 O
June O
1939 O
From O
prison B-TER
, O
June O
1939 O
My O
dear O
good O
Tante O
Thank O
you O
very O
much O
for O
trying O
so O
hard O
to O
sort O
things O
out O
for O
me O
. O

I O
hope O
I O
will O
be O
able O
to O
leave O
here O
soon O
. O

Leni B-PER
and O
Hansi B-PER
are O
travelling O
to O
America B-LOC
. O

At O
the O
moment O
I O
ca O
n’t O
join O
them O
because O
I O
was O
n’t O
registered B-TER
with O
the O
American B-LOC
Consulate B-TER
. O

However O
Leni B-PER
has O
now O
registered B-TER
me O
. O

But O
I O
have O
to O
wait O
for O
at O
least O
a O
year O
before O
I O
can O
travel O
. O

Please O
do O
n’t O
turn O
for O
help O
to O
the O
Vienna B-LOC
Kultusgemeinde O
, O
we O
do O
n’t O
want O
anything O
from O
people O
like O
that O
. O

They O
only O
support O
children B-TER
under O
their O
own O
patronage O
. O

Leni B-PER
has O
asked O
for O
help O
three O
times O
, O
she O
wanted O
to O
give O
me O
the O
money O
so O
that O
I O
could O
improve O
my O
situation O
, O
and O
they O
did O
n’t O
answer O
. O

I O
hope O
that O
I O
'll O
be O
able O
to O
go O
back O
home B-TER
even O
without O
their O
help O
. O

I O
hope O
to O
receive O
an O
answer O
from O
you O
soon O
. O

Thank O
you O
very O
much O
for O
you O
kindness O
and O
I O
hope O
that O
one O
day O
I O
will O
be O
able O
to O
repay O
you O
for O
everything O
. O

A O
thousand O
good O
wishes O
and O
kisses O
Martha B-PER
. O

Vienna B-LOC
, O
June O
1939 O
My O
dear O
Tante O
I O
received O
your O
letter B-TER
today O
. O

The O
man B-TER
from O
the O
Kultusgemeinde O
asked O
me O
whether O
I O
knew O
you O
so O
I O
told O
him O
yes O
, O
I O
do O
know O
you O
. O

I O
did O
n’t O
know O
I O
was O
n’t O
supposed O
to O
do O
it O
. O

But O
I O
did O
n’t O
say O
that O
my O
Tante O
is O
in O
prison B-TER
. O

That O
’s O
none O
of O
the O
Kultusgemeinde O
's O
business O
. O

I O
get O
food B-TER
for O
myself O
and O
Hansi B-PER
from O
the O
Jewish O
canteen O
and O
the O
woman B-TER
with O
whom O
Hansi B-PER
is O
living O
has O
only O
received O
10 O
Marks O
for O
him O
on O
two O
occasions O
. O

Three O
times O
now O
I O
have O
submitted O
an O
application O
for O
support O
to O
the O
jüdische O
Fürsorge O
[ O
Jewish O
Welfare B-TER
] O
on O
behalf O
of O
my O
Tante O
and O
have O
n’t O
had O
a O
reply O
. O

They O
always O
say O
there O
's O
no O
money O
. O

Do O
you O
really O
believe O
that O
the O
Kultusgemeinde O
cares O
about O
its O
own O
people O
? O
You O
could O
perish O
like O
a O
dog O
and O
they O
would O
n’t O
care O
. O

When O
I O
'm O
14 O
I O
'm O
going O
to O
drop O
religion B-TER
entirely O
. O

Please O
do O
n’t O
turn O
to O
the O
Kultusgemeinde O
any O
more O
, O
we O
do O
n’t O
want O
to O
have O
anything O
to O
do O
with O
them O
. O

I O
'm O
going O
to O
New B-LOC
York I-LOC
, O
perhaps O
in O
two O
weeks O
even O
, O
and O
if O
Tante O
Martha B-PER
agrees O
Hansi B-PER
can O
come O
along O
as O
well O
. O

I O
'm O
travelling O
with O
a O
party O
. O

And O
Tante O
Grete O
is O
in O
New B-LOC
York I-LOC
. O

She O
invited O
us O
. O

Thank O
you O
for O
being O
so O
good O
to O
us O
. O

But O
you O
do O
n’t O
need O
to O
worry O
about O
me O
and O
Hansi B-PER
any O
more O
. O

If O
you O
could O
send O
Tante O
Martha B-PER
an O
entry O
permit O
for O
Holland B-LOC
we O
would O
be O
very O
grateful O
to O
you O
. O

But O
first O
you O
will O
need O
to O
ask O
if O
she O
would O
be O
allowed O
to O
work O
there O
. O

Tante O
Grete O
has O
handed O
the O
matter O
over O
to O
a O
solicitor O
in O
New B-LOC
York I-LOC
and O
we O
hope O
that O
Tante O
Martha B-PER
will O
soon O
be O
able O
to O
come O
home B-TER
. O

So O
in O
the O
name O
of O
Tante O
Martha B-PER
please O
understand O
that O
we O
do O
n’t O
want O
to O
have O
anything O
to O
do O
with O
the O
Kultusgemeinde O
. O

Please O
do O
n’t O
show O
the O
lady B-TER
from O
the O
Comité O
this O
letter B-TER
. O

Otherwise O
she O
'll O
write O
to O
the O
Kultusgemeinde O
and O
then O
we O
wo O
n’t O
even O
get O
any O
food B-TER
. O

Perhaps O
the O
Comité O
could O
help O
Tante O
Martha B-PER
by O
sending O
her O
something O
so O
that O
she O
can O
improve O
the O
quality O
of O
her O
food B-TER
. O

Now O
I O
'll O
answer O
your O
questions O
. O

My O
sister B-TER
is O
seven O
years O
old O
and O
has O
been O
in O
London B-LOC
since O
December O
. O

My O
brother O
Julius B-PER
was O
18 O
years O
old O
and O
died B-TER
in O
Buchenwald B-LOC
. O

I O
was O
twelve O
on O
2 O
June O
and O
am O
still O
alive O
at O
the O
moment O
. O

My O
good O
Papi O
was O
53 O
years O
old O
and O
died B-TER
in O
October O
. O

Tante O
Martha B-PER
wo O
n’t O
tell O
me O
what O
he O
died B-TER
of O
. O

He O
was O
a O
police B-TER
inspector O
until O
March O
1938 O
. O

My O
dear O
Muttilein O
[ O
little O
Mummy O
] O
had O
been O
ill O
for O
seven O
years O
and O
the O
death B-TER
of O
my O
Papi O
was O
the O
end O
of O
her O
. O

She O
was O
53 O
years O
old O
as O
well O
. O

My O
Papi O
was O
the O
cousin O
of O
Tante O
Martha B-PER
. O

Papi O
's O
mother O
and O
Tante O
's O
Martha B-PER
father O
were O
brother O
and O
sister O
. O

Now O
I O
've O
told O
you O
everything O
. O

When O
I O
have O
got O
away O
from O
here O
I O
will O
send O
you O
a O
nice O
card B-TER
from O
America B-LOC
, O
and O
when O
I O
'm O
grown O
up O
I O
'll O
send O
you O
lots O
and O
lots O
of O
dollars O
. O

All O
best O
wishes O
and O
a O
million O
kisses O
. O

Your O
Leni B-PER
and O
Hans B-PER
. O

The O
food B-TER
from O
the O
canteen O
is O
very O
bad O
. O

Not O
even O
pigs O
would O
eat B-TER
it O
. O

That O
’s O
how O
much O
the O
Kultusgemeinde O
cares O
for O
its O
people O
. O

© O
Wiener O
Library O
for O
the O
Study O
of O
the O
Holocaust O
& O
Genocide O
, O
London O
