The O
person O
in O
question O
has O
given O
us O
the O
following O
information O
: O
Around O
the O
middle O
of O
June O
, O
1944 O
, O
two O
Slovakian B-TER
boys O
escaped B-TER
from O
Auschwitz B-LOC
. O

In O
Budapest B-LOC
they O
submitted O
two O
protocols O
, O
one O
24 O
- O
page O
- O
long O
the O
other O
16 O
, O
which O
were O
the O
first O
authentic O
descriptions B-ORG
of O
the O
death B-TER
camps I-TER
of O
Auschwitz B-LOC
and O
Birkenau B-LOC
. O

Having O
transformed O
these O
minutes O
into O
a O
single O
document O
we O
translated O
it O
into O
English O
, O
German O
, O
French O
and O
Italian O
. O

The O
local O
heads O
of O
the O
Somér B-TER
Hacajir I-TER
sent O
them O
to O
the O
Pope B-PER
, O
to O
the O
Swedish B-LOC
and O
English B-LOC
kings O
, O
to O
Roosevelt B-PER
, O
and O
to O
Erec B-LOC
Jiszroel I-LOC
partly O
through O
Istanbul B-LOC
, O
partly O
through O
Switzerland B-LOC
. O

The O
Hungarian O
version O
of O
the O
protocol B-ORG
was O
copied O
and O
presented O
to O
the O
Regent B-PER
, O
to O
the O
members O
of O
the O
government O
and O
to O
some O
prominent O
members O
of O
the O
Hungarian B-TER
political O
life O
. O

Meanwhile O
Rezső B-PER
Kasztner I-PER
started O
negotiations O
with O
the O
Germans B-ORG
. O

He O
offered O
to O
get O
foreign O
Jews O
pay O
either O
money O
or O
war O
material O
for O
each O
Jew O
who O
was O
not O
sent O
to O
death B-TER
camps I-TER
but O
were O
let O
leave O
for O
a O
neutral O
country O
through O
Germany B-TER
. O

( O
This O
meant O
the O
preparation O
of O
the O
first O
so O
- O
called O
alia O
, O
which O
resulted O
in O
the O
privileged O
state O
of O
prisoners B-TER
: O
24,000 O
in O
Strasshof B-LOC
and O
1,750 O
in O
Bergen B-LOC
- I-LOC
Belsen I-LOC
. O

) O
Miklós B-PER
Krausz I-PER
, O
who O
was O
the O
secretary O
of O
the O
Palestine B-ORG
Office I-ORG
, O
and O
got O
asylum O
thanks O
to O
his O
contacts O
in O
the O
Department O
for O
Foreign O
Interests O
of O
the O
Swiss B-ORG
Embassy I-ORG
of O
Szabadság B-LOC
Square I-LOC
, O
started O
negotiations O
regarding O
the O
emigration B-TER
with O
Consul O
Lutz B-PER
, O
and O
using O
his O
political O
relations O
, O
also O
with O
head O
of O
police B-TER
Batiszfalvy B-PER
. O

The O
30th O
of O
June O
, O
1944 O
, O
the O
group O
of O
1,750 O
people O
meant O
for O
Bergen B-LOC
- I-LOC
Belsen I-LOC
left O
. O

The O
following O
day O
, O
we O
started O
to O
register O
the O
next O
transports O
with O
the O
guide O
of O
Ottó B-PER
Komoly I-PER
and O
Rezső B-PER
Kasztner I-PER
in O
12 B-LOC
Síp I-LOC
Street I-LOC
. O

These O
transports O
were O
ready O
by O
the O
17th O
of O
July O
, O
but O
, O
to O
be O
more O
precise O
, O
we O
did O
not O
receive O
the O
permission O
of O
Eichmann B-ORG
’s I-ORG
people I-ORG
. O

17th O
of O
July O
, O
in O
the O
evening O
, O
Miklós B-PER
Krausz I-PER
invited O
us O
for O
a O
secret O
council O
. O

Others O
who O
participated O
were O
Ottó B-PER
Komoly I-PER
, O
Rafi O
, O
Pill O
, O
Albert B-PER
Geier I-PER
, O
Mihály B-PER
Salamon I-PER
, O
Dr. B-PER
Fábián I-PER
Herskovits I-PER
and O
me O
. O

On O
this O
meeting O
Miklós B-PER
Krausz I-PER
presented O
the O
following O
: O
The O
minutes O
we O
sent O
out O
at O
the O
end O
of O
June O
did O
reach O
their O
destination O
. O

As O
a O
result O
Roosevelt B-PER
sent O
a O
memorial O
to O
the O
Hungarian B-TER
government B-TER
, O
demanding O
they O
made O
possible O
the O
emigration B-TER
of O
those O
Jews O
who O
had O
a O
valid O
entry B-TER
permit I-TER
. O

This O
demand O
was O
answered O
by O
Prime B-PER
Minister I-PER
Sztójay I-PER
, O
who O
agreed O
to O
set O
up O
an O
office O
coordinating O
the O
process O
of O
emigration B-TER
as O
a O
part O
of O
the O
Swiss B-ORG
Embassy I-ORG
. O

On O
the O
top O
of O
that O
, O
at O
the O
end O
of O
June O
Miklós B-PER
Krausz I-PER
managed O
to O
make O
Ferenczy B-PER
believe O
what O
was O
indeed O
happening O
in O
Auschwitz B-LOC
, O
and O
achieved O
that O
there O
would O
be O
a O
meeting O
organised O
between O
Ferenczy B-PER
, O
his O
assistant O
Lullay B-PER
, O
Batiszfalvy B-PER
, O
Samu B-PER
Stern I-PER
, O
Károly B-PER
Wilhelm I-PER
and O
Ernő B-PER
Pető I-PER
in O
the O
flat O
of O
Samu B-PER
Stern I-PER
. O

At O
this O
meeting O
they O
agreed O
that O
in O
case O
the O
Regent B-PER
( O
as O
the O
supreme O
commander O
) O
instructed O
the O
gendarmes B-TER
of O
the O
countryside O
to O
come O
to O
Budapest B-LOC
, O
these O
would O
resist O
Germans B-TER
even O
if O
they O
used O
force O
to O
deport O
the O
Jews O
on O
the O
5th O
of O
July O
, O
which O
was O
the O
agreed O
date O
. O

That O
is O
what O
preceded O
the O
opening O
of O
the O
office O
in O
Vadász B-LOC
Street I-LOC
on O
the O
24th O
of O
July O
. O

Consul O
Lutz B-PER
requested O
that O
the O
office O
lay O
not O
far O
from O
the O
Swiss B-ORG
Embassy I-ORG
on O
Szabadság B-LOC
Square I-LOC
. O

We O
chose O
the O
office O
of O
the O
Weiss B-PER
company O
in O
29 O
Vadász B-LOC
Street I-LOC
. O

We O
made O
an O
appeal O
for O
this O
place O
in O
agreement O
with O
Artur B-PER
Weiss I-PER
, O
to O
the O
Housing B-ORG
Office I-ORG
of O
the O
government O
. O

Artur B-PER
Weiss I-PER
asked O
us O
to O
set O
up O
the O
office O
as O
soon O
as O
possible O
since O
the O
building O
would O
have O
been O
soon O
demanded O
also O
by O
his O
business O
rivals O
, O
and O
to O
preserve O
his O
dignity O
towards O
these O
rivals O
he O
also O
wanted O
to O
obtain O
a O
chief O
position O
there O
. O

Miklós B-PER
Krausz I-PER
as O
the O
head O
of O
the O
office B-ORG
entrusted O
him O
to O
be O
the O
administrative O
head O
. O

The O
office B-ORG
opened O
the O
24th O
of O
July O
. O

The O
first O
days O
Ferenczy B-PER
and O
Batiszfalvy B-PER
came O
to O
control O
whether O
the O
office O
functioned O
according O
to O
the O
intentions O
of O
the O
Hungarian B-TER
government B-TER
. O

The O
job O
of O
this O
office B-ORG
was O
to O
register O
everyone O
who O
applied O
for O
a O
permission O
to O
emigrate B-ORG
to O
Palestine B-LOC
. O

Already O
in O
the O
first O
days O
, O
moreover O
, O
before O
the O
office B-ORG
was O
opened O
, O
we O
agreed O
in O
the O
emigration B-ORG
of O
several O
thousands O
of O
Jews O
scheduled O
for O
the O
first O
few O
weeks O
, O
who O
were O
to O
be O
transported O
in O
groups O
of O
2,000 O
in O
personal O
vehicles O
, O
with O
collective O
passports B-TER
through O
Romania B-LOC
. O

Ferenczy B-PER
and O
Krausz B-PER
singled O
out O
the O
Palatinus O
- O
houses O
in O
Pozsonyi B-LOC
Road I-LOC
designated O
as O
a O
gathering O
place O
for O
the O
transports O
, O
from O
where O
they O
could O
collectively O
depart B-TER
. O

These O
were O
the O
seeds O
of O
what O
later O
became O
the O
protected B-TER
houses I-TER
. O

The O
office O
in O
Vadász B-LOC
Street I-LOC
was O
clearly O
a O
Zionist B-TER
institution O
or O
at O
least O
it O
started O
like O
that O
. O

We O
accepted O
the O
applications O
for O
passport B-TER
mostly O
from O
Zionists B-TER
. O

In O
the O
beginning O
of O
August O
, O
the O
fist O
collective O
passport B-TER
was O
ready O
. O

It O
had O
two O
volumes O
. O

We O
immediately O
received O
the O
Hungarian B-LOC
exit B-TER
permit I-TER
and O
the O
Romanian B-LOC
transit B-TER
permit I-TER
. O

They O
did O
not O
want O
to O
give O
us O
the O
German B-TER
exit B-TER
permit I-TER
though O
, O
because O
it O
was O
their O
goal O
to O
concentrate B-TER
the O
rest O
of O
the O
Jews O
in O
the O
Western O
part O
of O
Hungary B-LOC
after O
the O
first O
transit O
left O
. O

Nevertheless O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
gave O
the O
permit O
in O
October O
, O
which O
was O
valid O
until O
the O
1st O
of O
January O
, O
1945 O
. O

This O
was O
what O
legally O
happened O
in O
Vadász B-LOC
Street I-LOC
, O
and O
it O
was O
already O
heavily O
criticised O
by O
the O
journals B-TER
, O
for O
example O
by O
Déli O
Magyar O
Szó O
Southern O
Hungarian O
Word O
, O
where O
attention O
was O
directed O
to O
our O
activity O
twice O
in O
August O
. O

It O
was O
however O
the O
most O
important O
to O
find O
a O
neutral O
place O
for O
illegal B-TER
activity I-TER
where O
there O
was O
no O
chance O
to O
be O
caught O
. O

The O
Embassy B-ORG
was O
an O
excellent O
place O
for O
that O
, O
which O
had O
naturally O
extraterritorial O
rights O
. O

Evidently O
, O
we O
moved O
our O
illegal B-TER
activity I-TER
already O
in O
the O
first O
days O
to O
Vadász B-LOC
Street I-LOC
. O

In O
part O
, O
this O
was O
the O
place O
where O
we O
produced O
and O
distributed O
documents B-TER
proving B-TER
Christianity B-TER
. O

More O
importantly O
, O
this O
was O
the O
place O
where O
we O
organised O
illegal O
emigrations B-TER
( O
tijul O
) O
into O
Romania B-LOC
and O
Czechoslovakia B-LOC
. O

Our O
well O
organised O
smugglers B-TER
helped O
the O
way O
of O
several O
thousands O
of O
people O
from O
Szabadság B-LOC
Square I-LOC
to O
Arad B-LOC
, O
basically O
from O
house O
to O
house O
. O

I O
have O
to O
note O
that O
neither O
Artur B-PER
Weiss I-PER
nor O
Miklós B-PER
Krausz I-PER
assisted O
our O
illegal B-TER
activities I-TER
, O
what O
is O
more O
, O
it O
happened O
also O
that O
they O
banned O
Rafi O
, O
Mimis O
, O
Pill O
and O
Efra O
to O
enter O
the O
building O
of O
Vadász B-LOC
Street I-LOC
. O

( O
Of O
course O
, O
they O
ignored O
it O
. O

) O
There O
was O
another O
important O
ongoing O
project O
in O
Vadász B-LOC
Street I-LOC
. O

There O
were O
several O
Zionist B-TER
comrades O
kept O
in O
internment B-TER
camps I-TER
or O
jails B-TER
not O
so O
much O
because O
they O
were O
Jews O
but O
because O
of O
forging B-TER
documents I-TER
still O
in O
those O
times O
when O
masses O
of O
people O
crossed B-TER
the I-TER
borders I-TER
coming O
from O
Slovakia B-LOC
and O
other O
lands O
, O
and O
these O
people O
needed O
hiding B-TER
places O
. O

These O
people O
were O
freed O
using O
original O
American B-ORG
letters B-TER
of I-TER
protection I-TER
( O
which O
we O
stole O
, O
or O
rather O
I O
stole O
on O
Szabadság B-LOC
Square I-LOC
) O
. O

This O
is O
what O
preceded O
15th O
October O
. O

That O
morning O
we O
listened O
to O
Horthy B-PER
’s I-PER
proclamation O
in O
Vadász B-LOC
Street I-LOC
. O

The O
day O
after O
we O
entered O
the O
building O
knowing O
we O
would O
not O
leave O
the O
place O
till O
the O
rule O
of O
the O
Arrow B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
lasted O
. O

The O
first O
day O
there O
were O
only O
60 O
of O
us O
. O

The O
Swiss B-ORG
Embassy I-ORG
, O
which O
was O
the O
authority O
above O
us O
, O
declared O
that O
officers O
of O
the O
institute O
together O
with O
their O
families B-TER
could O
stay O
in O
the O
building O
with O
respect O
to O
the O
urgency O
of O
the O
work O
to O
be O
done O
. O

Finally O
, O
by O
the O
day O
of O
the O
liberation B-TER
the O
number O
of O
people O
living O
in O
the O
building O
raised O
to O
2,750 O
. O

Jewish B-TER
houses I-TER
came O
to O
be O
closed O
down O
and O
people O
were O
taken B-TER
away I-TER
. O

As O
a O
reaction O
young O
Zionists B-TER
dressed O
in O
the O
uniform B-TER
of O
the O
Arrow B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
started O
their O
mission O
from O
Vadász B-LOC
Street I-LOC
, O
and O
brought B-TER
back I-TER
bunches O
of O
Jews O
under O
the O
pretext O
that O
they O
were O
arrested B-TER
. O

We O
were O
500 O
already O
the O
third O
day O
. O

Day O
by O
day O
it O
was O
more O
difficult O
to O
put O
up O
with O
the O
lessening B-TER
space I-TER
, O
the B-TER
lack I-TER
of I-TER
food I-TER
and O
to O
cope O
with O
the O
problems O
of O
sanitation B-TER
. O

Luckily O
, O
International B-ORG
Red I-ORG
Cross I-ORG
was O
established O
in O
Mérleg B-LOC
Street I-LOC
in O
August O
, O
where O
the O
head O
was O
Ottó B-PER
Komoly I-PER
, O
the O
administrators O
were O
our O
Zionist B-TER
comrades O
, O
like O
Efra O
, O
the O
head O
of O
finances O
, O
who O
helped O
us O
overcome O
problems O
of O
food B-TER
supply I-TER
till O
the O
time O
also O
the O
office O
in O
Vadász B-LOC
Street I-LOC
set O
up O
its O
own O
financial O
department O
and O
kitchen B-TER
, O
and O
became O
self O
- O
sufficient O
. O

The O
first B-TER
attack I-TER
from O
the O
part O
of O
the O
Arrow B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
occurred O
on O
the O
17th O
of O
October O
. O

We O
managed O
to O
inform O
immediately O
Vice B-TER
- I-TER
Consul I-TER
Steiner B-PER
, O
who O
thwarted O
the O
action O
of O
the O
Arrow B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
bandits O
. O

The O
20th O
of O
October O
, O
men B-TER
between O
the O
age O
of O
14 O
to O
60 O
were O
taken B-TER
away I-TER
, O
and O
women B-TER
were O
ordered O
to O
be O
called O
up O
for O
the O
labour B-TER
service I-TER
by O
the O
23rd O
. O

The O
indicated O
place O
was O
the O
sports O
grounds O
of O
the O
National O
Centre O
for O
High O
School O
Sports O
Clubs O
. O

We O
phrased O
the O
text O
of O
the O
Schutzpass B-TER
that O
day O
, O
we O
dated O
them O
to O
the O
23rd O
of O
October O
, O
copied O
them O
on O
16 O
typewriters O
by O
day O
and O
night O
, O
and O
started O
to O
distribute O
them O
to O
anyone O
who O
belonged O
to O
the O
Jewish O
religion O
and O
made O
an O
appeal O
for O
them O
. O

Since O
there O
were O
no O
signatures O
on O
the O
Schutzpass B-TER
, O
we O
right O
away O
forged O
them O
. O

Unfortunately O
, O
even O
among O
people O
who O
found O
asylum O
in O
Vadász B-LOC
Street I-LOC
there O
were O
some O
who O
sold O
these O
stolen O
copies O
Schutzpass B-TER
for O
money O
. O

Since O
the O
permission O
to O
emigrate B-TER
was O
given O
according O
to O
7,800 O
certificates O
the O
government O
insisted O
that O
only O
7,800 O
people O
could O
obtain O
copies O
Schutzpass B-TER
. O

This O
amount O
of O
people O
received O
their O
Schutzpass B-TER
basically O
already O
the O
first O
day O
, O
therefore O
our O
strategy O
was O
to O
declare O
that O
the O
7,800 O
certificates O
regarded O
7,800 O
families O
, O
which O
comprised O
at O
least O
60,000 O
people O
. O

When O
the O
sad B-TER
march I-TER
of O
deportees B-TER
was O
set O
off O
on O
the O
highway O
to O
Vienna B-LOC
, O
we O
received O
neither O
cars O
nor O
officers O
from O
the O
Swiss B-ORG
Embassy I-ORG
to O
follow O
them O
and O
bring O
them O
back O
as O
the O
Swedish B-PER
had O
done O
. O

We O
bought O
a O
car O
pooling O
together O
the O
money O
, O
put O
a O
plate O
indicating O
diplomatic B-TER
affiliation O
on O
it O
and O
our O
Zionist B-TER
comrades O
went O
to O
the O
brick B-TER
factories I-TER
and O
everywhere O
until O
the O
border O
, O
Hegyeshalom B-LOC
, O
from O
where O
we O
had O
to O
bring B-TER
back I-TER
the O
people O
using O
the O
documents B-TER
we O
had O
produced O
. O

Men B-TER
were O
made O
to O
march B-TER
on O
foot O
close O
to O
Budapest B-LOC
, O
and O
we O
had O
success O
in O
several O
cases O
in O
bringing O
them O
back O
the O
same O
way O
. O

The O
beginning O
of O
November O
they O
singled O
out O
the O
protected B-TER
houses I-TER
. O

At O
first O
, O
there O
were O
so O
few O
houses O
provided O
for O
the O
people O
protected O
by O
the O
Swiss B-ORG
that O
not O
even O
7,800 O
people O
had O
enough O
place O
. O

Later O
, O
we O
managed O
to O
get O
more O
houses B-TER
for O
this O
purpose O
using O
Ferenczy B-PER
’s I-PER
influence O
. O

Altogether O
we O
put O
accommodated B-TER
around O
35 O
- O
40,000 O
people O
in O
the O
protected B-TER
houses I-TER
. O

Meanwhile O
the O
government B-TER
kept O
asking O
for O
the O
list O
of O
the O
7,800 O
, O
and O
we O
were O
working O
on O
it O
. O

Meanwhile O
the O
Housing O
Offices O
in O
14 B-LOC
SzentIstván I-LOC
Park I-LOC
and O
32 B-LOC
Pozsonyi I-LOC
Road I-LOC
were O
set O
up O
. O

The O
former O
was O
headed O
by O
professor O
Waldapfel B-PER
, O
the O
latter O
by O
Márton B-PER
Hirsch I-PER
. O

Still O
in O
the O
beginning O
of O
November O
, O
when O
circumstances O
in O
Vadász B-LOC
Street I-LOC
became O
almost O
unbearable O
, O
Dr. B-PER
Rezső I-PER
Mezei I-PER
decided O
that O
the O
place O
was O
not O
secure O
enough O
for O
him O
and O
his O
family B-TER
any O
longer O
, O
and O
wanted O
to O
open O
another O
subordinate O
office O
, O
and O
received O
the O
permission O
of O
the O
Embassy B-ORG
to O
do O
so O
. O

Mezei B-PER
had O
been O
an O
officer O
of O
a O
bank O
and O
got O
into O
Vadász B-LOC
Street I-LOC
only O
as O
a O
friend O
of O
Artur B-PER
Weiss I-PER
. O

His O
only O
merit O
was O
that O
his O
great O
loquacity O
saved O
the O
situation O
when O
men O
of O
the O
Arrow B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
attacked B-TER
us O
the O
17th O
of O
October O
. O

This O
is O
why O
the O
15th O
of O
November O
the O
office O
in O
Wekerle B-LOC
Sándor I-LOC
Street I-LOC
opened O
, O
where O
the O
so O
- O
called O
elite O
, O
that O
is O
, O
the O
capitalists O
lived O
in O
apparent O
security O
. O

It O
is O
part O
of O
Mezei B-PER
’s I-PER
story O
that O
he O
managed O
to O
save B-TER
around O
500 O
people O
living O
there O
. O

Although O
the O
office O
in O
Wekerle B-LOC
Sándor I-LOC
Street I-LOC
had O
no O
extraterritorial O
status O
he O
succeeded O
by O
using O
money O
and O
his O
suspicious O
connections O
. O

The O
23rd O
of O
November O
, O
5’o O
clock O
in O
the O
morning O
, O
gendarmes B-TER
woke O
us O
up O
in O
Vadász B-LOC
Street I-LOC
. O

Artur B-PER
Weiss I-PER
, O
who O
went O
through O
obvious O
changes O
under O
the O
heavy O
responsibilities O
he O
had O
, O
reacted O
in O
the O
most O
spirited O
way O
. O

I O
witnessed O
when O
he O
told O
the O
head O
of O
the O
gendarmes B-TER
, O
a O
lieutenant O
, O
the O
following O
: O
You O
’d O
better O
clear O
the O
house O
of O
the O
gendarmes O
in O
three O
minutes O
, O
otherwise O
unforeseeable O
consequences O
would O
follow O
this O
atrocity O
, O
since O
gendarmes O
seriously O
offended O
the O
rights O
of O
extraterritoriality O
. O

As O
a O
result O
gendarmes B-TER
indeed O
left O
the O
house O
without O
proceeding O
with O
their O
search O
for O
weapons O
. O

After O
this O
event O
the O
2,500 O
- O
2,700 O
inhabitants O
of O
the O
house O
in O
Vadász B-LOC
Street I-LOC
enjoyed O
relative O
tranquillity O
if O
one O
disregards O
the O
identity O
checks O
done O
by O
detectives O
at O
the O
gate O
of O
the O
house O
for O
days O
on O
, O
or O
those O
masses O
that O
were O
arrested O
by O
the O
Arrow B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
, O
while O
waiting O
in O
front O
of O
the O
house O
to O
apply O
for O
a O
Schutzpass B-TER
. O

Cellars O
, O
attics O
, O
and O
stores O
were O
all O
full B-TER
of I-TER
people I-TER
. O

As O
a O
result O
sanitation B-TER
got O
worse O
day O
after O
day O
, O
lice B-TER
started O
to O
spread O
, O
therefore O
we O
needed O
to O
move O
a O
part O
of O
the O
people O
into O
the O
neighbouring O
headquarter O
of O
the O
Hungarian O
Football O
Association O
. O

We O
resolved O
this O
question O
by O
breaking O
through O
the O
wall O
between O
the O
two O
buildings O
, O
blocking O
the O
gate O
of O
the O
building O
of O
the O
Football O
Association O
opening O
to O
Vadász B-LOC
Street I-LOC
, O
hence O
, O
the O
two O
buildings O
looked O
as O
if O
they O
were O
one O
, O
and O
the O
Arrow B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
did O
never O
learn O
who O
stayed O
in O
the O
building O
of O
the O
Football O
Association O
. O

Until O
the O
31st O
of O
December O
– O
although O
it O
was O
not O
possible O
to O
perform O
work O
regularly O
any O
more O
– O
we O
provided O
the O
food B-TER
supplies I-TER
of O
the O
protected B-TER
houses I-TER
from O
Vadász B-LOC
Street I-LOC
. O

We O
set O
up O
a O
hospital B-TER
in O
Tátra B-LOC
Street I-LOC
, O
and O
we O
provided O
it O
medicine B-TER
and O
lint O
. O

We O
were O
waiting O
and O
waiting O
for O
the O
liberation B-TER
. O

December O
the O
31st O
, O
around O
2:30 O
pm O
, O
we O
heard O
gunfire O
from O
the O
direction O
of O
the O
courtyard O
. O

First O
we O
thought O
this O
came O
from O
airplanes B-TER
that O
had O
machineguns O
on O
board O
but O
we O
realise O
this O
was O
untrue O
when O
we O
heard O
swears O
against O
Jews O
and O
obscene O
words O
coming O
from O
the O
street O
. O

As O
it O
turned O
out O
, O
9 O
young O
Arrow B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
men O
broke B-TER
in O
through O
the O
gates O
leading O
to O
the O
courtyard O
. O

Led O
by O
brother O
Balog O
they O
first O
fired O
a O
serious O
of O
shots B-TER
into O
the O
cellar O
which O
was O
used O
as O
an O
air B-TER
- I-TER
raid I-TER
shelter O
, O
where O
there O
were O
around O
1,000 O
of O
us O
in O
dark O
. O

They O
also O
threw B-TER
a I-TER
grenade I-TER
into O
the O
same O
cellar O
, O
and O
another O
one O
into O
the O
courtyard O
where O
the O
latrines O
were O
, O
which O
were O
naturally O
always O
surrounded O
by O
a O
great O
number O
of O
people O
. O

They O
broke B-TER
into I-TER
the O
house O
and O
forced O
some O
1,500 O
people O
to O
get O
out O
to O
the O
street O
. O

They O
did O
not O
find O
however O
either O
the O
correctly O
disguised O
entry O
of O
the O
so O
- O
called O
Somér B-TER
cellar O
or O
the O
entry O
of O
the O
Mizrahi B-TER
attic O
or O
the O
entry O
of O
the O
Football O
Association O
. O

During O
this O
time O
Arthur B-PER
Weisz I-PER
, O
having O
bronchitis B-TER
lay O
in O
bed O
in O
the O
flat O
of O
his O
parents O
, O
where O
he O
was O
continuously O
on O
the O
phone O
, O
calling O
Szabadság B-LOC
Square I-LOC
, O
city O
military B-TER
headquarters O
, O
the O
headquarters O
of O
the O
police B-TER
, O
and O
the O
Ministry B-TER
of I-TER
Foreign I-TER
Affairs I-TER
. O

We O
called O
the O
same O
organisations O
from O
the O
so O
- O
called O
council O
hall O
, O
where O
the O
Arrow B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
men O
entered O
only O
at O
the O
end O
. O

By O
this O
time O
, O
I O
already O
had O
a O
document O
certifying O
our O
extraterritorial O
rights O
signed O
by O
a O
German B-TER
commanding B-ORG
general I-ORG
. O

In O
the O
garage O
of O
the O
Glass B-LOC
House I-LOC
there O
was O
a O
guard O
made O
up O
of O
officer O
candidates O
with O
high O
school O
degree O
who O
took O
part O
in O
the O
resistance B-TER
movement O
because O
this O
was O
the O
place O
where O
the O
cars O
of O
the O
Romanian O
Department O
of O
the O
Swiss B-ORG
Embassy I-ORG
were O
parked O
. O

However O
, O
I O
have O
to O
say O
that O
neither O
this O
guard O
nor O
the O
police B-TER
patrolling O
in O
front O
of O
the O
building O
hindered O
the O
break O
- O
in O
of O
the O
Arrow B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
to O
the O
slightest O
extent O
. O

We O
were O
staying O
there O
in O
the O
street O
and O
knew O
our O
way O
would O
lead O
directly O
into B-TER
the I-TER
Danube I-TER
. O

Now O
, O
Arthur B-PER
Weisz I-PER
showed O
the O
most O
remarkable O
example O
of O
courageous O
behaviour O
. O

Although O
his O
wife B-TER
, O
his O
son B-TER
, O
and O
his O
two O
old O
parents B-TER
were O
also O
in O
the O
street O
, O
he O
did O
not O
get O
frightened O
even O
for O
a O
second O
, O
and O
while O
he O
had O
a O
gun O
pushed O
against O
his O
chest O
he O
told O
them O
to O
calm O
down O
and O
forcefully O
that O
the O
building O
belonged O
to O
the O
Swiss B-ORG
Embassy I-ORG
, O
and O
these O
people O
were O
officers O
and O
their O
relatives O
protected O
by O
the O
Swiss B-ORG
state I-ORG
, O
and O
if O
they O
treated O
us O
like O
that O
Hungarian B-TER
citizens O
would O
be O
treated O
the O
same O
way O
in O
Switzerland B-ORG
. O

Here O
I O
have O
to O
stop O
for O
a O
minute O
to O
explain O
that O
regarding O
the O
protected B-TER
houses I-TER
we O
made O
contacts O
with O
two O
members O
of O
the O
Arrow B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
called O
Medgyesi B-PER
and O
Bodor B-PER
, O
furthermore O
with O
police B-TER
chief O
Tarpataky B-PER
, O
who O
made O
some O
concessions O
to O
the O
protected B-TER
houses I-TER
in O
return O
for O
bribery B-TER
. O

Bodor B-PER
was O
in O
particular O
benign O
with O
us O
. O

When O
he O
was O
informed O
about O
the O
atrocity O
of O
the O
Arrow B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
, O
he O
came O
to O
our O
place O
immediately O
and O
started O
walking O
up O
and O
down O
in O
front O
of O
our O
lines O
with O
an O
automatic O
machinegun O
, O
ensuring O
us O
that O
nothing O
bad O
would O
happen O
. O

In O
fact O
, O
backing O
arrived O
and O
we O
could O
return O
to O
the O
house O
. O

The O
Arrow B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
shooting O
led O
to O
the O
death B-TER
of O
four O
( O
Mrs B-PER
Vilmos I-PER
Scheiber I-PER
, O
Jónás B-PER
Fenákel I-PER
, O
Ármin B-PER
Schwartz I-PER
) O
and O
seriously O
injured O
many O
. O

The O
next O
after O
, O
around O
1:30 O
pm O
the O
well O
known O
brother O
Balog O
appeared O
, O
who O
showed O
us O
at O
the O
gate O
an O
order O
, O
which O
obliged O
29 B-LOC
Vadász I-LOC
Street I-LOC
to O
hand O
over O
food B-TER
supply I-TER
for O
50 O
people O
for O
three O
days O
. O

Arthur B-PER
Weisz I-PER
called O
Miklós B-PER
Krausz I-PER
, O
who O
told O
him O
to O
give O
them O
the O
desired O
goods O
. O

We O
gave O
them O
50 B-TER
loaves I-TER
, I-TER
35 I-TER
cans I-TER
, I-TER
and I-TER
7 I-TER
bottles I-TER
of I-TER
wine I-TER
. O

I O
was O
standing O
at O
the O
gate O
, O
Balog O
remained O
outside O
, O
and O
next O
to O
me O
there O
was O
Arthur B-PER
Weisz I-PER
. O

All O
of O
a O
sudden O
Lieutenant B-TER
László B-PER
Fábry I-PER
turned O
up O
, O
who O
was O
the O
head O
of O
the O
so O
- O
called O
VÁP O
- O
team O
in O
charge O
of O
protecting O
Wekerle B-LOC
Sándor I-LOC
Street I-LOC
and O
Vadász B-LOC
Street I-LOC
and O
started O
to O
talk O
with O
Arthur B-PER
Weisz I-PER
. O

I O
do O
not O
know O
what O
it O
was O
about O
as O
I O
was O
engaged O
in O
counting O
the O
loaves B-TER
and I-TER
the I-TER
cans I-TER
. O

What O
attracted O
my O
attention O
was O
Fábry B-PER
telling O
Artur B-PER
Weiss I-PER
: O
Take O
it O
easy O
and O
come O
with O
me O
Mr. O
Weiss O
, O
to O
what O
I O
reacted O
in O
Hebrew O
telling O
Artur B-PER
Weiss I-PER
not O
to O
go O
. O

He O
made O
a O
gesture O
in O
an O
offhand O
manner O
. O

Fábry B-PER
then O
put O
Artur B-PER
Weiss I-PER
in O
his O
car O
, O
while O
Balog O
left O
in O
the O
opposite O
direction O
. O

He O
came O
back O
in O
10 O
minutes O
claiming O
that O
Artur B-PER
Weiss I-PER
would O
be O
back O
by O
5 O
pm O
giving O
his O
word O
of O
honour O
as O
an O
officer B-TER
of O
the O
army B-TER
. O

As O
we O
found O
out O
later O
, O
he O
gave O
Weiss B-PER
to O
Balog O
who O
took O
him O
to O
14 B-LOC
Városház I-LOC
Street I-LOC
and O
from O
there O
presumably B-TER
into I-TER
the I-TER
Danube B-LOC
. O

When O
Fábry B-PER
went O
to O
fetch O
him O
in O
Városház B-LOC
Street I-LOC
, O
as O
he O
claimed O
to O
have O
done O
, O
he O
was O
told O
that O
Artur B-PER
Weiss I-PER
had O
been O
already O
let O
go O
. O

This O
increased O
panic O
in O
Vadász B-LOC
Street I-LOC
day O
by O
day O
, O
which O
culminated O
after O
two O
days O
only O
to O
fade O
away O
completely O
when O
the O
new O
anxieties O
of O
the O
siege B-TER
took O
its O
place O
. O

Further O
on O
, O
the O
Arrow B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
came O
to O
us O
maybe O
two O
other O
times O
to O
fetch B-TER
food B-TER
, O
but O
started O
shouting O
already O
at O
the O
gate O
that O
no O
Jews O
would O
be O
hurt O
, O
they O
only O
wanted O
to O
get O
food B-TER
. O

Naturally O
, O
we O
showed O
no O
reluctance O
as O
we O
did O
not O
want O
to O
get O
hurt O
. O

The O
6th O
of O
January O
, O
in O
the O
afternoon O
, O
Jenő B-PER
Fränkl I-PER
sent O
a O
courier O
out O
for O
some O
reason O
, O
whose O
identity O
was O
checked O
by O
the O
detective O
of O
the O
Arrow B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
Pálóczy B-PER
, O
once O
an O
actor O
, O
in O
front O
of O
the O
house O
. O

During O
the O
identity O
check O
the O
boy O
was O
shouting O
that O
he O
just O
came O
out O
of O
the O
building O
of O
Vadász B-LOC
Street I-LOC
, O
that O
he O
was O
a O
courier O
. O

In O
this O
minute O
the O
car O
of O
the O
Embassy B-ORG
stopped O
and O
officers O
Andor B-PER
Gedeon I-PER
and O
Tibor B-PER
Szemere I-PER
jumped O
out O
. O

Comrade B-TER
Szimcha B-PER
Hunwald I-PER
, O
whose O
pseudonym O
as O
an O
officer O
of O
the O
Embassy B-ORG
was O
János B-PER
Kühne I-PER
stayed O
in O
the O
car O
. O

Gedeon B-PER
entered O
the O
gate O
, O
the O
same O
second O
Szemere B-PER
noticed O
that O
the O
courier O
was O
running O
towards O
the O
Embassy B-ORG
. O

There O
was O
a O
shot O
and O
the O
cry O
I O
am O
shot O
, O
and O
the O
boy O
fell O
in O
the O
arms O
of O
Szemere B-PER
. O

The O
detective O
of O
the O
Arrow B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
was O
already O
at O
the O
car O
– O
the O
driver O
could O
just O
get O
out O
in O
time O
– O
and O
took O
Kühne B-PER
and O
Szemere B-PER
with O
himself O
to O
the O
police B-TER
headquarters O
, O
and O
handed O
them O
over O
to O
the O
Germans B-TER
, O
who O
put O
them O
into O
the O
cellar O
of O
the O
royal O
palace O
. O

Thanks O
to O
his O
language O
knowledge O
Tibor B-PER
Szemere I-PER
was O
occupied O
as O
a O
translator O
and O
got O
freed O
when O
the O
castle O
was O
liberated B-TER
after O
40 O
days O
of O
jail B-TER
, O
while O
Szimcha B-PER
Hunwald I-PER
was O
shot B-TER
in O
the O
basement O
of O
the O
Ministry O
of O
Interior O
. O

Naturally O
, O
this O
case O
generated O
panic O
again O
in O
Vadász B-LOC
Street I-LOC
, O
but O
there O
were O
no O
more O
Arrow B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
atrocities B-TER
in O
the O
house O
or O
in O
the O
street O
in O
the O
last O
twelve O
days O
until O
the O
liberation B-TER
. O

There O
was O
one O
exception O
when O
Iván B-PER
Dénes I-PER
courier O
was O
shot B-TER
during O
the O
service O
he O
did O
for O
the O
protected B-TER
houses I-TER
. O

