Róża B-PER
Reibscheid I-PER
Testimony O
( O
doc O
. O

301/1713 O
) O
Original O
, O
manuscript O
, O
2 O
pages O
, O
210 O
x O
295 O
mm O
, O
Polish O
language O
Róża B-PER
Reibscheid I-PER
[ O
record O
taken O
by O
] O
[ B-PER
Róża I-PER
] I-PER
Bauminger I-PER
Cracow B-LOC
25 B-LOC
Starowiślna I-LOC
St. I-LOC
Seamstress O
Aryan B-TER
papers I-TER
When O
Jews O
from O
neighboring O
small O
towns O
were O
being O
concentrated O
in O
Wawrzeńczyce B-LOC
, O
Nowe B-LOC
Brzesko I-LOC
Correctly O
: O
the O
Miechów O
district O
district O
, O
Poles B-TER
warned O
us O
there O
something O
was O
in O
the O
air O
, O
especially O
after O
word O
of O
the O
incidents O
in O
Tarnów B-LOC
reached O
Wawrzeńczyce B-LOC
. O

Wojciech B-PER
Bartosik I-PER
, O
a O
parish O
priest B-TER
who O
was O
very O
kind O
to O
us O
, O
entrusted O
us O
to O
a O
squire O
from O
a O
neighboring O
estate O
, O
[ O
named O
] O
Buchowski B-PER
, O
who O
took O
my O
husband B-TER
on O
as O
a O
mechanic O
for O
all O
farm O
machinery O
and O
for O
driving O
a O
tractor O
, O
and O
his O
wife B-TER
recommended O
me O
as O
a O
seamstress O
in O
estates O
nearby O
. O

No O
one O
apart O
from O
them O
knew O
we O
were O
Jewish O
. O

My O
husband B-TER
later O
became O
head O
of O
a O
co O
- O
op O
warehouse O
, O
which O
gave O
us O
a O
very O
convenient O
financial O
standing O
, O
but O
farmers O
from O
Wawrzeńczyce B-LOC
who O
knew O
us O
would O
come O
[ O
to O
the O
warehouse O
] O
. O

Some O
Pole B-TER
turned B-TER
us I-TER
in I-TER
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
were O
looking O
for O
us O
all O
around O
the O
neighborhood O
, O
they O
called O
by O
the O
community O
leader O
, O
the O
Buchowscy B-PER
, O
they O
found O
out O
nothing O
; O
eventually O
, O
they O
came O
looking O
for O
us O
to O
Opatkowice B-LOC
. O

The O
community O
leader O
warned O
me O
, O
and O
at O
the O
same O
time O
sent O
his O
daughter B-TER
to O
the O
warehouse O
where O
my O
husband B-TER
was O
working O
to O
warn O
him O
. O

While O
the O
girl B-TER
was O
in O
the O
warehouse O
, O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
were O
already O
hovering O
about O
the O
yard O
. O

My O
husband B-TER
mounted O
his O
bike O
and O
escaped B-TER
, O
unnoticed O
by O
the O
Germans B-TER
. O

Me O
and O
my O
son B-TER
went O
to O
Buchowskis B-PER
place O
, O
they O
let O
me O
out O
because O
the O
high O
road O
and O
the O
mid O
- O
field O
roads O
were O
all O
covered O
, O
and O
the O
train B-TER
at O
the O
station O
was O
delayed O
3 O
hours O
while O
all O
passengers O
were O
being O
searched O
. O

I O
took O
my O
son B-TER
to O
the O
barber O
’s O
to O
shave O
his O
hair O
so O
that O
he O
would O
n’t O
be O
recognizable O
and O
I O
overheard O
the O
clients O
there O
saying O
a O
penal O
expedition O
had O
arrived O
and O
had O
searched O
through O
all O
the O
bushes O
by O
the O
Vistula B-LOC
[ O
river O
] O
. O

Meanwhile O
, O
my O
husband B-TER
had O
called O
by O
a O
priest B-TER
he O
knew O
in O
Michałowice B-LOC
, O
who O
put O
him O
up O
overnight O
. O

I O
went O
to O
Proszowice B-LOC
to O
see O
priest B-TER
Radosz B-PER
and O
ask O
him O
for O
advice O
. O

He O
reproached O
me O
for O
not O
having O
told O
him O
before O
I O
was O
a O
Jew O
, O
he O
would O
have O
arranged O
a O
job O
for O
my O
husband B-TER
in O
Radom B-LOC
, O
and O
he O
would O
send O
for O
horses O
for O
me O
now O
that O
would O
take O
me O
back O
to O
Michałowice B-LOC
. O

The O
day O
after O
a O
two O
- O
horse O
chaise O
arrived O
to O
collect O
me O
( O
I O
later O
learned O
that O
the O
priest B-TER
paid O
300 O
zlotys O
to O
rent O
those O
horses O
) O
and O
I O
traveled O
to O
Michałowice B-LOC
like O
a O
lady O
. O

There O
I O
met O
my O
husband B-TER
at O
the O
priest B-TER
’s O
place O
. O

I O
agreed O
with O
my O
husband B-TER
we O
’d O
meet O
in O
Cracow B-LOC
. O

It O
was O
utter O
hell O
in O
Cracow B-LOC
. O

Some O
Poles B-TER
we O
knew O
were O
afraid O
to O
take O
us O
on O
, O
we O
spent O
every O
night O
in O
a O
different O
place O
. O

Priest B-TER
Machaj B-PER
was O
very O
kind O
- O
hearted O
to O
us O
, O
he O
arranged O
for O
me O
to O
stay O
with O
the O
Norbertines O
for O
a O
few O
days O
in O
Salwator O
; O
he O
helped O
us O
out O
financially O
and O
recommended O
my O
husband B-TER
for O
the O
position O
of O
a O
mechanic O
in O
the O
Olszanica B-LOC
estate O
, O
7 O
km O
outside O
Cracow B-LOC
. O

When O
I O
left O
the O
nunnery O
I O
had O
nowhere O
to O
live O
and O
we O
decided O
to O
go O
to O
Warsaw B-LOC
, O
even O
though O
people O
scared O
us O
saying O
there O
were O
searches O
and O
lapankas B-TER
on O
the O
trains O
. O

We O
went O
without O
luggage O
, O
my O
husband B-TER
was O
only O
wearing O
a O
working O
outfit O
. O

We O
knew O
no O
one O
in O
Warsaw B-LOC
. O

What O
were O
we O
to O
do O
? O
I O
recalled O
the O
name O
of O
our O
Wawrzenice B-LOC
Correctly O
: O
Wawrzeńczyce O
host O
’s O
daughter O
’s O
mother O
- O
in O
- O
law O
. O

I O
remembered O
she O
lived O
on O
Okopowa B-LOC
Street I-LOC
but O
I O
did O
n’t O
know O
the O
number O
. O

I O
went O
from O
house O
to O
house O
and O
finally O
found O
a O
door O
plate O
. O

I O
walked O
in O
and O
said O
I O
had O
some O
business O
to O
do O
in O
Warsaw B-LOC
, O
that O
my O
host O
from O
Wawrzenice B-LOC
sent O
his O
commends O
. O

She O
took O
me O
in O
a O
very O
friendly O
way O
. O

My O
husband B-TER
met O
his O
friend O
, O
engineer O
Marian B-PER
Pawełek I-PER
, O
director O
of O
a O
railway O
production O
plant O
in O
Pruszków B-LOC
. O

He O
helped O
us O
financially O
. O

I O
turned O
to O
RGO B-ORG
for O
clothes B-TER
for O
my O
husband B-TER
. O

I O
told O
them O
a O
made O
- O
up O
story O
of O
how O
I O
’d O
come O
from O
Proszowice B-LOC
, O
where O
several O
families B-TER
had O
been O
shot B-TER
dead I-TER
for O
allegedly O
helping O
the O
partisans B-TER
, O
and O
since O
we O
had O
been O
friends O
with O
them O
we O
feared O
we O
would O
be O
finished O
off O
too O
and O
had O
come O
to O
Warsaw B-LOC
with O
just O
the O
clothes B-TER
on O
our O
backs O
. O

They O
referred O
us O
to O
Ms B-PER
Goetel I-PER
. O

I O
dressed O
my O
son B-TER
up O
as O
a O
girl O
, O
put O
a O
blonde O
wig O
with O
a O
fringe O
on O
his O
head O
and O
moved O
in O
with O
Goetel B-PER
. O

The O
place O
was O
first O
- O
rate O
, O
and O
so O
was O
the O
board O
. O

Ms B-PER
Goetel I-PER
’s I-PER
son O
- O
in O
- O
law O
, O
engineer O
Kulczycki B-PER
offered O
my O
husband B-TER
a O
job O
at O
his O
company O
, O
and O
Ms B-PER
Goetel I-PER
recommended O
me O
as O
a O
seamstress O
and O
gave O
me O
her O
sewing O
machine O
. O

She O
found O
out O
the O
truth O
about O
us O
from O
priest B-TER
Machaj B-PER
but O
it O
did O
n’t O
change O
her O
attitude O
to O
us O
in O
any O
way O
; O
actually O
, O
she O
was O
all O
the O
more O
kind O
. O

Two O
months O
later O
I O
got O
a O
flat O
from O
RGO B-ORG
in O
a O
building O
with O
apartments O
for O
the O
deported O
. O

I O
lived O
there O
until O
the O
uprising B-TER
. O

That O
’s O
when O
me O
and O
my O
husband B-TER
parted O
and O
I O
never O
saw O
him O
again O
. O

[ O
signature O
] O
Róża B-PER
Reibscheid I-PER
