Archive O
of O
the O
Jewish O
Historical O
Institute O
Testimony O
of O
Braun B-PER
Lida I-PER
Daughter B-TER
of O
Dawid B-PER
and O
Cyrla B-PER
, O
née O
Fiszer B-PER
, O
born O
in O
1933 O
in O
Glubokoye B-LOC
, O
voivodeship B-LOC
of I-LOC
Vilnius I-LOC
. O

Education B-TER
: O
three O
years O
of O
primary B-TER
school I-TER
. O

Until O
1942 O
, O
she O
lived O
with O
her O
parents B-TER
, O
the O
father B-TER
was O
a O
tailor O
. O

During O
the O
occupation B-TER
she O
lost O
her O
parents B-TER
, O
two O
brothers B-TER
and O
a O
sister B-TER
. O

When O
the O
Germans B-TER
came O
to O
our O
town O
in O
1941 O
, O
we O
lived O
at O
Bialystok B-LOC
street I-LOC
number I-LOC
48 I-LOC
. O

On O
the O
third O
day O
the O
Belarusians B-TER
incited O
the O
Germans B-TER
and O
they O
took O
away O
all O
the O
clothing B-TER
and O
cooking B-TER
utensils O
from O
our O
home O
. O

A O
few O
thousand O
Jews O
lived O
in O
our O
town O
. O

When O
the O
Germans B-TER
came O
, O
more O
than O
a O
thousand O
escaped B-TER
with O
the O
Russian B-ORG
army I-ORG
. O

After O
a O
few O
days O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
arrested B-TER
Dr. O
Geler B-PER
, O
Bodov B-PER
, O
Kozliner B-PER
and O
some O
others O
, O
about O
16 O
persons O
, O
brought O
them O
to O
a O
hill O
behind O
town O
called O
Piaskovatke O
and O
shot B-TER
them O
. O

Belarusians B-TER
buried B-TER
them O
. O

Jews O
had O
to O
bring O
all O
the O
goods O
from O
their O
shops O
to O
the O
German B-TER
authorities O
and O
traded O
in O
the O
marketplace O
. O

But O
the O
Belarussians B-TER
, O
not O
willing O
to O
have O
Jews O
in O
the O
marketplace O
, O
incited O
the O
Germans B-TER
and O
Jews O
were B-TER
forbidden I-TER
to I-TER
trade I-TER
in I-TER
the I-TER
marketplace I-TER
. O

At O
the O
same O
time O
the O
German B-TER
police B-TER
ordered B-TER
that I-TER
Jews I-TER
had I-TER
to I-TER
give I-TER
away I-TER
gold I-TER
and I-TER
furs I-TER
. O

After O
a O
certain O
time O
, O
Jews O
were O
moved O
into O
the O
following O
streets O
: O
Vilner B-LOC
, O
a O
half O
of O
Drujer B-LOC
, O
Kishleker B-LOC
, O
Dobrove B-LOC
, O
and O
told O
that O
Jews O
only O
had O
right O
to O
move O
in O
the O
territory O
of O
these O
streets O
. O

They O
carried O
white O
bands B-TER
on O
their O
arms O
, O
but O
the O
life O
was O
not O
so O
bad O
, O
the O
trade O
did O
not O
stop O
. O

A O
Judenrat B-TER
was O
created O
. O

Lederman B-PER
, O
a O
former O
fabric O
dealer O
, O
was O
appointed O
as O
the O
chairman B-TER
. O

The O
militia O
consisted O
of O
former O
traders O
: O
Ike B-PER
Libe I-PER
- I-PER
Toybes I-PER
, O
Yude B-PER
Blant I-PER
, O
Khaym B-PER
- I-PER
Ber I-PER
Gordon I-PER
, O
Ayzik B-PER
Vaynshteyn I-PER
and O
others O
. O

All O
Jews O
had O
to O
go O
to O
work B-TER
for O
the O
Germans B-TER
. O

The O
chairman B-TER
Lederman B-PER
would O
speak O
to O
people O
and O
warn O
them O
to O
be O
obedient O
, O
not O
to O
go O
to O
forbidden B-TER
areas I-TER
and O
not O
to O
try O
to O
avoid O
work B-TER
. O

When O
the O
Germans B-TER
demanded O
money O
and O
gold O
and O
Jews O
were O
not O
in O
hurry O
to O
bring O
it O
to O
the O
Judenrat B-TER
, O
the O
chairman B-TER
with O
the O
militia O
went O
to O
look O
for O
it O
in O
people O
’s O
homes O
. O

The O
police B-TER
would O
force O
the O
people O
to O
go O
to O
work B-TER
. O

If O
one O
of O
them O
was O
angry O
at O
someone O
, O
he O
would O
give O
that O
person O
in O
SS B-ORG
hands O
and O
the O
person O
would O
not O
come O
back O
. O

Once O
the O
policemen B-TER
came O
to O
the O
chairman B-TER
and O
explained O
that O
there O
were O
too O
many O
Jews O
, O
some O
of O
them O
had O
to O
be O
killed B-TER
. O

The O
chairman B-TER
pleaded O
that O
there O
were O
young O
people O
, O
good O
workers O
, O
who O
were O
useful O
to O
the O
authorities O
and O
they O
would O
continue O
to O
be O
very O
useful O
. O

And O
they O
answered O
that O
if O
there O
were O
strong O
ones O
and O
weak O
ones O
, O
two O
ghettos B-TER
would O
be O
established O
, O
one O
for O
the O
young O
who O
would O
work B-TER
and O
one O
for O
the O
old O
and O
weak O
who O
would O
be O
shot B-TER
in O
stages O
. O

The O
second O
ghetto B-TER
was O
in O
Kisholeyk B-LOC
street I-LOC
. O

The O
Jewish O
police B-TER
menaced O
every O
Jew O
with O
moving O
them O
to O
the O
second O
ghetto B-TER
. O

When O
the O
Germans B-TER
demanded B-TER
gold I-TER
, I-TER
a I-TER
contribution I-TER
, O
and O
a O
Jew O
could O
not O
pay O
this O
tax B-TER
, O
they O
would O
send O
him O
to O
the O
second O
ghetto B-TER
. O

Around O
a O
thousand O
people O
lived O
in O
the O
second O
ghetto B-TER
, O
the O
old O
and O
the O
sick B-TER
, O
as O
well O
as O
between O
twenty O
and O
thirty O
families B-TER
that O
did O
not O
have O
any O
gold B-TER
to I-TER
give I-TER
away I-TER
. O

Two O
days O
later O
the O
SS B-ORG
came O
to O
the O
Judenrat B-TER
and O
demanded O
700 O
persons O
to O
shoot B-TER
. O

As O
the O
second O
ghetto B-TER
had O
been O
established O
, O
the O
chairman B-TER
told O
them O
to O
go O
to O
Kisholeyk B-LOC
. O

On O
the O
same O
day O
, O
the O
police B-TER
surrounded O
Kisholeykes B-LOC
and O
took O
people O
out O
of O
their O
homes O
. O

A O
part O
of O
them O
hid B-TER
themselves O
and O
stayed O
inside O
, O
because O
the O
police B-TER
did O
not O
search O
too O
diligently O
. O

On O
the O
following O
day O
at O
dawn O
I O
saw O
the O
people O
from O
Kisholeyki B-LOC
marching O
one O
next O
to O
the O
other O
, O
with O
a O
hand O
on O
the O
other O
’s O
shoulder O
. O

They O
were O
led O
to O
the O
forest O
called O
Borok O
and O
shot B-TER
there O
. O

Two O
months O
later O
, O
the O
police B-TER
ordered O
all O
the O
Jews O
to O
assembly O
in O
one O
square O
( O
the O
horse O
market O
) O
and O
started O
to O
verify O
the O
work B-TER
cards O
. O

On O
some O
of O
them O
, O
they O
wrote O
master O
[ O
? O
] O
and O
from O
that O
we O
immediately O
understood O
that O
those O
who O
had O
such O
cards O
would O
live O
. O

The O
remaining O
ones O
received O
cards O
with O
coded O
names O
: O
Orsha B-LOC
, O
Borisov B-LOC
, O
Smolensk B-LOC
. O

Those O
with O
the O
master O
[ O
? O
] O
card O
immediately O
returned O
home O
. O

The O
remaining O
ones O
figured O
out O
that O
Borisov B-LOC
meant O
Borok B-LOC
. O

This O
is O
the O
forest O
where O
the O
killings B-TER
take O
place O
. O

Indeed O
, O
after O
a O
few O
hours O
these O
people O
were O
taken O
to O
the O
Borok B-LOC
forest O
and O
shot B-TER
by O
the O
Polish B-TER
police B-TER
. O

From O
then O
on O
, O
every O
evening O
, O
during O
the O
return O
from O
work B-TER
, O
Germans B-TER
would O
grab O
one O
Jew O
and O
shoot B-TER
him O
. O

After O
half O
a O
year O
of O
the O
ghetto B-TER
’s O
existence O
, O
when O
the O
partisans B-TER
attacked O
the O
neighbouring O
towns O
Dokshitsy B-LOC
and O
Krulevshtshina B-LOC
, O
with O
which O
lots O
of O
Germans B-TER
Sentence O
unclear O
in O
the O
original O
, O
some O
words O
must O
be O
missing O
. O

, O
the O
Germans B-TER
in O
Glubokoye B-LOC
became O
fearful O
the O
same O
would O
not O
happen O
in O
Glubokoye B-LOC
, O
and O
their O
order O
the O
vice B-TER
- I-TER
chairman I-TER
of O
the O
Judenrat B-TER
, O
Yudl B-PER
Blond I-PER
, O
to O
assemble O
all O
the O
Jews O
in O
order O
to O
be O
brought O
to O
Lublin B-LOC
. O

In O
the O
ghetto B-TER
, O
it O
suddenly O
became O
very O
silent O
, O
no O
one O
showed O
up O
in O
the O
street O
. O

After O
a O
few O
hours O
, O
as O
if O
they O
had O
concerted O
, O
a O
few O
women B-TER
with O
small O
bundles O
appeared O
in O
the O
street O
; O
as O
the O
men B-TER
were O
still O
nowhere O
to O
be O
seen O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
opened O
fire O
in O
the O
direction O
of O
ghetto B-TER
. O

No O
one O
answered O
them O
any O
shots O
, O
so O
they O
entered O
the O
ghetto B-TER
. O

Just O
as O
they O
appeared O
in O
the O
ghetto B-TER
streets O
, O
heavy O
fire O
met O
them O
. O

Grenades O
were O
thrown O
at O
them O
. O

Many O
of O
them O
fell B-TER
from O
the O
first O
shots O
. O

I O
saw O
three O
SS B-ORG
men B-TER
lying O
dead B-TER
. O

But O
the O
police B-TER
started O
to O
shoot O
at O
every O
house O
and O
threw O
a O
grenade O
in O
every O
window O
. O

The O
Jews O
realized O
that O
the O
situation O
was O
hopeless O
, O
so O
everyone O
took O
their O
bottle O
of O
petrol O
and O
set O
the O
house O
, O
where O
they O
were O
, O
on O
fire O
. O

In O
the O
smoke O
and O
fire O
, O
people O
ran O
where O
they O
could O
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
also O
set O
houses O
on O
fire O
. O

The O
fire O
flames O
illuminated O
the O
whole O
town O
. O

When O
the O
shooting O
started O
, O
my O
mother B-TER
went O
out O
into O
the O
street O
to O
look O
what O
was O
happening O
and O
was O
hit O
with O
a O
bullet O
in O
the O
neck O
. O

I O
, O
my O
father B-TER
, O
sister B-TER
and O
brother B-TER
went O
out O
, O
moved O
the O
mother B-TER
away O
from O
the O
street O
and O
went O
up O
to O
the O
attic O
. O

Because O
of O
the O
suffocating O
smoke O
, O
my O
father B-TER
went O
down O
. O

The O
mother B-TER
could O
not O
walk O
and O
fell O
down O
from O
the O
attic O
. O

I O
went O
down O
, O
helped O
the O
mother B-TER
to O
her O
feet O
and O
started O
to O
run O
to O
my O
father B-TER
and O
brother B-TER
. O

From O
below O
, O
I O
heard O
shouting O
: O
– O
Halt O
! O
I O
looked O
around O
and O
did O
not O
see O
my O
father B-TER
. O

We O
lied O
down O
on O
our O
bellies O
. O

A O
German B-TER
approached O
and O
shot O
at O
my O
mother B-TER
. O

I O
saw O
him O
loading O
his O
gun O
, O
so O
I O
stood O
up O
and O
ran O
away O
. O

After O
a O
second O
, O
I O
managed O
to O
hide B-TER
myself O
under O
a O
brick O
house O
. O

It O
was O
the O
evening O
already O
, O
the O
smoke O
was O
irritating O
the O
eyes O
, O
I O
could O
not O
see O
where O
I O
was O
going O
. O

Wandering O
around O
the O
ghetto B-TER
like O
that O
, O
I O
felt O
that O
someone O
was O
following O
me O
and O
I O
tried O
to O
pronounce O
my O
brother B-TER
’s O
name O
. O

Indeed O
, O
he O
answered O
. O

Then O
we O
both O
walked O
through O
the O
ruins O
. O

People O
were O
running O
, O
we O
followed O
them O
. O

The O
machine O
guns O
were O
still O
shooting O
. O

During O
a O
short O
distance O
we O
had O
to O
fall O
on O
our O
bellies O
a O
few O
times O
. O

When O
the O
ghetto B-TER
fence O
had O
burned O
down O
, O
I O
and O
my O
brother B-TER
left O
the O
ghetto B-TER
territory O
. O

We O
entered O
a O
garden O
and O
slept O
there O
until O
the O
dawn O
. O

When O
the O
day O
came O
, O
my O
brother B-TER
told O
me O
to O
go O
have O
a O
look O
where O
the O
Germans B-TER
where O
. O

I O
left O
the O
garden O
. O

Two O
Germans B-TER
were O
standing O
looking O
at O
the O
other O
direction O
. O

I O
could O
not O
go O
back O
, O
so O
I O
went O
through O
the O
fields O
and O
the O
forests O
to O
the O
villages O
and O
asked O
, O
where O
the O
partisans B-TER
where O
. O

During O
the O
fire O
, O
the O
father B-TER
told O
us O
that O
if O
someone O
from O
us O
stayed O
alive O
, O
they O
should O
go O
the O
village O
called O
Arebova B-LOC
Orekhovno O
, O
5 O
kilometers O
from O
Glubokoye B-LOC
. O

I O
spent O
a O
whole O
day O
wandering O
in O
the O
woods O
until O
I O
came O
to O
that O
village O
. O

I O
called O
my O
father B-TER
by O
name O
, O
but O
no O
one O
answered O
. O

However O
, O
peasants O
that O
knew O
my O
father B-TER
and O
heard O
me O
shouting O
, O
warned O
me O
I O
should O
quickly O
go O
away O
because O
the O
village O
elder O
was O
coming O
. O

I O
ran O
fast O
down O
the O
hill O
and O
entered O
a O
forest O
. O

Walking O
, O
a O
heard O
a O
pig O
squeak O
. O

Following O
the O
sound O
of O
the O
squeaks O
, O
I O
found O
myself O
on O
a O
path O
, O
where O
I O
met O
peasants O
from O
Glubokoye B-LOC
I O
knew O
; O
I O
followed O
their O
horse O
cart O
. O

I O
saw O
Germans B-TER
on O
the O
road O
, O
so O
I O
quickly O
ran B-TER
away I-TER
and O
entered O
a O
cemetery B-TER
. O

I O
saw O
that O
they O
were O
following O
me O
and O
they O
caught O
me O
. O

They O
asked O
me O
who O
I O
was O
. O

I O
answered O
that O
I O
was O
a O
Christian B-TER
girl B-TER
. O

They O
laughed O
and O
told O
me O
not O
to O
be O
afraid O
, O
that O
they O
knew O
I O
was O
a O
Jewish O
girl B-TER
. O

They O
asked O
me O
where O
I O
was O
going O
. O

– O
I O
’m O
following O
my O
nose O
, O
I O
answered O
. O

– O
Tell O
me O
, O
do O
you O
want O
to O
go O
to O
the O
partisans B-TER
? O
– O
one O
of O
them O
asked O
again O
. O

– O
I O
do O
n’t O
know O
, O
I O
do O
n’t O
have O
where O
to O
sleep O
– O
I O
answered O
. O

– O
Go O
to O
this O
house O
, O
you O
’ll O
be O
able O
to O
sleep O
there O
– O
one O
of O
them O
said O
and O
pointed O
where O
to O
go O
. O

I O
entered O
the O
house O
and O
asked O
for O
something O
to O
drink B-TER
. O

I O
received O
it O
. O

The O
owner O
of O
the O
house O
questioned O
me O
who O
I O
was O
, O
I O
answered O
that O
I O
was O
form O
Glubokoye B-LOC
, O
but O
he O
did O
not O
allow O
me O
to O
sleep O
at O
his O
place O
. O

He O
told O
me O
to O
go O
away O
immediately O
. O

Leaving O
a O
house O
, O
I O
saw O
a O
non O
- O
Jew O
ploughing O
. O

I O
approached O
him O
and O
asked O
if O
I O
could O
sleep O
at O
his O
place O
. O

He O
answered O
no O
, O
but O
called O
me O
back O
and O
gave O
me O
instructions O
to O
enter O
a O
barn O
where O
I O
could O
sleep O
. O

He O
brought O
me O
food B-TER
in O
the O
morning O
. O

Then O
he O
came O
back O
again O
soon O
and O
told O
me O
: O
– O
Two O
Jews O
have O
just O
passed O
by O
, O
run O
quickly O
! O
I O
ran O
and O
shouted O
to O
the O
Jews O
to O
wait O
, O
but O
they O
did O
not O
stop O
. O

I O
continued O
to O
run O
and O
caught O
up O
with O
them O
. O

They O
were O
people O
from O
Glubokoye B-LOC
I O
knew O
, O
a O
married B-TER
couple O
. O

I O
went O
to O
the O
partisan B-TER
area O
with O
them O
. O

They O
left O
me O
in O
a O
Christian B-TER
woman B-TER
’s O
house O
and O
left O
. O

I O
asked O
how O
to O
reach O
the O
partisan B-TER
units O
. O

I O
was O
not O
accepted O
into O
three O
units O
. O

Young O
guys B-TER
sat O
with O
guns O
. O

They O
questioned O
me O
who O
I O
was O
, O
from O
where O
I O
came O
and O
told O
me O
to O
go O
to O
another O
village O
1,5 O
kilometer O
away O
from O
that O
village O
. O

Going O
there O
I O
asked O
a O
peasant O
woman B-TER
where O
the O
commander O
was O
. O

At O
the O
moment O
, O
a O
man B-TER
was O
passing O
by O
on O
a O
bicycle O
and O
the O
woman B-TER
told O
me O
to O
ask O
him O
. O

I O
stopped O
him O
, O
showed O
him O
the O
note O
from O
the O
commander O
of O
the O
previous O
village O
which O
said O
we O
should O
contact O
the O
regional O
commander O
. O

He O
immediately O
led O
me O
to O
a O
house O
in O
the O
village O
. O

I O
waited O
in O
the O
street O
. O

He O
was O
the O
commander O
of O
the O
5th O
unit O
, O
from O
Moscow B-LOC
, O
Konstantinov B-PER
Vania I-PER
. O

I O
met O
Jews O
I O
knew O
there O
. O

The O
commander O
asked O
them O
if O
they O
knew O
me O
, O
they O
answered O
negatively O
, O
but O
I O
knew O
them O
. O

I O
entered O
the O
house O
. O

After O
having O
a O
rest O
, O
I O
went O
to O
the O
kitchen O
and O
helped O
to O
peel O
the O
potatoes B-TER
and O
with O
other O
chores O
. O

After O
two O
weeks O
, O
all O
the O
nine O
units O
went O
to O
attack O
Vileyka B-LOC
. O

I O
learnt O
that O
Konstantinov B-PER
and O
Rodionov B-PER
had O
been O
taken O
prisoners B-TER
by O
the O
Germans B-TER
. O

When O
the O
Germans B-TER
were O
shooting O
the O
Russian B-TER
prisoners B-TER
, O
Konstantinov B-PER
and O
Rodionov B-PER
proposed O
the O
Germans B-TER
to O
create O
a O
brigade O
to O
fight O
against O
the O
partisans B-TER
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
gave O
them O
a O
permission O
, O
and O
they O
organized O
quite O
a O
large O
group O
, O
armed O
with O
shotguns O
and O
machine O
guns O
. O

Konstantinov B-PER
and O
Rodionov B-PER
went O
over O
to O
the O
partisans B-TER
and O
created O
the O
nine O
units O
. O

I O
was O
5 O
kilometers O
from O
Vileyka B-LOC
and O
I O
was O
told O
that O
during O
the O
attack O
Vileyka B-LOC
had O
been O
burned O
down O
. O

People O
ran O
away O
, O
lots O
of O
Germans B-TER
were O
taken O
as O
prisoners B-TER
. O

From O
the O
midday O
, O
the O
fight O
continued O
until O
the O
following O
morning O
. O

Two O
Jewish O
young O
men B-TER
from O
our O
5th O
unit O
, O
Bik B-PER
Leybl I-PER
from O
Prozoroki B-LOC
and O
Ziomke B-PER
Krivitski I-PER
, O
were O
killed B-TER
, O
they O
were O
burned O
during O
the O
fire O
. O

Konstantinov B-PER
also O
fell B-TER
. O

Afterwards O
, O
we O
returned O
to O
the O
woods O
. O

Druboshovski B-PER
took O
over O
Konstantinov B-PER
’s O
place O
. O

Rodionov B-PER
decided O
to O
reach O
the O
front O
. O

Just O
as O
they O
had O
crossed O
the O
railway O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
surrounded O
them O
. O

We O
were O
15 O
persons O
to O
stay O
. O

We O
waited O
the O
Germans B-TER
to O
come O
looking O
for O
us O
, O
but O
they O
did O
not O
come O
. O

I O
learned O
that O
Rodionov B-PER
had O
also O
been O
killed B-TER
and O
that O
the O
brigade O
was O
scattered O
. O

Our O
hideout B-TER
was O
also O
discovered O
, O
15 O
persons O
were O
shot B-TER
. O

I O
ran O
away O
and O
hid B-TER
myself O
. O

