Abraham B-PER
Peller I-PER
Testimony O
( O
doc O
. O

301/1649 O
) O
Original O
, O
manuscript O
, O
2 O
pages O
210 O
x O
295 O
mm O
, O
1 O
page O
210 O
x O
140 O
mm O
, O
Polish O
language O
. O

Abraham B-PER
Peller I-PER
Born O
at O
Mszanka B-LOC
( O
the O
Gorlice B-LOC
county O
) O
in O
1894 O
Residing O
at O
Biecz B-LOC
, O
near O
Jasło B-LOC
[ O
recorded O
by O
] O
[ B-PER
Róża I-PER
] I-PER
Bauminger I-PER
Actions O
in O
Biecz B-LOC
In O
the O
early O
days O
of O
the O
occupation O
it O
was O
quiet O
in O
our O
town O
. O

But O
on O
January O
3 O
, O
1942 O
, O
the O
excesses O
began O
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
raided O
several O
Jewish O
homes O
and O
shot B-TER
8 O
people O
who O
happened O
to O
fall O
into O
their O
hands O
. O

The O
names O
of O
these O
people O
are O
: O
two O
Heller B-PER
brothers O
, O
Bornstein B-PER
from O
Łódź B-LOC
, O
Gilowa B-PER
from O
Łódź B-LOC
, O
a O
wife B-TER
of O
a O
tailor O
and O
mother O
of O
three O
children B-TER
, O
Chaim B-PER
Itzinger I-PER
with O
his O
daughter B-TER
Regina B-PER
, O
and O
Izak B-PER
Cześniower I-PER
. O

It O
was O
the O
so O
- O
called O
town O
quota O
. O

Similar O
acts O
of O
homicide B-TER
took O
place O
in O
the O
nearby O
towns O
: O
in O
Gorlice B-LOC
, O
and O
others O
. O

Some O
Polish B-TER
woman B-TER
from O
Jasło B-LOC
informed O
that O
Dr B-PER
Zucker I-PER
of O
Jasło B-LOC
had O
been O
a O
commissar O
during O
the O
times O
of O
the O
Soviets B-TER
. O

He O
and O
his O
wife B-TER
were O
shot B-TER
on O
the O
spot O
, O
and O
their O
daughters B-TER
were O
taken O
to O
Biecz B-LOC
. O

They O
were O
ordered O
to O
get O
out O
of O
the O
car O
and O
were O
shot B-TER
near O
my O
house O
. O

My O
son B-TER
ran O
to O
fetch O
a O
doctor B-TER
because O
one O
of O
the O
girls B-TER
was O
still O
alive O
, O
but O
her O
state O
was O
hopeless O
, O
and O
she O
died B-TER
half O
an O
hour O
later O
. O

Ignacy B-PER
Fornalik I-PER
, O
commandant O
of O
the O
Polish B-TER
police I-TER
, O
informed O
the O
police B-TER
that O
some O
Jews O
had O
tried O
to O
save O
a O
girl B-TER
who O
had O
been O
sentenced O
to O
death B-TER
, O
and O
on O
February O
16 O
, O
1942 O
, O
Polish B-TER
policemen I-TER
arrested B-TER
these O
boys B-TER
and O
their O
families B-TER
. O

My O
son B-TER
and O
I O
were O
arrested B-TER
, O
too O
. O

They O
blackmailed O
us O
to O
swindle O
us O
out O
of O
money O
, O
and O
they O
got O
a O
pretty O
large O
sum O
. O

Spielman B-PER
was O
freed O
immediately O
, O
I O
was O
to O
be O
released O
in O
the O
evening O
, O
and O
the O
boys B-TER
at O
night O
. O

But O
in O
the O
meantime O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
arrived O
, O
and O
they O
ordered O
to O
have O
Spielman B-PER
and O
his O
entire O
family B-TER
brought O
back O
, O
and O
apart O
from O
them O
also O
Hinda B-PER
Schnaps I-PER
with O
her O
two O
sons B-TER
and O
my O
entire O
family B-TER
of O
seven O
. O

All O
of O
us O
were O
handcuffed O
in O
pairs O
, O
and O
at O
7 O
pm O
everybody O
was O
shot B-TER
. O

I O
was O
at O
the O
very O
rear O
, O
and O
looked O
at O
the O
death B-TER
of O
my O
family B-TER
. O

Then O
they O
shot B-TER
Spielman B-PER
, O
who O
was O
handcuffed O
with O
me O
. O

He O
tumbled O
down O
, O
all O
covered O
with O
blood O
, O
and O
I O
fell O
with O
him O
. O

I O
was O
lying O
in O
a O
puddle O
of O
blood O
, O
and O
the O
Germans B-TER
thought O
that O
I O
was O
dead B-TER
, O
but O
they O
shot O
me O
in O
the O
arm O
just O
to O
make O
sure O
. O

Then O
they O
ordered O
Polish B-TER
policemen I-TER
to O
take O
the O
bodies B-TER
away O
. O

They O
removed O
our O
handcuffs O
, O
and O
when O
they O
went O
away O
for O
a O
break O
, O
I O
took O
advantage O
of O
their O
absence O
, O
raised O
myself O
and O
, O
dripping O
blood O
, O
managed O
to O
drag O
myself O
to O
the O
village O
of O
Moszczenica B-LOC
, O
20 O
kilometres O
away O
, O
to O
a O
Polish B-TER
peasant O
woman B-TER
, O
Adela B-PER
Jędrzejewska I-PER
, O
who O
was O
very O
generous O
towards O
me O
and O
gave O
me O
shelter B-TER
. O

I O
learnt O
from O
eye O
- O
witnesses O
that O
on O
February O
18 O
, O
100 O
Jews O
were O
taken O
from O
Biecz B-LOC
. O

They O
were O
kept O
in O
prison B-TER
for O
4 O
days O
, O
their O
money O
was O
confiscated O
, O
and O
after O
4 O
days O
69 O
of O
them O
were O
shot B-TER
( O
the O
Schützer B-PER
, O
Gewürz B-PER
, O
Kleinman B-PER
and O
Wagschaller B-PER
families B-TER
) O
. O

It O
turned O
out O
that O
the O
Polish B-TER
police I-TER
was O
responsible O
for O
organising O
this O
action O
, O
and O
when O
they O
got O
a O
phone O
call O
from O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
from O
Jasło B-LOC
, O
they O
had O
already O
killed B-TER
31 O
people O
. O

The O
Polish B-TER
police I-TER
blackmailed O
the O
Jews O
and O
they O
swindled O
250 O
thousand O
zlotys O
out O
of O
them O
, O
saying O
that O
if O
they O
did O
n’t O
pay O
, O
another O
similar O
action O
would O
be O
carried O
out O
. O

A O
few O
months O
later O
the O
Germans B-TER
took O
and O
shot B-TER
14 O
other O
Jews O
. O

Allegedly O
, O
the O
charge O
against O
them O
was O
was O
that O
their O
brothers O
were O
communists B-TER
. O

The O
names O
of O
some O
of O
the O
victims O
are O
: O
Schneider B-PER
, O
a O
family B-TER
of O
five O
, O
Kurz B-PER
, O
Jakóbowicz B-PER
, O
and O
Wagschal B-PER
with O
his O
wife B-TER
. O

In O
August O
1942 O
a O
liquidation B-TER
action O
took O
place O
. O

170 O
people O
were O
shot B-TER
on O
the O
spot O
and O
buried O
at O
the O
Jewish B-TER
cemetery I-TER
. O

700 O
people O
were O
loaded O
onto O
cattle B-TER
cars I-TER
and O
transported B-TER
to O
Bełżec B-LOC
. O

Those O
who O
managed O
to O
hide B-TER
were O
hunted O
down O
by O
the O
Polish B-TER
police I-TER
and O
turned O
over O
to O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
. O

I O
and O
my O
brother B-TER
and O
two O
other O
Jews O
were O
hiding B-TER
at O
Jędrzejewska B-PER
’s I-PER
home O
, O
and O
around O
70 O
other O
Jews O
were O
in O
hiding B-TER
in O
the O
same O
village O
. O

The O
commandant O
of O
the O
Polish B-TER
police I-TER
in O
that O
village O
, O
Bednarz B-PER
, O
was O
ordered O
to O
conduct O
a O
search O
for O
the O
Jews O
hiding B-TER
in O
the O
area O
. O

He O
warned O
us O
against O
the O
danger O
we O
were O
in O
, O
and O
we O
left O
Moszczenica B-LOC
. O

On O
the O
following O
day O
, O
he O
assembled O
70 O
peasants O
with O
pitchforks O
, O
and O
ordered O
them O
to O
look O
for O
Jews O
in O
the O
attics O
. O

They O
certainly O
failed O
to O
find O
a O
single O
Jew O
. O

Bednarz B-PER
risked O
his O
life O
several O
times O
to O
save O
Jews O
. O

He O
was O
blackmailed O
, O
and O
then O
removed O
by O
the O
commissar O
of O
the O
Polish B-TER
police I-TER
from O
that O
particular O
village O
( O
of O
Łużna B-LOC
) O
to O
Jasło B-LOC
. O

At O
present O
Bednarz B-PER
is O
a O
mayor B-TER
in O
Blasdorf B-LOC
Blasdorf O
bei O
Schömberg O
, O
Polish O
name O
: O
Błażejów O
. O

near O
Kamienna B-LOC
Góra I-LOC
. O

[ O
signed O
by O
] O
Abraham B-PER
Peller I-PER
