From O
Minister O
Tsutsui B-PER
Kiyoshi I-PER
( O
Bucharest B-LOC
) O
To O
: O
Foreign O
Minister O
Toyo O
( O
Tokyo B-LOC
) O
In O
my O
Telegram O
# O
97 O
of O
June O
of O
last O
year O
I O
proposed O
we O
should O
pay O
attention O
not O
to O
let O
Jews B-TER
into O
Greater B-TER
East I-TER
Asia I-TER
. O

In O
response O
( O
Telegram O
# O
34 O
of O
June O
of O
last O
year O
) O
the O
Ministry O
of O
Foreign O
Affairs O
was O
of O
the O
opinion O
that O
it O
should O
not O
make O
Jews B-TER
into O
a O
question O
. O

Since O
then O
in O
many O
countries O
in O
Europe B-LOC
persecution B-TER
of I-TER
Jews I-TER
has O
worsened O
. O

Recently O
, O
it O
is O
the O
same O
even O
in O
France B-LOC
, O
which O
has O
been O
considered O
their O
paradise O
/ O
haven O
. O

Therefore O
, O
when O
the O
war O
is O
over O
, O
many O
of O
the O
Jews B-TER
will O
leave B-TER
Europe B-LOC
and O
in O
that O
case O
we O
should O
pay O
attention O
so O
that O
they O
do O
n’t O
flow O
into O
Greater B-TER
East I-TER
Asia I-TER
. O

In O
my O
opinion O
, O
while O
building O
Greater B-TER
East I-TER
Asia I-TER
, O
from O
now O
on O
we O
need O
to O
diligently O
pay O
close O
attention O
so O
as O
to O
eliminate O
the O
Jewish O
influence O
entrenched O
in O
different O
parts O
of O
East O
Asia O
starting O
from O
Shanghai B-LOC
to O
the O
extent O
possible O
and O
to O
eradicate O
their O
foundation O
. O

At O
the O
present O
they O
are O
bound O
to O
engage O
in O
Fifth B-TER
Column I-TER
type I-TER
of I-TER
activities I-TER
for O
the O
enemy O
, O
so O
we O
need O
to O
pay O
attention O
to O
all O
Jews B-TER
regardless O
of O
their O
nationality B-TER
. O

