L.B. O
– O
Ka O
[ O
? O
] O
Female O
Social O
Activist O
, O
38 O
years O
old O
. O

Łódź B-LOC
Protocol O
Number O
107 O
( O
Compiled O
on O
January O
5 O
, O
1940 O
) O
On O
September O
5 O
, O
1939 O
, O
our O
Jews O
in O
Łódź B-LOC
volunteered O
en O
masse O
for O
the O
military B-ORG
. O

But O
there O
was O
no O
guarantee O
[ O
to O
be O
enlisted O
] O
and O
they O
were O
not O
employed O
. O

En O
masse O
Jews O
took O
part O
in O
building O
trenches O
etc O
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
invaded O
Łódź B-LOC
on O
September O
8 O
around O
6 O
pm O
. O

Only O
small B-ORG
military I-ORG
units I-ORG
arrived O
, O
who O
did O
not O
at O
all O
let O
the O
population O
feel O
their O
attitude O
towards O
them O
. O

The O
local O
Germans B-TER
took O
in O
the O
invading O
Germans B-TER
enthusiastically O
, O
welcoming O
them O
with O
flowers O
, O
offering O
them O
wine O
and O
pastries O
. O

The O
Polish B-TER
and O
Jewish O
male B-TER
population O
in O
military O
age O
left O
Łódź B-LOC
in O
masses O
in O
the O
night O
from O
September O
5 O
to O
6 O
. O

Officially O
, O
the O
German B-ORG
army I-ORG
invaded O
Łódź B-LOC
on O
September O
9 O
in O
the O
morning O
hours O
between O
10 O
and O
12 O
. O

The O
streets O
were O
overcrowded O
with O
local O
Germans B-TER
who O
welcomed O
the O
German B-ORG
army I-ORG
with O
enthusiasm O
calling O
out O
Heil O
Hitler O
etc O
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
population O
was O
dressed O
festively O
. O

The O
men B-TER
with O
top O
hats O
. O

The O
women B-TER
in O
festive O
attire O
. O

There O
were O
also O
Poles B-TER
on O
the O
streets O
. O

On O
their O
faces O
one O
could O
read O
dreariness O
and O
feeling O
lost O
. O

They O
were O
acting O
calmly O
and O
restrained O
. O

Among O
the O
Polish B-TER
intelligentsia O
one O
could O
see O
sorrow O
. O

One O
could O
even O
see O
a O
tear O
in O
someone O
’s O
eye O
. O

The O
Polish B-TER
mob O
watched O
the O
military B-ORG
indifferently O
and O
unaffected O
. O

Jews O
were O
not O
on O
the O
streets O
. O

I O
myself O
was O
walking O
on O
the O
streets O
with O
my O
eight B-TER
- I-TER
year I-TER
old I-TER
boy I-TER
because O
I O
was O
afraid O
to O
go O
out O
on O
my O
own O
. O

It O
was O
interesting O
to O
me O
to O
watch O
the O
scene O
. O

I O
was O
on O
Wolnośćy B-LOC
Square I-LOC
( O
Freedom O
Square O
) O
. O

We O
were O
standing O
there O
for O
around O
15 O
minutes O
– O
the O
consistent O
Heil O
exclamations O
became O
increasingly O
repulsive O
to O
me O
. O

I O
said O
to O
my O
boy B-TER
in O
Polish B-TER
: O
Come O
, O
let O
’s O
go O
! O
Then O
a O
German B-TER
woman B-TER
standing O
behind O
me O
said O
to O
us O
: O
Yes O
, O
yes O
, O
you O
can O
go O
. O

Here O
is O
no O
place O
for O
you O
. O

The O
stores O
were O
closed O
. O

The O
cafes O
open O
, O
but O
no O
one O
was O
inside O
. O

Life O
in O
the O
city B-LOC
seemed O
to O
be O
dead O
anticipating O
what O
is O
to O
come O
. O

Shabbat O
and O
Sunday O
passed O
by O
with O
festive O
welcoming O
of O
the O
German B-ORG
army I-ORG
by O
the O
local O
German B-TER
population O
. O

On O
September O
11 O
the O
stores O
were O
still O
closed O
. O

Already O
on O
September O
10 O
there O
were O
individual O
cases O
of O
looting B-TER
Jewish O
pastry O
and O
fruit O
shops O
. O

On O
the O
11th O
, O
big O
groups O
of O
local O
Germans B-TER
of O
several O
hundred O
men O
each O
started O
to O
break O
open O
the O
locked O
doors O
, O
to O
bust O
open O
the O
display O
cabinets O
in O
the O
Jewish O
stores O
and O
to O
rob O
the O
merchandise O
. O

Groups O
of O
the O
Polish B-TER
mob O
joined O
the O
Germans B-TER
. O

There O
were O
also O
individual O
German B-TER
soldiers B-ORG
among O
the O
assembled O
crowd O
. O

This O
lasted O
from O
Monday O
through O
Tuesday O
. O

They O
looted B-TER
the O
Pyetrikover B-LOC
, I-LOC
Novomayske I-LOC
( O
looted B-TER
in O
its O
entirety O
) O
, O
Zovadzke B-LOC
Streets I-LOC
. O

On O
Zovadzke B-LOC
, O
I O
was O
personally O
present O
when O
they O
looted B-TER
Ogurek B-PER
’s O
big O
shoe O
store O
. O

On O
Pyetrikover B-LOC
, O
for O
instance O
, O
they O
pillaged B-TER
: O
Rapaport B-PER
’s O
big O
store O
for O
men O
’s O
hats O
, O
Hekhtkop B-PER
’s O
shop O
for O
shoes O
, O
two O
stores O
of O
Bata B-ORG
. O

On O
Novomayske B-LOC
: O
at O
number O
19 O
there O
were O
big O
halls O
filled O
with O
different O
merchandise O
. O

There O
were O
150 O
stores O
. O

Everything O
was O
thoroughly O
looted B-TER
. O

The O
robbed B-TER
merchandise O
was O
taken O
for O
personal O
use O
. O

There O
were O
cases O
when O
the O
robbers B-TER
took O
several O
shoes O
– O
right O
or O
left O
. O

They O
stood O
in O
the O
middle O
of O
the O
crowd O
and O
cried O
out O
: O
Who O
has O
shoes O
of O
this O
and O
that O
kind O
, O
for O
the O
left O
or O
right O
foot O
. O

Let O
’s O
exchange O
with O
each O
other O
. O

Jews O
were O
afraid O
to O
show O
themselves O
in O
the O
streets O
and O
they O
consequently O
did O
not O
react O
to O
the O
looting B-TER
. O

On O
the O
streets O
, O
there O
was O
no O
police B-ORG
, O
only O
the O
civilian O
militia O
, O
from O
which O
the O
Jews O
had O
been O
immediately O
removed O
as O
soon O
as O
the O
Germans B-TER
invaded O
the O
city B-LOC
. O

The O
civilian O
militia B-TER
did O
not O
react O
to O
the O
looting B-TER
at O
all O
, O
watching O
it O
indifferently O
. O

There O
was O
not O
one O
case O
when O
Jews O
tried O
to O
rescue O
their O
property O
. O

If O
it O
incidentally O
occurred O
that O
a O
Jew O
went O
by O
, O
they O
did O
not O
beat O
him O
/ O
her O
because O
the O
mob O
was O
too O
busy O
looting B-TER
. O

It O
is O
estimated O
that O
around O
five O
hundred O
stores O
with O
textiles O
, O
shoes O
and O
haberdashery O
have O
been O
entirely O
looted B-TER
. O

On O
Tuesday O
, O
September O
12 O
, O
around O
noon O
, O
a O
Jewish O
delegation O
, O
led O
by O
Rumkowski B-PER
, O
who O
was O
designated O
as O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
chairman O
by O
the O
Germans B-TER
, O
turned O
to O
the O
German B-ORG
military I-ORG
commander I-ORG
. O

( O
There O
was O
also O
Levshteyn B-PER
– O
a O
manufacturer O
– O
and O
a O
third O
one O
whose O
name O
I O
have O
forgotten O
. O

) O
The O
delegation O
requested O
that O
steps O
be O
taken O
so O
that O
the O
looting B-TER
stopps O
. O

The O
commander O
replied O
that O
when O
the O
Jews O
open O
the O
stores O
the O
looting B-TER
will O
stop O
. O

On O
September O
13 O
, O
on O
Wednesday O
the O
eve O
of O
Rosh O
Hashanah O
, O
the O
military B-ORG
headquarters I-ORG
summoned O
the O
rabbis B-TER
Treystman B-PER
and O
Segal B-PER
. O

From O
the O
headquarters B-LOC
, O
SS B-ORG
men I-ORG
escorted O
them O
in O
an O
open O
car O
to O
the O
synagogue B-TER
on O
Kastshushka B-LOC
Street I-LOC
. O

This O
happened O
in O
the O
following O
way O
: O
in O
front O
of O
the O
military B-ORG
headquarters I-ORG
a O
car O
pulled O
up O
, O
so O
the O
rabbis B-TER
wanted O
to O
get O
in O
– O
they O
were O
brutally O
pushed O
away O
. O

The O
SS B-ORG
men I-ORG
got O
in O
the O
car O
. O

On O
the O
step O
on O
one O
side O
, O
the O
old O
sick B-TER
rabbi B-TER
Segal B-PER
was O
standing O
, O
on O
the O
other O
step O
, O
rabbi B-TER
Treystman B-PER
. O

Standing O
like O
this O
, O
they O
were O
driving O
to O
the O
synagogue B-TER
. O

Everyone O
entered O
the O
synagogue B-TER
– O
the O
escorting O
SS B-ORG
men I-ORG
and O
the O
rabbis B-TER
, O
no O
one O
else O
. O

The O
SS B-ORG
men I-ORG
forced O
the O
rabbis B-TER
to O
take O
out O
the O
Torah O
scrolls O
from O
the O
Holy O
Ark O
, O
they O
ordered O
them O
to O
spit O
on O
the O
scrolls O
, O
to O
tread O
on O
them O
with O
their O
feet O
and O
to O
tear O
them O
apart O
. O

The O
rabbis B-TER
refused O
to O
do O
that O
: O
You O
can O
shoot O
us O
. O

The O
SS B-ORG
men I-ORG
then O
spit O
into O
the O
rabbis B-TER
’ I-TER
faces O
, O
shaved B-TER
off I-TER
the I-TER
rabbis I-TER
’ I-TER
beards I-TER
and O
beat O
them O
with O
their O
fists O
. O

The O
old O
rabbi B-TER
Segal B-PER
fell O
, O
was O
kicked O
and O
muddled O
up O
the O
scrolls O
. O

From O
the O
synagogue B-TER
, O
the O
rabbis B-TER
were O
escorted O
back O
to O
the O
municipal B-LOC
headquarters I-LOC
. O

There O
, O
they O
received O
the O
orders O
that O
Jews O
are O
forbidden O
to O
pray O
in O
the O
synagogues B-TER
and O
in O
private O
minyans O
Quorum O
of O
ten O
adult O
men O
meeting O
to O
prayer O
. O

on O
Rosh O
Hashanah O
and O
Yom O
Kippur O
. O

Wherever O
Jews O
are O
caught O
praying O
they O
will O
be O
shot B-TER
. O

At O
the O
same O
time O
, O
the O
rabbis B-TER
received O
orders O
that O
the O
Jewish O
stores O
must O
be O
open O
during O
the O
Days O
of O
Awe O
and O
on O
the O
High O
Holidays O
. O

At O
the O
headquarters B-LOC
, O
the O
rabbis B-TER
were O
not O
beaten O
any O
longer O
. O

They O
were O
released O
. O

Then O
, O
the O
community O
published O
a O
printed O
bill O
, O
signed O
by O
the O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
chairman O
Rumkowski B-PER
and O
rabbi B-TER
Treystman B-PER
, O
that O
as O
per O
the O
decree B-TER
by O
the O
Germans B-TER
all O
Jewish O
stores O
have O
to O
be O
open O
, O
Jews O
are O
not O
allowed O
to O
pray O
collectively O
, O
Jewish O
stores O
have O
to O
be O
open O
on O
the O
Holidays O
, O
on O
Shabbats O
and O
on O
the O
Days O
of O
Awe O
. O

Since O
then O
, O
Jews O
keep O
their O
stores O
indeed O
open O
and O
do O
not O
pray O
collectively O
. O

As O
per O
the O
promise O
by O
the O
German B-TER
municipal O
commander O
, O
that O
if O
the O
stores O
will O
be O
opened O
, O
the O
looting B-TER
will O
stop O
, O
the O
mass O
robberies B-TER
ended O
, O
but O
in O
different O
streets O
individual O
robbery B-TER
cases O
consistently O
happened O
, O
the O
majority O
of O
them O
already O
by O
a O
larger O
percentage O
of O
German B-ORG
military I-ORG
personnel I-ORG
. O

The O
looting B-TER
was O
primarily O
done O
by O
local O
Germans B-TER
, O
Poles B-TER
in O
comparison O
participated O
not O
so O
much O
. O

The O
Polish B-TER
intelligentsia O
were O
deeply O
affected O
by O
Poland B-TER
’s O
destruction O
. O

They O
felt O
for O
the O
Jewish O
population O
but O
did O
not O
actively O
stand O
up O
against O
the O
fraction O
of O
Poles B-TER
who O
took O
part O
in O
the O
mentioned O
robberies B-TER
. O

So O
, O
my O
neighbor O
, O
for O
instance O
, O
a O
judge B-TER
from O
appeal O
court B-TER
in O
Łódź B-LOC
called O
Kemptshinski B-PER
from O
Galicia B-LOC
, O
expressed O
it O
to O
me O
as O
follows O
: O
the O
fraction O
of O
Polish B-TER
population O
taking O
part O
in O
looting B-TER
is O
an O
expression O
of O
solidarity O
with O
the O
Germans B-TER
. O

The O
things O
that O
satisfies O
the O
Germans B-TER
should O
not O
have O
been O
done O
. O

One O
could O
feel O
such O
dejection O
in O
his O
words O
that O
is O
was O
unrealistic O
that O
he O
or O
any O
other O
Polish B-TER
intelligent O
would O
in O
any O
way O
become O
active O
. O

After O
Sukkot O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
turned O
to O
the O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
with O
the O
demand O
that O
20 O
elegantly O
dressed O
Jews O
, O
preferably O
with O
top O
hats O
, O
in O
any O
case O
dressed O
in O
the O
way O
Jews O
dress O
on O
holidays O
for O
the O
synagogue B-TER
, O
shall O
come O
to O
the O
elegant O
synagogue B-TER
on O
Kashtshushki B-LOC
Avenue I-LOC
. O

The O
headquarters B-LOC
demanded O
that O
they O
shall O
stage O
praying O
in O
participation O
of O
rabbi B-TER
Treystman B-PER
. O

The O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
gathered O
around O
twenty O
Jews O
in O
the O
synagogue B-TER
, O
and O
the O
Germans B-TER
took O
several O
photographs B-TER
of O
the O
praying O
Jews O
. O

As O
it O
is O
understood O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
did O
this O
in O
order O
to O
show O
the O
world O
that O
they O
permit O
Jews O
to O
pray O
. O

Soon O
after O
the O
German B-TER
invaded O
, O
they O
caught O
Jews O
both O
from O
the O
streets O
and O
the O
homes O
. O

They O
were O
forced O
to O
cover O
with O
naked O
hands O
the O
trenches O
which O
had O
been O
digged O
out O
for O
protection O
from O
bombs O
from O
airplanes O
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
said O
during O
this O
: O
You O
took O
the O
biggest O
part O
in O
digging O
them O
out O
, O
now O
you O
have O
to O
fix O
what O
you O
have O
damaged O
. O

For O
the O
work B-TER
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
did O
not O
pay O
anything O
. O

There O
were O
cases O
when O
the O
workers B-TER
were O
given O
food B-TER
and O
when O
cigarettes O
were O
distributed O
among O
them O
. O

The O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
started O
to O
intervene O
saying O
Jews O
should O
n’t O
be O
snapped O
up O
for O
work B-TER
. O

The O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
obligated O
itself O
to O
supply O
700 O
Jews O
to O
work B-TER
daily O
on O
the O
condition O
that O
Jews O
are O
no O
longer O
snapped O
from O
the O
streets O
and O
homes O
. O

In O
response O
, O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
gave O
its O
consent O
. O

Nonetheless O
, O
Jews O
were O
still O
snapped O
from O
the O
streets O
to O
work B-TER
. O

From O
the O
homes O
, O
they O
were O
no O
longer O
dragged O
, O
though O
. O

As O
the O
consequence O
, O
the O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
stopped O
to O
send O
people O
to O
work B-TER
after O
a O
total O
of O
three O
weeks O
. O

For O
a O
Jew O
– O
man B-TER
or O
woman B-TER
– O
it O
was O
impossible O
to O
go O
through O
the O
streets O
because O
they O
were O
catching O
Jews O
for O
work B-TER
en O
masse O
. O

The O
relation O
to O
the O
caught O
Jews O
was O
better O
in O
the O
beginning O
when O
the O
regime O
in O
Łódź B-LOC
was O
a O
military B-ORG
one O
. O

Since O
October O
8 O
, O
1939 O
, O
the O
SS B-ORG
and O
SA B-ORG
and O
civilian O
local O
Germans B-TER
took O
over O
the O
power O
over O
the O
city B-LOC
( O
the O
Hitlerjugend O
and O
the O
Deutscher O
Selbstschutz O
) O
as O
well O
as O
the O
police B-ORG
, O
which O
was O
made O
up O
of O
local O
Germans B-TER
. O

The O
caught O
Jews O
are O
brutally O
beaten O
more O
and O
more O
. O

Clothes O
, O
watches O
, O
cigarette O
- O
boxes O
etc O
. O

is O
robbed B-TER
away O
from O
them O
. O

One O
can O
say O
that O
the O
catching O
for O
work B-TER
has O
become O
a O
system O
in O
order O
to O
pressure O
Jews O
to O
pay O
ransom O
. O

Not O
only O
the O
often O
inventive O
local O
Germans B-TER
but O
also O
officers O
from O
the O
SS O
and O
SA O
took O
part O
in O
robbing B-TER
the O
caught O
Jews O
by O
taking O
ransom O
. O

They O
forced O
the O
Jews O
to O
clean B-TER
toilets O
and O
gutters O
with O
their O
bare O
hands O
, O
to O
clean O
a O
whole O
building O
with O
a O
toothbrush O
. O

Even O
ten O
- O
year O
old O
Jewish O
children B-TER
are O
caught O
for O
work B-TER
. O

In O
front O
of O
my O
eyes O
, O
on O
September O
16 O
, O
around O
11 O
to O
12 O
in O
the O
morning O
on O
the O
street B-LOC
of I-LOC
11th I-LOC
November I-LOC
, O
a O
German B-TER
soldier B-TER
forced O
a O
ten B-TER
- I-TER
year I-TER
old I-TER
Jewish I-TER
boy I-TER
to O
carry O
a O
big O
suitcase O
. O

The O
boy B-TER
was O
not O
able O
to O
lift O
it O
. O

So O
he O
dragged O
it O
over O
the O
cobblestone O
pavement O
. O

The O
German B-TER
beat O
the O
boy B-TER
mercilessly O
and O
threw O
him O
to O
the O
ground O
. O

And O
while O
screaming O
out O
: O
Dirty O
Jews O
Schmutzige O
Juden O
. O

! O
he O
tore O
out O
the O
suitcase O
from O
the O
boy O
’s O
hands O
. O

I O
live O
in O
Łódź B-LOC
on O
Magistratske B-LOC
Street I-LOC
Number I-LOC
… O
Nearby O
, O
on O
Maludnyover B-LOC
Street I-LOC
82 I-LOC
or I-LOC
84 I-LOC
, O
the O
confiscated B-TER
palace O
of O
the O
Jewish O
textile O
magnate O
Yoysef B-PER
Krososhinski I-PER
is O
located O
. O

In O
this O
palace O
, O
there O
is O
now O
the O
home O
of O
the O
Hitlerjugend O
. O

It O
is O
a O
spacious O
three O
- O
story O
building O
, O
in O
which O
children B-TER
in O
the O
ages O
of O
10 O
- O
11 O
to O
15 O
- O
17 O
are O
gathering O
. O

In O
the O
morning O
, O
these O
German B-TER
children B-TER
go O
to O
school B-TER
. O

In O
the O
afternoon O
, O
they O
are O
in O
this O
building O
. O

In O
front O
of O
the O
building O
, O
on O
the O
pavement O
, O
2 O
boys O
are O
standing O
who O
keep O
watch O
. O

On O
their O
arms O
is O
a O
swastika B-TER
, O
in O
their O
belts O
a O
bayonet O
, O
in O
their O
hands O
a O
whip O
. O

Ten B-TER
- I-TER
year I-TER
old I-TER
German B-TER
boys B-TER
catch O
seventy O
- O
year O
old O
men O
, O
forcing B-TER
them I-TER
to I-TER
work I-TER
, O
demanding O
ransom O
, O
beating O
Jews O
mercilessly O
who O
are O
passing O
by O
. O

On O
December O
10 O
around O
4 O
pm O
, O
my O
14 O
- O
year O
old O
daughter B-TER
D O
… O
, O
a O
schoolgirl B-TER
, O
was O
caught O
for O
work B-TER
. O

She O
was O
on O
her O
way O
home O
. O

A O
10/11 O
- O
year O
old O
German B-TER
snapped O
her O
into O
the O
building O
. O

They O
took O
from O
her O
a O
pair O
of O
brown O
leather O
gloves B-TER
and O
gave O
her O
things O
for O
scrubbing O
and O
cleaning O
. O

My O
daughter B-TER
was O
held O
45 O
minutes O
until O
a O
German B-TER
soldier B-TER
arrived O
and O
said O
that O
such O
a O
young O
girl B-TER
can O
be O
sent O
home O
. O

Letting O
her O
go O
, O
they O
said O
to O
her O
that O
if O
she O
brings O
2 O
Mark O
or O
10 O
Deka O
tea B-TER
and O
a O
kilo O
of O
flour B-TER
, O
the O
gloves B-TER
will O
be O
returned O
to O
her O
. O

I O
myself O
was O
caught O
3 O
times O
for O
work B-TER
. O

Twice O
, O
I O
was O
led O
to O
work B-TER
in O
the O
police B-ORG
station I-ORG
on O
Abramovski B-LOC
Street I-LOC
29 I-LOC
. O

I O
was O
not O
beaten O
. O

I O
was O
made O
to O
carry O
buckets O
of O
water O
to O
the O
third O
level O
, O
forced O
to O
stand O
on O
a O
ladder O
that O
was O
barely O
holding O
itself O
and O
ready O
to O
fall O
over O
any O
minute O
, O
and O
to O
wipe O
clean O
the O
ceiling O
like O
that O
. O

When O
a O
woman B-TER
, O
who O
was O
with O
me O
, O
tried O
to O
hold O
up O
the O
ladder O
from O
below O
, O
the O
police B-ORG
officer I-ORG
did O
not O
permit O
it O
. O

Into O
the O
home O
of O
the O
Hitlerjugend O
, O
a O
14 O
- O
year O
old O
German B-TER
dragged O
me O
the O
last O
time O
. O

This O
was O
September O
16 O
at O
9:30 O
am O
. O

The O
schools B-TER
were O
not O
running O
due O
to O
vacations O
so O
the O
teenagers O
had O
time O
. O

Downstairs O
there O
was O
a O
corridor O
where O
everyone O
who O
enters O
takes O
off O
his O
/ O
her O
clothes O
and O
leaves O
the O
coat B-TER
with O
the O
things O
one O
brought O
. O

We O
were O
9 O
Jewish O
women B-TER
. O

We O
were O
given O
the O
task O
to O
clean O
and O
scrub O
the O
windows O
but O
they O
did O
not O
give O
us O
any O
cloth O
. O

We O
were O
forced O
to O
get O
undressed O
and O
to O
take O
off O
our O
underwear B-TER
and O
to O
clean O
the O
windows O
with O
it O
. O

( O
I O
got O
undressed O
in O
a O
separate O
room O
. O

) O
I O
was O
beaten O
, O
pushed O
, O
kicked O
. O

Above O
me O
, O
a O
12 B-TER
- I-TER
year I-TER
old I-TER
German B-TER
was O
standing O
in O
a O
uniform O
from O
the O
Hitlerjugend B-ORG
. O

I O
scrubbed O
the O
floors O
standing O
. O

On O
your O
knees O
! O
he O
ordered O
generally O
addressing O
me O
informally O
the O
whole O
time O
. O

I O
pretended O
that O
I O
did O
not O
hear O
him O
. O

So O
he O
pushed O
me O
so O
that O
my O
head O
knocked O
against O
the O
floor O
. O

It O
was O
getting O
dark O
before O
my O
eyes O
and O
I O
was O
working B-TER
this O
way O
from O
9:30am O
to O
1 O
pm O
. O

From O
my O
coat B-TER
, O
which O
stayed O
downstairs O
, O
nothing O
was O
taken O
. O

I O
suppose O
that O
this O
happened O
because O
there O
was O
a O
letter B-TER
from O
the O
Lithuanian B-LOC
consulate O
in O
my O
pocket O
. O

When O
I O
exited O
the O
building O
of O
the O
Hitlerjugend O
, O
a O
teenager O
keeping O
watch O
pushed O
me O
. O

On O
my O
way O
back O
home O
, O
there O
is O
an O
assembly O
point O
for O
Germanrefugees O
( O
non O
- O
Jews O
) O
. O

I O
did O
not O
manage O
to O
reach O
my O
home O
as O
I O
was O
dragged O
to O
work B-TER
again O
at O
the O
assembly O
point O
. O

I O
showed O
my O
dirty O
hands O
from O
work B-TER
arguing O
that O
I O
can O
not O
work B-TER
any O
longer O
. O

It O
did O
not O
help O
. O

Finally O
, O
a O
Jew O
, O
an O
acquaintance O
of O
mine O
called O
Moler B-PER
, O
a O
57 O
- O
years O
old O
traveling O
salesman O
, O
requested O
to O
let O
me O
go O
. O

Good O
, O
the O
German B-TER
said O
, O
but O
you O
will O
have O
to O
work O
for O
two O
: O
for O
yourself O
and O
for O
her O
. O

And O
so O
it O
was O
: O
Moler B-PER
was O
carrying O
coal O
for O
himself O
, O
and O
for O
me O
, O
he O
was O
scrubbing O
floors O
. O

Such O
work B-TER
was O
not O
necessary O
at O
all O
. O

The O
only O
goal O
was O
to O
torture B-TER
Jews O
and O
to O
make O
fun O
off O
them O
. O

They O
force O
one O
Jew O
, O
for O
instance O
, O
to O
beat O
another O
one O
. O

Or O
after O
work B-TER
, O
for O
example O
, O
they O
arrange O
the O
Jews O
in O
a O
row O
and O
order O
them O
to O
sing O
in O
a O
choir O
: O
We O
Jews O
are O
responsible O
for O
the O
war O
. O

Afterwards O
, O
they O
start O
to O
beat O
the O
Jews O
for O
the O
very O
reason O
that O
they O
are O
responsible O
for O
the O
war O
. O

They O
also O
force O
Jews O
to O
catch O
other O
Jews O
to O
work B-TER
by O
taking O
a O
Jew O
’s O
documents O
and O
threatening O
him O
to O
be O
taken O
to O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
if O
he O
does O
not O
deliver O
a O
certain O
number O
of O
Jews O
. O

Generally O
, O
Jews O
are O
treated O
like O
slaves B-TER
. O

The O
following O
cases O
might O
serve O
as O
an O
example O
: O
if O
a O
soldier B-TER
wants O
to O
get O
his O
shoes O
cleaned O
on O
Sundays O
, O
he O
goes O
out O
on O
the O
street O
and O
takes O
a O
Jew O
into O
the O
barracks O
to O
clean O
his O
shoes O
; O
if O
a O
German B-TER
, O
a O
military B-ORG
man I-ORG
or O
civilian O
, O
is O
carrying O
a O
bundle O
on O
the O
street O
, O
and O
it O
is O
too O
heavy O
for O
him O
, O
he O
catches O
the O
first O
Jew O
on O
the O
street O
and O
forces O
him O
to O
carry O
the O
bundle O
. O

I O
saw O
the O
following O
scene O
: O
In O
front O
of O
a O
heavy O
truck O
, O
four O
Jews O
were O
harnessed O
instead O
of O
horses O
, O
and O
two O
Jews O
were O
pushing O
the O
wagon O
from O
behind O
. O

A O
German B-TER
was O
beating O
the O
Jews O
with O
whips O
. O

Seared O
into O
every O
German B-TER
’s O
mind O
was O
the O
believe O
that O
the O
Jew O
is O
his O
slave B-TER
. O

Into O
our O
yard O
, O
a O
12- B-TER
to I-TER
13 B-TER
- I-TER
year I-TER
old I-TER
young B-TER
German B-TER
from O
the O
Hitlerjugend O
came O
driving O
on O
a O
bicycle O
. O

On O
the O
yard O
, O
Jewish O
children B-TER
were O
playing O
whom O
the O
German B-TER
forced O
to O
clean O
his O
bicycle O
. O

And O
the O
young O
German B-TER
said O
: O
You O
, O
Jews O
, O
are O
our O
servants O
. O

Also O
Jewish O
women B-TER
are O
captured O
for O
work B-TER
, O
regardless O
of O
their O
age O
, O
also O
children B-TER
from O
the O
age O
ten O
onwards O
. O

There O
was O
a O
case O
when O
on O
Gdańsk B-LOC
Street I-LOC
90 I-LOC
when O
the O
Germans B-TER
hit O
a O
Jewish O
woman B-TER
and O
broke O
her O
head O
into O
pieces O
. O

This O
woman B-TER
, O
who O
was O
dragged O
to O
work B-TER
, O
was O
over O
sixty O
years O
old O
. O

How O
the O
Germans B-TER
ripped O
away O
the O
trade B-TER
of O
Jews O
in O
Łódź B-LOC
Soon O
, O
two O
- O
three O
weeks O
after O
the O
Germans B-TER
had O
occupied B-TER
Łódź B-LOC
, O
they O
issued O
a O
decree B-TER
that O
the O
Jewish O
bakeries O
are O
prohibited O
from O
baking O
bread B-TER
. O

When O
the O
Jews O
were O
standing O
in O
the O
line O
of O
Christian B-TER
bakeries O
, O
they O
were O
pushed O
out O
of O
the O
lines O
. O

Even O
Poles B-TER
were O
pointing O
their O
fingers O
calling O
out O
: O
Jude O
! O
Jude O
! O
4 O
- O
6 O
weeks O
after O
the O
Germans B-TER
invaded O
Łódź B-LOC
, O
new O
decrees B-TER
against O
Jews O
started O
pouring O
out O
every O
day O
. O

All O
Jews O
had O
to O
report O
how O
much O
they O
owned O
. O

One O
was O
allowed O
to O
have O
up O
to O
two O
thousand O
Złoty O
, O
and O
the O
rest O
of O
the O
money O
had O
to O
be O
transferred O
to O
a O
blocked O
account O
. O

All O
Jews O
who O
owned O
stores O
, O
warehouses O
, O
factories B-TER
had O
to O
give O
notice O
of O
their O
merchandise O
and O
of O
their O
raw O
material O
and O
to O
seal O
everything O
until O
a O
new O
decree B-TER
[ O
is O
issued O
] O
. O

The O
small O
shops O
were O
automatically O
closed O
down O
this O
way O
. O

The O
bigger O
company O
factories B-TER
and O
warehouses O
were O
occupied O
by O
German B-TER
commissioners O
– O
so O
- O
called O
“ O
depositaries B-TER
. O

” O
The O
whole O
power O
was O
de O
facto O
transferred O
to O
the O
German B-TER
commissioner O
, O
and O
the O
real O
owner O
was O
nothing O
more O
than O
mere O
observer O
in O
his O
own O
store O
. O

In O
a O
big O
factory B-TER
or O
store O
, O
the O
owner O
received O
approximately O
200 O
Złoty O
per O
week O
and O
the O
rest O
of O
the O
money O
was O
transferred O
to O
the O
blocked O
account O
. O

In O
the O
big O
stores O
, O
one O
was O
allowed O
to O
sell O
merchandise O
to O
military B-ORG
personnel I-ORG
and O
Christians B-TER
. O

To O
Jews O
, O
one O
was O
not O
permitted O
to O
sell O
anything O
. O

In O
this O
transaction O
, O
the O
Jewish O
owner O
only O
took O
on O
the O
role O
of O
an O
observer O
. O

He O
did O
not O
collect O
the O
money O
. O

The O
Jewish O
money O
on O
the O
blocked O
accounts O
was O
put O
into O
different O
banks B-TER
. O

All O
banks B-TER
were O
shut O
down O
except O
for O
two O
German B-TER
banking B-TER
houses I-TER
where O
Jews O
usually O
did O
not O
hold O
their O
capital O
. O

In O
this O
way O
, O
the O
Jewish O
wealth O
was O
ruined O
in O
Łódź B-LOC
. O

Coinciding O
with O
the O
large O
scale O
industry O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
also O
destroyed O
Jewish O
small O
industry O
and O
Jewish B-TER
retail I-TER
trading I-TER
. O

On O
Vskhadnye B-LOC
Street I-LOC
, O
for O
example O
, O
the O
Jews O
were O
trading B-TER
frank O
and O
free O
with O
bread B-TER
, O
socks O
, O
reforms O
uncertain O
. O

etc O
. O

An O
order O
was O
issued O
saying O
that O
trade B-TER
on O
the O
street O
is O
banned O
. O

Another O
order O
was O
published O
that O
all O
Jewish O
coachmans O
have O
to O
give O
away O
their O
horse O
- O
drawn O
coaches O
together O
with O
the O
horses O
; O
the O
Jews O
in O
return O
received O
a O
receipt O
over O
a O
few O
Mark O
. O

The O
Jewish O
coachman O
and O
driver O
disappeared O
from O
Łódź B-LOC
. O

On O
November O
5 O
, O
1939 O
, O
a O
decree B-TER
was O
issued O
that O
Christian B-TER
stores O
are O
prohibited O
to O
sell O
anything O
to O
Jews O
. O

And O
one O
had O
to O
put O
up O
a O
leaflet O
[ O
saying O
] O
: O
Juden O
Eintritt O
verbotenJews O
entry O
forbidden O
.. O
A O
Jew O
had O
to O
beg O
one O
of O
his O
Christian B-TER
friends O
to O
buy O
shoes O
etc O
. O

for O
him O
. O

Also O
the O
peasants O
, O
who O
come O
to O
the O
city O
Łódź B-LOC
, O
were O
forced O
not O
to O
sell O
anything O
to O
a O
Jew O
. O

The O
peasants O
secretly O
sold O
Jews O
food B-TER
and O
did O
not O
take O
more O
money O
for O
it O
. O

In O
every O
sense O
, O
Jews O
were O
in O
a O
very O
difficult O
situation O
because O
food B-TER
was O
not O
sold O
to O
them O
in O
the O
stores O
cheaper O
and O
they O
were O
being O
chased O
out O
of O
the O
lines O
[ O
in O
front O
of O
the O
stores O
] O
. O

The O
life O
of O
the O
Jews O
was O
literally O
paralyzed O
. O

All O
buildings O
of O
the O
Jewish B-TER
schools I-TER
were O
soon O
occupied O
by O
the O
Germans B-TER
and O
the O
Jewish O
children B-TER
from O
these O
schools B-TER
studied O
in O
private O
apartments O
in O
3 O
shifts O
– O
from O
9 O
am O
to O
5 O
pm O
. O

The O
Yellow B-TER
Badge I-TER
The O
decree B-TER
regarding O
the O
yellow B-TER
badge I-TER
for O
Jews O
came O
out O
on O
November O
6 O
or O
7 O
, O
1939 O
. O

The O
decree B-TER
says O
that O
Jews O
– O
women B-TER
, O
men O
and O
children B-TER
– O
have O
to O
wear O
the O
yellow B-TER
badge I-TER
. O

On O
strollers O
of O
small O
children B-TER
, O
the O
yellow B-TER
badge I-TER
has O
to O
be O
attached O
. O

Jews O
who O
do O
not O
wear O
the O
yellow B-TER
badge I-TER
get O
the O
death B-TER
penalty O
. O

The O
decree B-TER
had O
a O
dreadful O
effect O
on O
the O
Jewish O
population O
. O

The O
Polish B-TER
intelligentsia O
felt O
very O
sorry O
for O
the O
Jews O
. O

The O
Polish B-TER
mob O
, O
in O
contrast O
, O
reacted O
to O
the O
Jews O
with O
their O
yellow B-TER
badges I-TER
with O
a O
mocking O
smile O
on O
their O
faces O
. O

Older O
local O
Germans B-TER
pretended O
that O
they O
do O
not O
see O
the O
yellow B-TER
badge I-TER
. O

The O
younger O
local O
Germans B-TER
reacted O
to O
it O
with O
content O
. O

Jews O
that O
had O
converted O
to O
Christianity B-TER
did O
not O
wear O
any O
badge B-TER
. O

Around O
November O
10 O
, O
a O
decree B-TER
came O
out O
pursuant O
to O
which O
it O
was O
prohibited O
to O
walk O
on O
Pyetrykover B-LOC
Street I-LOC
. O

Jews O
who O
lived O
on O
Pyetrykover B-LOC
Street I-LOC
had O
to O
buy O
passing O
permits O
for O
20 O
Złoty O
per O
month O
. O

They O
were O
allowed O
to O
walk O
on O
Pyetrykover B-LOC
Street I-LOC
only O
until O
11 O
am O
. O

This O
created O
huge O
difficulties O
for O
the O
Jewish O
population O
in O
their O
everyday O
life O
since O
the O
Pyetrykover B-LOC
Street I-LOC
cuts O
through O
the O
whole O
city O
and O
one O
has O
to O
cross O
Pyetrykover B-LOC
Street I-LOC
in O
order O
to O
make O
one O
’s O
way O
on O
one O
or O
the O
other O
side O
. O

Jews O
used O
to O
take O
a O
risk O
and O
jumped O
over O
from O
one O
street O
corner O
to O
the O
other O
side O
. O

This O
always O
ended O
in O
getting O
beaten O
up O
heavily O
and O
even O
in O
getting O
arrested B-TER
because O
on O
all O
street O
corners O
police B-ORG
guards I-ORG
or O
SS B-ORG
men I-ORG
were O
standing O
. O

To O
this O
day O
, O
the O
prisons B-TER
in O
Łódź B-LOC
are O
overcrowded O
with O
Jews O
, O
even O
with O
women B-TER
and O
children B-TER
who O
sinned O
by O
crossing O
Pyetrykover B-LOC
Street I-LOC
. O

To O
this O
day O
, O
no O
one O
of O
the O
detainees O
has O
been O
released O
. O

The O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
intervened O
but O
without O
success O
. O

Around O
November O
13 O
, O
a O
decree B-TER
appeared O
that O
Jews O
are O
allowed O
to O
walk O
[ O
on O
the O
streets O
] O
from O
8 O
am O
to O
5 O
pm O
. O

In O
the O
morning O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
used O
to O
turn O
back O
the O
pointer O
on O
their O
watches O
by O
a O
few O
minutes O
or O
, O
in O
the O
evening O
, O
turn O
it O
forward O
and O
they O
arrested B-TER
Jews O
accusing O
them O
of O
being O
on O
the O
street O
too O
early O
or O
of O
walking O
around O
too O
late O
. O

And O
the O
detainees O
have O
not O
been O
released O
to O
this O
day O
. O

Relatives O
of O
the O
detainees O
were O
refused O
any O
information O
and O
were O
told O
to O
leave O
threatening O
them O
that O
they O
will O
arrest O
those O
intervening O
as O
well O
. O

People O
became O
aware O
of O
the O
detainees O
only O
because O
the O
detainees O
, O
who O
receive O
parcels O
from O
outside O
three O
times O
per O
week O
, O
usually O
took O
pains O
to O
get O
out O
slips O
of O
paper O
with O
the O
names O
of O
those O
who O
are O
detained O
with O
the O
receptacles O
. O

Food B-TER
and O
warm O
clothes B-TER
were O
permitted O
. O

Food B-TER
and O
packages O
were O
usually O
permitted O
in O
the O
prisons B-TER
on O
Tuesdays O
, O
Thursdays O
and O
Shabbats O
– O
on O
all O
of O
these O
days O
, O
one O
could O
see O
large O
numbers O
of O
Jews O
in O
front O
of O
the O
prisons B-TER
. O

Soon O
, O
in O
the O
first O
days O
, O
after O
the O
Germans B-TER
had O
invaded O
Łódź B-LOC
, O
Jews O
started O
to O
be O
kicked O
out O
of O
their O
apartments O
. O

This O
happened O
in O
the O
following O
way O
: O
1 O
) O
The O
Germans B-TER
– O
military B-ORG
people I-ORG
, O
led O
by O
civilian O
local O
Germans B-TER
– O
usually O
entered O
a O
Jewish O
apartment O
and O
ordered O
them O
to O
leave O
[ O
their O
apartment O
] O
within O
two O
hours O
. O

They O
were O
only O
allowed O
to O
take O
things O
except O
for O
furniture O
. O

2 O
) O
They O
usually O
came O
into O
Jewish O
apartments O
and O
ordered O
[ O
the O
Jews O
] O
to O
leave O
the O
apartment O
– O
without O
any O
right O
to O
take O
anything O
with O
them O
. O

3 O
) O
They O
usually O
entered O
the O
apartments O
of O
rich O
Jews O
– O
ordered O
them O
to O
leave O
the O
apartment O
within O
2 O
hours O
and O
to O
take O
things O
– O
except O
for O
furniture O
. O

When O
the O
residents O
went O
out O
with O
their O
things O
, O
a O
guard O
, O
a O
soldier O
or O
SS B-ORG
man I-ORG
, O
was O
usually O
standing O
in O
front O
of O
the O
gate O
and O
they O
took O
the O
things O
away O
from O
the O
Jews O
. O

4 O
) O
Also O
, O
they O
occupied O
whole O
residential O
blocks O
with O
apartments O
of O
very O
poor O
Jews O
. O

There O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
prepared O
apartments O
for O
the O
Baltic O
Germans B-TER
. O

They O
forced O
[ O
the O
Jews O
] O
to O
clean O
up O
the O
apartments O
, O
to O
put O
fresh O
sheets O
on O
the O
beds O
. O

They O
were O
not O
permitted O
to O
take O
anything O
with O
them O
. O

All O
Jews O
living O
on O
Magistratske B-LOC
Street I-LOC
20 I-LOC
, I-LOC
21 I-LOC
, I-LOC
22 I-LOC
, O
for O
instance O
, O
were O
kicked O
out O
like O
that O
. O

The O
apartments O
stand O
empty O
to O
this O
day O
because O
the O
Baltic O
Germans B-TER
have O
n’t O
arrived O
yet O
. O

The O
looting B-TER
of O
Jewish O
apartments O
started O
in O
the O
early O
days O
of O
the O
Germans B-TER
in O
Łódź B-LOC
, O
which O
has O
taken O
on O
a O
much O
more O
systematic O
nature O
. O

They O
even O
carry O
furniture O
out O
of O
the O
apartments O
. O

There O
is O
almost O
no O
Jewish O
house O
from O
which O
they O
have O
n’t O
carried O
out O
underwear O
, O
clothes B-TER
or O
furniture O
and O
food B-TER
yet O
. O

In O
the O
looting B-TER
, O
higher O
officers O
participated O
as O
much O
as O
German B-TER
militiamen B-TER
, O
soldiers B-TER
and O
civilians O
with O
swastika B-TER
. O

The O
local O
Germans B-TER
usually O
pointed O
to O
the O
rich O
Jewish O
houses O
. O

Allegedly O
, O
they O
were O
searching O
for O
weapons O
but O
in O
doing O
so O
they O
took O
all O
the O
valuable O
things O
. O

For O
example O
, O
in O
the O
first O
October O
days O
, O
they O
robbed B-TER
from O
Glas B-PER
( O
Koperniko B-LOC
Street I-LOC
23 I-LOC
) O
– O
looking O
for O
weapons O
– O
beautiful O
furs O
. O

On O
Narutovitsha B-LOC
Street I-LOC
47 I-LOC
, O
in O
engineer O
Fromes B-PER
’ O
house O
, O
they O
robbed B-TER
a O
bigger O
sum O
of O
money O
and O
pulled O
off O
2 O
diamond O
rings O
from O
the O
fingers O
, O
and O
from O
the O
wrist O
– O
a O
golden O
watch O
. O

In O
the O
first O
days O
of O
December O
, O
they O
surrounded O
the O
streets O
Paludnyave B-LOC
, I-LOC
Kilinski I-LOC
, I-LOC
Pamarske I-LOC
. O

They O
allegedly O
searched O
for O
secret O
radio O
stations O
and O
robbed B-TER
the O
Jewish O
apartments O
. O

In O
the O
streets O
of O
Łódź B-LOC
one O
can O
see O
now O
how O
the O
masses O
of O
poorest O
Germans B-TER
are O
dressed O
elegantly O
in O
furs O
. O

Their O
apartments O
are O
opulently O
furnished O
. O

One O
could O
also O
see O
on O
the O
streets O
in O
evening O
hours O
, O
at O
dusk O
, O
how O
uniformed O
soldier B-TER
and O
civilian O
Germans B-TER
with O
swastika B-TER
led O
Jews O
through O
the O
gates O
, O
ostensibly O
looking O
for O
weapons O
, O
ordering O
them O
to O
lift O
the O
hands O
and O
taking O
watches O
, O
briefcases O
, O
money O
and O
generally O
valuable O
objects O
. O

In O
the O
first O
days O
of O
December O
, O
my O
neighbor O
, O
the O
factory B-TER
owner O
Volf B-PER
Frenkl I-PER
, O
Magistratske B-LOC
25 I-LOC
, O
was O
stopped O
in O
his O
gateway O
and O
when O
they O
searched O
him O
, O
they O
took O
away O
a O
briefcase O
with O
400 O
Złoty O
. O

Soldiers B-TER
used O
to O
stop O
Jewish O
women B-TER
as O
well O
asking O
how O
much O
money O
they O
had O
threatening O
them O
that O
if O
they O
understate O
the O
sum O
, O
it O
will O
be O
bad O
. O

The O
soldiers B-TER
used O
to O
take O
all O
of O
the O
money O
which O
they O
found O
with O
the O
victims O
of O
their O
arbitrariness O
. O

On O
the O
basis O
of O
decrees B-TER
, O
they O
used O
to O
take O
out O
all O
the O
goods O
of O
full O
warehouses O
. O

For O
example O
, O
they O
took O
away O
all O
the O
merchandise O
at O
the O
end O
of O
November O
here O
: O
From O
the O
pharmacy O
warehouse O
Pomerants B-PER
, O
Petrykover B-LOC
17 I-LOC
, O
From O
the O
pharmacy O
of O
Yankelevitsh B-PER
, O
Kastshelna B-LOC
21 I-LOC
( O
during O
it O
, O
they O
forced O
Yankelevitsh B-PER
to O
load O
the O
merchandise O
on O
the O
wagon O
himself O
. O

When O
he O
tried O
to O
let O
his O
employee O
do O
it O
, O
they O
hit O
Yankelevitsh B-PER
) O
. O

From O
the O
pharmacy O
Roznblum B-PER
, O
on O
the O
corner O
Trudmeyske B-LOC
/ I-LOC
Vultshinske I-LOC
( O
the O
wealthiest O
Jewish O
pharmacy O
) O
, O
From O
Perlman B-PER
, O
Tsigl B-LOC
Street I-LOC
37 I-LOC
. O

They O
systematically O
emptied O
the O
factory B-TER
warehouses O
of O
manufacture O
. O

The O
owners O
received O
receipts O
but O
no O
money O
. O

Jewelers O
were O
confiscated O
, O
inventoried O
and O
the O
keys O
were O
left O
with O
the O
owners O
. O

In O
some O
pharmacies O
, O
German B-TER
commissioners O
were O
installed O
, O
so O
- O
called O
depositaries O
( O
... O
) O
and O
until O
January O
1 O
the O
owners O
were O
inside O
, O
too O
. O

From O
other O
pharmacies O
, O
the O
Jews O
were O
immediately O
removed O
and O
German B-TER
pharmacists O
from O
Pomerania B-LOC
and O
Poznań B-LOC
were O
installed O
. O

During O
the O
first O
days O
, O
it O
seemed O
that O
the O
Germans B-TER
were O
not O
interested O
in O
social O
and O
political O
activists O
. O

The O
only O
one O
who O
the O
Germans B-TER
were O
looking O
for O
soon O
during O
the O
first O
days O
was O
the O
former O
head O
of O
the O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
Mintsberg B-PER
. O

Soon O
in O
the O
first O
days O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
came O
with O
the O
question O
: O
Where O
is O
the O
dog O
Mintsberg O
. O

They O
first O
threw O
themselves O
on O
revisionists O
. O

The O
leaders O
escaped O
, O
only O
the O
lower O
ranking O
activists O
stayed O
. O

They O
arrested B-TER
all O
who O
had O
the O
smallest O
connection O
to O
Zionism B-TER
, O
also O
all O
members O
of O
Maccabi O
, O
for O
example O
, O
engineer O
Vinerman B-PER
( O
he O
was O
released O
after O
7 O
weeks O
, O
on O
November O
11 O
they O
wanted O
to O
arrest B-TER
him O
again O
, O
but O
he O
was O
not O
Łódź B-LOC
anymore O
) O
, O
Dr. B-PER
Bresholts I-PER
from O
Hitakhdut O
and O
others O
, O
Miss O
Reznikov B-PER
, O
55 O
years O
old O
, O
from O
WIZO O
[ O
Women B-ORG
’s I-ORG
International I-ORG
Zionist I-ORG
Organization I-ORG
] O
( O
was O
released O
after O
6 O
weeks O
) O
. O

They O
did O
not O
touch O
communists O
at O
all O
. O

Around O
2 O
to O
3 O
weeks O
it O
was O
at O
first O
calm O
for O
other O
political O
activists O
. O

Later O
, O
they O
started O
to O
arrest B-TER
the O
members O
of O
the O
advisory O
council O
of O
the O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
that O
the O
Germans B-TER
had O
nominated O
. O

24 O
men B-TER
were O
arrested B-TER
( O
only O
Rumkowski B-PER
not O
) O
. O

What O
happened O
to O
them O
is O
not O
known O
. O

Rumkowski B-PER
’s O
intervention O
did O
not O
lead O
to O
anything O
. O

They O
arrested B-TER
the O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
clerk O
Kenig B-PER
. I-PER

When O
Rumkowski B-PER
intervened O
at O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
on O
Zgyerzsher B-LOC
115 I-LOC
, O
he O
was O
beaten O
bloody O
. O

On O
Zgyerzsher B-LOC
115 I-LOC
at O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
, O
a O
special O
commission O
was O
installed O
to O
torture B-TER
the O
arrested B-TER
Jews O
. O

From O
the O
cafe O
Astoria O
, O
they O
took O
out O
20 O
Jews O
( O
this O
was O
on O
November O
5 O
or O
6 O
) O
. O

They O
were O
ordered O
to O
come O
to O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
on O
the O
next O
day O
in O
order O
to O
reclaim O
the O
documents O
. O

There O
, O
15 O
were O
shot B-TER
dead I-TER
. O

And O
the O
5 O
who O
stayed O
alive O
had O
to O
bury O
the O
rest O
. O

Later O
, O
the O
5 O
were O
released O
, O
and O
this O
is O
how O
people O
learned O
about O
the O
execution B-TER
. O

These O
5 O
released O
ones O
were O
beaten O
up O
well O
before O
they O
were O
released O
and O
were O
prohibited O
to O
tell O
anything O
. O

Among O
the O
executed B-TER
ones O
there O
were O
the O
following O
: O
1 O
) O
Khaymovitsh B-PER
– O
merchant O
, O
Piromovitsh B-LOC
Street I-LOC
4 I-LOC
, O
2 O
) O
Perts B-PER
– O
wealthy O
manufacturer O
, O
3 O
) O
Levin B-PER
– O
traveling O
salesman O
, O
Petrikover B-LOC
109 I-LOC
, O
4 O
) O
Geyer B-PER
– O
manufacturer O
. O

The O
5 O
released O
ones O
were O
present O
when O
Rumkowski B-PER
came O
to O
intervene O
in O
the O
matter O
of O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
clerk O
Kenig B-PER
. O

The O
conversation O
was O
as O
follows O
: O
Rumkowski B-PER
: O
You O
arrested B-TER
the O
clerk O
from O
the O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
called O
Kenig B-PER
who O
works O
in O
the O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
nominated O
by O
you O
. O

The O
Gestapo B-ORG
- I-ORG
chief I-ORG
: O
Who O
are O
you O
? O
Rumkowski B-PER
: O
I O
am O
the O
Elder O
from O
the O
Jews O
. O

The O
Gestapo B-ORG
- I-ORG
chief I-ORG
: O
Ah O
, O
since O
you O
are O
the O
Elder O
of O
the O
Jews O
, O
you O
’ll O
get O
something O
for O
all O
the O
rest O
of O
your O
Jews O
. O

He O
gave O
a O
sign O
and O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
agents I-ORG
started O
to O
beat O
Rumkowski B-PER
up O
brutally O
. O

( O
Kenig B-PER
, O
the O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
clerk O
, O
remains O
in O
jail B-TER
to O
this O
day O
, O
and O
nobody O
knows O
where O
he O
is O
) O
. O

In O
the O
middle O
of O
this O
scene O
, O
the O
military B-ORG
city I-ORG
commander I-ORG
entered O
. O

Military B-ORG
city I-ORG
commander I-ORG
: O
I O
, O
the O
military B-ORG
city I-ORG
commander I-ORG
, O
come O
for O
the O
sir O
you O
are O
beating O
. O

Gestapo B-ORG
chief I-ORG
: O
Where O
is O
a O
sir O
here O
? O
The B-ORG
city I-ORG
commander I-ORG
: O
The O
sir O
who O
was O
nominated O
by O
me O
to O
be O
the O
Elder O
of O
the O
Jews O
. O

Gestapo B-ORG
chief I-ORG
: O
I O
do O
n’t O
know O
a O
sir O
here O
whatsoever O
, O
this O
there O
is O
a O
Jew O
. O

The B-ORG
city I-ORG
commander I-ORG
: O
The O
sir O
is O
untouchable O
and O
you O
are O
not O
allowed O
to O
beat O
him O
. O

Gestapo B-ORG
chief I-ORG
: O
Right O
now O
, O
he O
is O
not O
untouchable O
. O

In O
any O
case O
, O
he O
is O
my O
Jew O
and O
I O
do O
with O
him O
what O
I O
want O
. O

The B-ORG
city I-ORG
commander I-ORG
: O
No O
, O
the O
sir O
is O
my O
Jew O
and O
I O
ask O
for O
his O
release O
and O
to O
escort O
him O
to O
his O
car O
which O
is O
waiting O
for O
him O
. O

Gestapo B-ORG
chief I-ORG
: O
No O
, O
I O
wo O
n’t O
let O
him O
go O
and O
do O
whatever O
I O
will O
be O
doing O
. O

The B-ORG
city I-ORG
commander I-ORG
: O
I O
am O
( O
listing O
his O
title O
) O
and O
I O
demand O
that O
my O
Jew O
will O
be O
released O
. O

Gestapo B-ORG
chief I-ORG
: O
And O
I O
am O
first O
lieutenant O
and O
Gestapo B-ORG
chief I-ORG
. O

I O
am O
the O
boss O
here O
. O

The B-ORG
city I-ORG
commander I-ORG
: O
The O
sir O
is O
the O
Elder O
and O
he O
holds O
the O
office O
on O
my O
behalf O
. O

I O
demand O
that O
he O
will O
be O
released O
. O

Gestapo B-ORG
chief I-ORG
: O
( O
already O
gentler O
) O
But O
our O
conversation O
does O
n’t O
have O
to O
take O
place O
in O
front O
of O
witnesses O
. O

The B-ORG
city I-ORG
commander I-ORG
: O
As O
you O
wish O
… O
They O
both O
went O
into O
an O
office O
. O

In O
the O
meantime O
, O
Rumkowski B-PER
did O
not O
recover O
from O
the O
punches O
he O
received O
earlier O
. O

He O
tried O
to O
revive O
himself O
with O
drops O
which O
he O
always O
carries O
with O
him O
( O
he O
suffers O
from O
heart O
problems O
) O
. O

The O
Gestapo B-ORG
chief I-ORG
feared O
that O
Rumkowski B-PER
wants O
to O
poison O
himself O
. O

So O
he O
did O
not O
permit O
him O
to O
take O
the O
drops O
but O
called O
a O
German B-TER
doctor B-TER
who O
examined O
him O
and O
gave O
him O
drops O
. O

What O
the O
two O
Germans B-TER
discussed O
amongst O
each O
other O
in O
the O
office O
is O
not O
known O
. O

After O
the O
conversation O
, O
Rumkowski B-PER
was O
released O
. O

The O
five O
buriers O
were O
present O
during O
the O
whole O
time O
of O
the O
conversation O
. O

Disregarding O
the O
prohibition O
not O
to O
tell O
anyone O
about O
the O
murder B-TER
of O
the O
fifteen O
Jews O
, O
they O
informed O
the O
families B-TER
about O
it O
. O

Mass O
arrests B-TER
of O
social O
activists O
and O
of O
representatives O
of O
the O
upper O
classes O
started O
. O

Of O
the O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
’s O
advisory O
council O
the O
following O
were O
arrested B-TER
: O
The O
lawyer O
Rubin B-PER
, O
2 O
) O
the O
lawyer O
Glater B-PER
, O
3 O
) O
Dr. O
Shloser B-PER
( O
he O
had O
great O
influence O
amongst O
the O
Germans B-TER
, O
because O
he O
organized O
medical O
points O
) O
, O
4 O
) O
Levshpey B-PER
Uncertain O
spelling O
. O

, O
5 O
) O
Shtal B-PER
, O
6 O
) O
Hofman B-PER
. O

Also O
the O
following O
were O
arrested B-TER
: O
1 O
) O
Rozenfeld B-PER
– O
manufacturer O
of O
socks O
, O
head O
of O
the O
union O
for O
sock O
manufacturers O
( O
he O
was O
later O
shot B-TER
to I-TER
death I-TER
) O
. O

2 O
) O
Piotr B-PER
Khary I-PER
– O
head O
of O
the O
union O
of O
merchants O
Pamarske B-LOC
15 I-LOC
. O

3 O
) O
Nayman B-PER
– O
head O
of O
the O
artisan O
union O
. O

4 O
) O
Tsimerman B-PER
– O
member O
of O
the O
administration O
of O
the O
artisan O
union O
. O

5 O
) O
Shvartsman B-PER
– O
member O
of O
the O
administration O
of O
merchants O
’ O
union O
. O

From O
the O
upper O
classes O
the O
following O
were O
arrested B-TER
: O
Kaminski B-PER
– O
mechanical O
textile O
factory B-TER
. O

Bartshinski B-PER
– O
mechanical O
textile O
factory B-TER
. O

Hofman B-PER
– O
mechanical O
textile O
factory B-TER
. O

Nothing O
is O
known O
about O
the O
fate O
of O
the O
arrested B-TER
. O

Khary B-PER
was O
not O
at O
home O
when O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
came O
so O
that O
they O
took O
his O
16 O
- O
year O
old O
son B-TER
. O

The O
next O
day O
, O
the O
father B-TER
presented O
himself O
to O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
and O
his O
son B-TER
was O
released O
. O

They O
also O
used O
to O
arrest B-TER
women B-TER
if O
their O
men O
were O
not O
there O
. O

In O
this O
way O
, O
the O
bankier B-TER
Shif B-PER
’s O
wife B-TER
got O
arrested B-TER
and O
Shif B-PER
is O
not O
at O
home O
in O
general O
. O

They O
looked O
for O
Filman B-PER
( O
city O
councilman O
of O
the O
city B-LOC
hall I-LOC
) O
. O

In O
the O
meantime O
, O
they O
arrested B-TER
his O
wife B-TER
and O
son B-TER
. O

Filman B-PER
himself O
had O
fled O
. O

Before O
November O
11 O
, O
mass O
arrest B-TER
of O
the O
P.P.S. B-ORG
[ O
Polska B-ORG
Partia I-ORG
Socjalistyczna I-ORG
] O
, O
Bund O
and O
of O
communists O
started O
: O
After O
the O
invasion O
of O
the O
Germans B-TER
, O
all O
communist O
had O
been O
released O
. O

Now O
, O
they O
were O
arrested B-TER
anew O
and O
send O
off O
to O
Dachau B-LOC
. O

From O
the O
P.P.S. B-ORG
, O
they O
arrested B-TER
and O
shot B-TER
to I-TER
death I-TER
Aleksey B-PER
Rzshevski I-PER
. O

They O
arrested B-TER
the O
democrat O
Dr. O
Tomashevitsh B-PER
– O
city O
councilman O
. O

From O
the O
Bund O
, O
Poznanski B-PER
, O
Roze B-PER
Eykhner I-PER
were O
arrested B-TER
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
anticipated O
that O
on O
November O
11 O
, O
the O
21st O
anniversary O
of O
the O
Polish B-TER
independence O
, O
riots O
will O
break O
out O
in O
the O
city O
. O

In O
order O
to O
scare O
off O
the O
residents O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
did O
the O
following O
: O
very O
early O
in O
the O
morning O
on O
November O
11 O
, O
people O
noticed O
nine O
hanged B-TER
individuals O
in O
the O
city O
– O
three O
men O
on O
Liberty B-LOC
Square I-LOC
three O
men O
on O
the O
Green B-LOC
Market I-LOC
Square I-LOC
two O
men O
and O
one O
woman B-TER
on O
the O
Bałuty B-LOC
Market I-LOC
The O
faces O
of O
the O
9 O
hanged O
were O
blackened O
, O
smeared O
with O
ream O
so O
that O
it O
was O
impossible O
to O
recognize O
who O
it O
is O
. O

The O
whole O
city B-LOC
was O
terrified O
. O

On O
November O
12 O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
took O
down O
the O
hanged B-TER
from O
the O
gallows O
. O

On O
the O
11th O
, O
there O
was O
no O
attempt O
of O
rioting O
in O
the O
city B-LOC
. O

The O
hanged B-TER
shook O
the O
city B-LOC
to O
its O
core O
. O

Before O
November O
11 O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
blew O
up O
the O
Kashtshushki B-LOC
monument I-LOC
on I-LOC
Liberty I-LOC
Square I-LOC
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
only O
took O
Poles B-TER
to O
work B-TER
and O
clean O
up O
the O
rests O
of O
the O
monument O
. O

Amongst O
the O
Poles B-TER
, O
this O
led O
to O
a O
dreadful O
agitation O
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
were O
eagerly O
looking O
for O
the O
Bundist B-ORG
Zelmanovitsh B-PER
and O
Filman B-PER
, O
for O
the O
Zionist B-TER
Dr. O
Shvayg B-PER
and O
generally O
for O
political O
activists O
. O

The O
expulsion O
of O
the O
Jews O
from O
the O
environs O
of O
Łódź B-LOC
In O
the O
middle O
of O
the O
month O
of O
November O
, O
around O
the O
15th O
, O
news O
made O
their O
way O
to O
Łódź B-LOC
that O
the O
Germans B-TER
expulse O
the O
Jews O
from O
the O
border O
cities O
and O
from O
the O
cities O
that O
were O
incorporated O
into O
the O
German B-TER
Reich I-TER
. O

The O
first O
city O
from O
where O
Jews O
were O
expelled O
was O
Kalisz B-LOC
. O

The O
expulsion O
from O
Kalisz B-LOC
Thirteen O
thousand O
( O
13.000 O
) O
Jews O
lived O
in O
Kalisz B-LOC
. O

From O
the O
refugees B-TER
from O
Kalisz B-LOC
, O
who O
came O
to O
Łódź B-LOC
, O
we O
learned O
in O
detail O
how O
the O
expulsion O
of O
the O
Jews O
was O
carried O
out O
. O

Kalisz B-LOC
Jews O
were O
sitting O
at O
home O
not O
suspecting O
any O
decree B-TER
[ O
to O
be O
issued O
] O
. O

The O
female O
guard O
of O
the O
house O
appeared O
in O
front O
of O
the O
Jews O
and O
announced O
that O
they O
should O
gather O
in O
the O
yard O
. O

The O
Jews O
came O
down O
immediately O
as O
they O
were O
dressed O
, O
some O
women B-TER
in O
their O
dressing O
gowns O
. O

One O
quickly O
threw O
over O
a O
coat O
. O

In O
the O
yard O
, O
a O
German B-TER
patrol O
was O
already O
standing O
who O
led O
the O
Jews O
to O
the O
market B-LOC
square I-LOC
. O

He O
did O
not O
allow O
the O
Jews O
to O
go O
back O
up O
home O
and O
to O
take O
something O
with O
them O
. O

This O
was O
the O
way O
it O
happened O
in O
many O
houses O
. O

When O
there O
were O
already O
three O
thousand O
Jews O
on O
the O
market B-LOC
square I-LOC
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
started O
to O
chase O
them O
in O
a O
hurry O
and O
with O
bayonets O
. O

They O
chased O
them O
far O
outside O
the O
city O
screaming O
: O
Forward O
because O
we O
are O
shooting O
. O

This O
way O
, O
they O
chased O
them O
for O
approximately O
twenty O
kilometres O
, O
young O
and O
old O
. O

Afterwards O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
said O
that O
who O
dares O
and O
comes O
back O
to O
the O
city B-LOC
will O
be O
shot B-TER
. O

All O
apartments O
from O
the O
expelled O
were O
sealed O
. O

All O
of O
this O
went O
on O
for O
three O
days O
in O
a O
row O
. O

In O
the O
course O
of O
these O
three O
days O
, O
the O
whole O
Jewish O
population O
from O
Kalisz B-LOC
was O
expelled O
. O

The O
Jews O
were O
wandering O
through O
the O
neighboring O
cities O
and O
a O
part O
of O
them O
arrived O
in O
the O
protectorat O
. O

A O
large O
part O
of O
the O
expelled O
from O
Kalisz B-LOC
arrived O
in O
Łódź B-LOC
. O

The O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
took O
care O
of O
them O
, O
gave O
them O
food B-TER
, O
but O
one O
can O
not O
speak O
of O
bigger O
help O
because O
, O
at O
that O
time O
, O
the O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
in O
Łódź B-LOC
already O
did O
not O
have O
the O
funds O
. O

Poles B-TER
were O
not O
expelled O
from O
Kalisz B-LOC
at O
all O
. O

From O
Konin B-LOC
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
expelled O
both O
Poles B-TER
and O
Jews O
and O
afterwards O
from O
all O
cities O
in O
Pomerania B-LOC
, O
Vigdinye O
Uncertain O
. O

, O
Poznań B-LOC
, O
Gdańsk B-LOC
, O
Poyrn O
Uncertain O
. O

, O
Bydgoszcz B-LOC
– O
all O
Jews O
were O
expelled O
from O
there O
and O
also O
Poles B-TER
en O
masse O
. O

I O
also O
learned O
that O
the O
Germans B-TER
threatened O
all O
Jews O
from O
Zduńska B-LOC
Wola I-LOC
with O
an O
expulsion O
if O
they O
do O
not O
pay O
a O
contribution O
of O
about O
five O
million O
Złoty O
. O

They O
payed O
a O
part O
of O
the O
contribution O
and O
the O
expulsion O
was O
stopped O
for O
the O
time O
being O
. O

After O
that O
, O
the O
bigger O
part O
of O
the O
Jewish O
population O
( O
roughly O
two O
thirds O
) O
was O
expelled O
from O
Pabianice B-LOC
near O
Łódź B-LOC
. O

Jews O
were O
mainly O
chased O
from O
the O
bigger O
streets O
. O

This O
took O
place O
in O
the O
beginning O
of O
November O
. O

People O
also O
talked O
about O
that O
there O
will O
be O
an O
expulsion O
of O
Jews O
from O
Łódź B-LOC
but O
the O
Jews O
consoled O
themselves O
that O
it O
can O
not O
come O
to O
that O
because O
it O
is O
technically O
impossible O
. O

After O
all O
, O
Łódź B-LOC
counts O
a O
quarter O
million O
Jews O
! O
Expulsion O
from O
Łódź B-LOC
On O
December O
11 O
, O
early O
in O
the O
morning O
, O
we O
learned O
that O
on O
the O
building O
of O
the O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
there O
is O
a O
placard O
hanging O
in O
Polish B-TER
and O
German B-TER
saying O
that O
Łódź B-LOC
will O
become O
judenrein B-TER
free O
from O
Jews O
and O
that O
the O
Jews O
have O
to O
leave O
the O
city O
voluntarily O
or O
that O
they O
have O
to O
register O
with O
the O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
which O
will O
take O
care O
of O
sending O
them O
off O
from O
Łódź B-LOC
. O

No O
deadline O
was O
indicated O
. O

I O
learned O
that O
Rumkowski B-PER
, O
the O
head O
of O
the O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
nominated O
by O
the O
Germans B-TER
, O
called O
upon O
the O
Jews O
on O
the O
factory B-TER
railway B-LOC
station I-LOC
that O
they O
should O
leave O
Łódź B-LOC
. O

Afterwards O
I O
got O
to O
know O
from O
a O
clerk O
from O
the O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
how O
it O
came O
to O
that O
. O

A O
day O
earlier O
, O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
informed O
the O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
that O
the O
city O
Łódź B-LOC
has O
to O
become O
judenrein B-TER
and O
that O
they O
, O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
, O
will O
carry O
it O
out O
on O
their O
own O
. O

The O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
started O
to O
request O
that O
it O
should O
get O
the O
possibility O
to O
enforce O
it O
methodically O
, O
not O
en O
masse O
and O
not O
at O
once O
. O

The O
Gestapo B-ORG
replied O
that O
they O
will O
do O
a O
test O
: O
if O
the O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
sends O
off O
eight O
thousand O
Jews O
in O
the O
course O
of O
4 O
days O
( O
two O
thousand O
a O
day O
) O
, O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
will O
allow O
that O
everything O
should O
be O
carried O
out O
by O
the O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
. O

And O
indeed O
: O
soon O
, O
on O
the O
first O
day O
, O
the O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
began O
to O
work O
energetically O
on O
it O
. O

The O
yard O
of O
the O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
was O
literally O
sieged O
. O

First O
of O
all O
, O
the O
Jewish O
poor O
registered O
because O
the O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
gave O
50 O
Złoty O
( O
25 O
German B-TER
Mark O
) O
per O
family B-TER
and O
the O
poor O
who O
did O
not O
have O
anything O
were O
eager O
to O
get O
it O
. O

The O
first O
who O
registered O
had O
to O
come O
to O
the O
gathering O
point O
, O
which O
were O
determined O
by O
the O
Germans B-TER
– O
and O
from O
there O
, O
they O
were O
sent O
off O
to O
Radogoszcz B-LOC
[ O
prison B-TER
] O
, O
where O
they O
were O
held O
for O
three O
days O
. O

There O
they O
had O
to O
work B-TER
and O
the O
Germans O
also O
carried O
out O
searches O
through O
their O
stuff O
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
also O
did O
x O
- O
rays O
in O
order O
to O
make O
sure O
that O
the O
Jews O
had O
not O
swallowed O
any O
diamonds O
. O

One O
was O
allowed O
to O
take O
the O
following O
: O
one O
pair O
of O
underwear O
, O
one O
suit O
of O
clothes O
, O
one O
pair O
of O
shoes O
, O
a O
few O
pairs O
of O
socks O
, O
a O
fork O
, O
spoon O
, O
knife O
, O
one O
pillow O
, O
one O
blanket O
, O
one O
bedsheet O
and O
25 O
Mark O
in O
the O
wallet O
. O

The O
first O
group O
consisted O
of O
five O
hundred O
individuals O
. O

On O
the O
second O
day O
, O
already O
two O
thousand O
five O
hundred O
individuals O
were O
leaving O
, O
and O
the O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
was O
constantly O
sieged O
by O
Jews O
who O
were O
eager O
to O
leave O
the O
earlier O
the O
better O
. O

From O
Radogoszcz B-LOC
, O
the O
Jews O
from O
Łódź B-LOC
were O
put O
into O
sealed B-TER
- I-TER
up I-TER
train I-TER
waggons I-TER
and O
sent O
off O
in O
an O
unknown O
direction O
. O

Only O
after O
two O
weeks O
, O
we O
in O
Łódź B-LOC
learned O
about O
their O
fate O
, O
but O
on O
that O
later O
. O

In O
the O
first O
two O
days O
of O
the O
expulsion O
, O
Łódź B-LOC
looked O
like O
in O
the O
most O
horrific O
scene O
in O
a O
film O
. O

On O
all O
streets O
, O
one O
could O
see O
rows O
of O
waggons O
and O
buses O
which O
moved O
slowly O
with O
people O
and O
stuff O
on O
them O
. O

The O
freezing O
weather O
was O
dreadful O
. O

Everyone O
wanted O
to O
leave O
the O
city O
as O
soon O
as O
possible O
in O
all O
kinds O
of O
ways O
. O

In O
Łódź B-LOC
, O
there O
are O
two O
train B-LOC
stations I-LOC
. O

The O
Kalisz B-LOC
train B-LOC
station I-LOC
was O
now O
designated O
exclusively O
for O
the O
Germans B-TER
. O

So O
, O
for O
Jews O
, O
the O
factory B-TER
train B-LOC
station I-LOC
remained O
. O

There O
, O
scenes O
out O
of O
Dante O
took O
place O
. O

There O
were O
cases O
when O
the O
Germans B-TER
shot B-TER
into O
the O
queue O
in O
which O
Jews O
were O
standing O
to O
buy O
tickets O
. O

Three O
Jews O
were O
shot B-TER
dead I-TER
in O
situations O
like O
that O
. O

If O
the O
first O
two O
days O
were O
already O
terrifying O
, O
the O
third O
day O
of O
the O
expulsion O
was O
even O
more O
horrible O
. O

This O
is O
the O
case O
because O
, O
in O
the O
night O
from O
Wednesday O
to O
Thursday O
( O
December O
13 O
, O
1939 O
) O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
surrounded O
a O
few O
streets O
like O
Zgyerzsher B-LOC
, I-LOC
Lushamirsker I-LOC
, O
and O
entered O
the O
Jewish O
apartments O
and O
ordered O
the O
Jews O
to O
leave O
everything O
behind O
within O
five O
minutes O
and O
to O
come O
with O
them O
. O

There O
were O
cases O
when O
mothers B-TER
did O
not O
succeed O
in O
dress O
their O
infants O
properly O
. O

They O
chased O
the O
Jews O
with O
their O
families B-TER
dressed O
as O
they O
were O
to O
the O
train B-LOC
station I-LOC
, O
crammed O
them O
into O
sealed B-TER
- I-TER
up I-TER
train I-TER
waggons I-TER
and O
sent O
them O
off O
in O
an O
unknown O
direction O
. O

When O
we O
got O
to O
know O
about O
it O
the O
next O
day O
in O
the O
city B-LOC
, I-LOC
a O
terrible O
panic O
erupted O
. O

Through O
the O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
, O
it O
was O
still O
possible O
to O
take O
something O
with O
you O
. O

Those O
who O
got O
displaced O
directly O
by O
the O
Germans B-TER
, O
they O
went O
away O
naked O
and O
bare O
. O

The O
rich O
ran O
away O
with O
taxis O
and O
on O
buses O
. O

For O
a O
spot O
on O
a O
bus O
to O
Warsaw B-LOC
, O
one O
paid O
from O
500 O
to O
1000 O
Złoty O
. O

The O
poor O
, O
who O
could O
not O
go O
with O
buses O
, O
jump O
on O
waggons O
from O
the O
Warthegau O
( O
the O
part O
that O
was O
annexed O
to O
the O
German B-TER
Reich I-TER
) O
to O
the O
border O
of O
the O
protectorate O
to O
Głowno B-LOC
, O
approximately O
35 O
kilometres O
away O
from O
Łódź B-LOC
. O

Without O
any O
means O
and O
possibilities O
to O
go O
on O
, O
they O
were O
stuck O
there O
. O

There O
were O
probably O
around O
eight O
thousand O
Jews O
there O
. O

Since O
Głowno B-LOC
is O
a O
small O
shtetl O
, O
and O
there O
was O
nowhere O
to O
spend O
the O
night O
, O
the O
expelled O
Jews O
from O
Łódź B-LOC
lingered O
on O
the O
fields O
and O
in O
the O
forests O
in O
the O
freezing O
cold O
. O

The O
consequences O
were O
catastrophic O
: O
in O
the O
course O
of O
one O
night O
, O
400 O
children B-TER
froze O
to O
death B-TER
. O

The O
relationship O
from O
the O
Polish B-TER
peasants O
to O
the O
Jewish O
expellees O
was O
a O
good O
one O
. O

They O
took O
the O
Jews O
in O
into O
cottages O
and O
gave O
them O
food O
for O
free O
. O

But O
the O
stream O
[ O
of O
refugees B-TER
] O
was O
so O
big O
that O
the O
peasants O
’ O
help O
did O
not O
suffice O
. O

The O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
in O
Łódź B-LOC
was O
so O
helpless O
that O
it O
did O
not O
send O
anyone O
to O
Głowno B-LOC
. O

On O
Friday O
, O
December O
15 O
, O
in O
the O
morning O
, O
the O
rich O
Jews O
from O
Łódź B-LOC
gathered O
on O
Bałut B-LOC
Market I-LOC
– O
in O
the O
true O
Jewish O
center O
– O
and O
shouted O
: O
Jews O
, O
take O
money O
and O
jewelry O
. O

And O
they O
simply O
threw O
diamonds O
on O
the O
street O
. O

The O
Jews O
did O
not O
take O
it O
, O
though O
, O
because O
they O
said O
to O
the O
rich O
: O
The O
same O
danger O
that O
threatens O
you O
threatens O
us O
. O

A O
Jew O
is O
prohibited O
to O
have O
on O
him O
jewelry O
and O
money O
, O
and O
they O
did O
not O
take O
the O
money O
and O
jewelry O
. O

In O
the O
night O
from O
Friday O
to O
Shabbat O
( O
from O
the O
15th O
to O
the O
16th O
) O
, O
mass O
arrests B-TER
among O
the O
intelligentsia O
began O
, O
among O
doctors B-TER
, O
lawyers O
, O
teachers O
– O
both O
Jews O
and O
non O
- O
Jews O
. O

People O
were O
thinking O
that O
these O
were O
arrests B-TER
. O

In O
fact O
, O
this O
was O
an O
expulsion O
. O

Within O
five O
minutes O
, O
all O
families B-TER
from O
these O
detainees O
were O
sent O
off O
in O
sealed B-TER
- I-TER
up I-TER
train I-TER
cars I-TER
. O

When O
, O
by O
coincidence O
, O
there O
was O
a O
stranger O
in O
the O
home O
of O
such O
an O
intelligent O
, O
a O
stranger O
who O
does O
not O
belong O
to O
that O
category O
, O
they O
sent O
him O
off O
as O
well O
. O

There O
were O
eight O
cases O
when O
people O
were O
severely O
ill B-TER
and O
they O
could O
not O
be O
sent O
off O
– O
so O
the O
Germans B-TER
sealed O
up O
the O
apartments O
. O

The O
ones O
sealed O
- O
up O
remained O
confined O
like O
that O
for O
ten O
days O
. O

The O
neighbors O
heard O
the O
cries O
from O
the O
wretched O
ones O
. O

One O
froze O
from O
the O
cold O
, O
also O
the O
pipes O
from O
the O
water O
conduit O
froze O
so O
that O
there O
was O
no O
water O
. O

The O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
constantly O
intervened O
at O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
but O
without O
success O
. O

Only O
on O
the O
tenth O
day O
, O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
permitted O
to O
open O
the O
sealed O
- O
up O
apartments O
: O
in O
these O
apartments O
, O
one O
found O
two O
dead O
persons O
and O
the O
rest O
was O
unconscious O
and O
in O
terrible O
conditions O
. O

The O
expulsion O
of O
the O
Jews O
as O
well O
as O
the O
mass O
exodus O
lasted O
until O
Sunday O
morning O
, O
December O
17 O
, O
1939 O
. O

In O
the O
morning O
, O
news O
circulated O
fast O
as O
lightning O
across O
the O
city O
that O
the O
expulsion O
was O
stopped O
. O

I O
soon O
went O
to O
the O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
and O
they O
told O
me O
that O
on O
Shabbat O
in O
the O
afternoon O
, O
at O
four O
o’clock O
, O
a O
delegation O
from O
the O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
, O
namely O
Rumkowski B-PER
’s O
representative O
Dr. O
Helman B-PER
, O
the O
female O
lawyer O
Plivatska B-PER
and O
a O
third O
person O
, O
went O
to O
the O
commander O
of O
the O
city O
with O
the O
request O
that O
they O
should O
alleviate O
the O
expulsion O
. O

The O
Jewish O
delegation O
listed O
all O
the O
horror O
and O
consequences O
of O
the O
expulsion O
. O

The O
Jewish O
delegation O
was O
received O
by O
the O
commander O
of O
the O
city O
in O
the O
corridor O
and O
with O
a O
strict O
tone O
he O
said O
: O
The O
Jews O
have O
to O
leave O
the O
city O
en O
masse O
. O

Łódź O
has O
to O
become O
judenrein O
! O
If O
the O
number O
of O
Jews O
who O
will O
leave O
Łódź O
will O
be O
satisfying O
, O
the O
Germans O
wo O
n’t O
be O
dragging O
Jews O
from O
their O
apartments O
. O

With O
this O
, O
the O
Jewish O
delegation O
left O
thinking O
that O
their O
intervention O
did O
not O
lead O
to O
anything O
. O

Around O
midnight O
on O
Shabbat O
, O
there O
was O
a O
telephone O
call O
for O
Rumkowski B-PER
’s O
representative O
Dr. O
Helman B-PER
. O

The O
content O
of O
the O
call O
was O
: O
Please O
tell O
the O
Jews O
that O
they O
should O
not O
leave O
Łódź O
. O

Dr. O
Helman B-PER
began O
to O
ask O
for O
how O
long O
the O
expulsion O
will O
be O
halted O
but O
he O
did O
n’t O
receive O
any O
reply O
. O

On O
Sunday O
morning O
, O
the O
city B-LOC
learned O
about O
it O
and O
different O
rumors O
started O
to O
circulate O
. O

They O
said O
that O
it O
is O
temporary O
, O
as O
long O
as O
the O
freezing O
weather O
holds O
sway O
. O

Also O
that O
the O
expulsion O
is O
halted O
until O
March O
1 O
. O

Others O
said O
that O
it O
was O
an O
intervention O
from O
America O
which O
threatened O
that O
it O
will O
expel O
the O
Germans B-TER
from O
there O
on O
ships O
; O
others O
assured O
that O
it O
happened O
because O
it O
was O
technically O
impossible O
to O
send O
off O
such O
a O
big O
number O
of O
individuals O
because O
all O
paths O
were O
clogged O
up O
by O
the O
coaches O
and O
buses O
. O

The O
Jews O
from O
Łódź B-LOC
felt O
relieved O
. O

We O
kissed O
each O
other O
on O
the O
streets O
and O
wished O
mazl O
- O
tov O
. O

But O
nonetheless O
, O
the O
Jews O
from O
Łódź B-LOC
continued O
to O
leave O
the O
city B-LOC
in O
great O
numbers O
. O

The O
Jews O
from O
Łódź B-LOC
do O
not O
believe O
that O
the O
expulsion O
has O
been O
called O
off O
for O
good O
. O

They O
think O
that O
the O
halt O
of O
the O
expulsion O
is O
temporary O
because O
the O
official O
German B-TER
offices O
have O
not O
given O
any O
formal O
announcement O
. O

The O
panic O
to O
escape O
was O
not O
as O
frenzied O
as O
before O
but O
people O
still O
left O
the O
city B-LOC
en O
masse O
. O

The O
nervousness O
amongst O
the O
Jews O
of O
Łódź B-LOC
which O
has O
decreased O
a O
little O
was O
renewed O
again O
ten O
days O
later O
when O
we O
learned O
that O
the O
Germans B-TER
started O
to O
expel O
the O
Jews O
from O
neighboring O
cities O
like O
Pabianice B-LOC
, O
Aleksandrów B-LOC
( I-LOC
Łódzki I-LOC
) I-LOC
, O
Konstantynów B-LOC
( I-LOC
Łódzki I-LOC
) I-LOC
, O
Zg B-LOC
ierz B-LOC
and O
other O
shtetlekh O
surrounding O
Łódź B-LOC
. O

The O
Jews O
in O
Łódź B-LOC
once O
again O
had O
a O
nervous O
night O
[ O
leyl O
- O
shimurim O
= O
holiday O
eve O
, O
esp O
. O

the O
first O
night O
of O
Passover O
] O
. O

We O
were O
anxious O
. O

We O
were O
afraid O
that O
the O
expulsion O
would O
start O
anew O
because O
the O
roads O
were O
emptier O
again O
. O

On O
Shabbat O
, O
December O
30 O
, O
1939 O
, O
I O
drove O
out O
of O
Łódź B-LOC
and O
I O
do O
n’t O
know O
anything O
about O
the O
subsequent O
fate O
of O
the O
people O
from O
Łódź B-LOC
. O

Regarding O
the O
expelled O
Jews O
from O
Łódź B-LOC
to O
Głowno B-LOC
, O
I O
learned O
that O
only O
later O
– O
after O
two O
weeks O
after O
the O
expulsion O
– O
the O
Germans B-TER
sent O
the O
expelled O
Jews O
to O
Galicia B-LOC
, O
in O
small O
shtetlekh O
, O
in O
barracks O
à O
1000 O
individuals O
, O
on O
stony O
floors O
. O

From O
the O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
circle O
in O
Łódź B-LOC
, O
I O
got O
to O
know O
things O
that O
were O
not O
known O
in O
the O
city B-LOC
, O
namely O
: O
that O
the O
arrested B-TER
Jews O
were O
tortured B-TER
; O
they O
pulled O
out O
of O
their O
mouths O
golden O
teeth O
and O
crowns O
and O
there O
were O
also O
cases O
of O
castration O
. O

I O
learned O
in O
Łódź B-LOC
that O
the O
Germans B-TER
also O
expelled O
the O
Jews O
from O
Żychlin B-LOC
, O
which O
belongs O
to O
the O
protectorate O
, O
in O
the O
same O
way O
they O
did O
in O
Kalisz B-LOC
. O

This O
time O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
let O
packs O
of O
dogs O
chase O
after O
the O
Jews O
. O

