Rubinstyn B-PER
Marta B-PER
1906 O
15 O
/ O
IX O
Bełżyce B-LOC
Surname O
from O
first O
husband B-TER
: O
Zigelman B-PER
, I-PER
Marta I-PER
Testimony O
taken O
by O
P. B-PER
Mamet I-PER
, O
4.8.1946 O
Liquidation O
of O
the O
Jews O
of O
Bełżyce B-LOC
Until O
the O
outbreak O
of O
the O
war B-TER
in O
1939 O
, O
I O
lived O
in O
Lublin B-LOC
. O

In O
fall O
1940 O
, O
all O
Jews O
were O
deported B-TER
from O
Lublin B-LOC
by O
the O
Germans B-TER
and O
settled O
in O
the O
villages O
surrounding O
Lublin B-LOC
. O

The O
deported B-TER
Jews O
would O
be O
taken O
on O
wagon B-TER
s O
, O
frequently O
they O
would O
be O
driven O
en O
masse O
on O
foot O
, O
very O
often O
it O
would O
happen O
during O
such O
a O
deportation B-TER
that O
many O
succumbed O
. O

I O
, O
my O
husband B-TER
, O
and O
my O
two O
sons B-TER
aged O
12–13 O
were O
deported B-TER
to O
Lubartów B-LOC
near O
Lublin B-LOC
. O

I O
tore O
myself O
away B-TER
from O
the O
entire O
transport B-TER
and O
went O
back O
to O
my O
home O
in O
Lublin B-LOC
, O
and O
I O
hid B-TER
there O
in O
the O
attic B-TER
. O

My O
husband B-TER
and O
children B-TER
were O
taken O
to O
Lubartów B-LOC
. O

My O
brother B-TER
, O
Veisbrod B-PER
Leibush I-PER
, O
was O
living O
at O
that O
time O
in O
Bełżyce B-LOC
near O
Lublin B-LOC
– O
I O
called O
him O
on O
the O
telephone O
[ O
to O
ask O
] O
that O
he O
should O
send O
a O
wagon B-TER
for O
me O
, O
and O
so O
I O
arrived O
in O
Bełżyce B-LOC
. O

In O
Bełżyce B-LOC
I O
gathered O
together O
a O
few O
people B-TER
and O
organized O
a O
[ O
public O
] O
kitchen B-TER
, O
where O
the O
deportees B-TER
and O
the O
poor O
people B-TER
of O
Bełżyce B-LOC
would O
come O
to O
eat O
. O

We O
fed B-TER
around O
1200 O
to O
1500 O
people B-TER
. O

Also O
here O
I O
want O
to O
relate O
to O
what O
extent O
the O
German B-TER
regime I-TER
was O
rotten O
, O
that O
we O
could O
persuade O
the O
most O
important O
among O
them O
of O
anything O
for O
[ O
the O
price O
of O
] O
gold B-TER
or I-TER
valuables I-TER
. O

Near O
us O
was O
Standartenführer B-PER
Stemmler I-PER
, O
we O
could O
bribe B-TER
him O
with O
hard O
/ O
heavy O
gold O
and O
diamonds O
as O
well O
as O
fabric O
and O
boots O
– O
redeeming O
Jews O
from O
the O
camp B-TER
of O
Józefów B-LOC
near O
Pulawy B-LOC
, O
not O
far O
from O
Warsaw B-LOC
– O
from O
death B-TER
. O

As O
a O
result O
of O
our O
acquaintance O
with O
the O
Jewish B-TER
representatives I-TER
, O
such O
as O
Dr. B-PER
Feltscher I-PER
, O
the O
SS B-ORG
men O
Kranbuegel B-PER
and O
Engel B-PER
, O
who O
were O
considered O
the O
most O
famous O
camp B-TER
directors I-TER
in O
Poland B-LOC
– O
until O
1942 O
we O
were O
able O
for O
various O
prices O
to O
ensure O
that O
no O
ghetto B-TER
or O
camp B-TER
would O
be O
established O
in O
our O
city O
( O
Bełżyce B-LOC
) O
. O

Nevertheless O
in O
1942 O
, O
in O
the O
eighth O
month O
, O
a O
Jewish O
quarter O
[ O
city O
] O
was O
established O
in O
our O
town O
. O

They O
gathered B-TER
all O
the O
Jews O
from O
the O
entire O
Lublin B-LOC
district O
– O
they O
deceived O
them O
and O
told O
them O
to O
bring O
everything O
with O
them O
– O
it O
was O
pitiful O
to O
see O
how O
the O
Jews O
even O
dragged O
with O
them O
wood O
. O

In O
this O
way O
, O
with O
us O
in O
Bełżyce B-LOC
were O
gathered B-TER
together O
around O
9000 O
Jews O
. O

They O
allowed O
them O
to O
rest O
for O
three O
days O
– O
on O
the O
third O
day O
, O
the O
SS B-ORG
man O
inspector O
Engel B-PER
entered O
the O
Jewish O
quarter O
– O
this O
was O
a O
beast O
in O
the O
form O
of O
a O
man B-TER
– O
straight O
away O
in O
the O
square O
he O
murdered B-TER
700 O
people B-TER
– O
the O
rest O
were O
taken O
away O
to O
Bełżec B-LOC
near O
Tomaszów B-LOC
. O

There O
they O
burned B-TER
them O
in O
the O
crematoria B-TER
. O

There O
remained O
Jews O
in O
hiding B-TER
, O
who O
had O
hidden B-TER
in O
the O
city O
and O
the O
surrounding O
forests O
and O
came O
back O
after O
the O
aktion B-TER
– O
around O
600 O
persons B-TER
. O

From O
these O
people B-TER
a O
camp B-TER
was O
created O
in O
Bełżyce B-LOC
– O
our O
camp B-TER
was O
directed O
by O
the O
SS B-ORG
men O
Engel B-PER
and O
Yakab O
. O

Spelling O
uncertain O
- O
Vakab O
? O
Yakab O
? O
The B-ORG
camp I-ORG
committee I-ORG
and O
the O
police O
were O
Jews O
. O

People B-TER
worked O
at O
hacking O
stones O
, O
building O
highways O
, O
for O
the O
firm O
Keymer O
. O

On O
8.V.1943 O
, O
some O
of O
the O
people B-TER
from O
the O
camp B-TER
were O
murdered B-TER
and O
a O
few O
, O
even O
before O
this O
when O
they O
saw O
that O
a O
camp B-TER
was O
created O
, O
fled B-TER
from O
Bełżyce B-LOC
via O
various O
means O
. O

I O
myself O
left O
Bełżyce B-LOC
in O
the O
following O
way O
. O

At O
3 O
AM O
I O
went O
out O
with O
my O
son B-TER
, O
who O
was O
sick O
with O
typhus B-TER
, O
running O
with O
him O
to O
the O
wires O
of O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

I O
cut B-TER
through I-TER
the O
wires O
and O
set O
out O
for O
Warsaw B-LOC
. O

On O
V.5.1943 O
, O
I O
arrived O
in O
Warsaw B-LOC
. O

The O
news O
that O
the O
camp B-TER
had O
been O
decimated O
was O
brought O
to O
me O
already O
in O
Warsaw B-LOC
by O
my O
brother B-TER
. O

I O
want O
just O
to O
mention O
here O
the O
camp B-TER
director O
of O
Bełżyce B-LOC
by O
the O
name O
Göth B-PER
– O
he O
murdered B-TER
a O
few O
hundred O
children B-TER
in O
the O
following O
manner O
– O
he O
gathered O
them O
all O
together O
, O
took O
them O
to O
the O
cemetery B-TER
, O
ordered O
the O
children B-TER
to O
undress O
, O
lined O
them O
up O
naked O
in O
a O
row O
, O
and O
, O
with O
a O
cruel O
, O
cold O
- O
bloodedness O
shot B-TER
them O
all O
. O

One O
young O
boy B-TER
, O
his O
name O
was O
Kuropotvo B-PER
, O
hid B-TER
among O
the O
dead B-TER
children B-TER
and O
came O
to O
the O
city O
the O
next O
day O
, O
early O
in O
the O
morning O
, O
covered O
in O
blood O
, O
because O
the O
bullet O
did O
not O
hit O
him O
, O
and O
he O
told O
me O
the O
entire O
story O
. O

The O
day O
after O
the O
children B-TER
were O
taken O
away O
, O
the O
camp B-TER
director O
Goth B-PER
, O
who O
was O
also O
one O
of O
the O
camp B-TER
directors O
with O
whom O
we O
were O
acquainted O
and O
whom O
we O
would O
bribe B-TER
, O
told O
us O
, O
I O
have O
taken O
good O
care O
of O
all O
the O
children O
– O
I O
brought O
them O
all O
to O
Poniatowa O
near O
Lublin O
! O
– O
The O
young O
boy B-TER
Kuropotvo B-PER
who O
avoided O
death B-TER
at O
the O
hands O
of O
Göth B-PER
fell O
during O
a O
later O
aktion B-TER
. O

The O
children B-TER
’s I-TER
aktion B-TER
during O
which O
Göth B-PER
murdered B-TER
them O
took O
place O
in O
March O
1943 O
in O
Bełżyce B-LOC
. O

Marta B-PER
Rubinstyn I-PER
. O

