Fanny B-PER
Günzenberger I-PER
presents O
the O
following O
: O
My O
personal O
tragedy O
started O
in O
1941 O
, O
when O
they O
collected O
Jews O
of O
Polish B-TER
origin O
in O
Hungary B-LOC
. O

That O
time O
, O
they O
took O
me O
and O
my O
parents O
, O
5 O
brothers O
and O
sisters O
of O
mine O
and O
a O
great O
number O
of O
relatives O
. O

No O
one O
remained O
alive O
except O
for O
me O
. O

I O
managed O
to O
escape B-TER
from O
Kamenetz B-LOC
- I-LOC
Podolsk I-LOC
before O
they O
shot B-TER
all O
those O
enormous O
number O
of O
Jews O
. O

The O
way O
back O
was O
really O
horrible O
, O
I O
dared O
to O
walk O
only O
during O
the O
night O
in O
the O
bottom O
of O
ditches O
. O

During O
the O
day O
I O
hid B-TER
in O
a O
stack O
of O
hay O
or O
in O
a O
stall O
. O

I O
ate B-TER
what O
I O
found O
on O
the O
fields O
and O
in O
the O
woods O
, O
edible O
plants O
, O
carrots B-TER
, O
and O
potatoes B-TER
. O

For O
me O
, O
the O
suffering O
in O
Germany B-TER
was O
not O
a O
surprise O
or O
a O
novelty O
. O

Finally O
, O
I O
managed O
to O
get O
back O
into O
Hungary B-LOC
, O
however O
I O
did O
not O
return O
to O
our O
village O
but O
worked O
for O
Jewish O
families B-TER
in O
Ungvár B-LOC
. O

In O
1943 O
, O
when O
Germans B-TER
entered O
the O
country O
, O
they O
constructed O
the O
ghetto B-TER
in O
Ungvár B-LOC
soon O
, O
and O
all O
Jews O
had O
to O
enter O
it O
. O

We O
still O
lived B-TER
well O
in O
the O
ghetto B-TER
disregarding O
that O
they O
beat O
and O
interrogated O
richer O
Jews O
to O
find O
out O
where O
they O
hid O
their O
valuables O
. O

Around O
6 O
weeks O
later O
, O
we O
were O
entrained O
and O
we O
arrived O
in O
Auschwitz B-LOC
after O
a O
three O
- O
day O
- O
long O
miserable O
journey O
. O

Here O
they O
immediately O
separated B-TER
strong O
people B-TER
suitable O
for O
hard O
work B-TER
from O
the O
elderly O
, O
the O
young O
and O
the O
weak O
. O

They O
took O
us O
into O
the O
baths O
, O
seized O
our O
belongings O
, O
cut O
our O
hair O
, O
washed O
us O
, O
and O
let O
us O
stay O
nude O
in O
the O
cold O
room O
for O
hours O
before O
they O
gave O
us O
some O
ragged O
clothes B-TER
. O

They O
led O
us O
into O
a O
barrack B-TER
where O
there O
was O
empty O
place O
only O
on O
the O
ground O
. O

We O
spent O
all O
the O
time O
in O
Auschwitz B-LOC
queuing O
up O
for O
roll B-TER
calls I-TER
. O

From O
the O
morning O
till O
noon O
there O
was O
a O
roll B-TER
call I-TER
, O
then O
there O
was O
the O
roll B-TER
call I-TER
before O
lunch O
, O
and O
another O
two O
hours O
waiting O
in O
the O
afternoon O
. O

In O
between O
, O
the O
hut O
was O
cleaned O
and O
we O
were O
forced O
to O
stay O
in O
the O
open O
. O

There O
were O
frequent O
selections B-TER
causing O
always O
terrible O
anxiety O
as O
we O
already O
knew O
what O
they O
meant O
, O
why O
flames O
were O
coming O
out O
of O
the O
chimneys O
of O
the O
crematorium B-TER
day O
and O
night O
. O

Only O
10 O
days O
passed O
before O
they O
selected B-TER
me O
into O
a O
transport B-TER
for O
work B-TER
. O

They O
made O
me O
have O
another O
bath O
and O
put O
me O
on O
a O
train B-TER
heading O
to O
Bergen B-LOC
- I-LOC
Belsen I-LOC
. O

We O
were O
glad O
that O
the O
two O
of O
us O
who O
knew O
each O
other O
still O
from O
Hungary B-LOC
could O
stay O
together O
, O
and O
that O
we O
got O
out O
of O
Auschwitz B-LOC
that O
meant O
constant O
anxiety O
. O

We O
did O
not O
have O
a O
better O
situation O
either O
in O
Bergen B-LOC
- I-LOC
Belsen I-LOC
. O

Food B-TER
was O
extremely O
scarce B-TER
, O
treatment O
was O
cruel O
. O

People B-TER
were O
beaten O
up O
all O
the O
time O
. O

We O
had O
to O
do O
some O
awfully O
difficult O
work B-TER
carrying O
heavy O
loads O
. O

Every O
day O
a O
lot O
of O
us O
died B-TER
here O
. O

Luckily O
, O
we O
did O
not O
stay O
here O
long O
either O
but O
set O
off O
soon O
for O
Salzwedel B-LOC
. O

The O
lager O
in O
Salzwedel B-LOC
was O
small O
, O
altogether O
1,300 O
women B-TER
were O
kept O
here O
. O

They O
treated O
us O
less O
cruelly O
as O
in O
Bergen B-LOC
. O

Daily O
food B-TER
comprised O
of O
half O
litre O
of O
black O
coffee B-TER
in O
the O
morning O
and O
the O
evening O
, O
some O
watery O
vegetable O
soup B-TER
at O
noon O
and O
200 O
grams O
of O
bread B-TER
. O

Sometimes O
we O
got O
20 O
grams O
of O
margarine B-TER
, O
or O
marmalade B-TER
. O

We O
were O
awfully O
starving B-TER
. O

We O
had O
a O
lot O
of O
work B-TER
to O
do O
even O
if O
it O
was O
not O
so O
difficult O
. O

Mostly O
we O
shovelled O
sand O
and O
pebbles O
for O
12 O
hours O
a O
day O
. O

Many O
died B-TER
of O
exhaustion O
. O

Everyone O
was O
as O
thin O
as O
a O
skeleton O
. O

When O
Americans B-TER
got O
closer O
they O
wanted O
to O
take O
us O
away O
but O
had O
no O
time O
to O
do O
so O
as O
Americans B-TER
already O
arrived B-TER
into I-TER
the I-TER
camp I-TER
. O

