Mr. O
Ota B-PER
Klinger I-PER
, O
Prague B-LOC
I. I-LOC
, O
Betlémská B-LOC
8 O
, O
made O
the O
following O
statement O
available O
to O
the O
Documentation B-TER
Campaign I-TER
. O

1945 O
. O

----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- O
To O
my O
mother B-TER
, O
my O
fiancée B-TER
, O
my O
comrades O
, O
and O
to O
all O
of O
those O
who O
exercised O
in O
JPT O
( O
Union O
of O
Proletarian O
Sports O
) O
with O
the O
hero O
of O
these O
lines O
, O
Honza B-PER
Hermann I-PER
. O

I O
would O
like O
to O
describe O
for O
you O
the O
final O
moments O
of O
your O
true O
hero O
in O
life O
and O
death B-TER
. O

This O
roughly O
31 O
- O
year O
- O
old O
athlete O
in O
body O
and O
spirit O
, O
whose O
politically O
active O
brother B-TER
was O
killed O
by O
the O
occupiers O
, O
was O
originally O
a O
builder O
, O
but O
spent O
long O
months O
in O
the O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
Ghetto I-LOC
working O
as O
a O
cook B-TER
and O
, O
later O
, O
due O
to O
his O
skillfulness O
, O
as O
the O
leader O
of O
a O
work B-TER
group O
. O

Beloved O
by O
all O
of O
his O
fellow B-TER
prisoners I-TER
for O
his O
honesty O
, O
skill O
as O
a O
worker O
, O
and O
, O
last O
but O
not O
least O
, O
for O
his O
great O
sense O
of O
fairness O
, O
he O
is O
departing O
on O
a O
transport B-TER
to O
Auschwitz B-LOC
now O
. O

Once O
there O
, O
he O
is O
selected B-TER
from O
the O
thousands O
of O
the O
strongest O
to O
leave O
Auschwitz B-LOC
, O
leaving O
his O
mother O
to O
an O
uncertain O
fate O
along O
with O
the O
rest O
of O
the O
11,000 O
prisoners B-TER
, O
10,500 O
of O
whom O
will O
be O
executed B-TER
in I-TER
the I-TER
gas I-TER
chambers I-TER
. O

In O
the O
Schwarzheide B-LOC
labor B-TER
camp I-TER
near O
Oranienburg B-LOC
, O
firmly O
believing O
in O
the O
victory O
of O
the O
allies B-TER
, O
he O
works B-TER
for O
12 O
hours O
a O
day O
, O
except O
for O
the O
hours O
spent O
in O
attendance O
at O
roll B-TER
calls I-TER
and O
on O
the O
way O
to O
work B-TER
. O

His O
strong O
athlete O
’s O
body O
holds O
out O
against O
unbearable O
suffering O
, O
back O
- O
breaking O
work B-TER
, O
and O
hunger B-TER
, O
and O
he O
outlives O
many O
of O
his O
friends O
who O
are O
dying B-TER
from O
starvation B-TER
and O
torture O
. O

He O
rejoices O
over O
, O
and O
suffers O
as O
a O
result O
of O
, O
the O
countless O
airstrikes B-TER
that O
we O
experience O
in O
the O
synthetic O
gasoline O
factory B-TER
. O

Although O
we O
have O
built O
many O
multi O
- O
storeyed O
shelters O
with O
3 O
meter O
reinforced O
concrete O
ceilings O
, O
we O
have O
to O
wait O
out O
the O
bombings B-TER
close O
to O
the O
factory B-TER
inside O
wooden O
buildings O
that O
are O
subjected O
to O
frequent O
hits O
. O

The O
bombs B-TER
that O
strike O
here O
injure O
comrade O
Honza B-PER
so O
slightly O
that O
he O
recovers O
in O
several O
months O
and O
is O
once O
more O
sent O
off O
to O
become O
part O
of O
a O
work B-TER
group O
whose O
sole O
purpose O
is O
to O
completely O
exhaust O
the O
workers O
. O

He O
solemnly O
swears O
revenge O
upon O
those O
who O
ignored O
his O
injuries O
and O
sent O
him O
to O
be O
destroyed O
. O

More O
air B-TER
strikes I-TER
land O
and O
we O
are O
the O
victims O
of O
the O
Germans B-TER
’ O
brutality O
. O

During O
the O
last O
airstrike B-TER
, O
comrade O
Honza B-PER
leaves O
the O
room O
in O
which O
we O
eat B-TER
and O
goes O
to O
the O
room O
where O
we O
sleep O
. O

He O
wants O
to O
escape O
the O
thought O
that O
he O
could O
be O
hit O
again O
. O

The O
bomb B-TER
falls O
several O
meters O
from O
our O
wooden O
building O
, O
and O
many O
shards O
bounce O
off O
the O
concrete O
slabs O
of O
the O
washroom O
that O
has O
been O
reduced O
to O
dust O
and O
strike O
dozens O
of O
prisoners B-TER
who O
are O
lying O
on O
the O
floor O
of O
the O
house O
. O

Our O
Honza B-PER
is O
among O
the O
unfortunate O
ones O
. O

Shrapnel O
has O
sliced O
his O
leg O
open O
close O
to O
the O
groin O
. O

Everyone O
is O
heavily O
wounded O
. O

A O
punctured O
stomach O
, O
a O
ripped O
up O
back O
, O
a O
sliced O
off O
hand O
, O
and O
much O
worse O
. O

We O
rush O
to O
Honza B-PER
’s O
side O
. O

We O
want O
to O
wrap O
him O
in O
a O
blanket O
and O
carry O
him O
off O
to O
the O
sickroom B-TER
. O

Honza B-PER
refuses O
, O
and O
tells O
us O
to O
take O
those O
with O
lighter O
injuries O
who O
can O
still O
be O
helped O
. O

He O
points O
our O
attention O
to O
his O
significant O
blood O
loss O
, O
hopeless O
condition O
, O
his O
maimed O
body O
. O

This O
shows O
what O
a O
great O
man O
he O
truly O
was O
. O

His O
selflessness O
is O
a O
quality O
one O
would O
be O
hard O
- O
pressed O
to O
find O
here O
above O
this O
tomb B-TER
of O
thousands O
and O
millions O
of O
people O
. O

It O
made O
us O
shiver O
to O
hear O
his O
words O
of O
eternal O
, O
incomprehensibly O
great O
friendship O
. O

I O
do O
n’t O
think O
I O
exaggerate O
when O
I O
state O
that O
such O
brotherhood O
is O
described O
only O
in O
the O
Bible O
. O

Our O
friend O
passed B-TER
away I-TER
3 O
days O
later O
and O
left O
us O
with O
an O
everlasting O
memory O
– O
a O
symbol O
of O
humanity O
, O
as O
well O
as O
vigilance O
to O
make O
sure O
that O
those O
who O
caused O
these O
atrocities O
do O
not O
go O
unpunished O
. O

Although O
he O
helped O
build O
the O
medical O
shelters O
that O
were O
5 O
minutes O
away O
from O
our O
camp B-TER
, O
leaving O
a O
little O
bit O
of O
himself O
there O
every O
day O
, O
our O
Honza B-PER
is O
taken O
to O
a O
wholly O
unfit O
wooden O
hut O
. O

Here O
, O
a O
medical B-TER
attendant I-TER
, O
a O
German O
surgeon B-TER
, O
operates O
on O
him O
. O

Prisoners B-TER
are O
only O
allowed O
to O
assist O
and O
stitch O
up O
heavy O
wounds O
using O
a O
plain O
needle O
used O
to O
sew O
bags O
. O

The O
medical B-TER
attendant I-TER
operates O
with O
a O
regular O
wood O
saw O
from O
the O
camp B-TER
’s O
joinery O
workshop O
, O
and O
dozens O
of O
our O
friends O
, O
victims O
of O
the O
bombing B-TER
, O
die B-TER
after O
going O
through O
indescribable O
agony O
alongside O
tens O
of O
thousands O
of O
others O
worked O
and O
tortured O
to O
death O
. O

May O
they O
rest O
in O
peace O
. O

Signature O
: O
Ota B-PER
Klinger I-PER
Statement O
accepted O
by O
: O
B.Gerzonová B-PER
Signature O
of O
witnesses O
: O
Lebovič O
Lebovič O
- O
uncertain O
, O
unreadable O
Simon B-PER
Alexander I-PER
Max B-PER
Widder I-PER
Accepted O
on O
behalf O
of O
the O
Documentation B-TER
Campaign I-TER
by O
: O
19 O
. O

XI O
. O

1945 O
Scheck B-PER
On O
behalf O
of O
the O
archive O
: O
Alex B-PER
. I-PER

Schmiedt I-PER
