( O
1 O
) O
R. O
Ministry B-ORG
of I-ORG
Foreign I-ORG
Affairs I-ORG
, O
Rome B-LOC
( O
2 O
) O
R. O
Representation O
of O
Italy B-LOC
for O
Greece B-LOC
, O
Athens B-LOC
Thessaloniki B-LOC
, O
11th O
August O
[ O
1943 O
] O
1 O
) O
End O
of O
the O
Jewish B-TER
colony I-TER
of O
Thessaloniki B-LOC
2 O
) O
Follow O
- O
up O
to O
the O
cable O
of O
this O
R. O
Office O
no O
. O

4050/889 O
of O
11th O
inst O
. O

The O
last O
Jews B-TER
still O
remaining O
in O
the O
“ B-LOC
Baron I-LOC
Hirsch I-LOC
” I-LOC
Ghetto I-LOC
have O
left O
in O
the O
night O
from O
10th O
to O
11th O
August O
. O

The O
special O
SS B-ORG
Police I-ORG
left O
yesterday O
. O

Their O
chief O
Vesleceny B-PER
[ O
sic O
] O
left O
this O
morning O
by O
aeroplane O
for O
Berlin B-LOC
. O

The O
Jewish B-TER
colony O
of O
Thessaloniki B-LOC
, O
which O
was O
founded O
before O
the O
discovery O
of O
America O
and O
which O
comprised O
approx O
. O

60,000 O
people O
, O
is O
no O
more O
. O

Over O
the O
centuries O
the O
Jews B-TER
had O
set O
up O
highly O
valuable O
factories B-TER
, O
such O
as O
that O
of O
the O
Italian B-LOC
Torres B-TER
, O
to O
name O
but O
one O
, O
which O
produced O
fabrics O
and O
jute O
and O
was O
the O
most O
important O
in O
the O
entire O
Balkans B-LOC
. O

They O
had O
amassed O
enormous O
wealth B-TER
, O
which O
was O
plundered B-TER
and I-TER
stolen I-TER
by O
the O
Greeks B-LOC
and O
by O
the O
Germans B-TER
. O

The B-TER
elimination I-TER
of O
the O
Israelite B-TER
colony O
took O
place O
and O
was O
completed O
among O
atrocities B-TER
, I-TER
horrors I-TER
and I-TER
crimes I-TER
such O
as O
I O
had O
never O
heard O
described O
in O
the O
history O
of O
all O
times O
and O
of O
all O
peoples O
. O

The O
Italian B-LOC
Israelite B-TER
colony O
was O
able O
to O
reach O
safety O
by O
moving O
to O
Athens B-LOC
; O
the O
same O
can O
be O
said O
of O
the O
small O
Argentine B-LOC
and O
Portuguese B-LOC
colonies O
. O

The O
Spanish O
colony O
, O
which O
for O
the O
past O
two O
months O
had O
lived O
in O
hope B-TER
of I-TER
being I-TER
transferred I-TER
to I-TER
Spain I-TER
, O
at O
the O
last O
moment O
received O
a O
Spanish O
refusal O
and O
was O
deported B-TER
by O
the O
Germans B-TER
, O
including O
the O
Spanish O
Vice O
- O
Consul O
, O
who O
had O
been O
accepted O
and O
acknowledged O
as O
such O
and O
had O
served O
Spain O
in O
Thessaloniki B-LOC
for O
a O
great O
many O
years O
. O

For O
us O
Italians B-LOC
the O
elimination O
of O
our O
Jewish B-TER
colony O
means O
an O
extremely O
serious O
loss O
that O
can O
not O
be O
measured O
in O
millions O
. O

Suffice O
it O
to O
say O
that O
before O
the O
present O
war O
the O
Italian B-LOC
merchant O
marine O
was O
the O
second O
in O
Thessaloniki B-LOC
, O
immediately O
after O
the O
Greek B-LOC
. O

The O
maritime O
traffic O
was O
mostly O
originated O
by O
the O
trade B-TER
and O
by O
the O
factories B-TER
of I-TER
the I-TER
Italian I-TER
Jews I-TER
of O
Thessaloniki B-LOC
. O

G. B-PER
Castruccio I-PER
