Testimony O
Given O
by O
Sonya B-PER
Yofe I-PER
born O
in O
Vilna B-LOC
, O
17.IX.1946 O
. O

Recorded O
by O
Levental B-PER
Nachman I-PER
The O
camp B-TER
of O
Kailis B-LOC
was O
as O
follows O
: O
two O
blocks O
on O
Rydz B-LOC
- I-LOC
Śmigły I-LOC
Street O
, O
where O
Jewish O
hat O
- O
makers O
lived O
and O
worked B-TER
. O

There O
were O
around O
2000 O
people B-TER
there O
, O
who O
worked B-TER
at O
fur O
- O
hat O
making O
. O

The O
entire O
time O
it O
was O
relatively B-TER
good I-TER
. O

The O
last O
period O
, O
in O
June O
1944 O
, O
they O
took O
fifty O
people B-TER
, O
strong O
men B-TER
, O
to O
Ponar B-LOC
to O
work B-TER
and O
they O
never O
came O
back O
. O

On O
March O
27 O
, O
1944 O
, O
they O
gathered O
together O
the O
children B-TER
, O
young O
and O
old O
people B-TER
, O
dressed B-TER
them O
neatly O
and O
took O
them O
to O
the O
hospital B-TER
, O
ostensibly O
for O
an O
inspection O
– O
they O
took O
them O
through O
one O
door O
and O
out O
through O
another O
. O

There O
stood O
ready O
Ukrainians B-TER
and O
Lithuanians B-TER
in O
uniforms B-TER
with O
machine O
guns O
. O

And O
they O
took O
all O
the O
children B-TER
with O
the O
mothers B-TER
and O
the O
old O
people O
, O
flinging O
them O
into O
the O
trucks B-TER
– O
they O
transported B-TER
them O
through O
Kovno B-LOC
. O

After O
the O
Children B-TER
’s I-TER
Action B-TER
[ O
Kinder O
Aktion O
] O
, O
a O
month O
later O
, O
they O
liquidated O
the O
camp B-TER
of O
Kailis B-LOC
. O

Some O
they O
sent O
to O
Riga B-LOC
, O
and O
some O
to O
Kazlova B-LOC
- I-LOC
Ruda I-LOC
[ O
Kazlų B-LOC
Rūda I-LOC
] O
, O
eighty O
people B-TER
with O
a O
profession O
to O
Kovno B-LOC
. O

Only O
400 O
people B-TER
remained O
in O
Kailis B-LOC
. O

They O
were O
only O
in O
Kailis B-LOC
for O
another O
two O
weeks O
. O

Ten O
days O
before O
the O
liberation B-TER
, O
they O
took O
all O
the O
Jews O
, O
among O
them O
doctors O
Feyglis B-PER
and O
Dr. O
Burak B-PER
, O
Eng O
. O

Pap B-PER
( O
they O
did O
not O
let O
themselves O
be O
taken O
– O
they O
were O
dragged O
out O
to O
the O
trucks O
with O
force O
) O
. O

They O
took O
them O
to O
Ponar B-LOC
and O
shot B-TER
them O
there O
. O

On O
the O
day O
of O
the O
liberation B-TER
, O
when O
the O
Jews O
of O
Vilna B-LOC
who O
were O
in O
hiding B-TER
places I-TER
came O
to O
Ponar B-LOC
at O
night O
, O
they O
found O
the O
photographs B-TER
and O
many O
Jews B-TER
lying I-TER
unburied I-TER
in O
their O
clothes B-TER
– O
because O
they O
[ O
the O
Germans B-TER
] O
were O
hurrying O
and O
did O
not O
manage O
to O
bury B-TER
them O
. O

Signed O
: O
Sonya B-PER
Strazshi I-PER
- I-PER
Yoffe I-PER
