Białoszer B-PER
Niusia I-PER
, O
born O
on O
the O
30th O
of O
May O
, O
1923 O
in O
Warsaw B-LOC
. O

Daughter B-TER
of O
Josel B-PER
and O
Dwora B-PER
, O
mother B-TER
née O
Bieniakońska B-PER
. O

Education O
: O
secondary O
school O
( O
matura O
) O
. O

Family B-TER
: O
not O
married O
. O

Profession O
: O
before O
the O
war B-TER
– O
at O
school O
, O
during O
the O
war B-TER
and O
at O
present O
– O
office O
employee O
. O

During O
the O
war B-TER
more O
or O
less O
the O
whole O
family B-TER
perished B-TER
. O

I O
survived O
alone O
with O
my O
mother B-TER
. O

When O
the O
war B-TER
broke O
out O
, O
I O
was O
living O
in O
Vilnius B-LOC
with O
my O
mother B-TER
. O

We O
lived O
at O
Vilner B-LOC
Street I-LOC
number I-LOC
4 I-LOC
. O

On O
the O
21st O
of O
June O
, O
1941 O
the O
war B-TER
between O
Germany B-TER
and O
the O
Soviet B-LOC
Union I-LOC
broke O
out O
. O

When O
the O
war B-TER
broke O
out O
, O
I O
and O
my O
family B-TER
were O
living O
in O
Vilnius B-LOC
, O
at O
Vilner B-LOC
Street I-LOC
number I-LOC
4 I-LOC
. O

The O
town O
was O
bombarded O
by O
German B-TER
planes O
for O
two O
days O
. O

On O
the O
23rd O
of O
June O
, O
1941 O
the O
German B-ORG
army I-ORG
marched O
into O
Vilnius B-LOC
. O

The O
city O
has O
fallen O
without O
a O
fight O
. O

There O
were O
70 O
000 O
Jews O
in O
Vilnius B-LOC
. O

A O
considerable O
part O
of O
young O
Jewish O
people O
succeeded O
to O
escape B-TER
to O
the O
Soviet B-LOC
Union I-LOC
. O

But O
many O
of O
them O
were O
killed B-TER
on O
their O
way O
. O

Just O
after O
the O
city O
was O
taken O
by O
the O
Germans B-TER
, O
the O
city O
municipality O
confiscated B-TER
all O
Jewish O
businesses O
and O
real O
estate O
. O

The O
Jews O
were O
forced O
to O
start O
to O
sell O
away O
their O
possessions O
in O
order O
to O
buy O
food B-TER
. O

Lithuanians B-TER
hang O
out O
posters O
in O
cinemas O
, O
cafés O
and O
shops O
: O
Entry O
for O
Jews O
is O
forbidden O
. O

German B-TER
soldiers B-TER
, O
as O
well O
as O
Lithuanian B-TER
policemen B-TER
, O
went O
to O
Jewish O
homes O
, O
beat O
Jews O
and O
took O
away O
their O
valuables O
. O

The O
Gestapo B-ORG
and O
the O
SS B-ORG
destroyed O
all O
the O
synagogues B-TER
, O
burned O
and O
stamped O
on O
Torah O
scrolls O
and O
religious O
books O
. O

One O
day O
three O
German B-TER
soldiers B-TER
and O
two O
Lithuanian B-TER
policemen B-TER
with O
guns O
in O
their O
hands O
came O
to O
our O
home O
. O

They O
ordered O
us O
to O
remain O
sitting O
where O
we O
were O
. O

They O
menaced O
us O
that O
they O
would O
shoot B-TER
anyone O
who O
would O
make O
a O
move O
. O

One O
of O
the O
Lithuanians B-TER
stayed O
to O
guard O
us O
, O
and O
others O
searched O
through O
the O
whole O
apartment O
. O

They O
left O
after O
taking O
all O
the O
valuables O
. O

The O
German B-TER
authorities O
forced O
the O
Jews O
to O
pay O
a O
contribution O
of O
1 O
000 O
000 O
roubles O
. O

The O
order O
was O
made O
known O
through O
posters O
on O
the O
walls O
of O
buildings O
. O

In O
order O
to O
raise O
the O
sum O
, O
Jews O
gave O
away O
their O
last O
money O
and O
jewelry O
. O

Many O
even O
gave O
away O
their O
wedding O
rings O
. O

The O
contribution O
was O
raised O
. O

At O
the O
same O
time O
, O
a O
hundred O
Jewish O
hostages B-TER
were O
arrested B-TER
. O

The O
Gestapo B-ORG
and O
the O
SS B-ORG
men B-TER
came O
to O
the O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
office O
and O
arrested B-TER
all O
the O
employees O
. O

Among O
them O
were O
Jakub B-PER
Wygodzki I-PER
( O
the O
chairman O
of O
the O
community B-TER
) O
, O
Saul B-PER
Trocki I-PER
, O
Kruk B-PER
, O
Langbard B-PER
and O
the O
lawyer B-TER
Katsenelson B-PER
. O

Other O
hostages B-TER
were O
rabbis B-TER
and O
Jewish O
intelligentsia O
. O

The O
SS B-ORG
arrested B-TER
them O
in O
their O
own O
homes O
. O

Engineer O
Vigushin B-PER
and O
rabbi B-TER
Frid B-PER
were O
among O
them O
. O

After O
a O
few O
days O
the O
Gebietskommissar O
Hingst B-PER
issued O
an O
order B-TER
that O
was O
posted O
on O
the O
walls O
of O
buildings O
: O
Jews O
must O
give O
away O
all O
of O
their O
jewelry O
, O
gold O
and O
silver O
. O

And O
a O
second O
order B-TER
: O
Jews O
are O
forbidden O
to O
walk O
on O
the O
sidewalks O
and O
to O
travel O
by O
car O
, O
tram O
or O
train O
. O

Jews O
can O
not O
set O
foot O
in O
the O
main O
streets O
of O
the O
city O
, O
such O
as O
Zawalna O
, O
Mickiewicza O
, O
Trocka O
, O
Pohulanka O
, O
Zakretowa O
, O
Wielka O
. O

At O
the O
same O
time O
the O
German B-TER
authorities O
issued O
the O
following O
order B-TER
in O
the O
form O
of O
a O
poster O
: O
All O
Jews O
from O
three O
years O
old O
must O
carry O
patches O
on O
the O
left O
side O
of O
breast O
and O
back O
. O

The O
patches O
must O
be O
fabricated O
from O
white O
cloth O
, O
10 O
centimetres O
wide O
with O
an O
embroidered O
yellow O
circle O
and O
a O
letter O
J O
in O
the O
centre O
. O

This O
patch B-TER
was O
changed O
into O
another O
, O
in O
the O
form O
of O
a O
yellow B-TER
star I-TER
of I-TER
David I-TER
on O
the O
breast O
and O
on O
the O
back O
. O

The O
patch B-TER
remained O
like O
that O
until O
the O
end O
. O

At O
that O
time O
roundups B-TER
of O
Jewish O
men B-TER
started O
. O

German B-TER
SS B-ORG
and O
Lithuanian B-TER
police B-TER
would O
round B-TER
up I-TER
Jewish O
men B-TER
on O
the O
streets O
or O
go O
into O
Jewish O
homes O
and O
take O
away O
both O
old O
and O
young O
without O
any O
difference O
. O

They O
would O
even O
drag O
out O
the O
sick B-TER
from O
their O
beds O
. O

By O
such O
means O
the O
SS B-ORG
would O
round B-TER
up I-TER
a O
few O
hundred O
Jews O
every O
day O
. O

It O
was O
supposed O
to O
be O
for O
work B-TER
. O

But O
instead O
of O
work B-TER
, O
the O
SS B-ORG
would O
bring O
the O
Jewish O
men B-TER
to O
the O
Łukiszki B-LOC
prison B-TER
and O
from O
there O
to O
a O
forest O
12 O
kilometers O
from O
Vilnius B-LOC
. O

The O
forest O
is O
called O
Ponar O
. O

In O
the O
beginning O
we O
thought O
that O
Ponar O
was O
a O
work B-TER
camp I-TER
. O

Gradually O
we O
became O
aware O
that O
it O
was O
a O
place O
of O
executions B-TER
and O
that O
the O
SS B-ORG
tortured O
and O
shot B-TER
about O
10 O
000 O
of O
our O
men B-TER
there O
. O

In O
August O
1941 O
rumours O
about O
closing O
the O
Jews O
in O
a O
ghetto B-TER
started O
to O
spread O
. O

The O
German B-TER
Gebietskommissar O
Hingst B-PER
and O
the O
Lithuanian B-TER
mayor O
Burokas B-PER
called O
a O
meeting O
with O
some O
of O
their O
employees O
and O
worked O
out O
the O
plan O
of O
the O
ghetto B-TER
. O

On O
Saturday O
, O
the O
31st O
of O
August O
1941 O
, O
the O
German B-TER
authorities O
hung O
out O
the O
following O
posters O
: O
On O
the O
corner O
of O
Breyte O
and O
Glezer O
streets O
, O
the O
Jews O
have O
murdered O
two O
Germansoldiers O
in O
a O
terrible O
way O
. O

We O
have O
to O
take O
revenge O
for O
their O
blood O
. O

On O
Sunday O
, O
the O
1st O
of O
September O
1941 O
, O
at O
midnight O
the O
Lithuanian B-TER
SS B-ORG
encircled O
the O
streets O
that O
were O
largely O
inhabited O
by O
Jews O
: O
Żydowska B-LOC
, O
Niemiecka B-LOC
, O
Dziśnieńska B-LOC
, O
Jatkowa B-LOC
and O
a O
part O
of O
Wielka B-LOC
. O

Lithuanian B-TER
soldiers B-TER
entered O
the O
Jewish O
homes O
and O
dragged O
away O
even O
the O
old O
and O
the O
children B-TER
naked O
from O
their O
beds O
, O
not O
giving O
them O
any O
time O
to O
put O
some O
clothes B-TER
on O
. O

The O
women B-TER
wept O
and O
the O
children B-TER
cried O
out O
for O
their O
mothers B-TER
. O

The O
Lithuanians B-TER
drove O
everyone O
out O
in O
the O
street O
with O
no O
mercy O
. O

It O
was O
completely O
dark O
outside O
. O

The O
men B-TER
lost O
their O
wives B-TER
in O
the O
crowd O
and O
the O
women B-TER
– O
their O
children B-TER
. O

No O
one O
could O
orient O
themselves O
where O
the O
others O
were O
. O

During O
this O
provocation O
4000 O
Jews O
were O
rounded B-TER
up I-TER
. O

The O
Lithuanian B-TER
SS B-ORG
encircled O
them O
with O
a O
strong O
guard O
and O
marched O
them O
to O
the O
Łukiszki B-LOC
prison B-TER
. O

From O
there O
the O
Lithuanians B-TER
took O
them O
by O
trucks O
to O
Ponar B-LOC
. O

