From O
Minister O
Yamaji B-PER
Akira I-PER
( O
Sofia B-LOC
, O
Bulgaria B-LOC
) O
To O
: O
Foreign O
Minister O
Shigemitsu B-PER
Mamoru I-PER
( O
Tokyo B-LOC
) O
Concerning O
the O
Jewish O
Question O
Currently O
there O
are O
about O
50,000 O
Jews B-TER
in O
this O
country O
, O
of O
which O
about O
26,000 O
live O
in O
Sofia B-LOC
. O

Although O
they O
do O
not O
appear O
to O
have O
any O
influence O
in O
the O
cultural B-TER
sphere I-TER
, O
in O
business B-TER
( O
especially O
commerce O
) O
they O
are O
extremely O
influential O
. O

As O
a O
result O
, O
there O
is O
increasingly O
the O
view O
that O
something O
must O
be O
done O
about O
this O
. O

In O
response O
to O
this O
, O
In O
the O
“ B-TER
Law I-TER
for I-TER
the I-TER
Protection I-TER
of I-TER
the I-TER
nation I-TER
, I-TER
” I-TER
promulgated O
in O
January O
1941 O
, O
the O
Government B-TER
established O
several O
articles O
concerning O
the O
Jewish O
population O
. O

However O
, O
the O
actual O
effect O
was O
rather O
limited O
. O

As O
a O
result O
, O
last O
fall O
the O
government B-TER
received O
full O
authority O
to O
deal O
with O
the O
Jews B-TER
. O

Consequently O
, O
they O
established O
a O
new O
bureau O
and O
required O
Jews B-TER
to O
wear O
yellow B-TER
tags I-TER
, O
placed O
limitation B-TER
on O
their O
residence O
as O
well O
as O
on O
their O
activities O
besides O
business O
, O
and O
their O
control O
of O
property B-TER
2.6 O
billion O
leva O
etc O
. O

The O
government B-TER
pursued O
a O
policy B-TER
similar O
to O
that O
of O
Germany B-LOC
. O

However O
, O
such O
policies B-TER
were O
not O
very O
popular O
. O

In O
January O
this O
year O
the O
vice O
speaker O
of O
the O
Parliament O
and O
about O
forty O
members O
of O
the O
Parliament O
criticized O
the O
government O
measures O
, O
leading O
to O
the O
resignation O
of O
the O
vice O
speaker O
. O

( O
There O
is O
rumor O
that O
the O
Jews B-TER
spent O
a O
lot O
of O
money O
for O
this O
) O
. O

Recently O
many O
Jews B-TER
are O
accused O
of O
being O
involved O
in O
terror O
, O
sabotage B-TER
, O
spying O
and O
other O
forms O
of O
political O
agitation O
, O
and O
engaging O
in O
black B-TER
market I-TER
that O
should O
be O
called O
the O
cancer O
of O
Bulgarian O
economy B-TER
. O

The O
government B-TER
came O
to O
force O
Jews B-TER
living O
in O
Sofia B-LOC
to O
relocate O
to O
local O
areas O
because O
it O
was O
not O
very O
successful O
to O
leave O
the O
matter O
to O
their O
own O
will O
( O
only O
2,600 O
had O
moved B-TER
out I-TER
so O
far O
) O
That O
is O
to O
say O
, O
the O
government B-TER
will O
notify O
Jews B-TER
about O
the O
destination O
for O
their O
relocation B-TER
within O
two O
to O
three O
weeks O
. O

After O
receiving O
the O
notice O
the O
Jews B-TER
must O
leave O
the O
city O
within O
three O
days O
. O

Concerning O
this O
new O
measure O
the O
head O
of O
the O
Orthodox B-TER
Church I-TER
Stefan B-PER
and O
others O
lodged O
protest B-TER
against O
and O
it O
was O
not O
very O
popular O
in O
general O
. O

The O
Government B-TER
, O
however O
, O
considers O
that O
the O
city O
’s O
political B-TER
and I-TER
economic I-TER
condition O
will O
improve O
after O
the O
expulsion O
of O
all O
of O
its O
Jews B-TER
. O

12,000 O
Jews B-TER
who O
live O
in O
the O
new O
territories O
of O
Macedonia B-LOC
and O
Thrace B-LOC
have O
been O
deported B-TER
to O
Poland B-LOC
. O

( O
Now O
the O
Jews B-TER
who O
live O
in O
these O
new O
territories O
are O
mainly O
those O
with O
foreign O
citizenship B-TER
and O
number O
no O
more O
than O
6,700 O
. O

) O
Although O
there O
was O
a O
plan O
to O
deport B-TER
the O
10,000 O
Jews B-TER
who O
live O
in O
the O
old O
territories O
, O
as O
a O
result O
of O
the O
new O
measure O
this O
plan O
was O
put O
on O
hold O
. O

Through O
the O
intermediary O
of O
Switzerland B-LOC
, O
the O
Bulgarian B-LOC
Government B-TER
has O
reached O
an O
agreement O
with O
Britain B-LOC
to O
send O
5,000 O
Jews B-TER
to O
Palestine B-LOC
. O

However O
, O
they O
became O
entangled O
in O
the O
detailed O
articles O
and O
the O
agreement O
had O
not O
been O
implemented O
. O

