- O
1 O
- O
Transcript O
of O
photocopy O
. O

( O
Letter B-TER
of O
the O
only O
( O
? O
) O
surviving B-TER
member I-TER
of O
the O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
in O
Potsdam B-LOC
deported B-TER
to O
Riga B-LOC
to O
their O
former O
rabbi B-TER
Dr. O
Schreiber B-PER
. O

) O
Johanna B-PER
Rosenthal I-PER
Haessleholm B-LOC
, O
June O
26 O
, O
1945 O
Haessleholm B-LOC
/ O
Sweden B-LOC
Dear O
Dr. O
Schreiber B-PER
! O
I O
was O
greatly O
pleased O
about O
the O
fast O
fulfillment O
of O
my O
request O
. O

On O
Saturday O
( O
Sunday O
? O
) O
at O
12 O
noon O
I O
received O
your O
telegram O
. O

I O
had O
already O
asked O
to O
send O
a O
telegram O
for O
me O
from O
here O
. O

But O
already O
4 O
hours O
later O
a O
telegram O
from O
my O
husband B-TER
arrived O
. O

Now O
my O
joy O
was O
even O
greater O
, O
because O
I O
immediately O
got O
the O
address O
of O
the O
children B-TER
. O

Praise O
God O
that O
everybody O
is O
in O
good O
health O
. O

Hopefully O
these O
lines O
reach O
you O
also O
in O
best O
health O
. O

Thank O
God O
, O
my O
condition O
improves O
daily O
. O

They O
are O
using O
now O
a O
new O
medicament O
to O
fight O
the O
bacteria B-TER
, O
and O
one O
hopes O
that O
it O
works O
faster O
. O

Up O
to O
now O
you O
had O
to O
have O
negative O
swabs O
6 O
times O
in O
a O
row O
. O

But O
nobody O
has O
made O
it O
here O
in O
the O
7 O
[ O
? O
] O
weeks O
yet O
. O

But O
so O
far O
I O
'm O
not O
missing O
anything O
. O

The O
doctors B-TER
as O
well O
as O
the O
nurse O
and O
anyway O
the O
whole O
population B-TER
of O
Sweden B-LOC
are O
really O
devoted O
. O

Now O
, O
dear O
Doctor B-PER
, O
I O
want O
to O
give O
You O
a O
short O
report O
about O
the O
recent O
time O
. O

When O
we O
received O
forms O
from O
the O
Potsdam B-LOC
Gestapo B-ORG
2 O
days O
before O
our O
evacuation O
wherein O
to O
list O
all O
our O
possessions B-TER
, O
it O
was O
especially O
emphasized O
that O
there O
was O
nothing O
to O
worry O
about O
. O

In O
the O
course O
of O
Thursday O
we O
, O
the O
individuals O
mentioned O
below O
, O
were O
asked O
to O
report O
to O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
at O
8 O
o’clock O
on O
Friday O
morning O
. O

There O
everybody O
got O
2 O
officers B-TER
assigned O
to O
return O
with O
them O
to O
our O
apartments B-TER
. O

When O
we O
arrived O
there O
, O
we O
were O
told O
that O
we O
had O
to O
give O
up O
our O
apartments B-TER
immediately O
, O
as O
we O
would O
be O
given O
a O
new O
residence B-TER
in O
the O
East O
. O

We O
were O
allowed O
to O
pack O
the O
bare O
necessities O
, O
under O
supervision O
. O

We O
have O
never O
seen O
anything O
of O
that O
again O
. O

At O
11 O
o'clock O
we O
were O
back O
at O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
where O
they O
took O
all O
our O
money O
and O
papers B-TER
away O
from O
us O
. O

Then O
they O
locked O
us O
up O
for O
2 O
days O
. O

Sunday O
, O
January O
11 O
, O
we O
went O
in O
covered O
trucks O
to O
Berlin B-LOC
to O
be O
assigned O
to O
a O
transport B-TER
. O

Here O
we O
had O
to O
go O
through O
another O
very O
thorough O
check O
, O
even O
food B-TER
was O
taken O
away O
from O
us O
. O

Here O
we O
met O
the O
entire O
old B-TER
people I-TER
's I-TER
home I-TER
Grosse B-LOC
Hamburgerstr I-LOC
. O

, O
also O
patients O
from O
hospitals B-TER
who O
were O
fetched O
out O
of O
their O
beds O
by O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
. O

On O
Tuesday O
, O
January O
13 O
, O
we O
were O
transported B-TER
to O
Riga B-LOC
, O
1200 O
people O
in O
an O
unheated O
overcrowded O
train B-TER
. O

Food B-TER
and O
drink B-TER
were O
- O
2 O
- O
the O
first O
thing O
we O
were O
weaned O
off O
, O
so O
we O
traveled O
3 O
days O
and O
3 O
nights O
without O
a O
sip O
of O
something O
warm O
to O
drink B-TER
or O
anything O
else O
. O

At O
minus O
40 O
° O
C O
we O
arrived O
on O
Friday O
, O
January O
16 O
, O
in O
the O
afternoon O
in O
Riga B-LOC
. O

We O
were O
received O
at O
the O
station O
with O
bludgeoning O
and O
screaming O
by O
the O
German B-LOC
and O
Latvian B-LOC
SS B-ORG
. O

Our O
last O
remaining O
luggage O
, O
e.g. O
rucksacks O
or O
bags O
, O
we O
had O
to O
leave O
behind O
. O

Those O
who O
were O
able O
to O
walk O
had O
to O
walk O
4 O
hours O
to O
get O
to O
our O
new O
home O
. O

The O
sick B-TER
etc O
. O

were O
transported B-TER
in I-TER
cars I-TER
, O
but O
they O
never O
arrived O
in O
the O
ghetto B-LOC
. O

We O
found O
the O
ghetto B-LOC
in O
a O
terribly O
desolate O
state O
. O

At O
the O
beginning O
of O
December O
, O
about O
30 O
- O
40,000 O
Latvian B-LOC
Jews O
had O
been O
shot B-TER
there O
on O
the O
spot O
. O

Filled O
plates O
and O
pots O
were O
still O
on O
the O
tables O
, O
from O
which O
one O
could O
see O
how O
suddenly O
this O
attack O
had O
happened O
. O

Only O
3800 O
Latvian B-LOC
men B-TER
and O
200 O
women B-TER
were O
remaining O
, O
and O
they O
were O
separated O
from O
our O
ghetto B-LOC
by O
barbed O
wire O
. O

Our O
ghetto B-LOC
consisted O
of O
about O
10,000 O
Jews B-TER
. O

They O
came O
from O
all O
parts O
of O
Germany B-LOC
, O
e.g. O
Cologne B-LOC
, O
Duesseldorf B-LOC
, O
Kassel B-LOC
, O
Prague B-LOC
, O
Hanover B-LOC
, O
Leipzig B-LOC
, O
Berlin B-LOC
and O
Vienna B-LOC
. O

We O
were O
the O
first O
transport B-TER
from O
Berlin B-LOC
. O

Two O
more O
followed O
in O
the O
next O
14 O
days O
. O

These O
transports B-TER
were O
even O
worse O
, O
because O
there O
were O
only O
cattle B-TER
cars I-TER
and O
especially O
because O
there O
were O
only O
old O
people O
. O

Some O
of O
these O
people O
already O
went O
mad B-TER
on O
the O
way O
and O
died B-TER
. O

They O
always O
kept O
some O
strong O
men B-TER
to O
clean O
up O
the O
train B-TER
. O

At O
our O
transport B-TER
Feist B-PER
junior O
, O
Gormanns B-PER
junior O
and O
Gerd B-PER
Wohl I-PER
stayed O
back O
. O

We O
waited O
for O
them O
in O
the O
ghetto B-LOC
in O
vain O
. O

Feist B-PER
senior O
, O
Gersmann B-PER
A. I-PER
, O
Meierstein B-PER
/ O
Fahrland B-LOC
, O
Selma B-PER
Mannheim I-PER
, O
Fridchen B-PER
Rubert I-PER
and O
a O
Miss O
Grossmann B-PER
from O
Geltow B-LOC
stayed O
behind O
with O
the O
sick B-TER
. O

Despite O
all O
despair O
we O
had O
to O
create O
a O
home B-TER
for O
ourselves O
. O

In O
the O
first O
4 O
½ O
months O
I O
lived O
together O
with O
the O
Apriaskys B-PER
, O
the O
Salomons B-PER
, O
Mrs. O
Urbach B-PER
and O
Mrs. O
L. B-PER
Gersmann I-PER
. O

Sleeping O
on O
the O
floor O
, O
2 O
slices O
of O
bread B-TER
a O
day O
, O
thus O
the O
months O
passed O
. O

We O
were O
assigned O
to O
work B-TER
. O

Shoveling O
snow O
at O
minus O
40 O
° O
C O
, O
the O
men B-TER
had O
to O
go O
to O
the O
high O
forest O
to O
prepare O
new O
mass B-TER
graves I-TER
, O
etc O
. O

On O
the O
5th O
of O
February O
... O
o’clock O
in O
the O
morning O
, O
a O
large O
contingent O
of O
SS B-ORG
arrived O
. O

Everybody O
get O
out O
of O
the O
apartments B-TER
! O
Roll B-TER
call I-TER
on O
the O
street O
. O

Sick B-TER
and O
old O
people O
, O
and O
also O
some O
in O
their O
best O
years O
, O
were O
selected B-TER
and O
taken O
away O
in O
covered B-TER
cars I-TER
and O
we O
never O
heard O
from O
them O
again O
. O

Of O
4000 O
people O
2500 O
remained O
. O

Only O
the O
groups O
Berlin B-LOC
and O
Vienna B-LOC
were O
affected O
by O
this O
action O
. O

At O
the O
end O
of O
March O
and O
beginning O
of O
April O
something O
similar O
again O
in O
the O
whole O
ghetto B-LOC
. O

Roll B-TER
call I-TER
before O
the O
commander O
. O

Again O
, O
there O
were O
many O
thousands O
- O
3 O
- O
less O
. O

Mrs. O
Urbach B-PER
and O
Fraenze B-PER
Grand I-PER
were O
hit O
by O
this O
action B-TER
. O

Relatives O
of O
Miss O
Grand B-PER
, O
a O
Mr. O
Behrend B-PER
and O
his O
wife O
from O
Berlin B-LOC
as O
well O
. O

5 O
- O
6 O
hour O
long O
roll B-TER
calls I-TER
without O
any O
reason O
at O
minus O
35 O
- O
38 O
° O
C O
happened O
frequently O
. O

About O
mid- O
March O
Mr. O
Samter B-PER
died O
of O
starvation B-TER
and O
frostbite B-TER
. O

On O
March O
27 O
, O
I O
was O
assigned O
to O
a O
permanent O
work B-TER
detachment I-TER
with O
the O
Wehrmacht B-ORG
, O
they O
called O
it O
Armeebe O
kleidung B-TER
samt O
( O
army O
clothing B-TER
office O
) O
701 O
( O
abbreviated O
A.B.A. O
701 O
) O
. O

Even O
though O
hunger B-TER
and O
cold O
reigned O
and O
heavy O
work B-TER
had O
to O
be O
done O
, O
I O
endured O
. O

Thus O
I O
was O
lucky O
all O
these O
years O
. O

After O
two O
weeks O
I O
already O
got O
the O
position O
of O
a O
foreman O
. O

I O
kept O
this O
position O
until O
the O
dissolution O
on O
September O
27 O
, O
1944 O
. O

About O
August O
1942 O
, O
Mr. O
Gormanns B-PER
died B-TER
, O
and O
Rose B-PER
Cohn I-PER
in O
September O
1942 O
. O

I O
forgot O
to O
report O
that O
the O
Dornbuschs B-PER
took B-TER
their I-TER
own I-TER
life I-TER
8 O
days O
after O
our O
arrival O
. O

Gradually O
we O
settled O
down O
in O
the O
ghetto B-LOC
. O

In O
order O
to O
preserve O
our O
lives O
, O
everything O
we O
found O
in O
the O
apartments B-TER
was O
bartered O
for O
food B-TER
. O

This O
was O
punishable O
by O
death B-TER
, O
but O
it O
did O
not O
matter O
already O
in O
which O
way O
one O
had O
to O
die B-TER
. O

Many O
had O
to O
pay O
by O
being O
shot B-TER
or O
hanged B-TER
. O

As O
a O
deterrent O
we O
were O
led O
past O
the O
gallows O
in O
the O
evening O
when O
we O
returned O
from O
work O
, O
but O
we O
continued O
to O
barter O
. O

In O
summer O
1943 O
the O
order O
came O
, O
the O
ghetto B-LOC
must O
be O
dissolved O
. O

All O
Jews B-TER
had O
to O
be O
placed O
in O
the O
K.Z. B-LOC
. O

A O
giant O
K.Z. B-LOC
was O
constructed O
in O
Riga B-LOC
called O
Kaiserwald O
. O

Here O
not O
only O
the O
SS B-ORG
was O
in O
command O
but O
also O
the O
most O
dangerous O
professional O
criminals O
had O
life O
and O
death B-TER
of O
the O
Jews B-TER
at O
their O
disposal O
. O

But O
there O
was O
, O
thank O
God O
, O
still O
some O
small O
- O
scale O
barracking B-TER
in O
the O
city O
and O
the O
surrounding O
area O
. O

Our O
A.B.A. O
quartered O
us O
here O
on O
November O
6 O
, O
1943 O
. O

But O
of O
course O
it O
was O
subject O
to O
the O
Kaiserwald O
. O

On O
the O
2nd O
of O
November O
, O
a O
few O
days O
before O
our O
barracking B-TER
, O
there O
was O
again O
a O
gigantic O
action B-TER
in O
the O
ghetto B-LOC
. O

2,260 O
men B-TER
, O
women B-TER
and O
children B-TER
were O
loaded O
into O
cattle B-TER
wagons I-TER
to O
be O
transported B-TER
into O
the O
unknown O
. O

One O
spoke O
of O
Auschwitz B-LOC
. O

On O
this O
day O
countless O
children B-TER
were O
snatched O
from O
their O
parents B-TER
, O
and O
vice O
versa O
. O

About O
4 O
weeks O
later O
there O
was O
another O
action B-TER
and O
thus O
the O
ghetto B-LOC
was O
finally O
dissolved O
. O

On O
November O
2 O
, O
the O
Rubert O
siblings B-TER
, O
Mrs. O
Gersmann B-PER
, O
Mrs. O
Fabian B-PER
and O
Mrs. O
Meierstein B-PER
were O
present O
. O

Apriaskys B-PER
, O
Mrs. O
Gersmann B-PER
, O
Salomons B-PER
, O
Lotte B-PER
Henschel I-PER
, O
Reg B-PER
. I-PER

Hirschburg I-PER
, O
Margot B-PER
Brauer I-PER
, O
Stella B-PER
Loewenberg I-PER
, O
Inge B-PER
Mannheim I-PER
had O
already O
been O
sent O
to O
Kaiserwald B-LOC
in O
the O
course O
of O
time O
. O

Mrs. O
Schoetz B-PER
, O
Kassmann B-PER
and O
Feist B-PER
were O
quartered O
in O
barracks B-TER
together O
with O
me O
at O
the O
A.B.A O
.. O
We O
had O
been O
living O
together O
in O
the O
ghetto B-LOC
the O
last O
1 O
¼ O
years O
. O

But O
even O
now O
we O
still O
had O
no O
peace O
. O

Soon O
there O
was O
another O
transport B-TER
to O
Kaiserwald B-LOC
. O

- O
4 O
- O
In O
March O
Mrs. O
K. B-PER
went O
on O
a O
transport B-TER
to O
another O
A.B.A. O
in O
Krottingen B-LOC
. O

The O
few O
children B-TER
who O
could O
be O
rescued O
during O
the O
action O
in O
the O
ghetto B-LOC
were O
picked O
up O
by O
the O
SS B-ORG
on O
April O
22 O
. O

Destination O
unknown O
. O

On O
the O
evening O
of O
June O
28 O
: O
Everybody O
gets O
ready O
without O
luggage O
! O
An O
SS B-TER
doctor I-TER
from O
the O
Kaiserwald B-LOC
selects B-TER
people O
. O

Sick B-TER
and O
healthy O
! O
Destination O
unknown O
. O

Mrs. O
Schoetz B-PER
was O
there O
. O

On O
July O
7 O
, O
all O
the O
women B-TER
had O
their O
hair O
shaved O
off O
. O

3 O
- O
4 O
weeks O
later O
in O
the O
morning O
at O
6 O
o'clock O
: O
Everything O
get O
up O
for O
the O
roll B-TER
call I-TER
. O

500 O
people O
were O
selected B-TER
to O
be O
taken B-TER
away I-TER
to O
Stutthof B-LOC
/ O
Gdansk B-LOC
. O

No O
matter O
if O
in O
a O
nightgown B-TER
or O
without O
shoes B-TER
. O

Riga B-LOC
was O
gradually O
evacuated O
. O

On O
the O
25th O
of O
September O
all O
of O
a O
sudden O
end O
of O
work O
, O
there O
was O
a O
roll B-TER
call I-TER
. O

60 O
people O
( O
50 O
men B-TER
and O
10 O
young B-TER
girls I-TER
) O
remained O
here O
, O
everybody O
else O
went O
to O
Stutthof B-LOC
/ O
Gdansk B-LOC
. O

At O
the O
last O
minute O
the O
permission O
came O
, O
200 O
Jews O
are O
allowed O
to O
stay O
with O
the O
A.B.A O
.. O
I O
was O
already O
standing O
at O
the O
car O
when O
the O
camp B-TER
leader I-TER
said O
to O
me O
: O
Mrs. O
Rosenthal O
, O
disappear O
to O
the O
right O
. O

Thus O
I O
was O
saved O
. O

That O
evening O
, O
as O
with O
every O
action O
, O
families B-TER
were O
torn O
apart O
. O

It O
was O
exemplary O
how O
well O
they O
understood O
the O
idea O
of O
always O
tearing O
families B-TER
apart O
. O

Mrs. O
Feist B-PER
was O
present O
at O
the O
penultimate O
Stutthof B-LOC
transport B-TER
. O

So O
I O
was O
the O
only O
one O
from O
Potsdam B-TER
left O
behind O
. O

Two O
days O
later O
, O
just O
on O
Yom O
Kippur O
, O
our O
unit O
A.B.A. O
moved O
its O
headquarters O
to O
Libau B-LOC
. O

We O
traveled O
there O
by O
boat B-TER
. O

In O
the O
beginning O
we O
had O
to O
work B-TER
day O
and O
night O
, O
but O
then O
it O
got O
troubled O
here O
, O
too O
. O

The O
Russians B-ORG
came O
closer O
and O
closer O
. O

There O
were O
air B-TER
raids I-TER
several O
times O
a O
day O
. O

Twice O
it O
missed O
me O
by O
a O
hair O
. O

I O
was O
standing O
approximately O
1 O
meter O
away O
from O
the O
impact O
. O

On O
October O
22nd O
, O
during O
the O
first O
disaster O
, O
one O
of O
our O
women B-TER
lost B-TER
her I-TER
life I-TER
. O

In O
this O
explosion O
I O
lost O
my O
hearing O
for O
14 O
days O
. O

It O
’s O
not O
quite O
all O
right O
yet O
, O
but O
unfortunately O
there O
's O
nothing O
you O
can O
do O
about O
it O
here O
, O
because O
they O
fear O
that O
the O
bacteria B-TER
will O
take O
hold O
in O
my O
ear O
. O

Exactly O
2 O
months O
later O
there O
was O
the O
second O
impact B-TER
and O
we O
had O
to O
mourn O
13 O
dead B-TER
, O
and O
4 O
people O
were O
buried O
alive O
. O

Chance O
had O
it O
that O
I O
was O
n’t O
standing O
next O
to O
my O
girlfriend O
and O
so O
I O
stayed O
alive O
and O
she O
was O
dead B-TER
. O

Thus O
I O
should O
live O
. O

From O
Libau B-LOC
we O
were O
all O
to O
go O
to O
Stutthof B-LOC
/ O
Gdansk B-LOC
. O

But O
there O
was O
no O
boat B-TER
available O
for O
us O
, O
and O
besides O
our O
SS B-ORG
master I-ORG
sergeant I-ORG
had O
been O
fatally O
wounded O
during O
the O
air B-TER
raid I-TER
in O
December O
22 O
. O

On O
February O
19 O
, O
it O
happened O
that O
our O
unit O
wanted O
to O
go O
to O
Luebeck B-LOC
with O
us O
. O

On O
the O
way O
our O
commander O
got O
a O
radio O
message O
that O
we O
had O
to O
be O
dropped O
off O
in O
Hamburg B-LOC
. O

Here O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
received O
us O
- O
5 O
- O
and O
put O
us O
in O
prison B-TER
at O
Fuhlsbuettel B-LOC
jail O
. O

On O
April O
11th O
the O
decision O
came O
, O
we O
move B-TER
to O
Kiel B-LOC
to O
a O
labour B-TER
camp I-TER
. O

After O
the O
march B-TER
of O
90 O
km O
, O
15 O
of O
us O
arrived O
to O
this O
hell O
more O
dead O
than O
alive O
. O

Meanwhile O
, O
56 O
men B-TER
had O
been O
sent O
to O
the O
K.Z. B-LOC
Bergen I-LOC
- I-LOC
Belsen I-LOC
near O
Hanover B-LOC
. O

Without O
recovering O
, O
we O
went O
to O
work B-TER
every O
day O
. O

2 O
hours O
there O
, O
2 O
hours O
back O
, O
during O
the O
day O
very O
hard O
work B-TER
with O
stone O
. O

In O
the O
morning O
, O
wake O
- O
up O
call O
at O
4 O
o'clock O
, O
then O
roll B-TER
call I-TER
for O
hours O
until O
we O
went O
to O
work B-TER
at O
7 O
o'clock O
. O

Whether O
it O
was O
raining O
or O
not O
, O
it O
did O
n’t O
matter O
at O
the O
roll B-TER
call I-TER
or O
at O
work B-TER
. O

At O
6 O
o'clock O
we O
came O
back O
. O

There O
was O
food B-TER
: O
red O
beetroot B-TER
boiled O
in O
water O
or O
yellow O
turnip B-TER
. O

In O
the O
morning O
2 O
thin O
slices O
of O
bread B-TER
. O

Hardly O
time O
for O
eating O
, O
and O
then O
muster O
at O
roll B-TER
call I-TER
. O

It O
never O
added O
up O
, O
so O
we O
had O
to O
stand O
for O
hours O
. O

There O
was O
no O
water O
, O
so O
we O
could O
not O
wash O
. O

If O
someone O
tried O
to O
get O
himself O
some O
water O
, O
there O
were O
blows O
with O
the O
truncheon O
. O

Straw O
bags O
did O
n’t O
exist O
either O
, O
we O
had O
to O
sleep O
on O
raw O
planks O
. O

We O
did O
n’t O
have O
underwear B-TER
and O
clothes B-TER
to O
change O
, O
so O
we O
saved O
time O
on O
dressing O
. O

We O
women B-TER
had O
a O
blanket O
, O
the O
men B-TER
had O
none O
. O

About O
40 O
people O
were O
shot B-TER
every O
day O
in O
this O
hell O
after O
they O
had O
been O
tortured B-TER
. O

But O
thank O
God O
our O
stay O
there O
did O
not O
last O
long O
, O
because O
on O
May O
1st O
our O
salvation O
came O
. O

A O
woman B-TER
of O
69 O
years O
, O
who O
had O
all O
exertions O
behind O
her O
, O
even O
the O
march O
Hamburg B-LOC
and O
Kiel B-LOC
, O
was O
shot B-TER
5 O
days O
before O
our O
liberation B-TER
. O

I O
forgot O
to O
report O
at O
the O
beginning O
that O
about O
2000 O
men B-TER
were O
sent O
to O
an O
extermination B-LOC
camp I-LOC
near O
Riga B-LOC
. O

In O
this O
camp O
, O
it O
was O
called O
Salaspils B-LOC
, O
approximately O
1000 B-TER
people I-TER
were O
killed B-TER
. O

Causes O
of O
death B-TER
were O
very O
hard O
work B-TER
, O
vermin O
, O
no O
washing O
facilities O
and O
hunger B-TER
of O
the O
greatest O
extent O
. O

Being O
hanged B-TER
or O
shot B-TER
was O
part O
of O
the O
main O
program O
. O

This O
camp B-LOC
existed O
for O
8 O
months O
. O

Those O
who O
returned O
from O
there O
were O
half O
dead B-TER
. O

Enough O
of O
that O
. O

--- O
Now O
, O
dear O
Doctor B-PER
, O
to O
Potsdam B-LOC
. O

Unfortunately O
I O
ca O
n’t O
give O
you O
any O
other O
information O
than O
that O
I O
do O
n’t O
know O
what O
happened O
to O
the O
people O
left O
behind O
. O

Until O
January O
9 O
, O
1942 O
, O
the O
wife O
of O
Sanitaetsrat O
( O
medical O
consultant O
) O
Naumann B-PER
still O
lived O
in O
her O
apartment O
. O

The O
wife O
of O
Justizrat O
( O
judicial O
council O
) O
Josephsohn B-PER
, O
Frau O
Wilk B-PER
etc O
. O

, O
they O
all O
had O
not O
yet O
been O
ordered O
to O
leave O
their O
apartment O
. O

The O
only O
one O
was O
Mr. O
Bernhard B-PER
, O
Neue B-LOC
Koenigstrasse I-LOC
, O
who O
was O
sent O
to O
the O
retirement B-TER
home I-TER
Babelsberg B-LOC
. O

The O
retirement B-TER
home I-TER
had O
been O
visited O
some O
times O
by O
interested O
parties O
, O
but O
nothing O
had O
happened O
up O
to O
the O
day O
. O

We O
still O
lived O
quite O
undisturbed O
in O
Potsdam B-LOC
- O
6 O
– O
despite O
our O
yellow B-TER
star I-TER
badge I-TER
. O

Unfortunately O
, O
I O
do O
n’t O
think O
that O
it O
lasted O
for O
a O
long O
time O
. O

It O
was O
reported O
by O
people O
from O
later O
transports B-TER
that O
old O
people O
were O
brought O
to O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
. O

Now O
the O
big O
question O
is O
: O
did O
they O
endure O
this O
? O
In O
December O
1942 O
some O
young B-TER
people I-TER
from O
Berlin B-LOC
who O
were O
placed O
in O
the O
Riga B-LOC
area O
were O
sent O
to O
our O
ghetto B-LOC
for O
delousing O
. O

They O
had O
been O
evacuated O
in O
September O
. O

Of O
course O
I O
was O
interested O
in O
getting O
some O
information O
. O

But O
I O
only O
got O
the O
information O
that O
there O
was O
no O
retirement B-TER
home I-TER
anymore O
. O

So O
I O
must O
assume O
the O
same O
thing O
, O
which O
I O
unfortunately O
had O
in O
front O
of O
my O
eyes O
every O
day O
, O
happened O
there O
. O

Please O
forgive O
me O
if O
I O
do O
n’t O
moderate O
my O
remarks O
, O
but O
unfortunately O
all O
of O
us O
have O
become O
dulled O
by O
the O
experiences O
of O
the O
last O
years O
, O
one O
might O
say O
heartless O
. O

Mr. O
James B-PER
Gersmann I-PER
was O
the O
one O
who O
had O
the O
best O
of O
it O
. O

In O
January O
1942 O
, O
the O
latter O
became O
seriously O
ill B-TER
and O
was O
sent O
to O
St. B-LOC
Joseph I-LOC
Hospital I-LOC
. O

On O
January O
11 O
, O
when O
we O
were O
still O
in O
Levetzowstrasse B-LOC
, O
Mr. O
Gersmann B-PER
died B-TER
. O

Thus O
, O
with O
the O
dissolution O
of O
the O
Potsdam B-LOC
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
, O
also O
the O
founder O
of O
it O
all O
deceased O
. O

For O
Mrs. O
Simonsohn B-PER
it O
must O
have O
been O
terrible O
to O
lose O
all O
her O
brothers B-TER
and O
sisters B-TER
. O

Well O
, O
dear O
Doctor B-PER
, O
please O
give O
my O
warmest O
greetings O
to O
Your O
wife B-TER
and O
be O
warmly O
greeted O
by O
Your O
Hanni B-PER
Rosenthal I-PER
- O
7 O
- O
Transcript O
of O
photocopy O
List O
of O
those O
who O
were O
deported B-TER
to O
Riga B-LOC
( O
January O
1942 O
) O
Apriasky B-PER
, O
I. O
Kla B-PER
. O

Gersman B-PER
, I-PER
A. I-PER
, O
Li B-PER
. I-PER

Salomon B-PER
H. O
Rita B-PER
Gormanns B-PER
S(iegfried I-PER
) I-PER
P(aula B-PER
) I-PER
junior B-PER
( I-PER
Walter I-PER
? I-PER
) I-PER
Wohl B-PER
Siegfried I-PER
Erna B-PER
Inge B-PER
Gerd B-PER
Rubert B-PER
Martha I-PER
Grete B-PER
Fridchen B-PER
Feist B-PER
Albert I-PER
junior B-PER
Betti B-PER
Dornbusch B-PER
family B-TER
Mannheim B-PER
Selma I-PER
Inge B-PER
Haase O
Juergen O
, O
however O
, O
stayed O
in O
Berlin B-LOC
because O
he O
was O
ill B-TER
. O

Meierstein B-PER
family B-TER
( O
from O
) O
Fahrland B-LOC
Meiersohn O
family B-TER
but O
stayed O
in O
Berlin B-LOC
because O
of O
attempted O
suicide B-TER
. O

Child B-TER
Mendel O
’s O
sister B-TER
Samter B-PER
Heinz I-PER
Fabian B-PER
Rosa I-PER
Hirschburg B-PER
Regine I-PER
Henschel B-PER
Lotte I-PER
Brauer B-PER
Margot I-PER
Loewenberg B-PER
Stella I-PER
au O
pair O
girl O
with O
the O
Rose O
family O
( O
in O
) O
Babelsberg B-LOC
- O
8 O
- O
2nd O
page O
of O
the O
List O
of O
those O
who O
were O
deported O
etc O
... O
Kassmann B-PER
Hilde I-PER
Schoetz B-PER
Rosa I-PER
Cohn B-PER
Rose I-PER
Urbach B-PER
Cilli I-PER
Grand B-PER
Fraenze I-PER
Grossmann B-PER
( O
from O
) O
Geltow B-LOC
Rosenthal B-PER
Johanna I-PER
