From O
: O
Minister O
Hideo B-PER
Masutani I-PER
( O
Helsinki B-LOC
) O
To O
: O
MOFA O
Togo B-PER
Shigenori I-PER
( O
Tokyo B-LOC
) O
Re O
: O
Conversation O
with O
Slovakian B-LOC
Minister O
about O
domestic O
affairs O
… O
. O

3 O
. O

The O
issue O
of O
Jews B-TER
who O
have O
great O
influence O
in O
economy B-TER
is O
an O
important O
political B-TER
issue I-TER
. O

Current O
cabinet O
minister O
and O
head O
of O
the O
Hlinka B-ORG
Guard I-ORG
Sano B-PER
Mach I-PER
is O
using O
his O
skills O
to O
resolve O
it O
. O

