Statement O
Copied O
from O
the O
original O
statement O
signed O
by O
Mrs. O
Ruth B-PER
Morgensternová I-PER
, O
residing O
in O
Brno B-LOC
, O
Na B-LOC
ponávce I-LOC
10 O
former O
prisoner B-TER
in O
the O
Bergen B-LOC
- I-LOC
Belsen I-LOC
concentr B-TER
. I-TER

camp I-TER
and O
a O
labor B-TER
camp I-TER
in O
Estonia B-LOC
Transport B-TER
Be I-TER
Theresienstadt I-TER
- O
Estonia B-LOC
. O

I. O
IX O
. O

1942 O
departure B-TER
from I-TER
Theresienstadt I-TER
, O
direction O
Riga B-LOC
. O

The O
journey O
went O
well O
; O
the O
escort O
was O
decent O
. O

The O
train B-TER
stands O
in O
Riga B-LOC
for O
a O
day O
and O
then O
rides O
on O
to O
Estonia B-LOC
. O

After O
a O
five O
- O
day O
journey O
, O
the O
train B-TER
stops O
25 O
km O
from O
Tallinn B-LOC
in O
Raasiku B-LOC
. O

The O
SS B-TER
and O
SD B-ORG
, O
with O
beautiful O
, O
blue O
buses O
, O
are O
waiting O
for O
us O
there O
. O

We O
stand O
in O
front O
of O
the O
train B-TER
and O
one O
SSman B-TER
selects O
the O
young O
people O
who O
will O
apparently O
be O
walking O
. O

The O
rest O
are O
told O
to O
put O
away O
their O
luggage O
and O
step O
onto O
the O
bus O
. O

We O
’ve O
heard O
no O
news O
of O
them O
since O
. O

We O
, O
the O
young O
ones O
( O
75 O
women B-TER
and O
about O
150 O
men B-TER
) O
, O
leave O
on O
trucks O
with O
all O
of O
the O
luggage O
from O
the O
transport B-TER
to O
the O
nearby O
JAGALLA B-LOC
camp B-TER
. O

It O
’s O
a O
camp B-TER
in O
the O
middle O
of O
a O
forest O
, O
with O
old O
, O
broken O
down O
buildings B-TER
, O
surrounded O
by O
a O
barbed O
wire O
fence O
. O

The O
Lagerführer B-TER
is O
an O
Estonian B-LOC
SDman B-ORG
; O
his O
adjutant O
a O
Baltic O
German B-TER
. O

The O
guards O
are O
Estonian B-LOC
. O

Our O
valuables O
and O
extra O
clothes B-TER
are O
taken O
away O
on O
the O
first O
evening O
( O
body O
search O
) O
. O

The O
next O
day O
, O
our O
clothes B-TER
are O
returned O
. O

Three O
days O
later O
, O
they O
lead O
us O
to O
large O
buildings B-TER
where O
we O
unpack O
and O
sort O
the O
items O
from O
our O
transport B-TER
. O

The O
men B-TER
, O
whom O
we O
glimpse O
from O
far O
away O
, O
are O
sent O
to O
work B-TER
in O
the O
forest O
. O

Only O
the O
sick B-TER
return O
to O
us O
, O
and O
they O
are O
sent O
away O
, O
allegedly O
to O
Dorpat B-LOC
, O
where O
there O
is O
an O
infirmary B-TER
. O

Supposedly O
, O
the O
rest O
of O
the O
transport B-TER
is O
there O
, O
but O
we O
never O
heard O
from O
any O
inhabitant O
of O
Dorpat B-LOC
that O
there O
were O
Jews O
there O
. O

Women B-TER
are O
treated O
well O
; O
men B-TER
fare O
far O
worse O
, O
especially O
when O
they O
work B-TER
outside O
, O
where O
the O
Estonians B-LOC
rob O
then O
and O
do O
n’t O
give O
them O
anything O
to O
eat B-TER
. O

The O
food B-TER
is O
not O
bad O
; O
connection O
to O
the O
outside O
world O
is O
impossible O
. O

In O
October O
, O
another O
transport B-TER
arrives O
from O
Germany B-LOC
( O
Frankfurt B-LOC
and O
Berlin B-LOC
) O
. O

Once O
again O
, O
luggage O
and O
some O
of O
the O
people O
go O
to O
Jagälla B-LOC
. O

In O
December O
, O
a O
large O
transport B-TER
of O
women B-TER
leaves O
for O
Revala B-LOC
( I-LOC
Tallinn I-LOC
) I-LOC
and O
supposedly O
to O
Dorpat B-LOC
( O
only O
the O
older B-TER
and O
sick B-TER
) O
. O

The O
rest O
of O
the O
women B-TER
( O
there O
are O
45 O
of O
them O
and O
almost O
all O
are O
Czech B-TER
) O
move O
into O
very O
nice O
buildings B-TER
. O

After O
their O
work B-TER
in O
Schleuse B-TER
is O
done O
, O
the O
women B-TER
go O
to O
the O
forest O
to O
chop B-TER
down O
trees O
and O
tear B-TER
down I-TER
old O
buildings O
. O

The O
work B-TER
is O
very O
hard O
. O

In O
August O
1943 O
, O
the O
rest O
of O
the O
women B-TER
leave O
for O
Tallinn B-LOC
; O
the O
camp B-TER
is O
liquidated O
. O

Before O
we O
leave O
, O
most O
of O
our O
things O
are O
taken O
away O
from O
us O
. O

In O
Tallinn B-LOC
, O
we O
live B-TER
in O
the O
central O
prison B-TER
, O
where O
we O
meet O
up O
with O
the O
first O
transport B-TER
, O
and O
work B-TER
together O
doing O
cleaning O
work B-TER
in O
the O
port O
under O
the O
supervision O
of O
the O
OT B-ORG
. O

Here O
, O
we O
see O
the O
men B-TER
from O
our O
transport B-TER
who O
also O
return O
to O
the O
prison B-TER
after O
their O
work B-TER
is O
done O
. O

The O
food B-TER
in O
prison B-TER
is O
terrible O
, O
but O
we O
can O
sometimes O
procure O
something O
for O
ourselves O
. O

In O
December O
1943 O
, O
all O
of O
the O
women B-TER
leave O
Tallinn B-LOC
and O
go O
to O
EREDA B-LOC
( O
about O
30 O
km O
from O
Narva B-LOC
) O
. O

The O
men B-TER
remain O
in O
Tallinn B-LOC
, O
and O
this O
is O
where O
we O
last O
hear O
from O
them O
in O
March O
1944 O
. O

Ereda B-LOC
is O
a O
small O
camp B-TER
. O

It O
already O
houses O
about O
1,000 O
Jews O
from O
Lithuania B-LOC
( O
Vilnius B-LOC
and O
Kovno B-LOC
) O
and O
Latvia B-LOC
. O

They O
are O
lice B-TER
- I-TER
infested I-TER
and O
without O
their O
belongings O
. O

In O
the O
surrounding O
area O
, O
there O
are O
several O
other O
similar O
camps B-TER
. O

There O
are O
also O
several O
Czechs B-TER
there O
, O
arriving O
from O
Riga B-LOC
. O

The O
SS B-TER
has O
already O
taken O
leadership O
of O
it O
; O
guards O
are O
Est B-LOC
. I-LOC

and O
O.T. B-ORG
The O
food B-TER
is O
bad O
, O
but O
we O
have O
the O
option O
to O
obtain O
things O
for O
ourselves O
, O
but O
only O
the O
fearless O
among O
us O
attempt O
this O
. O

We O
work B-TER
in O
the O
forest O
and O
on O
the O
construction O
of O
a O
new O
camp B-TER
a O
few O
km O
away O
. O

There O
is O
typhus B-TER
; O
there O
are O
sick B-TER
people I-TER
; O
the B-TER
elderly I-TER
and O
children B-TER
are O
constantly O
sent O
away O
( O
most O
likely O
to O
Auschwitz B-LOC
) O
. O

When O
the O
Russians B-ORG
approach O
( O
in O
July O
1944 O
) O
, O
we O
depart O
for O
Tallinn B-LOC
, O
where O
a O
boat O
is O
supposed O
to O
be O
waiting O
for O
us O
. O

It O
’s O
not O
there O
, O
and O
so O
we O
go O
to O
a O
suburb O
of O
Tallinn B-LOC
to O
a O
large O
meadow O
, O
where O
we O
stay O
for O
three O
weeks O
with O
no O
shelter B-TER
. O

We O
dig B-TER
trenches I-TER
. O

There O
is O
famine B-TER
in O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

In O
August O
, O
we O
finally O
sail O
to O
Germany B-LOC
. O

We O
sail O
for O
five O
days O
without O
food B-TER
. O

We O
arrive O
in O
Danzig B-LOC
and O
sail O
down O
the O
Vistula B-LOC
to O
Stutthof B-LOC
. O

There O
, O
we O
are O
sent O
to O
the O
baths O
, O
our O
belongings O
are O
taken O
away O
, O
and O
we O
are O
given O
new O
clothes B-TER
. O

Our O
hair O
was O
already O
cut O
before O
we O
left O
Estonia B-LOC
. O

Women B-TER
who O
are O
capable O
of O
working B-TER
leave O
for O
Hamburg B-LOC
after O
three O
weeks O
to O
work B-TER
in O
a O
munitions O
plant B-TER
. O

From O
there O
, O
we O
are O
evacuated O
in O
April O
1945 O
to O
Bergen B-LOC
- I-LOC
Belsen I-LOC
, O
where O
we O
remain O
until O
liberation B-TER
. O

Signature O
: O
Schicková B-PER
Statement O
copied O
by O
: O
Helena B-PER
Schicková I-PER
copied O
from O
the O
original O
statement O
Signature O
of O
witnesses O
: O
B. B-PER
Gerzonová I-PER
Accepted O
on O
behalf O
of O
the O
documentation B-TER
campaign I-TER
: O
Scheck B-PER
On O
behalf O
of O
the O
archive O
: O
