[ O
… O
] O
On O
December O
1 O
, O
the O
Press B-TER
published O
a O
Circular O
of O
the O
Provincial O
Presidents O
, O
who O
now O
unite O
the O
posts O
as O
( O
administrative O
) O
Prefect O
and O
( O
political O
) O
Fascist B-TER
leader O
in O
the O
Province O
, O
by O
the O
following O
Police B-TER
Ordinance B-TER
: O
1 O
) O
All O
Jews B-TER
, O
including O
those O
occupying O
a O
special O
position O
of O
any O
nationality B-TER
residing O
in O
Italy B-ORG
, O
must O
be O
put O
in O
concentration B-TER
camps I-TER
. O

All O
their O
property B-TER
, O
movable O
property O
, O
and O
immovable O
property O
will O
be O
seized O
immediately O
until O
they O
can O
be O
confiscated B-TER
for O
the O
benefit O
of O
the O
Social B-ORG
Italian I-ORG
Republic I-ORG
, O
which O
will O
use O
them O
to O
the O
best O
for O
the O
casualties O
of O
the O
hostile O
airstrikes B-TER
. O

All O
those O
who O
are O
offspring O
of O
a O
mixed B-TER
Marriage I-TER
, O
are O
recognized O
under O
applicable O
Italian B-ORG
Racial B-TER
Law I-TER
as O
of O
Aryan B-TER
descent O
and O
must O
be O
placed O
under O
special O
police B-TER
supervision I-TER
. O

With O
regard O
to O
the O
Press B-TER
’s I-TER
comments O
on O
these O
new O
Regulations B-TER
, O
one O
is O
permitted O
to O
state O
the O
following O
; O
REGIME O
FASCISTA O
on O
the O
2 O
December O
seeks O
to O
justify O
the O
new O
Precautions O
against O
the O
Jews B-TER
, O
by O
stating O
first O
, O
that O
Italian B-ORG
Jews B-TER
under O
Badoglio B-PER
's I-PER
government B-TER
were O
active O
in O
an O
anti B-TER
- I-TER
fascist I-TER
movement O
, O
and O
participated O
in O
the O
destruction O
of O
fascist O
property O
, O
etc O
. O

and O
that O
before O
the O
war B-TER
- O
as O
is O
evident O
from O
various O
texts O
quoted O
- O
sought O
to O
instigate O
. O

There O
is O
thus O
no O
doubt O
about O
their O
responsibility O
. O

The O
logical O
answer O
is O
that O
we O
should O
exterminate B-TER
the O
Jews B-TER
. O

But O
, O
as O
always O
, O
the O
Italian B-ORG
people O
appear O
extremely O
noble O
and O
have O
confined O
themselves O
to O
robbing B-TER
them O
of O
their O
possessions O
. O

The O
bombing B-TER
of O
our O
cities O
is O
wanted O
and O
praised O
by O
the O
Jewish B-TER
International I-TER
. O

What O
is O
more O
reasonable O
than O
their O
possessions O
being O
used O
, O
to O
relieve O
the O
consequences O
of O
the O
Hebrew O
crime O
to O
some O
degree O
? O
[ O
… O
] O
Livorno B-LOC
magazine O
TELEGRAFO O
on O
the O
8/12 O
publishes O
a O
Note O
, O
dated O
Rome B-LOC
, O
7/12 O
, O
of O
the O
following O
: O
Only O
twelve O
hours O
after O
the O
republican- O
fascist B-TER
government B-TER
had O
decreed O
that O
the O
Jews B-TER
should O
be O
eliminated B-TER
from O
the O
life O
of O
the O
Italian B-ORG
state O
, O
the O
capital O
has O
begun O
the O
process O
of O
purification O
. O

In O
total O
, O
10,000 O
Persons O
of O
Semitic B-TER
descent O
have O
been O
chased O
out O
. O

Some O
of O
the O
Jews B-TER
of O
Rome B-LOC
have O
already O
left O
the O
city O
some O
time O
ago O
and O
set O
off O
for O
northern O
Italy B-ORG
. O

It O
is O
expected O
that O
in O
this O
way O
approx O
. O

20,000 O
apartments O
, O
will O
be O
made O
available O
for O
injured O
Roman B-LOC
families O
and O
for O
refugees O
from O
southern O
Italy B-ORG
. O

However O
, O
the O
Roman B-LOC
magazines B-TER
did O
not O
contain O
any O
such O
message O
, O
just O
as O
the O
legation O
have O
not O
heard O
anything O
to O
confirm O
this O
. O

Otto B-PER
Wadsted I-PER
