Report O
of O
the O
1st O
Secretary O
of O
the O
Legation O
, O
Carlo B-PER
Alberto I-PER
de I-PER
Vera I-PER
d’Aragona I-PER
to O
the O
Italian O
Ministry O
of O
Foreign O
Affairs O
. O

Incoming O
telegram O
no O
. O

2356 O
R. O
By O
courier O
Decoded O
by O
: O
SE O
– O
Cleartext O
R. O
Legation O
Bratislava B-LOC
27.3.42.XX O
Bratislava O
, O
6.4.42.XX O
Copy O
modified O
in O
assigning O
Assigned O
to O
A.G. O
A.E.M. O
Re O
: O
Measures B-TER
against I-TER
the I-TER
Jews I-TER
014 O
- O
The O
new O
measures O
against O
the O
Jews B-TER
that O
had O
been O
announced O
have O
all O
of O
a O
sudden O
seen O
a O
drastic O
implementation O
. O

Ten B-TER
thousand I-TER
Jews I-TER
in O
towns O
and O
in O
villages O
had O
received O
personal O
summonses O
in O
order O
to O
be O
assembled O
in O
concentration B-TER
camps I-TER
. O

Due O
to O
the O
ease O
with O
which O
one O
may O
convert O
to O
the O
evangelical B-TER
Church I-TER
and O
because O
many O
of O
those O
summoned O
were O
aware O
that O
public O
opinion O
was O
mostly O
opposed O
to O
the O
anti B-TER
- I-TER
Semitic I-TER
campaign I-TER
, O
and O
also O
because O
rumour B-TER
had O
it O
that O
the O
President O
of O
the O
Republic B-LOC
, O
Monsignor O
Tiso B-PER
, O
was O
indirectly O
opposed O
to O
such O
methods O
of O
persecution O
, O
many O
Jews O
did O
not O
comply O
with O
the O
orders B-TER
given O
by O
Minister B-PER
Mach I-PER
. O

So O
in O
the O
night O
from O
23rd O
to O
24th O
March O
patrols O
formed O
by O
police B-TER
and I-TER
Guardsmen I-TER
who O
had O
been O
joined O
by O
SS B-TER
men I-TER
arrived O
from O
over O
the O
nearby O
border O
, O
entered O
Jewish O
homes O
, O
seized O
three O
thousand O
women O
aged O
18 O
to O
35 O
years O
, O
and O
carried O
them O
swiftly O
on O
a O
lorry O
to O
the O
munitions O
factory O
in O
Bratislava O
and O
to O
the O
internment O
areas O
of O
Nitra B-LOC
, O
Žilina B-LOC
, O
Prešov B-LOC
, O
etc O
. O

The O
Authorities O
closest O
to O
the O
President O
are O
denying O
or O
trying O
to O
downplay O
the O
extent O
of O
the O
events O
that O
have O
clearly O
shaken O
the O
public O
opinion O
here O
, O
although O
everyone O
knows O
that O
the O
originator O
of O
this O
undertaking O
is O
Minister B-PER
Mach I-PER
, O
Commander O
of O
the O
Hlinka B-ORG
Guard I-ORG
, O
who O
is O
being O
instigated O
by O
elements O
from O
beyond O
the O
border O
and O
by O
others O
who O
oppose O
the O
President O
, O
and O
who O
accuses O
the O
Jews B-TER
themselves O
of O
being O
responsible O
for O
everything O
and O
deserving O
of O
the O
worst O
punishments O
. O

It O
is O
well O
- O
known O
that O
the O
Minister O
of O
Interior O
, O
who O
is O
entirely O
subservient O
to O
the O
orders O
from O
beyond O
the O
Danube O
, O
intends O
to O
gradually O
carry O
out O
the O
concentration O
and O
mass O
deportation O
of O
all O
the O
Israelites B-TER
of O
Slovakia B-LOC
, O
that O
is O
approximately O
70 O
thousand O
souls O
, O
the O
older O
ones O
to O
the O
General B-TER
Governorate I-TER
of I-TER
Poland I-TER
( O
Lublin B-LOC
area O
) O
and O
the O
younger O
to O
Ukrainian O
locations O
, O
to O
be O
employed O
in O
farm O
labour O
and O
in O
the O
Organisation O
Todt O
. O

However O
, O
since O
at O
least O
for O
the O
time O
being O
they O
are O
mostly O
women O
still O
in O
the O
bloom O
of O
youth O
and O
of O
good O
social O
standing O
, O
no O
doubt O
their O
employ O
will O
be O
of O
an O
entirely O
different O
character O
and O
purpose O
, O
in O
the O
train O
of O
the O
German O
units O
operating O
in O
southern O
Russia O
. O

The O
announcement O
of O
harsher O
anti O
- O
Semitic O
measures O
had O
already O
prompted O
the O
Holy O
See O
to O
deliver O
a O
note O
to O
the O
Minister O
of O
Slovakia O
, O
Mister O
Sidor O
; O
the O
persecutions O
that O
have O
since O
taken O
place O
have O
then O
given O
rise O
to O
repeated O
démarches O
on O
the O
part O
of O
the O
Apostolic O
Delegate O
, O
Monsignor O
Burzio O
, O
with O
Prime O
Minister O
Tuka B-PER
. O

As O
things O
now O
stand O
, O
the O
events O
described O
above O
have O
caused O
a O
rift O
not O
yet O
made O
public O
but O
dangerous O
between O
Prime O
Minister O
Tuka B-PER
and O
Minister B-PER
Mach I-PER
on O
the O
one O
side O
and O
President O
Tiso B-PER
on O
the O
other O
. O

The O
consequences O
are O
easy O
to O
predict O
if O
the O
anti O
- O
Semitic O
persecution O
should O
continue O
in O
the O
manner O
reported O
above O
and O
the O
President O
of O
the O
Republic O
, O
being O
a O
cleric O
and O
a O
parish O
priest O
with O
the O
care O
of O
souls O
, O
should O
sooner O
or O
later O
be O
faced O
with O
a O
serious O
crisis O
of O
conscience O
. O

De B-PER
Vera I-PER
