Y.L. O
, O
18 O
years O
old O
Cutter O
and O
stitcher O
of O
shoe O
- O
leather O
Z.L. O
, O
21 O
years O
old O
Carpenter O
Brothers B-TER
from O
Ostrów B-LOC
Mazowiecka I-LOC
Details O
about O
the O
mass B-TER
massacre I-TER
in O
Ostrów B-LOC
Mazowiecka I-LOC
Protocol O
No O
. O

192 O
( O
compiled O
on O
February O
18 O
, O
1940 O
) O
We O
can O
give O
the O
following O
details O
about O
the O
mass B-TER
massacre I-TER
of O
Jews O
in O
Ostrów B-LOC
Mazowiecka I-LOC
( O
Great B-LOC
Ostrów I-LOC
) O
. O

It O
was O
Thursday O
, O
November O
9 O
, O
1939 O
. O

On O
this O
day O
, O
561 O
Jews B-TER
died I-TER
. O

We O
ourselves O
talked O
to O
the O
daughter B-TER
of O
the O
perished B-TER
Yosl B-PER
Modrykamyen I-PER
, O
who O
was O
also O
killed B-TER
on O
this O
very O
day O
( O
he O
was O
approximately O
35 O
years O
old O
) O
. O

Yosl B-PER
Modrykamyen I-PER
’s O
wife B-TER
died B-TER
as O
well O
. O

Only O
his O
daughter B-TER
was O
able O
to O
save O
herself O
. O

We O
also O
talked O
with O
a O
Jew O
, O
who O
was O
in O
Ostrów B-LOC
on O
the O
day O
of O
the O
massacre B-TER
and O
survived O
owing O
to O
the O
fact O
that O
he O
was O
wearing O
a O
Christian B-TER
[ O
peaked O
] O
cap O
, O
a O
matsheyuvke O
, O
a O
kind O
of O
cap O
with O
a O
visor O
and O
he O
was O
shaved O
and O
generally O
looked O
like O
a O
Christian B-TER
. O

They O
both O
related O
that O
the O
Germans B-TER
themselves O
placarded O
posters O
on O
the O
streets O
announcing O
that O
the O
Jews O
of O
Ostrów B-LOC
died B-TER
in O
accordance O
with O
a O
verdict O
of O
a O
German B-TER
court B-TER
. O

The O
calamity O
happened O
under O
the O
following O
circumstances O
: O
One O
side O
of O
Rinek B-LOC
caught O
fire O
( O
Rinek B-LOC
the O
street O
is O
called O
where O
once O
there O
was O
a O
market O
; O
officially O
: O
Square O
of O
the O
Duchess O
Anna O
Mazowiecka O
) O
. O

Only O
Jewish O
houses O
are O
located O
there O
like O
the O
house O
of O
Teytel B-PER
, O
Likhtnshteyn B-PER
, O
Kronenberg B-PER
, O
Bromberg B-PER
and O
of O
others O
. O

There O
were O
stores O
for O
textiles O
, O
haberdasheries O
, O
groceries O
and O
also O
a O
candy O
store O
. O

It O
was O
almost O
the O
main O
street O
. O

We O
presume O
that O
the O
Germans B-TER
themselves O
set O
the O
houses O
on O
fire O
. O

The O
houses O
burnt O
a O
whole O
night O
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
later O
implied O
that O
the O
Jews O
set O
the O
fire O
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
promised O
the O
Poles B-TER
25 O
Złoty O
per O
head O
when O
they O
turn O
over O
Jews O
, O
and O
the O
Poles B-TER
constantly O
dragged O
Jews O
to O
the O
city B-LOC
hall I-LOC
where O
the O
German B-TER
police B-TER
station O
was O
located O
. O

The O
Polish B-TER
mob O
together O
with O
the O
Germans B-TER
dragged O
the O
Jews O
out O
of O
the O
houses O
. O

Everyone O
was O
dragged O
out O
, O
also O
old O
people O
, O
women B-TER
, O
and O
children B-TER
. O

From O
the O
city B-LOC
hall I-LOC
the O
Jews O
were O
led O
to O
Warsaw B-LOC
Road I-LOC
, O
after O
Starastve B-LOC
Street I-LOC
, O
near O
the O
woods O
of O
the O
former O
Polish B-TER
commander O
where O
once O
there O
was O
a O
summer O
house O
. O

This O
is O
located O
one O
and O
a O
half O
kilometres O
away O
from O
Ostrów B-LOC
Mazowiecka I-LOC
. O

There O
, O
561 O
Jews O
were O
gathered O
, O
and O
the O
Germans B-TER
ordered O
the O
Jews O
to O
dig O
out O
pits B-TER
. O

And O
the O
Jews O
had O
to O
lay O
themselves O
into O
the O
pits B-TER
. O

Parents O
had O
to O
throw O
their O
own O
children B-TER
into O
the O
pits B-TER
, O
and O
with O
rifles O
and O
revolvers O
all O
Jews O
were O
shot B-TER
to I-TER
death I-TER
. O

The O
remaining O
Jews O
, O
who O
were O
caught O
after O
the O
execution B-TER
[ O
had O
taken O
place O
] O
, O
were O
led O
into O
the O
prison B-TER
as O
well O
as O
into O
the O
ice O
cellar O
of O
the O
brewery O
of O
the O
brothers B-TER
Teytel B-PER
. O

Since O
Ostrów B-LOC
is O
less O
than O
2 O
kilometres O
away O
from O
the O
Soviet B-TER
border O
, O
the O
majority O
of O
Ostrów B-LOC
’s O
inhabitants O
ran O
away O
to O
the O
Russian B-TER
side O
. O

Roughly O
15 O
families B-TER
remained O
who O
have O
n’t O
had O
the O
opportunity O
to O
leave O
because O
of O
the O
older O
people O
. O

In O
Ostrów B-LOC
, O
refugees B-TER
from O
Warsaw B-LOC
, O
Łódź B-LOC
and O
other O
cities O
arrived O
. O

The O
refugees B-TER
were O
n’t O
able O
to O
cross O
the O
Russian B-TER
border O
anymore O
which O
was O
already O
closed O
and O
they O
returned O
to O
Ostrów B-LOC
and O
there O
they O
died B-TER
. O

Among O
the O
victims O
from O
Ostrów B-LOC
Mazowiecka I-LOC
, O
the O
following O
names O
are O
known O
: O
1–2 O
) O
Two O
daughters B-TER
of O
Knorpel B-PER
( O
the O
owner O
of O
a O
vinegar O
factory B-TER
and O
the O
chairman O
of O
the O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
) O
; O
both O
girls B-TER
were O
over O
20 O
years O
old O
. O

Their O
father B-TER
, O
the O
chairman O
of O
the O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
Knorpel B-PER
, O
survived O
because O
of O
a O
large O
sum O
of O
money O
thanks O
to O
which O
Christians B-TER
took O
him O
across B-TER
the I-TER
border I-TER
. O

3–4 O
) O
Dvoyre B-PER
Veydenboym I-PER
, O
from O
Lipsker O
’s O
home O
, O
a O
midwife O
, O
around O
35 O
to O
40 O
years O
old O
; O
also O
her O
little O
daughter B-TER
, O
7 O
years O
of O
age O
, O
studying O
in O
a O
Tarbut O
school O
. O

( O
Christians B-TER
hid B-TER
this O
child B-TER
. O

But O
then O
Poles B-TER
denounced B-TER
these O
Christians B-TER
to O
the O
Germans B-TER
and O
the O
latter O
shot B-TER
the O
child B-TER
in O
front O
of O
the O
mother B-TER
. O

Her O
husband B-TER
, O
engineer O
Veydenboym B-PER
, O
is O
in O
Białystok B-LOC
. O

) O
5 O
) O
Rivke B-PER
Lipsker I-PER
, O
the O
sister B-TER
of O
Dvoyre B-PER
Veydenboym I-PER
. O

Rivke B-PER
Lipsker I-PER
was O
approximately O
35 O
years O
old O
. O

She O
was O
a O
hotel O
owner O
, O
a O
widow O
. O

6 O
) O
Perl B-PER
, O
the O
daughter B-TER
of O
Rivke B-PER
Lipsker I-PER
, O
roughly O
20 O
years O
old O
, O
a O
domestic O
worker O
, O
unmarried O
. O

( O
Rivke B-PER
Lipsker I-PER
’s O
son B-TER
, O
Velvl B-PER
, O
who O
was O
serving O
in O
the O
Polish B-TER
army B-TER
, O
is O
located O
in O
Białystok B-LOC
now O
. O

) O
A O
mass O
of O
refugees B-TER
were O
taken O
out O
of O
Rivke B-PER
Lipsker I-PER
’s O
hotel O
and O
killed B-TER
. O

7 O
) O
Volmark B-PER
Shelke I-PER
, O
in O
his O
fifties O
, O
a O
coachman O
. O

On O
the O
day O
of O
the O
massacre B-TER
, O
he O
hid B-TER
on O
the O
Jewish B-TER
cemetery I-TER
. O

Then O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
came O
there O
and O
chopped B-TER
off I-TER
his I-TER
head I-TER
with O
a O
sword O
. O

His O
son B-TER
Mendl B-PER
Volmark I-PER
, O
who O
had O
left O
Ostrów B-LOC
long O
before O
, O
is O
in O
Białystok B-LOC
now O
. O

The O
Jew O
, O
who O
survived O
thanks O
to O
his O
Christian B-TER
appearance O
, O
told O
us O
that O
he O
remembers O
well O
the O
faces O
of O
some O
Poles B-TER
, O
who O
informed O
the O
Germans B-TER
where O
Jews O
were O
living O
and O
dragged O
them O
out O
and O
turned O
them O
over O
to O
the O
Germans B-TER
for O
money O
. O

The O
Jew O
will O
not O
rest O
and O
testify O
whenever O
it O
will O
be O
possible O
. O

Our O
father B-TER
survived O
miraculously O
. O

A O
bomb O
entered O
the O
house O
but O
he O
was O
not O
harmed O
. O

Signed O
: O
Y.R. O
