Dawid B-PER
Kohane I-PER
Testimony O
( O
doc O
. O

301/191 O
) O
Original O
, O
manuscript O
, O
6 O
pages O
, O
145 O
x O
208 O
mm O
, O
Polish O
language O
Dawid B-PER
Kohane I-PER
Born O
10th O
of O
July O
1917 O
in O
Rzepiennik B-LOC
( O
Gorlice B-LOC
district I-LOC
) O
It O
has O
not O
been O
possible O
to O
establish O
which O
Rzepiennik O
the O
author O
lived O
in O
: O
R. O
Biskupi O
, O
R. O
Marciszewski O
, O
R. O
Strzyżowski O
or O
R. O
Suchy O
A O
Talmudist O
– O
a O
yeshiva O
in O
Tarnów B-LOC
When O
the O
war B-TER
broke O
out O
– O
with O
the O
army B-TER
. O

Wounded O
and O
taken O
captive O
near O
Lvov B-LOC
on O
22nd O
of O
September O
1939 O
. O

Escaped B-TER
. O

Came O
back O
home O
. O

Rzepiennik B-LOC
– O
500 O
Jews O
There O
were O
no O
German B-TER
authorities B-TER
until O
1942 O
. O

Things O
were O
very O
peaceful O
. O

In O
December O
1941 O
an O
order O
arrived O
( O
from O
Gorlice B-LOC
) O
to O
give O
up O
fur O
coats O
. O

From O
1942 O
a O
Sturmführer B-TER
from O
Arbeitsamt B-ORG
used O
to O
arrive O
and O
take O
people O
( O
men B-TER
) O
to O
work B-TER
. O

He O
took O
ransom B-TER
in O
the O
form O
of O
vodka B-TER
, O
pork B-TER
fat I-TER
, O
bedclothes O
, O
coffee B-TER
, O
tea B-TER
. O

He O
would O
take O
30 O
- O
35 O
men B-TER
into O
a O
camp B-TER
near O
Sanok B-LOC
. O

They O
worked B-TER
for O
2 O
months O
. O

Then O
they O
escaped B-TER
. O

A O
deputy O
of O
Kreishauptmann B-TER
, O
District O
head O
Gartner B-PER
, O
the O
Schulrat O
, O
Schools O
supervisor O
came O
from O
Jasło B-LOC
in O
March O
to O
inspect O
schools B-TER
. O

He O
’d O
burst O
into O
Jewish O
flats B-TER
. O

He O
’d O
beat O
the O
women B-TER
. O

He O
broke B-TER
one O
elderly B-TER
lady I-TER
’s O
arm O
and O
leg O
. O

He O
burst O
into O
the O
Judenrat B-TER
with O
a O
revolver O
, O
threatening B-TER
to O
kill B-TER
everyone O
unless O
he O
’d O
be O
given O
20 O
litres O
of O
slivovitz B-TER
. O

All O
Jews O
escaped B-TER
. O

He O
vandalized O
flats B-TER
, O
robbed B-TER
whatever O
he O
could O
. O

A O
Polish B-LOC
canon B-TER
priest I-TER
Krzemień B-PER
accompanied O
him O
( O
[ O
he O
had O
been O
] O
in O
Rzepiennik B-LOC
before O
then O
) O
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
would O
always O
stop O
by O
at O
his O
place O
; O
they O
drank O
at O
his O
place O
and O
with O
him O
too O
. O

He O
would O
always O
invite O
them O
. O

A O
German B-TER
committee O
of O
8 O
people O
arrived O
in O
April O
for O
junaks O
. O

They O
demanded O
the O
Judenrat B-TER
deliver O
vodka B-TER
and O
cigarettes O
– O
it O
did O
. O

They O
asked O
for O
more O
vodka B-TER
to O
be O
prepared O
for O
the O
evening O
– O
there O
was O
n’t O
any O
. O

All O
Jews O
had O
fled B-TER
. O

In O
the O
evening O
they O
went O
looking O
for O
Jews O
and O
thieving O
with O
the O
Polish B-LOC
police B-TER
: O
Jan B-PER
Wid I-PER
and O
Hubert B-PER
Kuczera I-PER
. O

They O
caught O
a O
60 O
year O
- O
old O
woman B-TER
from O
Cracow B-LOC
, O
Lorier B-PER
. O

They O
beat B-TER
her O
in O
a O
horrible O
manner O
, O
they O
told O
her O
to O
climb O
over O
a O
wall O
( O
Wid B-PER
) O
. O

A O
contribution B-TER
in O
July O
– O
25000 O
. O

A O
few O
days O
later O
they O
demanded B-TER
35 O
men O
’s O
suits B-TER
. O

Next O
, O
Romański B-PER
, O
head O
of O
Liegenschaftsamt O
, O
Real O
estate O
office O
came O
and O
robbed B-TER
everything O
: O
furniture B-TER
, O
clothes B-TER
. O

He O
filled O
up O
10 O
trucks O
. O

July O
1942 O
The O
Judenrat B-TER
gave O
a O
Jew O
deported B-TER
from O
Łódź B-LOC
a O
paper O
to O
a O
Jew O
who O
lived O
2 O
kilometres O
outside O
Rzepiennik B-LOC
. O

When O
stopped O
outside O
the O
town O
, O
the O
Jew O
produced O
this O
paper O
as O
identification O
. O

Thus O
, O
the O
Judenrat B-TER
was O
accused O
of O
issuing O
passes O
. O

A O
day O
later O
the O
Obmann O
Obmann O
– O
president O
, O
head O
and O
the O
Judenrat B-TER
’s I-TER
secretary O
received O
a O
summons O
from O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
in O
Gorlice B-LOC
. I-LOC

From O
there O
they O
were O
sent O
on O
, O
allegedly O
to O
a O
court O
hearing O
in O
Jasło B-LOC
, O
and O
shot B-TER
dead B-TER
the O
day O
after O
. O

Beginning O
of O
August O
– O
Kreishauptmann B-TER
arrives O
from O
Jasło B-LOC
. O

Doctor B-PER
Gentz I-PER
– O
on O
the O
square O
all O
Jews O
are O
put O
on O
a O
registry O
. O

He O
calculated O
. O

He O
asked O
boys B-TER
between O
18 O
and O
35 O
year O
- O
old O
to O
step O
forward O
. O

There O
were O
45 O
men B-TER
. O

Everyone O
came O
back O
home B-TER
. O

An O
order O
came O
two O
days O
later O
from O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
in O
Jasło B-LOC
, O
saying O
these O
men B-TER
were O
to O
go O
to O
work B-TER
in O
Bobowa B-LOC
. O

The O
Judenrat B-TER
’s I-TER
Obmann O
in O
Bobowa B-LOC
asked O
for O
a O
few O
people O
to O
be O
released O
, O
to O
which O
he O
got O
this O
reply O
from O
a O
Gestapo B-ORG
soldier O
: O
Die O
Leute O
werden O
mir O
dankbar O
sein O
, O
dass O
sie O
hier O
sind O
. O

These O
people O
will O
be O
grateful O
to O
me O
for O
being O
here O
. O

They O
were O
taken O
to O
Prokocim B-LOC
on O
8th O
August O
1942 O
. O

On O
11th O
August O
1942 O
the O
head O
of O
Gestapo B-ORG
came O
to O
Rzepiennik B-LOC
from O
Jasło B-LOC
along O
with O
the O
head O
of O
Liegenschaftsamt O
and O
they O
demanded O
a O
contribution B-TER
of O
10000 O
for O
restoration O
of O
furniture B-TER
. O

At O
the O
same O
time O
, O
they O
summoned O
the O
commune O
head O
and O
the O
chief O
of O
Polish B-LOC
police O
to O
choose O
a O
location O
for O
a O
Jewish O
grave O
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
came O
with O
the O
junaks O
at O
3 O
in O
the O
morning O
the O
day O
after O
, O
they O
woke O
all O
Jews O
up O
, O
telling O
them O
they O
’d O
be O
deported B-TER
. O

They O
told O
everyone O
to O
take O
25 O
kg O
of O
their O
best O
possessions O
. O

( O
The O
youth O
were O
digging O
a O
grave O
at O
that O
time O
. O

) O
Everyone O
was O
herded O
into O
a O
square O
, O
along O
with O
their O
bundles O
. O

Twelve O
Gestapo B-ORG
men O
arrived O
, O
they O
went O
into O
a O
tavern O
, O
drank O
12 O
liters O
of O
vodka B-TER
. O

They O
told O
everyone O
to O
kneel O
down O
– O
3 O
hours O
, O
6 O
- O
9 O
in O
the O
morning O
, O
they O
told O
them O
to O
give B-TER
up I-TER
their I-TER
belongings I-TER
, O
put O
them O
on O
autos O
. O

Next O
they O
were O
all O
taken O
towards O
a O
forest O
( O
and O
beaten B-TER
along O
the O
way O
) O
, O
to O
a O
square O
near O
Dąbra B-LOC
. O

Forest O
near O
Rzepiennik O
They O
were O
told O
to O
give B-TER
up I-TER
money I-TER
. O

Then O
, O
they O
were O
told O
to O
take O
clothes B-TER
off O
, O
10 O
people O
at O
a O
time O
. O

Adults O
were O
shot O
, O
thrown O
into O
the O
grave O
, O
often O
wounded O
but O
still O
alive O
; O
they O
buried O
the O
people O
, O
shouts O
could O
be O
heard O
: O
It O
’s O
burning O
my O
eyes O
. O

Children B-TER
were O
smashed O
against O
trees O
and O
torn O
apart O
. O

After O
the O
execution B-TER
was O
over O
the O
canon B-TER
priest I-TER
invited O
all O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
men O
to O
dinner O
. O

The O
shooting B-TER
went O
on O
from O
10 O
o’clock O
in O
the O
morning O
until O
3 O
o’clock O
[ O
in O
the O
afternoon O
] O
. O

Abel B-PER
Kahane I-PER
( O
currently O
in O
Cracow B-LOC
) O
witnessed O
the O
execution B-TER
, O
he O
was O
standing O
on O
a O
hill O
100 O
metres O
away O
. O

He O
, O
his O
sister B-TER
and O
her O
husband B-TER
and O
children B-TER
and O
one O
other O
family B-TER
lived O
out O
of O
the O
town O
and O
so O
they O
did O
n’t O
get O
surrounded O
by O
the O
police O
cordon O
and O
managed O
to O
escape B-TER
. O

The O
OD B-TER
who O
came O
to O
wake O
them O
up O
saved O
himself O
too O
. O

All O
of O
them O
, O
however O
, O
except O
for O
Abel B-PER
Kahane I-PER
, O
died B-TER
later O
. O

Abel B-PER
Kahane I-PER
hid B-TER
in O
the O
forest O
. O

His O
sister B-TER
and O
her O
children B-TER
took O
hide B-TER
with O
a O
farmer O
. O

Four O
weeks O
later O
, O
when O
the O
farmer O
would O
not O
have O
them O
any O
more O
, O
Dawid B-PER
Kahane I-PER
came O
( O
without O
the O
band O
) O
from O
a O
camp B-TER
and O
took O
his O
family O
to O
the O
ghetto B-TER
in O
Tarnów B-LOC
, O
and O
took O
his O
brother B-TER
to O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

46 O
people O
from O
Rzepiennik B-LOC
worked O
in O
Prokocim B-LOC
. O

Three O
months O
later O
, O
5 O
people O
, O
sensing O
that O
things O
were O
getting O
unsteady O
, O
escaped B-TER
to O
Rzepiennik B-LOC
. O

They O
paid O
their O
Polish B-TER
neighbours O
there O
for O
letting O
them O
hide B-TER
at O
their O
place O
, O
sometimes O
hid B-TER
in O
forests B-TER
, O
sometimes O
also O
ventured O
further O
away O
when O
manhunts O
were O
on O
. O

Two O
friends O
of O
Dawid B-PER
Kahane I-PER
from O
a O
neighbouring O
village O
– O
Samuel B-PER
Oline I-PER
and O
Michael B-PER
Schiff I-PER
hid B-TER
with O
farmers O
in O
Łużna B-LOC
. O

They O
were O
denounced B-TER
and O
police B-TER
came O
from O
Gorlice B-LOC
to O
take O
them O
. O

They O
were O
stripped B-TER
naked I-TER
( O
January O
1943 O
) O
, O
handcuffed O
. O

While O
the O
Polish B-TER
were O
digging O
a O
grave O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
went O
to O
a O
tavern O
. O

The O
boys O
escaped B-TER
, O
went O
to O
a O
carpenter O
who O
cut O
through O
the O
handcuffs O
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
came O
after O
them O
. O

Oline B-PER
grabbed O
hold O
of O
a O
wooden O
board O
, O
hit B-TER
a O
German B-TER
on O
the O
head O
. O

The O
German B-TER
fell O
down O
. O

The O
other O
German B-TER
shot B-TER
one O
Jew O
dead B-TER
. O

Oline B-PER
escaped B-TER
. O

A O
few O
hours O
later O
he O
was O
caught O
too O
. O

I.[za B-PER
] I-PER
L.[auer I-PER
] I-PER
Signature O
of O
the O
person O
recording O
the O
testimony O
. O

