So O
far O
one O
of O
the O
principal O
difficulties O
for O
Jews B-TER
wishing O
to O
flee B-TER
the O
perils O
of O
Romania B-LOC
was O
that O
the O
Turkish B-TER
Legation O
here O
was O
not O
empowered O
to O
give O
a O
transit O
visa O
unless O
the O
applicant O
could O
show O
a O
visa B-TER
for O
Palestine B-LOC
or O
Syria B-LOC
which O
the O
British B-TER
have O
not O
given O
us O
authority O
to O
grant O
, O
and O
which O
is O
not O
accorded O
to O
residents O
of O
enemy B-TER
occupied B-TER
countries I-TER
such O
as O
Romania B-LOC
. O

I O
was O
therefore O
struck O
yesterday O
when O
my O
Turkish B-TER
colleague O
called O
to O
say O
that O
he O
had O
strongly O
urged O
by O
telegram O
upon O
his O
Government B-ORG
the O
desirability O
of O
conferring O
with O
the O
British B-TER
, O
and O
, O
out O
of O
courtesy O
, O
with O
the O
French B-TER
, O
to O
see O
whether O
there O
was O
not O
some O
way O
to O
arrange O
temporary O
lodgings O
in O
barracks O
in O
Syria B-LOC
or O
Palestine B-LOC
for O
the O
unfortunate O
Jews B-TER
still O
left O
in O
Romania B-LOC
. O

[ O
... O
] O
I O
am O
wholly O
in O
accord O
with O
his O
proposal O
which O
, O
if O
adopted O
, O
might O
save B-TER
many O
innocent O
lives O
and O
spare O
extreme O
human O
suffering O
. O

I O
have O
no O
illusions O
, O
however O
, O
that O
the O
Romanians B-TER
will O
ever O
let O
these O
poor B-TER
people I-TER
out O
of O
their O
clutches O
with O
more O
than O
the O
clothes B-TER
on O
their O
backs O
. O

