Dear O
Mrs. O
Schmolka B-PER
, O
I O
have O
received O
your O
letter O
of O
August O
2nd O
, O
written O
on O
behalf O
of O
the O
Hicem B-ORG
of O
Prague B-LOC
, O
and O
relating O
to O
the O
tragic O
position O
of O
the O
Jews B-TER
from O
the O
Burgenland B-LOC
on O
board O
of O
the O
Laortis O
. O

The O
Committee O
of O
the O
Council B-ORG
for I-ORG
German I-ORG
Jewry I-ORG
carefully O
considered O
the O
matter O
, O
but O
could O
not O
accept O
the O
proposal O
made O
to O
them O
that O
they O
should O
contribute O
£ O
4,000 O
for O
the O
rescue O
of O
four O
families B-TER
. O

This O
is O
far O
in O
excess O
of O
any O
grant O
that O
has O
been O
previously O
made O
, O
and O
we O
felt O
that O
we O
should O
not O
be O
justified O
, O
in O
view O
of O
the O
many O
other O
claims O
that O
we O
must O
endeavour O
to O
meet O
, O
to O
expend O
so O
large O
a O
sum O
for O
the O
benefit O
of O
such O
a O
small O
number O
of O
persons O
. O

I O
much O
regret O
that O
I O
do O
not O
feel O
able O
to O
ask O
the O
Committee O
to O
reconsider O
this O
decision O
. O

Yourse O
sincerely O
, O
SAMUEL B-PER
. I-PER

