The O
person O
in O
question O
has O
given O
us O
the O
following O
information O
: O
I O
started O
my O
labour B-TER
service I-TER
on O
May O
11 O
, O
1942 O
in O
Tápiósüly B-LOC
where O
we O
dug O
sewers O
standing O
in O
the O
chest O
- O
high O
water O
. O

Moreover O
after O
work O
we O
had O
exercise O
too O
. O

It O
was O
forbidden O
to O
have O
visiting O
family B-TER
members I-TER
and O
so O
was O
obtaining O
food B-TER
through O
them O
. O

If O
despite O
of O
this O
we O
managed O
to O
get O
some O
food B-TER
then O
Lieutenant B-TER
Kőszegi B-PER
punished O
us O
in O
the O
cruellest O
way O
: O
he O
compelled O
us O
to O
do O
exercise B-TER
and O
trussed B-TER
people O
up O
. O

Sergeant B-TER
Forgács B-PER
urged O
us O
to O
work B-TER
by O
shooting O
around O
our O
feet O
and O
hitting O
us O
with O
a O
rifle O
. O

butt O
. O

From O
here O
we O
were O
taken O
to O
Nagykáta B-LOC
where O
Lieutenant B-TER
Colonel I-TER
Muray B-PER
tortured B-TER
people O
and O
hit B-TER
us O
in O
the O
face O
because O
the O
yellow B-TER
star I-TER
was O
never O
sewn O
on O
our O
clothes B-TER
in O
a O
proper O
way O
. O

Fifty O
- O
five O
of O
us O
were O
crammed O
into O
a O
very O
small B-TER
room I-TER
; O
it O
was O
impossible O
to O
even O
move O
. O

We O
could O
wash B-TER
ourselves I-TER
only O
in O
the O
canal O
. O

We O
had O
a O
lance B-TER
sergeant I-TER
( O
unfortunately O
I O
do O
not O
know O
his O
name O
, O
all O
I O
know O
is O
that O
he O
used O
to O
be O
a O
barber O
in O
the O
Pajor O
sanatorium B-TER
in O
Budapest B-LOC
) O
, O
who O
kicked B-TER
and I-TER
beat I-TER
people O
and O
did O
not O
allow O
us O
to O
report O
as O
sick B-TER
. O

From O
Nagykáta B-LOC
we O
were O
taken O
to O
Ukraine B-LOC
. O

When O
we O
arrived O
at O
the O
station O
, O
the O
Hungarian B-TER
soldiers I-TER
who O
were O
leaving O
for O
home O
made O
the O
following O
remark O
: O
They O
are O
n’t O
coming O
back O
for O
sure O
... O
The O
deputy B-TER
commander I-TER
of O
the O
company O
was O
Warrant B-TER
Officer I-TER
Leidl B-PER
, O
who O
talked O
to O
the O
men O
in O
the O
rudest O
tone O
. O

Lance B-TER
Sergeant I-TER
Bajor B-PER
( O
a O
worker O
from O
a O
Pest B-LOC
brick O
factory B-TER
) O
beat B-TER
the O
people O
all O
the O
time O
and O
told O
us O
many O
times O
that O
we O
were O
all O
going O
to O
perish O
. O

When O
we O
came O
home O
from O
work B-TER
in O
the O
evening O
, O
he O
even O
made O
us O
exercise B-TER
. O

Lance B-TER
Sergeant I-TER
Borza B-PER
was O
a O
guard O
to O
labour B-TER
service I-TER
company I-TER
no O
. O

101/11 O
and O
the O
whip O
never O
rested O
in O
his O
hands O
. O

Once O
we O
were O
leaving O
for O
work B-TER
at O
7 O
am O
in O
double O
quick O
pace O
and O
I O
tripped O
and O
fell O
in O
the O
darkness O
. O

Borza B-PER
stepped O
up O
to O
me O
and O
while O
shouting O
that O
I O
was O
a O
saboteur O
, O
he O
beat B-TER
me O
to O
a O
pulp O
. O

Privates B-TER
Bottka B-PER
and O
Bótha B-PER
were O
also O
very O
cruel B-TER
to O
the O
labour B-TER
servicemen I-TER
. O

Later O
Warrant B-TER
Officer I-TER
Ligety B-PER
( O
of O
Jewish O
descent O
) O
was O
appointed B-TER
commander I-TER
of O
our O
company B-TER
. I-TER

He O
also O
committed O
a O
series O
of O
cruel B-TER
acts O
. O

He O
called O
upon O
the O
guards O
to O
torture B-TER
us O
and O
every O
so O
often O
he O
declared O
that O
on O
his O
list O
of O
priority O
number O
one O
was O
the O
Hungarian B-TER
soldier I-TER
, O
number O
two O
was O
nobody O
, O
number O
three O
was O
nobody O
too O
and O
the O
Jew O
came O
only O
after O
these O
: O
he O
also O
said O
that O
there O
was O
no O
other O
way O
to O
talk O
to O
the O
Jews O
only O
by O
a O
whip O
. O

Cadet B-TER
Sergeant I-TER
Fritz O
( O
a O
counterintelligence B-TER
officer I-TER
) O
took O
away O
all O
of O
our O
clothes B-TER
. O

He O
beat B-TER
people O
with O
a O
whip O
; O
he O
walked O
around O
with O
a O
whip O
in O
his O
hand O
. O

On O
October O
22 O
, O
1942 O
partisans B-TER
attacked O
the O
village O
where O
we O
were O
accommodated O
. O

Forty O
- O
one O
brothers O
- O
in O
- O
arms O
and O
me O
joined O
the O
partisans B-TER
and O
fought O
the O
Germans B-TER
. O

I O
was O
a O
partisan B-TER
until O
November O
10 O
, O
1943 O
, O
then O
for O
three O
months O
I O
worked O
as O
a O
physician B-TER
. O

Later O
I O
was O
taken O
to O
another O
civilian O
hospital B-TER
. O

Later O
I O
was O
sent O
to O
a O
one O
- O
month O
- O
long O
further O
training O
to O
Orel B-LOC
. O

I O
came O
back O
to O
Hungary B-LOC
with O
a O
mixed O
transport O
through O
Romania B-LOC
. O

