Doc O
. O

2 O
Mr. O
Foreign B-PER
minister I-PER
, O
Through O
the O
Hungarian B-LOC
National B-TER
Radio I-TER
Broadcasts I-TER
, O
it O
was O
announced O
that O
, O
in O
mid O
- O
January O
, O
the O
Prime O
Minister O
, O
General O
Antonescu B-PER
, O
had O
been O
on O
a O
1 O
- O
day O
visit O
with O
Chancellor O
Hitler B-PER
. O

In O
Bucharest B-LOC
was O
the O
meeting O
not O
officially O
mentioned O
, O
and O
therefore O
gave O
rise O
to O
some O
remarkable O
rumours O
. O

A O
few O
days O
after O
the O
General O
’s O
return O
, O
a O
German B-ORG
General I-ORG
Staff I-ORG
Officer I-ORG
, O
Major B-PER
Döring I-PER
, O
was O
murdered O
on O
the O
street O
in O
Bucharest O
. O

The O
killer O
is O
said O
to O
be O
a O
man O
with O
a O
Greek B-LOC
name O
, O
Dimitrie B-PER
Sarandos I-PER
, O
who O
had O
come O
from O
America B-LOC
with O
a O
Turkish B-LOC
passport O
and O
whose O
profession O
is O
stated O
as O
being O
a O
wrestler O
. O

The O
cause O
of O
the O
murder B-TER
has O
so O
far O
not O
been O
resolved O
; O
officials O
say O
that O
they O
are O
still O
investigating O
the O
crime O
. O

However O
, O
this O
resulted O
in O
General O
Antonescu B-PER
’s I-PER
dismissal O
of O
the O
legionary B-ORG
Minister B-ORG
of I-ORG
the I-ORG
Interior I-ORG
, O
General B-PER
Petrovicescu I-PER
, O
who O
was O
accused O
of O
not O
taking O
immediate O
action O
for O
a O
thorough O
investigation O
. O

The O
Legionary O
Press B-TER
protested O
against O
this O
dismissal O
, O
while O
at O
the O
same O
time O
emphasizing O
its O
strong O
association O
with O
the O
Axis B-TER
Powers I-TER
, O
calling O
for O
revenge O
on O
those O
who O
stood O
behind O
the O
killer O
. O

It O
can O
thus O
be O
concluded O
, O
that O
the O
murder O
was O
not O
aimed O
at O
the O
presence B-TER
of I-TER
the I-TER
Axis I-TER
in O
Romania B-LOC
, O
as O
Romanian O
Patriots O
suggested O
it O
in O
a O
British B-LOC
Radio O
broadcasts O
, O
since O
the O
warring O
parties O
agree O
that O
only O
the O
Axis O
military O
precautions O
in O
Romania O
save O
them O
from O
further O
segregation O
between O
their O
hostile O
neighbours O
. O

One O
could O
not O
fail O
to O
notice O
that O
the O
Press O
controlled O
by O
the O
Legionnaires O
made O
propaganda B-TER
for O
the O
Revolution O
, O
i.e. O
further O
looting O
of O
the O
possessive O
classes O
and O
especially O
of O
the O
Jews B-TER
and O
new O
members O
of O
the O
Freemasons B-TER
. O

Finally O
, O
it O
was O
clear O
to O
the O
Prime O
Minister O
that O
he O
ruled O
with O
some O
Ministers O
in O
one O
direction O
, O
i.e. O
on O
the O
basis O
of O
the O
existence O
of O
evolutionary O
development O
, O
while O
the O
Deputy O
Prime O
Minister O
, O
Legionary B-ORG
Commander O
Horia B-PER
Sima I-PER
with O
other O
Ministers O
, O
ruled O
towards O
a O
Revolution O
and O
immediate O
looting O
and O
destruction O
of O
everything O
of O
endurance O
. O

The O
situation O
was O
unsustainable O
and O
as O
a O
first O
serious O
countermeasure O
from O
the O
Prime O
Minister O
’s O
site O
emerged O
on O
21 O
of O
this O
month O
a O
decree O
abolishing O
the O
main O
efforts O
of O
the O
Legionnaires O
to O
militarize O
the O
Romanian O
institutions O
as O
well O
as O
important O
State O
enterprises O
. O

I O
have O
reported O
this O
in O
my O
above O
- O
mentioned O
report O
. O

The O
answer O
to O
this O
relatively O
peaceful O
act O
was O
that O
the O
Legionary O
Party O
on O
the O
22 O
of O
this O
month O
occupied O
a O
police O
barrack O
with O
600 O
men O
, O
located O
right O
next O
to O
the O
Foreign B-ORG
Ministry I-ORG
, O
where O
the O
Prime O
Minister O
has O
his O
Bureau O
as O
well O
as O
his O
temporary O
residence O
. O

Thus O
, O
the O
rebellion B-TER
had O
begun O
. O

It O
soon O
became O
clear O
that O
the O
Legionnaires O
were O
well O
supplied O
with O
rifles B-TER
and I-TER
ammunition I-TER
, O
and O
that O
they O
had O
prepared O
the O
action O
by O
pre B-TER
- I-TER
occupying I-TER
houses O
taken O
from O
wealthy B-TER
Jews I-TER
in O
all O
districts O
. O

The O
garrison O
commanded O
by O
General O
Antonescu B-PER
, O
finally O
succeeded O
in O
capturing O
the O
Police O
barrack O
, O
from O
which O
the O
Legionnaires O
attacked O
the O
Foreign O
Ministry O
with O
the O
purpose O
of O
killing O
the O
General O
. O

On O
the O
first O
day O
, O
the O
military O
sought O
to O
avoid O
shooting O
and O
trusted O
the O
effect O
of O
their O
sole O
appearance O
. O

However O
, O
as O
Soldier B-TER
everywhere O
where O
shot O
down O
, O
during O
the O
course O
of O
the O
second O
day O
, O
a O
common O
battle O
erupted O
throughout O
the O
city O
, O
during O
which O
the O
military O
, O
with O
guns O
, O
tanks O
and O
machine O
guns O
, O
damaged O
the O
fortified O
houses O
of O
the O
Legionnaires O
. O

There O
were O
many O
dead O
and O
wounded O
on O
both O
sides O
, O
but O
we O
do O
not O
know O
how O
many O
. O

However O
, O
the O
number O
of O
victims O
is O
hardly O
proportional O
to O
the O
periodic O
violent O
cannonade O
that O
lasted O
all O
day O
and O
night O
for O
more O
than O
2 O
days O
. O

All O
this O
time O
, O
Legionnaire O
gangs O
carried O
out O
gruesome O
pogroms B-TER
, O
notably O
against O
the O
Jewish B-TER
Proletariat I-TER
in O
the O
suburbs O
, O
where O
large O
- O
scale O
assassinations B-TER
and O
looting O
took O
place O
. O

In O
short O
, O
the O
vast O
majority O
of O
the O
so O
fiercely O
proclaimed O
Legionary B-ORG
Movement I-ORG
people O
, O
i.e. O
The O
dregs O
of O
the O
City O
, O
took O
the O
opportunity O
to O
show O
who O
they O
really O
were O
, O
without O
the O
so O
- O
called O
leadership O
being O
able O
to O
limit O
the O
struggle O
to O
its O
true O
purpose O
, O
which O
was O
the O
creation O
of O
a O
pure O
Legionary O
government O
under O
Horia B-PER
Sima I-PER
. O

Following O
the O
culmination O
of O
the O
Romanian O
Military O
’s O
efforts O
early O
on O
Thursday O
( O
the O
23rd O
) O
, O
Horia B-PER
Sima I-PER
sent O
out O
, O
via O
Radio O
and O
leaflets O
, O
an O
order B-TER
to O
the O
Legionnaires O
to O
put O
down O
the O
weapons O
. O

The O
fighters O
only O
partially O
complied O
with O
the O
order O
, O
but O
in O
the O
course O
of O
the O
afternoon O
, O
at O
least O
, O
they O
succeeded O
in O
establishing O
peace O
while O
motorized O
divisions O
of O
the O
present O
German B-ORG
Armed I-ORG
Forces I-ORG
demonstratively O
drove O
through O
the O
city O
obviously O
prepared O
to O
assist O
the O
Romanian O
military O
if O
necessary O
. O

By O
Friday O
morning O
, O
the O
uprising O
was O
dissolved B-TER
and O
the O
entire O
city O
occupied O
by O
the O
Romanian O
Military O
, O
which O
began O
searching O
for O
the O
Legionnaires O
’ O
hidden O
abode O
and O
large O
quantities O
of O
stolen O
goods O
distributed O
over O
many O
houses O
have O
since O
been O
brought O
to O
light O
. O

Undoubtedly O
, O
the O
entire O
Rebellion O
has O
been O
planned O
and O
staged O
by O
General O
Antonescu B-PER
’s I-PER
closest O
Employees O
in O
the O
Legionary O
State O
’s O
leadership O
. O

The O
police B-ORG
were O
searching O
for O
Deputy O
Prime O
Minister O
Horia B-PER
Sima I-PER
and O
it O
is O
said O
that O
he O
has O
been O
arrested O
today O
. O

The O
appointment O
of O
a O
general O
government O
was O
generally O
expected O
, O
but O
so O
far O
, O
nothing O
has O
been O
published O
regarding O
the O
transformation O
of O
the O
government O
, O
let O
alone O
its O
dismissal O
. O

In O
reality O
, O
it O
is O
fair O
to O
say O
that O
the O
country O
is O
currently O
administered O
solely O
the O
Governor O
, O
General O
Antonescu B-PER
, O
currently O
administers O
the O
country O
with O
the O
help O
of O
the O
declared O
state O
of O
emergency O
. O

Intelligence B-TER
from O
the O
Province O
suggests O
that O
rebellions O
of O
the O
same O
kind O
as O
here O
have O
been O
common O
in O
the O
larger O
cities O
, O
while O
the O
rural O
population O
itself O
has O
turned O
against O
the O
plans O
of O
the O
Legionnaires O
. O

After O
the O
rebellion O
, O
General O
Antonescu B-PER
issued O
a O
comprehensive O
Proclamation O
to O
the O
People O
. O

The O
general B-PER
thanked O
the O
Army O
for O
its O
courage O
, O
describing O
the O
suffering O
he O
went O
through O
before O
it O
became O
inevitable O
to O
shoot O
at O
the O
people O
, O
he O
declares O
that O
from O
now O
on O
he O
will O
personally O
take O
charge O
of O
the O
youth O
’s O
education O
and O
that O
all O
who O
are O
guilty O
will O
be O
punished B-TER
. O

General O
Disarmament O
will O
now O
be O
implemented O
by O
the O
Military O
. O

The O
Romanians O
here O
have O
stated O
to O
me O
that O
the O
proclamation O
is O
well O
suited O
to O
make O
an O
impression O
, O
especially O
within O
the O
large O
Romanian O
peasant O
population O
, O
but O
at O
the O
same O
time O
, O
it O
is O
found O
to O
be O
too O
lyrical O
and O
weak O
to O
deter O
future O
troublemakers O
. O

Especially O
regarding O
the O
last O
point O
, O
it O
is O
apparent O
that O
the O
general B-PER
now O
faces O
a O
number O
of O
challenges O
in O
setting O
up O
a O
new O
Ministry O
, O
but O
the O
situation O
is O
still O
too O
unclear O
to O
be O
overlooked O
. O

H.m O
. O

King B-PER
Mihai I-PER
and O
the O
Royal O
family O
have O
before O
and O
during O
the O
rebellion O
period O
stayed O
in O
Sinaia B-LOC
without O
being O
directly O
involved O
in O
the O
events O
, O
as O
far O
as O
we O
know O
here O
in O
Bucharest O
. O

With O
the O
honourable O
mention O
, O
I O
have O
the O
honour O
to O
remain O
Mr. B-PER
Foreign I-PER
Minister I-PER
’s I-PER
most O
reverent O
, O
Erik B-PER
Biering I-PER
