Mirka B-PER
Winer I-PER
Testimony O
( O
doc O
. O

301/1169 O
) O
Original O
, O
manuscript O
, O
4 O
pages O
, O
210 O
x O
295 O
mm O
, O
Polish O
language O
Voivodship B-ORG
’s I-ORG
Historical I-ORG
Commission I-ORG
In O
Lublin B-LOC
On O
15 O
November O
1945 O
Mirka B-PER
Winer I-PER
Testifies O
for O
the O
record O
Born O
4 O
February O
1932 O
Tatooed O
number O
A O
3977 O
in O
Auschwitz B-LOC
Student B-TER
Before O
the O
war B-TER
she O
resided O
in O
Bełżyce B-LOC
near O
Lublin B-LOC
Presently O
in O
Lublin B-LOC
, O
8 B-LOC
Lubartowska I-LOC
Street I-LOC
apt I-LOC
. I-LOC

12 I-LOC
Has O
mother O
; O
a O
merchant O
’s O
daughter O
Record O
taken O
by O
: O
Irena B-PER
Szajowicz I-PER
; O
Head O
of O
Historical B-ORG
Commission I-ORG
in I-ORG
Lublin I-ORG
I O
was O
living O
in O
Bełżyce B-LOC
when O
Germans B-TER
entered O
Poland O
in O
1939 O
. O

The O
commandant O
for O
the O
town O
was O
a O
German B-TER
named O
Engel B-PER
. O

We O
were O
terribly O
afraid O
of O
him O
, O
because O
he O
used O
to O
beat O
and O
shoot B-TER
people O
. O

He O
would O
invade O
a O
flat O
and O
kill B-TER
whole O
families B-TER
. O

That O
’s O
what O
happened O
to O
the O
Silbernadel B-PER
family B-TER
: O
father O
Kuna B-PER
Herisch I-PER
, O
sons O
Usze B-PER
and O
Jankiel B-PER
for O
trading O
meat O
. O

He O
also O
stole O
and O
plundered B-TER
Jewish O
flats O
. O

A O
few O
times O
a O
week O
gendarmes B-TER
would O
come O
from O
a O
neighbouring O
town O
10 O
kilometres O
away O
– O
Niedźwice B-LOC
. O

Niedrzwica O
They O
had O
us O
give O
them O
money O
, O
autos O
, O
horses O
. O

They O
kept O
making O
new O
demands O
. O

It O
all O
started O
with O
a O
contribution O
of O
20000 O
zlotys O
, O
and O
then O
they O
just O
kept O
demanding O
more O
. O

Once O
SS B-TER
- I-TER
men I-TER
came O
from O
Lublin B-LOC
and O
took O
400 O
men O
to O
Majdanek B-LOC
, O
many O
people O
died B-TER
then O
, O
shot B-TER
by O
the O
SS B-TER
. O

In O
1941 O
they O
took O
several O
hundred O
men B-TER
and O
women B-TER
to O
Majdanek B-LOC
. O

One O
Tuesday O
in O
1942 O
Ukrainians B-TER
and O
SS B-TER
- I-TER
men I-TER
came O
. O

They O
shot O
at O
people O
and O
took O
people O
away O
, O
loaded O
them O
into O
train B-TER
cars I-TER
and O
transported B-TER
to O
Treblinka B-LOC
. O

We O
stayed O
hidden O
, O
in O
a O
hideout B-TER
under O
the O
floor O
there O
was O
a O
pit O
. O

It O
was O
in O
my O
cousin B-TER
’s O
flat O
. O

There O
were O
50 O
people O
there O
. O

It O
was O
terribly O
stuffy O
, O
so O
stuffy O
that O
one O
2 O
- O
year O
old O
child B-TER
died B-TER
of O
lack O
of O
air O
. O

The O
action O
went O
on O
for O
almost O
2 O
days O
. O

After O
we O
went O
out O
, O
SS B-TER
- I-TER
men I-TER
from O
Niedźwice B-LOC
, O
who O
were O
searching O
Jewish O
flats O
, O
caught O
us O
; O
they O
smashed O
furnaces O
, O
ripped O
off O
floorboards O
and O
so O
forth O
. O

We O
were O
locked O
up O
in O
a O
synagogue B-TER
. O

After O
one O
day O
we O
managed O
to O
escape O
. O

Later O
, O
the O
SS B-TER
- I-TER
men I-TER
demanded O
20000 O
per O
family B-TER
in O
return O
for O
making O
a O
camp B-TER
and O
not O
killing B-TER
us O
but O
making O
us O
work B-TER
. O

Hess B-PER
was O
the O
commandant O
. O

The O
camp B-TER
was O
fenced O
with O
wire O
and O
we O
were O
guarded O
only O
by O
Jewish B-TER
militia I-TER
. O

Hess B-PER
did O
n’t O
torment O
us O
too O
much O
. O

Almost O
9 O
months O
later O
an O
SS B-TER
- I-TER
man I-TER
named O
Feiks B-PER
Notorious O
SS O
functionary O
Reinhold O
Feix O
came O
with O
Gestapo B-ORG
officers O
. O

500 O
women B-TER
and O
children B-TER
were O
killed B-TER
and O
the O
remaining O
100 O
and O
the O
men B-TER
were O
taken O
to O
Budzyń B-LOC
. O

I O
was O
saved O
because O
I O
mingled O
with O
the O
group O
who O
’d O
been O
selected B-TER
to O
go O
. O

Feiks B-PER
was O
commandant O
for O
the O
camp B-TER
in O
Budzyń B-LOC
, O
where O
at O
that O
time O
there O
were O
already O
Jews O
from O
other O
towns O
: O
from O
Kraśnik B-LOC
, O
even O
[ O
from O
] O
Warsaw B-LOC
. O

There O
was O
a O
total O
of O
about O
5000 O
of O
us O
. O

SS B-TER
- I-TER
men I-TER
kept O
guard O
there O
. O

People O
died B-TER
every O
day O
. O

They O
died B-TER
of O
hunger B-TER
( O
we O
were O
given O
a O
loaf O
of O
bread B-TER
between O
10 O
people O
; O
the O
soup B-TER
was O
thin O
and O
the O
potatoes B-TER
raw O
) O
. O

From O
time O
to O
time O
selections B-TER
took O
place O
; O
the O
weaker O
and O
the O
children B-TER
were O
selected B-TER
and O
machine O
guns O
were O
fired O
. O

Beforehand O
they O
had O
to O
dig O
their O
own O
graves O
, O
where O
the O
others O
buried O
them O
in O
later O
. O

Typhus B-TER
fever I-TER
decimated O
people O
. O

I O
worked B-TER
in O
the O
kitchen O
. O

Women B-TER
worked B-TER
in O
the O
German B-TER
estate O
and O
in O
ammunition O
and O
plane O
plants O
. O

Men B-TER
worked B-TER
in O
plants O
and O
built O
roads O
. O

Our O
plight O
was O
very O
miserable O
. O

Feiks B-PER
and O
an O
SS B-TER
Oberscharführer I-TER
Mohe B-PER
were O
especially O
cruel O
. O

A O
year O
later O
they O
dressed O
us O
in O
striped O
uniforms B-TER
and O
moved O
to O
a O
new O
camp B-TER
named O
Barakenbau O
; O
it O
was O
located O
near O
Budzyń B-LOC
, O
but O
administered O
by O
Majdanek B-LOC
. O

Leipold B-PER
was O
the O
commandant O
. O

He O
and O
SS B-TER
Unterscharführer I-TER
Jungfleisch B-PER
and O
Oberscharführer B-TER
Willi B-PER
Kleist I-PER
beat O
, O
shot O
and O
tormented O
us O
inhumanly O
. O

Leipold B-PER
hanged B-TER
people O
head O
down O
from O
the O
barracks O
ceiling O
for O
any O
petty O
offence O
. O

The O
victims O
hung O
like O
this O
for O
several O
hours O
and O
many O
died B-TER
like O
this O
. O

Some O
time O
later O
we O
were O
moved O
from O
Barakenbau O
. O

I O
ca O
n’t O
put O
an O
exact O
date O
on O
Majdanek B-LOC
. O

In O
Majdanek B-LOC
I O
was O
n’t O
all O
that O
miserable O
. O

When O
the O
Red B-ORG
Army I-ORG
approached O
, O
Germans B-TER
moved O
us O
to O
Ćmielów B-LOC
; O
we O
walked B-TER
170 O
kilometres O
on O
foot O
. O

Those O
who O
could O
n’t O
make O
it O
were O
shot B-TER
. O

For O
8 O
days O
we O
were O
driven O
in O
rain O
with O
almost O
no O
food B-TER
. I-TER

In O
Ćmielów B-LOC
we O
were O
loaded O
onto O
trains B-TER
and O
taken O
to O
Auschwitz B-LOC
. O

We O
had O
numbers O
embossed O
and O
wee O
directed O
to O
work B-TER
right O
away O
. O

I O
worked B-TER
in O
lager B-TER
Lager O
– O
( O
Ger O
. O

) O
camp O
B O
in O
Strassenkommando O
. O

I O
worked B-TER
very O
hard O
. O

I O
had O
claimed O
I O
was O
16 O
to O
save O
myself O
. O

And O
so O
I O
had O
to O
work B-TER
like O
adults O
. O

They O
kept O
making O
selections B-TER
, O
but O
I O
ran O
away O
every O
time O
. O

Later O
, O
in O
autumn O
there O
was O
a O
major O
selection B-TER
. O

A O
lot O
of O
women B-TER
were O
sent O
to O
the O
chamber B-TER
, O
and O
the O
rest O
– O
including O
me O
– O
[ O
were O
] O
sent O
to O
Belsen B-LOC
Bergen I-LOC
. O

Concentration O
camp O
Bergen O
- O
Belsen O
near O
Hanover O
. O

The O
journey O
took O
a O
week O
. O

In O
terrible O
conditions B-TER
and O
we O
suffered O
hunger B-TER
. O

In O
Belsen B-LOC
Bergen I-LOC
we O
lived O
in O
tents B-TER
. O

We O
would O
freeze O
terribly O
and O
get O
wet O
in O
the O
rain O
. O

Food B-TER
was O
scarce O
. O

Krämer B-PER
arrived O
later O
on O
, O
as O
did O
Lagerältester O
Stenia B-PER
from O
Auschwitz B-LOC
, O
Stanisława O
Starostka O
, O
capo O
in O
Auschwitz O
camp O
, O
promoted O
to O
Lagerälteste O
in O
Bergen O
- O
Belsen O
. O

who O
was O
terribly O
cruel O
to O
us O
. O

[ O
There O
were O
] O
plenty O
of O
SS B-TER
- I-TER
women I-TER
from O
Auschwitz B-LOC
and O
they O
molested O
us O
very O
much O
, O
but O
I O
forget O
the O
names O
. O

We O
did O
not O
work B-TER
. O

Krämer B-PER
introduced O
strict O
rigour O
and O
relations O
deteriorated O
to O
a O
state O
worse O
than O
in O
Auschwitz B-LOC
. O

Next O
, O
we O
left O
with O
500 O
women B-TER
to O
Raguhn B-LOC
near O
Dessau B-LOC
. O

We O
did O
very O
hard O
work B-TER
in O
an O
ammunition O
plant O
there O
. O

Aufseherin B-TER
Lanni B-PER
and O
Unterscharführer O
, O
whose O
name O
I O
ca O
n’t O
remember O
, O
molested O
us O
dreadfully O
. O

Americans B-TER
were O
coming O
closer O
. O

We O
were O
loaded O
up O
onto O
auto O
and O
transported B-TER
around O
for O
two O
weeks O
. O

They O
beat O
and O
kicked O
us O
terribly O
and O
gave O
almost O
no O
food B-TER
. O

Finally O
, O
we O
arrived O
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
where O
we O
were O
to O
be O
burnt O
. O

There O
were O
60000 O
people O
there O
. O

The O
commandant O
pledged O
with O
the O
Red B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
to O
spare O
his O
and O
his O
wife B-TER
and O
child B-TER
’s O
lives O
if O
he O
would O
disobey O
the O
order O
and O
not O
burn O
the O
people O
. O

The O
Red B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
took O
care O
of O
that O
and O
that O
’s O
how O
we O
were O
saved O
. O

[ O
signature O
] O
Winer B-PER
Mirka I-PER
