Nelly B-PER
Wolffheim I-PER
MENSCHLICHE O
VERSUCHS O
- O
KANINCHEN O
HUMAN O
GUINEA O
PIGS O
Name O
: O
Miklos B-PER
Fâbri I-PER
( O
formerly O
Fried B-PER
) O
Born O
: O
30 O
August O
1903 O
. O

In O
Ungvár B-LOC
, O
Hungary B-LOC
Religion B-TER
: O
Jewish O
Occupation O
: O
Businessman B-TER
( O
textiles O
) O
. O

Studied O
in O
Reichenberg B-LOC
, O
Bohemia B-LOC
, O
at O
the O
Textile B-TER
Institute I-TER
, O
2 O
- O
year O
course O
Parents O
: O
Textile O
business B-TER
. O

Perished O
in O
Auschwitz B-LOC
. O

Mr O
Fábri B-PER
’s I-PER
sufferings O
started O
even O
before O
Hitler B-PER
invaded B-TER
Hungary B-LOC
. O

He O
had O
previously O
been O
living O
with O
his O
wife B-TER
and O
daughter B-TER
in O
comfortable O
circumstances O
in O
Ungvár B-LOC
. O

When O
part O
of O
Czechoslovakia B-LOC
, O
to O
which O
Ungvár B-LOC
belonged O
, O
was O
transferred O
to O
Hungary B-LOC
in O
1939 O
as O
a O
result O
of O
a O
pact O
between O
Hitler B-PER
and O
Horthy B-PER
, O
Horthy B-PER
passed O
anti B-TER
- I-TER
Jewish I-TER
laws I-TER
: O
Jewish O
assets B-TER
were I-TER
confiscated I-TER
, O
Jewish O
employees O
were O
sacked O
and O
Jewish O
work B-TER
camps I-TER
were O
opened O
. O

Mr O
Fábri B-PER
spent O
about O
3 O
years O
in O
the O
Kosice B-LOC
and O
Uzok B-LOC
work B-TER
camps I-TER
until O
he O
was O
released B-TER
in O
1943 O
. O

On O
19 O
March O
1944 O
Hitler B-PER
invaded B-TER
Hungary B-LOC
and O
for O
Jews O
this O
was O
the O
start O
of O
torments O
which O
Mr B-PER
Fábri I-PER
describes O
in O
their O
entire O
enormity O
. O

All O
Jews O
from O
Ungvár B-LOC
and O
the O
surrounding O
area O
were O
herded O
together O
in O
a O
ghetto B-TER
, O
in O
a O
brick O
factory B-TER
in O
Ungvár B-LOC
. O

There O
were O
about O
30 O
000 O
people B-TER
. O

The O
families B-TER
stayed O
together O
in O
the O
carriages O
. O

All O
possessions B-TER
: O
homes B-TER
, O
money B-TER
( O
insofar O
as O
accessible O
) O
and O
clothing B-TER
had O
first O
been O
confiscated B-TER
. O

Criminals B-TER
from O
the O
prison B-TER
, O
sick B-TER
people B-TER
from O
the O
hospital B-TER
and O
even O
women B-TER
who O
had O
just O
given O
birth O
were O
put O
in O
the O
ghetto B-TER
. O

Mr O
Fábri B-PER
says O
that O
only O
someone O
who O
has O
seen O
a O
brick O
factory B-TER
can O
have O
any O
idea O
of O
what O
this O
situation O
was O
like O
. O

For O
brick O
manufacture O
the O
air O
in O
the O
buildings O
has O
to O
circulate O
and O
the O
buildings O
have O
to O
be O
well O
- O
ventilated O
and O
wet O
; O
the O
barracks O
had O
no O
walls O
. O

There O
was O
one O
barrack O
which O
was O
set O
apart O
from O
the O
others O
where O
people B-TER
were O
beaten B-TER
if O
they O
wanted O
to O
find O
out O
where O
they O
had O
hidden B-TER
money B-TER
or O
gold O
. O

Some O
died B-TER
in O
the O
process O
. O

Once O
a O
day O
the O
prisoners B-TER
were O
given O
soup B-TER
, O
they O
had O
to O
carry O
the O
water B-TER
to O
the O
barracks O
themselves O
and O
were O
often O
beaten B-TER
on O
the O
way O
. O

The O
prisoners B-TER
remained O
in O
the O
brick O
factory B-TER
until O
17 O
May O
and O
were O
then O
loaded O
into O
carriages B-TER
and O
taken O
to O
Auschwitz B-LOC
. O

The O
transport B-TER
took O
place O
in O
locked O
carriages B-TER
where O
they O
had O
to O
stand O
close O
together O
. O

They O
were O
given O
no O
food B-TER
, O
no O
water B-TER
; O
there O
was O
one O
bucket O
for O
100 O
people B-TER
. O

There O
was O
no O
air O
, O
as O
neither O
doors O
nor O
windows O
were O
opened O
. O

Some O
people B-TER
could O
n’t O
stand O
it O
, O
died B-TER
maybe O
, O
went O
mad B-TER
. O

A O
mother O
hanged B-TER
her O
child B-TER
to O
spare O
it O
this O
and O
what O
was O
to O
come O
. O

After O
3 O
days O
the O
doors O
were O
opened O
, O
everyone O
was O
let O
out O
. O

The O
people B-TER
arriving O
were O
met O
by O
German B-LOC
soldiers B-TER
, O
some O
prisoners B-TER
who O
had O
been O
in O
Auschwitz B-LOC
for O
longer O
were O
there O
too O
. O

Men B-TER
and O
women B-TER
were O
now O
separated B-TER
. O

Mr O
Fábri B-PER
was O
so O
agitated O
and O
confused O
that O
he O
did O
not O
notice O
this O
and O
did O
not O
say O
goodbye O
to O
either O
his O
wife B-TER
and O
child B-TER
or O
to O
his O
other O
family B-TER
members I-TER
, O
a O
sister O
with O
a O
two O
- O
year O
- O
old O
child B-TER
and O
several O
cousins O
. O

His O
mother O
was O
also O
amongst O
them O
. O

He O
saw O
none O
of O
them O
again O
despite O
the O
fact O
that O
, O
to O
avoid O
panic O
, O
the O
prisoners B-TER
were O
promised O
that O
they O
would O
see O
their O
relatives B-TER
again O
in O
the O
evening O
. O

There O
were O
cars O
standing O
there O
for O
the O
old O
people B-TER
who O
could O
not O
walk O
. O

They O
were O
driven O
to O
Reisko O
[ O
handwritten O
note O
in O
the O
margin O
: O
RAJSK O
? O
] O
, O
an O
area O
where O
open O
graves B-TER
were O
waiting O
, O
in O
which O
they O
were O
buried B-TER
alive I-TER
. O

The O
old O
people B-TER
who O
could O
still O
walk O
were O
sent O
into O
the O
gas B-TER
chambers I-TER
. O

Mengele B-PER
, O
doctor B-TER
and O
camp B-TER
commander I-TER
, O
was O
waiting O
for O
the O
new O
arrivals O
at O
the O
entrance O
to O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

He O
pointed O
at O
random O
to O
people B-TER
who O
were O
to O
be O
cremated B-TER
immediately O
and O
those O
who O
were O
to O
stay O
alive O
were O
directed O
to O
the O
other O
side O
. O

Mr O
Fábri B-PER
’s I-PER
father O
was O
also O
amongst O
those O
selected B-TER
to O
die B-TER
. O

This O
transport B-TER
was O
the O
last O
in O
which O
a O
selection B-TER
was O
made O
, O
from O
the O
next O
transport B-TER
on O
all O
the O
prisoners B-TER
were O
taken O
straight O
to O
the O
gas B-TER
chambers I-TER
. O

It O
should O
be O
mentioned O
here O
as O
an O
aside O
that O
Mengele B-PER
was O
hanged B-TER
in O
Auschwitz B-LOC
after O
the O
Nuremberg B-LOC
trial B-TER
. O

In O
the O
camp B-TER
the O
people B-TER
had O
all O
their O
clothes B-TER
taken O
away O
. O

Their O
heads O
and O
bodies O
were O
shaved O
, O
they O
were O
showered B-TER
and O
given O
their O
convicts O
clothing B-TER
and O
the O
branded O
camp B-TER
number O
, O
Mr O
F B-PER
’s I-PER
was O
A O
14086 O
. O

Then O
they O
were O
taken O
to O
the O
gypsy B-TER
concentration B-TER
camp I-TER
Birkenau B-LOC
. O

Here O
they O
were O
housed B-TER
in O
windowless O
barracks B-TER
which O
had O
previously O
been O
used O
as O
stables O
. O

2000 O
people B-TER
together O
, O
only O
room O
to O
stand O
, O
no O
beds O
. O

Mad B-TER
and O
dying B-TER
people B-TER
amongst O
them O
. O

For O
2 O
days O
they O
were O
given O
nothing O
to O
eat B-TER
, O
then O
a O
bowl O
of O
soup B-TER
for O
4 O
people B-TER
but O
no O
spoons O
. O

Once O
a O
day O
they O
were O
allowed O
to O
relieve O
themselves O
. O

After O
a O
week O
a O
further O
selection B-TER
was O
made O
amongst O
those O
who O
were O
under O
44 O
years O
old O
. O

Mr O
Fábri B-PER
was O
41 O
and O
was O
allocated O
to O
Camp B-LOC
No I-LOC
. I-LOC

1 I-LOC
, O
assigned O
to O
agricultural O
work B-TER
. O

To O
get O
to O
their O
workplace B-TER
they O
had O
to O
run O
10 O
– O
12 O
kilometres O
at O
a O
fast O
pace O
. O

Anyone O
who O
was O
too O
slow O
was O
beaten O
by O
the O
Kapos O
( O
German B-LOC
soldiers B-TER
or O
Poles B-LOC
) O
in O
charge O
. O

The O
prisoners B-TER
had O
to O
get O
up O
at O
4:30 O
in O
the O
morning O
, O
then O
stand O
for O
roll B-TER
call I-TER
until O
6:30 O
, O
then O
go O
to O
work B-TER
where O
they O
spent O
the O
whole O
day O
bending O
down O
pulling O
out O
weeds O
. O

Standing O
up O
straight O
was O
not O
allowed O
. O

At O
midday O
there O
was O
a O
break O
when O
they O
were O
given O
dried O
vegetables B-TER
. O

One O
day O
they O
were O
told O
to O
take O
white O
sand O
which O
was O
standing O
ready O
in O
boxes O
and O
scatter O
it O
on O
the O
fields O
by O
hand O
. O

The O
sand O
was O
the O
bone O
meal O
of O
the O
people B-TER
who O
had O
been O
cremated B-TER
. O

It O
burned O
the O
prisoners B-TER
’ O
hands O
which O
were O
damp O
due O
to O
the O
heat O
and O
many O
people B-TER
sustained O
deep O
wounds B-TER
. O

One O
day O
, O
when O
Mr O
Fábri B-PER
could O
no O
longer O
walk O
fast O
enough O
, O
an O
SS B-ORG
soldier B-TER
shot O
him O
in O
the O
foot O
. O

He O
was O
then O
taken O
to O
the O
camp B-TER
hospital I-TER
. O

This O
was O
on O
10 O
August O
1944 O
. O

On O
30 O
August O
a O
doctor B-TER
came O
and O
picked O
out O
40 O
patients O
from O
amongst O
those O
present O
, O
amongst O
them O
Mr O
Fábri B-PER
. O

The O
selected B-TER
men B-TER
were O
taken O
to O
a O
secret O
barrack O
as O
guinea O
pigs O
for O
medical O
experiments O
. O

Mr O
Fábri B-PER
was O
given O
malaria B-TER
and O
infected O
with O
other O
substances O
unknown O
to O
him O
. O

For O
this O
he O
was O
strapped O
to O
a O
table O
and O
a O
kind O
of O
saw O
was O
used O
to O
make O
deep O
incisions O
into O
which O
the O
substance O
was O
introduced O
. O

Pieces O
were O
cut O
out O
so O
as O
to O
be O
able O
to O
see O
the O
effect O
in O
the O
wound B-TER
better O
. O

This O
was O
done O
without O
any O
kind O
of O
anaesthetic B-TER
and O
was O
of O
course O
extremely O
painful O
. O

Even O
today O
I O
was O
still O
able O
to O
see O
the O
resulting O
scars O
on O
his O
hands O
and O
legs O
. O

On O
16 O
January O
1945 O
, O
37 O
of O
the O
40 O
men B-TER
used O
for O
the O
experiments B-TER
were O
fetched O
and O
gassed B-TER
immediately O
so O
as O
to O
not O
disclose O
the O
crime O
. O

Only O
Mr O
Fábri B-PER
and O
two O
other O
men B-TER
stayed O
behind O
as O
the O
wounds B-TER
had O
not O
yet O
healed O
and O
the O
experiments B-TER
could O
therefore O
not O
be O
regarded O
as O
completed O
. O

The O
three O
were O
thus O
the O
only O
survivors B-TER
. O

Mr O
Fábri B-PER
has O
documents O
which O
confirm O
the O
events O
. O

( O
see O
film O
) O
. O

Mr O
Fábri B-PER
stayed O
in O
the O
hospital B-TER
in O
Auschwitz B-LOC
, O
where O
he O
had O
been O
taken O
from O
the O
secret O
barrack O
, O
until O
the O
camp B-TER
was O
liberated B-TER
by O
the O
Russians B-LOC
on O
16 O
January O
1945 O
. O

The O
Russians B-LOC
took O
him O
immediately O
to O
Krakow B-LOC
in O
Poland B-LOC
. O

There O
it O
was O
found O
that O
Mr O
Fábri B-PER
, O
who O
had O
in O
the O
past O
weighted O
80 O
kilos O
, O
now O
only O
weighted O
35 O
kilos O
. O

On O
15 O
July O
1945 O
he O
was O
discharged O
from O
hospital B-TER
and O
, O
together O
with O
another O
group O
, O
made O
his O
way O
to O
Budapest B-LOC
, O
travelling O
on O
foot O
( O
which O
was O
only O
possible O
with O
orthopaedic B-TER
boots I-TER
, O
see O
final O
remark O
) O
and O
breaking O
the O
journey O
from O
time O
to O
time O
. O

Welfare B-TER
organisations I-TER
helped O
them O
with O
this O
undertaking O
. O

On O
the O
way O
they O
received O
help O
and O
friendly O
treatment O
from O
Poles B-LOC
and O
Czechs B-LOC
. O

The O
Russians B-LOC
suspected O
them O
of O
being O
spies O
, O
which O
caused O
problems O
. O

On O
arrival O
in O
Budapest B-LOC
Mr O
Fábri B-PER
found O
his O
only O
surviving B-TER
sister B-TER
who O
had O
spent O
the O
time O
in O
Ravensbrück B-LOC
. O

He O
went O
to O
Ungvár B-LOC
to O
see O
what O
had O
become O
of O
his O
former O
house B-TER
and O
found O
that O
the O
Russians B-LOC
had O
taken O
everything O
that O
had O
been O
left O
there O
. O

Only O
money B-TER
that O
he O
had O
buried O
was O
still O
there O
and O
this O
helped O
him O
to O
pay O
for O
his O
subsistence O
because O
until O
1948 O
he O
was O
too O
sick B-TER
to O
be O
able O
to O
work B-TER
. O

Then O
he O
began O
to O
weave O
scarves O
and O
was O
able O
to O
make O
a O
living O
from O
this O
. O

On O
25 O
October O
1945 O
he O
married B-TER
Ilona B-PER
Braun I-PER
from O
Ungvár B-LOC
, O
who O
had O
also O
been O
in O
Auschwitz B-LOC
. O

A O
separate O
report O
will O
describe O
her O
experiences O
there O
. O

After O
outbreak O
of O
the O
revolution O
on O
25 O
August O
1957 O
the O
couple O
emigrated B-TER
legally O
to O
London B-LOC
as O
they O
had O
a O
passport B-TER
. O

As O
they O
received O
some O
money B-TER
from O
the O
USA B-LOC
this O
helped O
them O
during O
the O
initial O
period O
. O

Now O
Mr O
Fábri B-PER
weaves O
scarves O
here O
for O
sale O
, O
using O
a O
small O
hand O
weaving O
machine O
which O
he O
himself O
has O
invented O
and O
which O
he O
plans O
to O
have O
patented O
. O

Mrs O
Fábri B-PER
is O
currently O
working B-TER
part O
- O
time O
. O

As O
his O
foot O
is O
completely O
crippled O
as O
a O
result O
of O
the O
shot O
in O
the O
foot O
while O
in O
the O
concentration B-TER
camp I-TER
, O
and O
the O
affected O
leg O
is O
also O
much O
thinner O
, O
Mr O
Fábri B-PER
can O
not O
do O
any O
work B-TER
that O
involves O
standing O
. O

Without O
his O
orthopaedic B-TER
shoes I-TER
he O
can O
not O
walk O
at O
all O
and O
is O
thus O
extremely O
handicapped O
. O

Mr O
Fábri B-PER
told O
me O
that O
the O
reason O
for O
their O
decision O
to O
emigrate B-TER
was O
that O
as O
former O
capitalists O
they O
believed O
they O
were O
again O
in O
danger O
and O
therefore O
preferred O
to O
go O
to O
a O
free B-TER
country I-TER
. O

21 O
October O
1958 O
Fábri B-PER
Miklos I-PER
Statutory O
declaration O
Today O
Dr O
Alfred B-PER
Boris I-PER
, O
senior B-TER
radiologist I-TER
, O
resident O
in O
Budapest B-LOC
, O
XIV O
. O

Cházár B-LOC
A. I-LOC
Gasse I-LOC
16 O
. O

, O
appeared O
before O
me O
and O
confirms O
the O
following O
: O
In O
the O
month O
of O
August O
1944 O
he O
was O
in O
Auschwitz B-LOC
in O
the O
same O
hospital B-TER
as O
Nikolaus B-PER
Fábri I-PER
/ I-PER
Fried/ I-PER
born O
in O
Ungvár B-LOC
on O
30 O
August O
1903 O
, O
resident O
in O
Budapest B-LOC
, O
XIII O
. O

Katona B-LOC
József I-LOC
Gasse I-LOC
22 O
. O

In O
this O
hospital B-TER
Nikolaus B-PER
Fábri I-PER
was O
given O
medical B-TER
treatment I-TER
because O
of O
a O
foot O
wound B-TER
. O

This O
foot O
wound B-TER
had O
been O
caused O
by O
an O
SS B-ORG
guard B-TER
. O

Dr O
Boris B-PER
further O
confirmed O
the O
following O
: O
As O
doctor O
assigned O
to O
the O
28th O
hospital O
block O
of O
the O
Main O
Camp O
I O
learned O
on O
10 O
September O
1944 O
that O
the O
GermanSSdoctor O
Dr O
Kausch O
was O
performing O
vivisection O
experiments O
on O
Jewish O
prisoners O
. O

One O
day O
I O
was O
able O
to O
gain O
access O
to O
a O
hospital O
room O
. O

To O
my O
immense O
surprise O
I O
saw O
Nikolaus O
Fábri O
there O
and O
he O
told O
me O
that O
vivisection O
experiments O
were O
being O
performed O
on O
his O
feet O
and O
arms O
and O
also O
internally O
. O

Wounds O
on O
his O
body O
, O
feet O
and O
arms O
had O
been O
created O
by O
infection O
, O
which O
began O
to O
fester O
after O
a O
short O
time O
. O

These O
experiments O
were O
extremely O
painful O
. O

Fábri O
was O
also O
inoculated O
with O
malaria O
bacilli O
. O

He O
was O
given O
Atebrin O
pastilles O
to O
try O
to O
treat O
the O
resulting O
malaria O
. O

Fábri O
had O
to O
repeatedly O
take O
25 O
pastilles O
. O

These O
various O
experiments B-TER
were O
– O
to O
my O
knowledge O
– O
continued O
until O
the O
evacuation B-TER
of O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

Budapest B-LOC
1 O
August O
1957 O
. O

[ O
signature O
] O
