The O
person O
in O
question O
has O
given O
us O
the O
following O
information O
: O
On O
the O
10th O
of O
May O
1944 O
, O
a O
detective O
appeared O
in O
my O
flat O
and O
told O
me O
to O
go O
to O
Svábhegy B-LOC
to O
testify O
in O
a O
case O
. O

Of O
course O
this O
detective O
reassured O
me O
with O
a O
smile O
that O
it O
was O
all O
nothing O
and O
I O
would O
be O
back O
home O
the O
same O
day O
. O

There O
was O
no O
interrogation B-TER
for O
two O
days O
. O

When O
finally O
I O
was O
interrogated B-TER
, O
they O
asked O
me O
whether O
I O
had O
participated O
in O
a O
certain O
excursion O
. O

I O
found O
out O
that O
some O
members O
of O
the O
company O
with O
whom O
I O
had O
indeed O
been O
on O
an O
excursion O
had O
been O
arrested B-TER
, O
and O
I O
myself O
was O
also O
suspected O
. O

After O
the O
interrogation B-TER
, O
saying O
that O
they O
would O
take O
me O
home O
they O
took O
me O
into O
Rökk B-LOC
Szilárd I-LOC
street I-LOC
. O

Of O
course O
I O
never O
made O
it O
home O
, O
I O
was O
incarcerated O
in O
Rökk B-LOC
Szilárd I-LOC
Street I-LOC
for O
a O
month O
. O

Around O
the O
12th O
of O
June O
, O
I O
was O
taken O
into O
a O
camp B-TER
for O
the O
sick B-TER
in O
Szabolcs B-LOC
Street I-LOC
, O
where O
I O
could O
work O
as O
a O
doctor B-TER
. O

This O
camp B-TER
was O
emptied O
soon O
afterwards O
and O
I O
was O
again O
taken O
back O
into O
Rökk B-LOC
Szilárd I-LOC
Street I-LOC
. O

The O
next O
day O
, O
I O
was O
entrained O
at O
Keleti B-LOC
railway O
station O
, O
I O
ended O
up O
in O
Kistarcsa B-LOC
, O
from O
where O
I O
was O
taken O
to O
Auschwitz B-LOC
three O
days O
later O
. O

I O
arrived O
in O
Auschwitz B-LOC
on O
the O
17th O
of O
June O
1944 O
. O

People B-TER
were O
sorted B-TER
out O
already O
at O
the O
station O
. O

Men B-TER
and O
women B-TER
had O
to O
stand O
separately B-TER
. O

Old O
people O
and O
children B-TER
were O
separated B-TER
from O
men B-TER
. O

In O
the O
baths O
, O
which O
was O
a O
huge O
building O
, O
we O
had O
to O
get O
completely O
naked O
. O

We O
could O
only O
keep O
our O
shoes B-TER
and O
glasses O
. O

They O
shaved O
our O
hair O
off O
also O
on O
our O
bodies O
. O

We O
were O
standing O
there O
naked O
for O
hours O
till O
finally O
we O
had O
a O
bath O
and O
were O
disinfected O
. O

We O
got O
rags O
in O
return O
for O
our O
clothes B-TER
. O

They O
did O
not O
even O
check O
what O
size O
of O
clothing B-TER
would O
fit O
each O
person B-TER
. O

They O
gave O
long O
, O
baggy O
dresses B-TER
for O
small O
people B-TER
and O
vice O
versa O
. O

There O
were O
some O
who O
could O
parade O
in O
evening B-TER
dresses I-TER
… O
Soup B-TER
, O
toothbrush O
, O
towel O
? O
What O
for O
? O
I O
got O
into O
Camp B-LOC
C I-LOC
, O
which O
was O
a O
transport B-LOC
camp I-LOC
. O

I O
worked B-TER
here O
for O
two O
and O
a O
half O
months O
as O
a O
doctor B-TER
, O
therefore O
my O
rations B-TER
were O
somewhat O
better O
than O
those O
of O
simple O
bunk O
dweller O
. O

It O
was O
already O
a O
great O
thing O
that O
I O
did O
not O
have O
to O
sleep B-TER
on O
a O
bunk O
made O
for O
ca O
. O

5 O
people B-TER
with O
twelve O
, O
thirteen O
or O
fourteen O
other O
people B-TER
. O

In O
Camp B-LOC
C I-LOC
I O
saw O
many O
, O
very O
many O
selections B-TER
. O

It O
was O
awfully O
difficult O
to O
be O
a O
doctor B-TER
in O
Auschwitz B-LOC
. O

I O
did O
not O
work B-TER
in O
the O
hospital B-TER
, O
I O
was O
a O
block O
doctor B-TER
. O

It O
was O
very O
difficult O
, O
for O
example O
, O
to O
hide O
infectious B-TER
patients I-TER
. O

If O
one O
of O
two O
siblings O
finally O
had O
to O
be O
taken O
to O
hospital B-TER
, O
this O
could O
mean O
that O
they O
would O
never O
see O
each O
other O
again O
. O

The O
SS B-TER
particularly O
enjoyed O
separating O
people B-TER
who O
belonged O
together O
. O

I O
saw O
Dr O
Mengele B-PER
a O
number O
of O
times O
in O
the O
hospital B-TER
, O
where O
they O
controlled O
day O
by O
day O
whether O
patients B-TER
were O
treated O
alright O
, O
whether O
they O
had O
enough O
food B-TER
. O

The O
next O
day O
it O
could O
happen O
that O
with O
a O
wave O
of O
his O
hand O
while O
whistling O
he O
sent B-TER
the O
person B-TER
into O
the O
gas B-TER
chamber I-TER
about O
whose O
health O
he O
had O
been O
the O
most O
anxious O
the O
day O
before O
. O

On O
these O
occasions O
he O
was O
even O
more O
horrible O
than O
when O
he O
brutally O
kicked O
someone O
or O
pulled O
out O
his O
pistol O
. O

The O
doctors B-TER
working I-TER
in O
the O
hospital B-TER
told O
me O
that O
once O
a O
sick B-TER
young O
girl B-TER
managed O
to O
commit O
suicide B-TER
. O

She O
may O
have O
been O
less O
then O
20 O
, O
the O
miserable O
creature O
. O

When O
they O
told O
this O
to O
Mengele B-PER
, O
to O
whom O
the O
number O
of O
patients B-TER
had O
to O
be O
reported O
every O
day O
of O
course O
, O
he O
was O
startled O
and O
said O
with O
an O
expression O
of O
surprise O
on O
his O
face O
: O
Selbstmord O
? O
Warumdenn O
… O
So O
jung O
… O
After O
two O
months O
, O
from O
Camp B-LOC
C I-LOC
I O
went O
to O
F.K.L. B-LOC
( B-LOC
Camp I-LOC
A I-LOC
) I-LOC
, O
as O
a O
Verfügbar O
. O

I O
worked B-TER
for O
seven O
weeks O
in O
commissions B-TER
outside I-TER
the I-TER
camp I-TER
. O

A O
transport B-TER
of O
labourers B-TER
left O
for O
Sachsenhausen B-LOC
, O
I O
was O
assigned O
there O
as O
doctor B-TER
. O

I O
was O
in O
Sachenhausen B-LOC
for O
only O
one O
day O
before O
we O
carried O
on O
towards O
Berlin B-LOC
- I-LOC
Reinickendorf I-LOC
, O
and O
from O
there O
with O
a O
small O
Arbeitskommando B-TER
to O
nearby O
Schönholz B-LOC
. O

I O
was O
the O
doctor B-TER
of O
the O
transport B-TER
for O
two O
and O
a O
half O
months O
. O

On O
the O
17th O
of O
February O
1945 O
, O
I O
got O
into O
Ravensbrück B-LOC
as O
a O
patient B-TER
. O

I O
saw O
many O
selections B-TER
here O
, O
too O
. O

Unfortunately O
, O
they O
had O
already O
gas B-TER
here O
as O
well O
. O

For O
when O
Auschwitz B-LOC
ceased O
to O
exist O
as O
such O
, O
the O
leader O
and O
specialist O
of O
the O
local O
crematorium B-TER
came O
to O
Ravensbrück B-LOC
to O
introduce O
the O
gas B-TER
system O
there O
. O

As O
far O
as O
I O
know O
, O
in O
Ravensbrück B-LOC
they O
had O
used O
poison O
before O
. O

On O
the O
29th O
of O
April O
1945 O
, O
they O
were O
driving O
and O
hurrying O
us O
from O
the O
approaching O
Russians B-ORG
for O
2 O
days O
. O

I O
managed O
to O
escape B-TER
on O
the O
road O
and O
hid B-TER
in O
a O
wood O
, O
where O
the O
liberating B-TER
Russian B-ORG
troops I-ORG
found O
me O
. O

After O
my O
liberation B-TER
I O
worked O
for O
a O
while O
as O
a O
doctor B-TER
in O
the O
hospital B-TER
in O
Neustrelitz B-LOC
. O

As O
an O
interesting O
point O
, O
I O
would O
like O
to O
mention O
that O
at O
Berlin B-LOC
- I-LOC
Reinickendorf I-LOC
Arbeitskommando B-TER
only O
a O
certain O
percentage O
of O
the O
people B-TER
were O
allowed O
to O
be O
ill B-TER
. O

They O
would O
always O
ask O
how O
come O
so O
many O
Jews O
were O
ill B-TER
, O
after O
all O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
also O
had O
very O
little O
to O
eat B-TER
. O

