Statement O
Written O
with O
Mr. O
Erich O
Schön O
, O
born O
18 O
. O

2 O
. O

1911 O
, O
residing O
in O
Vsetín B-LOC
, O
Žerotínova O
992 O
, O
former O
prisoner B-TER
of O
the O
concentration B-TER
camps I-TER
Spielberg B-LOC
, O
Dachau B-LOC
, O
Hamburg B-LOC
- I-LOC
Neuengamme I-LOC
, O
Auschwitz B-LOC
and O
Birkenau B-LOC
, O
profession O
clerk B-TER
, O
Czech O
nationality O
. O

Report O
on O
the O
tragic O
fate O
of O
Jakub B-PER
Edelstein I-PER
’s I-PER
family O
. O

On O
December O
20th O
, O
1943 O
, O
roughly O
5,000 O
men B-TER
, O
women B-TER
, O
and O
children B-TER
, O
most O
of O
them O
Czech B-TER
Jews I-TER
, O
arrived O
in O
Auschwitz B-LOC
- I-LOC
Birkenau I-LOC
from O
the O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
ghetto I-LOC
. O

They O
were O
placed O
in O
the O
special O
so O
- O
called O
Czech O
Family B-TER
Camp I-TER
in I-TER
Birkenau I-TER
, O
section O
B B-TER
- I-TER
II I-TER
- I-TER
B I-TER
. O

Amongst O
them O
was O
the O
family O
of O
Jakub B-PER
Edelstein I-PER
from O
Prague B-LOC
. O

However O
, O
Jakub B-PER
Edelstein I-PER
, O
together O
with O
three O
companions O
, O
was O
called O
away O
from O
the O
transport B-TER
at O
the O
Auschwitz B-LOC
train O
station O
and O
brought O
by O
car O
to O
the O
main O
camp O
Auschwitz B-LOC
I I-LOC
. O

Here O
, O
they O
were O
imprisoned B-TER
in O
block O
no O
. O

11 O
, O
the O
so O
- O
called O
Bunker O
, O
which O
was O
used O
as O
an O
investigation O
prison B-TER
by O
the O
camp O
Gestapo B-TER
, O
the O
so O
- O
called O
Politische O
Abteilung O
. O

Few O
made O
it O
out O
alive O
from O
there O
. O

It O
contained O
all O
kinds O
of O
instruments O
of O
torture O
, O
which O
were O
used O
to O
force O
either O
true O
or O
false O
confessions O
from O
the O
accused O
. O

Executions B-TER
took O
place O
in O
the O
courtyard O
of O
this O
block O
. O

Edelstein B-PER
was O
interrogated B-TER
several O
times O
and O
accused O
of O
enabling O
the O
escape B-TER
of O
several O
people O
from O
the O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
ghetto I-LOC
. O

Meanwhile O
, O
his O
family O
was O
in O
camp O
B B-TER
- I-TER
II I-TER
- I-TER
b I-TER
. O

His O
wife B-PER
worked O
at O
the O
children B-TER
’s I-TER
home I-TER
, O
which O
was O
overseen O
by O
Fredy B-PER
Hirsch I-PER
. O

She O
, O
along O
with O
her O
mother O
and O
child B-PER
was O
faring O
quite O
well O
. O

Through O
Jakub B-PER
, O
who O
was O
a O
guard B-TER
in O
block O
no O
. O

11 O
, O
we O
managed O
to O
put O
Jakub B-PER
Edelstein I-PER
in O
Auschwitz B-LOC
I I-LOC
in O
contact O
with O
his O
family O
in O
Birkenau B-TER
. O

Two O
letters B-TER
were O
exchanged O
in O
secret O
. O

Sometime O
in O
February O
1944 O
, O
high O
- O
ranking O
SS B-TER
officer O
Eichmann B-PER
of O
the O
RSHA B-ORG
arrived O
in O
Auschwitz B-TER
- I-TER
Birkenau I-TER
. O

He O
spoke O
with O
Fredy B-PER
Hirsch I-PER
and O
Janowitz B-PER
, O
was O
briefed O
on O
the O
conditions O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
, O
and O
asked O
to O
see O
Edelstein B-PER
’s I-PER
wife B-PER
. O

He O
asked O
her O
how O
she O
was O
doing O
and O
whether O
she O
had O
a O
request O
. O

He O
also O
asked O
her O
whether O
she O
knew O
about O
her O
husband B-PER
. O

She O
requested O
to O
be O
allowed O
to O
see O
her O
husband B-PER
. O

He O
promised O
she O
would O
be O
able O
to O
do O
so O
at O
a O
later O
date O
and O
asked O
her O
to O
write O
a O
letter B-TER
to O
her O
husband B-PER
, O
which O
he O
promised O
to O
deliver O
. O

Edelstein B-PER
was O
supposedly O
somewhere O
in O
the O
Reich B-TER
. O

About O
one O
month O
after O
his O
departure O
, O
the O
liquidation B-TER
of O
the O
Czech O
Family B-TER
Camp I-TER
took O
place O
. O

On O
March O
8th O
, O
3,860 O
men O
, O
women B-TER
, O
and O
children B-TER
from O
the O
transports B-TER
of O
September O
7th O
and O
9th O
, O
1943 O
, O
were O
annihilated B-TER
in O
the O
gas B-TER
chambers I-TER
of O
Crematorium B-TER
I O
and O
II O
. O

We O
found O
out O
that O
the O
prisoners B-TER
of O
the O
Czech O
Family B-TER
Camp I-TER
were O
ordered O
Sonderbehandlung O
( O
SB O
) O
after O
being O
in O
quarantine B-TER
for O
half O
a O
year O
. O

According O
to O
this O
, O
the O
second O
liquidation B-TER
was O
then O
expected O
on O
June O
20th O
, O
1944 O
. O

The O
second O
liquidation B-TER
took O
place O
a O
short O
time O
later O
, O
but O
it O
it O
began O
exactly O
on O
June O
20th O
with O
the O
annihilation B-TER
of O
the O
Edelstein B-PER
family O
, O
which O
happened O
like O
this O
: O
On O
June O
20th O
in O
the O
afternoon O
, O
a O
prison B-TER
transport O
vehicle O
( O
paddy O
wagon O
) O
arrived O
in O
front O
of O
block O
no O
. O

11 O
in O
Auschwitz B-LOC
I I-LOC
. O

The O
escorting O
SS B-TER
man O
from O
Politische O
Abteilung O
requested O
that O
Jakub B-PER
Edelstein I-PER
and O
his O
companions O
be O
brought O
to O
him O
. O

He O
told O
the O
guard B-TER
that O
they O
would O
be O
released O
to O
the O
Czech O
Family B-TER
Camp I-TER
and O
took O
their O
personal O
files O
with O
them O
. O

They O
told O
Edelstein B-PER
that O
he O
would O
go O
to O
his O
family O
. O

They O
were O
taken O
away O
by O
car O
, O
but O
not O
to O
the O
Family B-TER
Camp I-TER
. O

In O
fact O
, O
they O
were O
brought O
to O
Crematorium B-TER
III O
in O
Birkenau B-LOC
. O

The O
same O
car O
then O
drove O
to O
the O
Family B-TER
Camp I-TER
, O
from O
where O
it O
was O
supposed O
to O
take O
Edelstein B-PER
’s I-PER
wife B-PER
and O
his O
family O
. O

That O
same O
day O
, O
E B-PER
. O

’s O
wife B-PER
, O
gravely O
ill B-TER
, O
lay O
in O
block O
no O
. O

32 O
. O

The O
doctor B-TER
refused O
to O
release O
her O
with O
the O
explanation O
that O
she O
was O
unable O
to O
be O
transported O
. O

The O
car O
left O
. O

A O
few O
minutes O
later O
, O
the O
car O
returned O
with O
a O
strict O
order O
by O
Schwarzhuber B-PER
, O
the O
commander B-TER
of O
the O
camp B-LOC
, O
that O
Mrs. O
Edelstein B-PER
and O
her O
family O
must O
be O
released O
immediately O
in O
the O
state O
that O
she O
was O
in O
. O

They O
were O
also O
brought O
to O
Crematorium B-TER
III O
. O

There O
, O
all O
of O
them O
were O
then O
shot B-TER
to I-TER
death I-TER
in O
the O
execution O
hall O
and O
burned O
in O
the O
crematorium B-TER
. O

This O
statement O
can O
be O
verified O
by O
the O
eyewitnesses O
who O
have O
returned O
: O
Filip B-PER
Müller I-PER
, O
Sered B-LOC
n. I-LOC
Váhom I-LOC
, O
who O
saw O
the O
execution B-TER
in O
Crematorium B-TER
III O
. O

, O
Josef B-PER
Neumann I-PER
, O
Žilina B-LOC
, O
was O
was O
a O
prisoner O
in O
block O
11 O
in O
Auschwitz B-LOC
and O
spoke O
with O
Jakub B-PER
Edelstein I-PER
. O

Signature O
: O
Erich B-PER
Schön I-PER
Statement O
was O
accepted O
by O
: O
Berta B-PER
Gerzonová I-PER
Signatures O
of O
witnesses O
: O
Helena B-PER
Schicková I-PER
Marta B-PER
Fischerová I-PER
On O
behalf O
of O
the O
Documentary B-TER
campaign I-TER
: O
Scheck B-PER
On O
behalf O
of O
the O
archive O
: O
Alex B-PER
. I-PER

Schmiedt I-PER
26 O
. O

X. O
1945 O
