Gabersee B-LOC
Blok O
N O
number O
13 O
Adler B-PER
Lea I-PER
, O
seventeen O
years O
old O
. O

Finished O
two O
classes O
of O
gymnasium B-TER
. O

Born O
in O
Zboriv B-LOC
, O
Poland B-LOC
. O

In O
the O
first O
period O
of O
the O
occupation B-TER
they O
carried O
out O
a O
pogrom B-TER
. O

After O
the O
pogrom B-TER
, O
there O
was O
an O
aktion B-TER
. O

During O
the O
action O
, O
they O
decimated B-TER
almost O
all O
the O
Jews O
of O
the O
city O
. O

From O
cold B-TER
and I-TER
hunger I-TER
people B-TER
died B-TER
en I-TER
masse I-TER
. O

During O
the O
liquidation B-TER
of I-TER
the I-TER
ghetto I-TER
, O
I O
, O
together O
with O
my O
parents B-TER
and O
brother B-TER
, O
hid B-TER
in O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

Not O
being O
eighteen O
years O
old O
, O
I O
had O
to O
leave O
and O
part O
with O
my O
parents B-TER
. O

I O
hid B-TER
with O
my O
relatives B-TER
, O
to O
whom O
my O
parents B-TER
sent O
me O
. O

Coming O
out O
of O
the O
bunker B-TER
, O
I O
discovered O
that O
my O
parents B-TER
, O
poor O
things O
, O
were O
not B-TER
alive I-TER
. O

I O
left O
the O
bunker B-TER
on O
August O
19 O
, O
1944 O
. O

Adler B-PER
Lea I-PER
