Prague B-LOC
, O
IV O
. O

, O
Na B-LOC
Bašte I-LOC
sv I-LOC
. I-LOC

Ludmily I-LOC
19 I-LOC
. O

18.10.45 O
My O
dear O
ones O
, O
this O
time O
, O
as O
an O
exception O
, O
I O
am O
writing O
you O
in O
German O
. O

For O
this O
letter B-TER
, O
which O
will O
probably O
be O
very O
long O
, O
is O
not O
just O
for O
our O
dear O
friends O
who O
have O
written O
so O
cordially O
to O
us O
– O
that O
is O
, O
for O
Anny O
, O
Josef O
, O
Alfred O
, O
the O
Wintersteins B-PER
– O
but O
also O
for O
all O
the O
many O
others O
, O
some O
of O
whom O
may O
not O
be O
able O
to O
read O
Czech O
, O
others O
not O
English O
. O

Do O
n’t O
be O
angry O
that O
I O
report O
so O
collectively O
. O

But O
it O
is O
not O
only O
technically O
, O
but O
also O
emotionally O
a O
very O
difficult O
task O
to O
keep O
telling O
these O
terrible O
things O
again O
and O
again O
. O

Before O
I O
report O
about O
us O
, O
I O
want O
to O
narrate O
in O
general O
about O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
. O

Because O
that O
is O
where O
we O
left O
most O
of O
our O
common O
friends B-TER
in O
May O
1944 O
, O
whom O
we O
unfortunately O
have O
mostly O
not O
seen O
again O
. O

You O
will O
have O
heard O
and O
read O
more O
than O
enough O
about O
concentration B-TER
camps I-TER
. O

You O
probably O
do O
n’t O
know O
much O
about O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
, O
but O
it O
was O
very O
bad O
. O

Especially O
because O
if O
our O
people O
had O
had O
some O
good O
will O
, O
it O
could O
have O
become O
a O
very O
tolerable O
social O
construct O
. O

We O
really O
had O
self B-TER
- I-TER
administration I-TER
, O
it O
was O
absolutely O
not O
a O
concentration B-TER
camp I-TER
. O

But O
as O
it O
was O
, O
it O
became O
a O
morass O
of O
corruption O
and O
arbitratiness O
. O

There O
were O
3 O
very O
clearly O
distinguished O
castes O
: O
1./ O
The O
prominent O
persons O
( O
this O
is O
not O
ridicule O
, O
but O
die O
Prominenten O
was O
the O
official O
designation O
) O
, O
their O
favorites O
, O
and O
their O
hangers O
- O
on O
. O

– O
2./ O
The O
hard O
workers B-TER
, O
including O
doctors B-TER
and O
caregivers O
. O

– O
3./ O
The O
old O
and O
those O
unable O
to O
work B-TER
. O

– O
The O
first O
group O
lived O
in O
luxury O
and O
, O
above O
all O
, O
was O
protected O
from O
the O
feared O
transports B-TER
to O
unknown O
destinations O
. O

– O
The O
second O
group O
earned O
money O
with O
great O
difficulty O
, O
but O
at O
any O
rate O
acquired O
its O
piece O
of O
bread B-TER
and O
was O
not O
all O
too O
hungry B-TER
, O
if O
never O
entirely O
sated O
. O

– O
The O
third O
group O
starved B-TER
already O
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
, O
if O
they O
had O
no O
connections O
to O
Group O
1 O
. O

– O
So O
only O
one O
segment O
had O
it O
really O
bad O
there O
. O

But O
the O
people O
behaved O
as O
if O
everything O
was O
a O
matter O
of O
life O
and O
death O
, O
like O
in O
the O
concentration B-TER
camp I-TER
, O
completely O
ruthlessly O
and O
demoralized O
. O

I O
can O
say O
with O
pride O
that O
our O
mutual O
friends O
were O
among O
the O
very O
few O
left O
to O
the O
old O
, O
Dr. O
Lederer B-PER
- I-PER
Beers I-PER
, O
Dr. O
Erwin B-PER
Langs I-PER
, O
Dr. O
Alts B-PER
, O
Igel O
and O
Rita O
, O
Dr. O
Tschiassnys B-PER
, O
Dr. O
Reisz B-PER
. O

None O
of O
these O
ever O
returned B-TER
. O

I O
do O
n’t O
know O
about O
Igel O
and O
Rita O
. O

But O
both O
were O
very O
ill B-TER
. O

– O
Most O
of O
these O
friends B-TER
did O
not O
come O
to O
Auschwitz B-LOC
until O
October O
44 O
. O

At O
this O
time O
, O
one O
prominent O
person O
after O
the O
other O
was O
called O
in O
and O
shot O
dead B-TER
: O
at O
the O
beginning O
of O
the O
year O
Dr. B-PER
Edelstein I-PER
, O
later O
Zucker B-PER
, O
Friedmann B-PER
, O
Epstein B-PER
/Berlin O
, O
Krämer B-PER
, O
unfortunately O
also O
Dr. B-PER
Kahn I-PER
and O
his O
wife B-TER
, O
who O
had O
long O
suffered O
severe O
depression O
. O

All O
of O
these O
prominent O
persons O
, O
who O
knew O
too O
much O
, O
had O
to O
pay O
so O
dearly O
for O
their O
privileged O
position O
. O

When O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
was O
then O
liquidated B-TER
, O
the O
rest O
were O
arrested B-TER
as O
all O
- O
too O
- O
eager O
slavedrivers O
for O
the O
Germans B-TER
. O

– O
Of O
our O
closer O
acquaintances O
, O
the O
following O
have O
returned B-TER
: O
my O
brother B-TER
Hans O
( O
Hans O
asks O
whether O
the O
Schäfer B-PER
- I-PER
Maierhofers I-PER
still O
have O
Niky B-PER
Himmelblau I-PER
's O
things O
. O

All O
the O
Himmelblaus B-PER
are O
dead B-TER
. O

) O
, O
Minka B-PER
Krieger I-PER
– O
both O
without O
family B-TER
– O
Dr. O
Schild B-PER
, O
Dr. O
Richavy B-PER
– O
both O
without O
their O
wives B-TER
– O
the O
two O
brothers B-TER
Dr. O
Paul O
and O
master O
builder O
Otto B-PER
Bellak I-PER
, O
Dr. O
Wurzel B-PER
from O
Witkowitz B-LOC
with O
his O
family B-TER
, O
Erna B-PER
Roth I-PER
and O
her O
daughter B-TER
, O
currently O
recuperating O
from O
severe O
typhus B-TER
fever O
in O
Sweden B-LOC
. O

Dr. O
Julek B-PER
Wechsb I-PER
. O

And O
Dr. O
Liewer B-PER
already O
committed O
suicide B-TER
in O
Ostrau B-LOC
, O
Julek O
as O
a O
prisoner B-TER
of O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
. O

Dear O
Alfred O
, O
it O
is O
great O
good O
fortune O
that O
you O
decided O
so O
quickly O
back O
then O
. O

– O
The O
returned O
doctors B-TER
probably O
have O
good O
prospects O
of O
opening O
private O
practices O
, O
but O
a O
managing O
position O
in O
a O
hospital B-TER
is O
out O
of O
the O
question O
. O

I O
am O
very O
curious O
whether O
and O
how O
you O
have O
decided O
. O

Unfortunately O
there O
is O
hardly O
any O
hope O
, O
dear O
Anny O
, O
that O
Sidy O
will O
turn O
up O
. O

I O
was O
often O
together O
with O
her O
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
. O

She O
looked O
good O
and O
well O
cared O
for O
, O
had O
an O
easy O
, O
profitable O
position O
as O
seamstress O
in O
the O
children B-TER
’s I-TER
home I-TER
, O
and O
lived O
relatively O
very O
well O
. O

I O
do O
n’t O
know O
when O
she O
left O
. O

We O
were O
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
from O
Sept. O
42 O
to O
May O
44 O
. O

Aside O
from O
the O
generally O
depressing O
conditions B-TER
, O
we O
had O
terrible O
private O
misfortune O
: O
we O
came O
immediately O
in O
the O
transports B-TER
to O
Poland B-LOC
. O

Lissi O
came O
down O
with O
a O
severe O
scarlet B-TER
fever I-TER
and O
then O
jaundice B-TER
, O
so O
that O
she O
lay O
for O
3 O
months O
in O
the O
hospital B-TER
, O
hungry B-TER
and O
miserable O
. O

This O
misfortune O
was O
our O
good O
fortune O
, O
because O
it O
meant O
we O
escaped B-TER
the O
transports B-TER
. O

But O
my O
father B-TER
, O
Irka O
, O
and O
Lore O
, O
and O
many O
friends O
had O
to O
die B-TER
. O

– O
We O
were O
all O
three O
heavy O
laborers B-TER
. O

I O
worked O
in O
the O
laundry O
, O
Lissi O
as O
a O
nurse B-TER
on O
the O
infections B-TER
ward I-TER
, O
Franzi O
in O
agriculture B-TER
. O

In O
Spring O
43 O
, O
Erwin O
and O
Lizzi O
came O
to O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
. O

Lizzi O
worked O
with O
me O
in O
the O
laundry O
, O
was O
brave O
, O
hardworking O
, O
and O
indescribably O
goodhearted O
. O

At O
Pentecost B-TER
43 O
a O
terrible O
misfortune O
happened O
. O

Franzi O
, O
who O
had O
had O
an O
unexplained O
fever B-TER
for O
weeks O
– O
probably O
an O
undiagnosed O
scarlet B-TER
fever I-TER
– O
jumped B-TER
one O
night O
from O
the O
2nd O
upper O
storey O
of O
her O
barracks O
and O
lay O
there O
with O
a O
broken O
pelvis O
and O
smashed O
ankles O
. O

She O
had O
no O
reason O
at O
all O
to O
do O
this O
. O

We O
lived O
in O
the O
best O
harmony O
, O
and O
she O
had O
a O
magnificent O
fiance O
, O
whom O
she O
loved O
very O
much O
. O

She O
was O
suspended O
between O
life O
and O
death O
for O
a O
half O
a O
year O
. O

She O
got O
typhoid B-TER
fever I-TER
as O
well O
. O

But O
this O
misfortune O
was O
our O
good O
fortune O
, O
too O
. O

We O
were O
in O
the O
transport B-TER
again O
, O
and O
again O
we O
got O
out O
of O
it O
. O

But O
Lizzi O
, O
Erwin O
, O
Franzi O
's O
boy O
went O
and O
were O
lost B-TER
. O

Franzi O
recovered O
, O
despite O
all O
the O
predictions O
of O
the O
doctors B-TER
, O
and O
is O
more O
beautiful O
and O
in O
better O
condition O
than O
ever O
, O
she O
's O
just O
easily O
fatigued O
. O

So O
we O
did O
n’t O
come O
to O
Auschwitz B-LOC
until O
May O
44 O
. O

We O
were O
glad O
to O
go O
, O
because O
we O
looked O
forward O
to O
seeing O
our O
loved O
ones O
, O
and O
of O
course O
we O
did O
n’t O
know O
that O
it O
was O
Auschwitz B-LOC
. O

We O
learned O
immediately O
that O
they O
were O
all O
dead B-TER
. O

Franzi O
withstood O
this O
shock O
wonderfully O
, O
Lissi O
less O
so O
. O

I O
had O
to O
be O
brave O
for O
all O
three O
of O
us O
. O

Our O
transport B-TER
was O
the O
first O
that O
was O
mustered O
out O
for O
work B-TER
in O
Germany B-LOC
, O
about O
2 O
months O
after O
our O
arrival O
. O

Of O
course O
, O
I O
was O
rejected O
because O
I O
looked O
terrible O
. O

But O
I O
came O
along O
anyway O
and O
so O
we O
were O
transported B-TER
to O
Christianstadt B-LOC
, O
Germany B-LOC
's I-LOC
biggest O
munitions O
factory B-TER
. O

This O
was O
a O
subdivision O
of O
the O
concentration B-TER
camp I-TER
Gross B-LOC
- I-LOC
Rosen I-LOC
. O

Until O
the O
Fall O
, O
we O
maintained O
more O
or O
less O
. O

But O
with O
the O
cold B-TER
, O
our O
hunger B-TER
became O
intolerable O
. O

And O
when O
we O
were O
evacuated B-TER
at O
the O
beginning O
of O
February O
45 O
, O
it O
got O
catastrophic O
. O

On O
the O
third O
day O
of O
this O
miserable O
hike B-TER
, O
the O
children B-TER
and O
I O
resolved O
we O
would O
rather O
be O
shot B-TER
dead I-TER
trying O
to O
escape B-TER
than O
exhausted O
at O
the O
side O
of O
the O
road O
. O

We O
were O
not O
shot B-TER
dead I-TER
. O

We O
went O
without O
bread B-TER
, O
without O
papers O
, O
clothed B-TER
in O
shreds O
of O
rags O
right O
through O
Germany B-LOC
on O
the O
border O
between O
Silesia B-LOC
and O
Brandenburg B-LOC
, O
always O
eastward O
toward O
the O
sun O
and O
the O
thunder O
of O
the O
artillery O
on O
the O
nearby O
front O
, O
toward O
the O
Russians B-ORG
. O

/ O
The O
other O
refugees B-TER
had O
turned O
to O
the O
West O
, O
away O
from O
the O
front O
. O

/ O
Farmers B-TER
took O
pity O
on O
us O
and O
let O
us O
spend O
the O
night O
in O
the O
cattle O
stall O
, O
as O
we O
asked O
, O
and O
gave O
us O
food B-TER
, O
which O
we O
never O
had O
to O
ask O
for O
. O

On O
the O
6th O
day O
we O
found O
ourselves O
in O
the O
middle O
of O
the O
German B-TER
front I-TER
fleeing O
from O
Breslau B-LOC
. O

In O
this O
dire O
danger O
, O
when O
a O
single O
call O
would O
cost O
us O
our O
lives O
, O
the O
only O
Catholic B-TER
church I-TER
in O
the O
whole O
area O
was O
the O
first O
building O
that O
opened B-TER
its I-TER
doors I-TER
to O
us O
. O

The O
priest B-TER
, O
whom O
we O
told O
the O
whole O
story O
, O
took O
us O
in O
and O
hid B-TER
us O
, O
even O
though O
he O
had O
Germans B-TER
quartered I-TER
in O
the O
building O
. O

We O
received O
from O
him O
and O
the O
others O
in O
the O
building O
wonderful O
, O
warm O
quarters O
, O
fantastic O
food B-TER
, O
linens O
, O
clothed B-TER
, O
and O
shoes O
; O
they O
did O
all O
this O
so O
cheerfully O
and O
as O
a O
matter O
of O
course O
, O
even O
though O
they O
themselves O
were O
in O
need O
and O
danger O
. O

This O
change O
from O
darkness O
to O
light O
was O
our O
most O
staggering O
experience O
of O
these O
years O
. O

After O
a O
week O
, O
the O
Russians B-ORG
were O
there O
. O

After O
7 O
weeks O
, O
we O
had O
recovered O
enough O
to O
work O
as O
members O
of O
the O
Red B-ORG
Army I-ORG
as O
linens O
seamstresses O
in O
the O
military B-TER
workshops B-TER
, O
i.e. O
, O
we O
traveled O
along O
barely O
behind O
the O
front O
, O
where O
we O
had O
lots O
of O
work O
, O
but O
wonderful O
treatment O
and O
plenty O
of O
food B-TER
. O

At O
the O
end O
of O
April O
, O
we O
joined O
a O
column O
of O
people O
returning O
to O
Czechoslovakia B-LOC
and O
arrived O
in O
Ostrau B-LOC
in O
mid- O
June O
after O
a O
march O
of O
350 O
kilometers O
. O

Franzi O
soon O
moved O
to O
Prague B-LOC
; O
she O
is O
an O
assistant O
to O
Erich B-PER
Ziffer I-PER
, O
who O
returned O
from O
Russia B-LOC
. O

They O
lost O
their O
son B-TER
, O
who O
was O
a O
Russian B-ORG
soldier I-ORG
. O

Lissi O
finished O
her O
old O
high B-TER
school I-TER
within O
3 O
months O
, O
took O
her O
final O
examination O
with O
honors O
and O
has O
matriculated O
at O
the O
Technical B-TER
University I-TER
here O
to O
become O
an O
engineer O
. O

She O
already O
knows O
the O
required O
languages O
– O
Spanish O
and O
Russian O
in O
addition O
to O
those O
learned O
at O
the O
school B-TER
. O

Both O
children B-TER
learned O
Russian O
at O
my O
wish O
back O
then O
in O
Prague B-LOC
, O
and O
that O
rescued B-TER
us O
. O

Because O
otherwise O
we O
would O
n’t O
have O
risked O
fleeing O
toward O
the O
Russians B-ORG
. O

– O
So O
we O
have O
been O
in O
Prague B-LOC
for O
14 O
days O
now O
. O

We O
have O
strenuous O
months O
behind O
us O
trying O
to O
replace O
our O
destroyed O
documents O
. O

Our O
name O
is O
now O
Šorková B-PER
– O
after O
Schorek B-PER
[ O
an O
old O
nickname O
of O
Josef B-PER
Schornstein I-PER
] O
. O

We O
ca O
n’t O
think O
about O
emigrating B-TER
now O
, O
this O
is O
not O
allowed O
because O
of O
the O
shortage O
of O
workers O
. O

We O
thank O
you O
all O
, O
especially O
you O
, O
dear O
Rufus O
, O
for O
your O
willingness O
to O
help O
, O
just O
as O
we O
must O
thank O
Samek O
and O
Brüll B-PER
. O

It O
is O
very O
cold B-TER
, O
and O
if O
you O
can O
help O
us O
with O
stockings B-TER
, O
gloves B-TER
, O
oil O
, O
or O
fat O
, O
that O
would O
mean O
a O
lot O
, O
especially O
cigarettes O
. O

– O
Soci O
and O
Marta O
, O
do O
n’t O
be O
angry O
that O
I O
'm O
not O
answering O
you O
separately O
. O

We O
have O
conveyed O
your O
wishes O
. O

Dear O
Dr. O
Erich B-PER
Böhm I-PER
, O
your O
cottage O
is O
orphaned O
. O

Poor O
Erwin O
referred O
us O
to O
you O
when O
we O
parted O
, O
he O
was O
the O
children B-TER
’s I-TER
guardian O
. O

I O
long O
the O
most O
for O
the O
Spitzers O
. O

Are O
the O
Budapesters O
rescued O
? O
Mila O
, O
Evchen O
, O
now O
I O
am O
really O
an O
old O
woman B-TER
, O
but O
a O
healthy O
one O
, O
despite O
everything O
. O

If O
I O
only O
had O
n’t O
had O
such O
a O
yearning O
, O
especially O
for O
Lizzi O
. O

My O
poor O
primarius O
[ O
chef O
doctor B-TER
, O
Annys O
partner O
in O
Prag B-LOC
] O
has O
n’t O
come O
either O
. O

All O
, O
all O
of O
you O
, O
write O
and O
in O
detail O
. O

We O
embrace O
all O
our O
dear O
friends B-TER
, O
all O
children B-TER
! O
All O
three O
Šoreks B-PER
, O
your O
Anny O
