Leon B-PER
Perelsztejn I-PER
Testimony O
( O
doc O
. O

301/106 O
) O
Typescript O
, O
6 O
pages O
, O
210 O
x O
295 O
mm O
, O
Polish O
language O
From O
the O
collection O
of O
the O
Warsaw O
Historical O
Commission O
for O
Investigation O
of O
Nazi O
Crimes O
Testimony O
of O
Leon B-PER
Perelsztejn I-PER
Born O
January O
13 O
, O
1902 O
, O
in O
Warsaw B-LOC
Residing O
at O
Grochów B-LOC
, O
ul B-LOC
. I-LOC

Stanisława I-LOC
Augusta I-LOC
24 I-LOC
Regarding O
the O
prisoners B-TER
’ O
rebellion B-TER
, O
and O
preparations O
leading O
up O
to O
it O
, O
at O
the O
Treblinka B-LOC
extermination I-LOC
camp I-LOC
On O
September O
27 O
, O
1942 O
, O
I O
was O
arrested B-TER
in O
Ostrowiec B-LOC
Kielecki I-LOC
; O
Ostrowiec O
Świętokrzyski O
. O

I O
had O
fled O
there O
from O
Warsaw B-LOC
in O
order O
to O
avoid O
being O
put O
in O
the O
ghetto B-TER
and O
taken O
to O
Treblinka B-LOC
. O

I O
was O
at O
Treblinka B-LOC
from O
late O
September O
1942 O
until O
August O
2 O
, O
1943 O
. O

The O
camp B-TER
at O
Treblinka B-LOC
was O
a O
typical O
extermination B-TER
camp I-TER
. O

Jews O
from O
all O
over O
Poland B-LOC
and O
from O
abroad O
were O
brought O
there O
. O

During O
the O
month O
of O
October O
, O
until O
November O
, O
I O
was O
assigned O
to O
the O
group O
of O
Jewish O
workers B-TER
that O
was O
sorting O
clothing B-TER
[ O
of O
the O
Jews O
who O
had O
been O
killed B-TER
] O
. O

Later O
I O
was O
appointed O
as O
the O
warehouseman O
for O
the O
toolshop O
, O
where O
I O
worked B-TER
till O
my O
escape B-TER
from O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

People O
were O
exterminated B-TER
in O
the O
following O
way O
: O
every O
day O
, O
a O
transport B-TER
of O
about O
twelve O
to O
twenty O
thousand O
people O
arrived O
. O

Three O
trains B-TER
a O
day O
arrived O
at O
the O
camp B-TER
by O
the O
branch O
line O
. O

On O
average O
, O
the O
train B-TER
had O
60 O
cars O
with O
one O
hundred O
people O
each O
. O

After O
arriving O
, O
the O
people O
would O
be O
taken O
to O
the O
courtyard O
, O
which O
was O
surrounded O
by O
barracks B-TER
. O

They O
were O
told O
to O
strip O
naked O
, O
and O
their O
belongings O
were O
piled O
in O
a O
heap O
. O

There O
were O
women B-TER
, O
children B-TER
and O
old O
people O
among O
those O
who O
arrived O
. O

Within O
two O
hours O
, O
the O
entire O
transport B-TER
would O
be O
murdered B-TER
. O

This O
happened O
in O
the O
following O
way O
: O
in O
the O
barracks B-TER
there O
were O
shower O
stalls O
, O
10 O
stalls O
; O
people O
would O
be O
sent O
to O
the O
baths O
, O
one O
hundred O
people O
to O
a O
stall O
. O

In O
the O
stalls O
, O
there O
were O
towels O
and O
washbasins O
, O
which O
made O
it O
seem O
like O
real O
baths O
. O

After O
they O
were O
let O
in O
, O
with O
the O
push O
of O
a O
button O
, O
the O
doors O
would O
be O
hermetically O
sealed O
and O
the O
people O
would O
be O
suffocated B-TER
with O
some O
kind O
of O
gas B-TER
, O
what O
kind O
, O
I O
do O
not O
know O
, O
within O
ten O
minutes O
. O

Ten O
minutes O
later O
, O
the O
floor O
moved O
aside O
automatically O
and O
the O
bodies B-TER
fell O
into O
a O
hole O
several O
meters O
deep O
. O

A O
ditch O
several O
meters O
wide O
went O
from O
the O
pit O
for O
many O
hundreds O
of O
meters O
. O

The O
corpses B-TER
were O
pulled O
on O
stretcher O
- O
carts O
by O
workers O
and O
carried O
out O
to O
piles O
, O
after O
which O
they O
were O
doused O
with O
gasoline O
and O
burned O
. O

Before O
people O
entered O
the O
stalls O
, O
their O
gold O
teeth O
were O
ripped O
out O
and O
women B-TER
’s O
hair O
was O
cut O
, O
the O
hair O
and O
gold O
were O
sent O
outside O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

The O
prisoners B-TER
who O
were O
ill B-TER
were O
separated O
from O
each O
transport B-TER
and O
taken O
to O
a O
fence O
covered O
with O
a O
hedge O
with O
a O
sign O
that O
said O
Lazaret O
where O
they O
would O
be O
taken O
one O
by O
one O
[ O
and O
] O
an O
SS B-TER
man O
holding O
a O
revolver O
or O
a O
machine O
gun O
would O
kill B-TER
them O
. O

Prisoners B-TER
with O
Red B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
armbands O
would O
put O
the O
corpses B-TER
in O
piles O
and O
burn O
them O
immediately O
. O

Untersturmführer B-TER
Franz B-PER
SS‑Hauptsturmführer O
Franz O
Paul O
Stangl O
, O
the O
camp O
commandant O
at O
the O
Treblinka O
extermination O
camp O
from O
August O
1942 O
. O

was O
in O
charge O
, O
he O
was O
the O
camp B-TER
commandant O
. O

His O
deputy O
was O
Hauptscharführer B-TER
Kittner B-PER
. O

Kittner B-PER
’s I-PER
deputy O
was O
Scharführer B-TER
Mitte B-PER
. O

They O
were O
Germans B-TER
from O
the O
SS B-TER
( O
Sonderkommando O
) O
. O

There O
were O
forty O
- O
odd O
Germans B-TER
. O

In O
addition O
to O
them O
, O
there O
were O
approximately O
200 O
Ukrainians B-LOC
in O
the O
German B-TER
service O
who O
, O
as O
camp B-TER
guards B-TER
, O
also O
wore O
green O
uniforms O
and O
badges O
with O
the O
death’s O
- O
head O
and O
SS B-TER
. O

As O
a O
warehouseman O
, O
I O
could O
walk O
all O
over O
the O
entire O
camp B-TER
, O
since O
my O
job O
was O
to O
check O
the O
tools O
of O
workers B-TER
who O
were O
doing O
various O
tasks O
in O
groups O
. O

A O
prisoner B-TER
named O
eng[ineer O
] O
Galewski B-PER
( O
from O
Warsaw B-LOC
) O
was O
in O
charge O
of O
the O
prisoner B-TER
- O
workers B-TER
, O
he O
was O
[ O
also O
] O
a O
prisoner B-TER
, O
a O
very O
decent O
person O
, O
who O
knew O
about O
our O
conspiracy O
and O
who O
, O
although O
he O
was O
not O
taking O
an O
active O
part O
in O
it O
, O
used O
to O
help O
all O
of O
us O
carry O
out O
our O
plans O
. O

In O
the O
warehouse O
where O
I O
was O
working O
, O
the O
idea O
for O
an O
armed O
revolt O
came O
up O
. O

About O
150 O
meters O
from O
the O
warehouse O
was O
a O
weapons O
storeroom O
. O

We O
decided O
to O
get O
inside O
. O

A O
prisoner B-TER
who O
was O
a O
locksmith O
had O
already O
made O
a O
key O
to O
the O
storeroom O
in O
March O
before O
my O
arrival O
, O
he O
carried O
it O
with O
him O
and O
did O
not O
let O
on O
in O
any O
way O
[ O
that O
he O
was O
involved O
] O
. O

Grundland B-PER
the O
capo B-TER
from O
the O
camp B-TER
hospital B-TER
and O
I O
, O
along O
with O
a O
tailor O
from O
Kielce B-LOC
, O
who O
was O
about O
46 O
years O
old O
, O
Moniek O
, O
the O
capo B-TER
from O
the O
first O
barracks B-TER
, O
who O
was O
about O
18 O
or O
19 O
, O
one O
[ O
fellow O
] O
known O
as O
Jacek O
, O
and O
several O
other O
people O
, O
whose O
names O
I O
do O
n’t O
remember O
, O
neither O
first O
nor O
last O
names O
, O
worked O
out O
a O
plan O
to O
take O
over O
the O
weapons O
storeroom O
, O
which O
we O
did O
on O
August O
2 O
, O
1943 O
. O

Our O
first O
earlier O
attempt O
was O
unsuccessful O
and O
twelve O
people O
- O
who O
had O
been O
betrayed O
by O
a O
prisoner B-TER
, O
a O
man O
who O
used O
to O
make O
wire O
mesh O
for O
a O
living O
from O
Częstochowa B-LOC
- O
paid O
for O
it O
with O
their O
lives O
. O

We O
were O
supposed O
to O
take O
over O
the O
warehouse O
and O
begin O
the O
action O
around O
July O
12 O
, O
1943 O
. O

Having O
been O
unable O
to O
get O
into O
the O
weapons O
storeroom O
that O
day O
, O
we O
postponed O
the O
action O
. O

A O
few O
days O
later O
, O
fourteen O
people O
from O
various O
work B-TER
columns O
who O
had O
been O
taking O
part O
in O
the O
conspiracy O
were O
taken O
away O
. O

I O
was O
released O
along O
with O
a O
certain O
turner O
, O
whose O
name O
I O
do O
not O
remember O
, O
because O
there O
were O
no O
other O
prisoners B-TER
to O
work B-TER
in O
our O
positions O
, O
and O
despite O
being O
beaten O
, O
we O
did O
not O
confess O
and O
they O
did O
not O
have O
any O
evidence O
against O
us O
. O

Those O
twelve O
were O
taken O
away O
to O
Treblinka B-LOC
II O
, O
The O
extermination O
camp O
is O
described O
in O
the O
literature O
as O
Treblinka O
II O
, O
and O
the O
labor O
camp O
next O
to O
it O
as O
Treblinka O
I. O
The O
witness O
calls O
Treblinka O
I O
part O
of O
the O
camp O
in O
which O
prisoners O
were O
kept O
, O
Treblinka O
II O
as O
the O
actual O
extermination O
center O
and O
Treblinka O
III O
as O
the O
labor O
camp O
where O
they O
were O
shot B-TER
. O

We O
did O
not O
see O
them O
die B-TER
, O
but O
we O
heard O
the O
shots O
from O
a O
distance O
of O
300 O
meters O
. O

We O
did O
not O
stop O
working O
on O
new O
plans O
for O
a O
revolt O
, O
however O
. O

At O
night O
, O
we O
worked O
in O
strict O
secrecy O
. O

In O
each O
group O
of O
workers O
, O
we O
chose O
people O
, O
former O
soldiers B-TER
, O
who O
knew O
how O
to O
use O
weapons O
, O
and O
we O
assigned O
them O
specific O
military O
tasks O
in O
the O
action O
and O
did O
not O
make O
them O
privy O
to O
our O
plans O
, O
and O
told O
them O
to O
wait O
for O
our O
signal O
. O

We O
assigned O
three O
to O
set O
the O
barracks B-TER
on O
fire O
with O
gasoline O
. O

I O
had O
the O
task O
of O
storming O
the O
camp B-TER
headquarters O
, O
destroying O
the O
telephone O
and O
disposing O
of O
the O
secretary O
, O
the O
SS B-TER
- I-TER
man I-TER
Messing B-PER
, O
and O
the O
Stabsscharführer B-TER
Stadi B-PER
, O
Stabsscharführer O
was O
not O
a O
rank O
but O
a O
position O
of O
company O
sergeant O
major O
. O

which O
I O
was O
to O
do O
with O
eight O
other O
people O
. O

The O
locksmith O
gave O
us O
the O
key O
. O

Two O
boys B-TER
, O
18 O
or O
19 O
years O
old O
, O
who O
worked B-TER
cleaning O
the O
barracks B-TER
, O
observed O
the O
weapons O
storeroom O
for O
two O
weeks O
and O
had O
the O
task O
of O
getting O
inside O
and O
passing O
the O
weapons O
through O
the O
barred O
window O
. O

The O
masons O
were O
supposed O
to O
come O
with O
carts O
used O
for O
carting O
away O
rubble O
and O
take O
the O
weapons O
to O
the O
garage O
, O
where O
there O
was O
an O
enormous O
cellar O
. O

From O
there O
, O
when O
the O
signal O
was O
given O
, O
the O
weapons O
were O
to O
be O
distributed O
and O
the O
action O
was O
to O
start O
. O

The O
second O
and O
final O
attempt O
was O
to O
be O
made O
on O
August O
2 O
, O
at O
4:15 O
p.m. O
, O
which O
was O
when O
the O
fighting O
was O
supposed O
to O
begin O
. O

One O
of O
the O
cleaners O
, O
Jacek O
, O
entered O
the O
weapons O
storeroom O
at O
1:15 O
p.m. O
, O
the O
second O
stood O
at O
the O
door O
on O
guard O
. O

Jacek B-PER
passed O
all O
the O
weapons O
through O
the O
window O
to O
the O
men O
with O
the O
carts O
. O

They O
took O
them O
to O
the O
garage O
. O

At O
2:30 O
p.m. O
, O
weapons O
began O
to O
be O
distributed O
from O
the O
garage O
to O
all O
the O
groups O
of O
workers O
throughout O
the O
entire O
camp B-TER
. O

All O
the O
designated O
former O
soldiers B-TER
got O
weapons O
. O

At O
4:15 O
p.m. O
, O
when O
the O
action O
was O
supposed O
to O
start O
, O
I O
was O
waiting O
at O
the O
storeroom O
with O
a O
revolver O
that O
had O
been O
ready O
for O
a O
month O
. O

The O
detailed O
plan O
had O
been O
set O
for O
that O
time O
because O
a O
train B-TER
of O
Jewish O
and O
Polish B-LOC
prisoners B-TER
going O
from O
work B-TER
from O
Małkinia B-LOC
to O
Treblinka B-LOC
III I-LOC
Treblinka O
III O
– O
labor O
camp O
( O
actually O
Treblinka O
I O
) O
. O

would O
pass O
through O
the O
camp B-TER
as O
it O
did O
every O
day O
at O
that O
time O
, O
and O
we O
wanted O
to O
intercept O
them O
and O
have O
them O
join O
our O
action O
. O

They O
were O
not O
privy O
to O
the O
plan O
. O

At O
3:35 O
p.m. O
, O
two O
workers O
who O
came O
to O
the O
barracks B-TER
for O
their O
things O
roused O
the O
suspicion O
of O
the O
confidant O
Kuba O
, O
the O
barracks B-TER
elder I-TER
, O
who O
summoned O
Hauptscharführer B-TER
Kittner B-PER
. O

Kittner B-PER
summoned O
them O
to O
the O
square O
in O
front O
of O
my O
door O
, O
searched O
them O
, O
found O
money O
on O
them O
, O
began O
to O
whip O
them O
and O
wanted O
to O
shoot O
them O
. O

When O
I O
saw O
that O
, O
I O
gave O
the O
signal O
to O
start O
the O
action O
through O
the O
back O
window O
. O

The O
tailor O
Zalcberg B-PER
, O
from O
the O
second O
barracks B-TER
, O
began O
shooting B-TER
at O
Kittner B-PER
. O

Kittner B-PER
started O
running O
towards O
his O
barracks B-TER
to O
get O
a O
machine O
gun O
. O

The O
action O
began O
. O

No O
longer O
able O
to O
carry O
out O
my O
task O
, O
my O
people O
and O
I O
cut O
through O
the O
barbed O
wire O
in O
order O
to O
get O
to O
the O
back O
entrance O
to O
the O
tower O
, O
where O
the O
Ukrainians B-LOC
were O
. O

A O
former O
lieutenant O
in O
the O
Czech B-LOC
army B-TER
, O
whose O
first O
name O
was O
Rudolf B-PER
, O
had O
the O
most O
important O
task O
. O

He O
and O
a O
second O
prisoner B-TER
from O
Czechoslovakia B-LOC
took O
a O
heavy O
machine O
gun O
by O
cart O
with O
some O
people O
to O
the O
camp B-TER
zoo O
, O
went O
into O
the O
little O
tower O
and O
began O
shooting O
at O
the O
camp B-TER
’s O
headquarters O
and O
the O
guard O
posts O
. O

None O
of O
the O
Germans B-TER
or O
Ukrainians B-LOC
who O
were O
there O
could O
get O
out O
, O
and O
they O
all O
died B-TER
. O

The O
barracks B-TER
were O
set O
on O
fire O
. O

During O
the O
fighting O
, O
many O
prisoners B-TER
died B-TER
, O
but O
almost O
the O
entire O
camp B-TER
staff I-TER
at O
that O
time O
died B-TER
on O
the O
spot O
. O

The O
whole O
camp B-TER
was O
on O
fire O
. O

I O
saw O
Kittner B-PER
and O
SS B-TER
- I-TER
man I-TER
Suchomil B-PER
die B-TER
with O
my O
own O
eyes O
, O
shot O
in O
a O
barracks B-TER
window O
. O

The O
SS B-TER
- I-TER
man I-TER
, O
head O
of O
the O
SS B-ORG
Strasebahn O
, O
whose O
last O
name O
I O
do O
not O
remember O
, O
was O
killed B-TER
by O
a O
prisoner B-TER
who O
worked O
as O
a O
driver O
. O

His O
killer O
was O
shot B-TER
by O
some O
Ukrainian B-LOC
. O

The O
action O
was O
lightning O
- O
quick O
. O

At O
4:30 O
p.m. O
the O
entire O
camp B-TER
, O
with O
or O
without O
weapons O
, O
was O
free O
. O

And O
we O
fled O
to O
the O
surrounding O
forests O
. O

No O
one O
chased O
us O
. O

Unfortunately O
we O
did O
not O
manage O
to O
include O
the O
train O
with O
the O
workers O
, O
because O
when O
shots O
were O
heard O
, O
it O
was O
stopped O
before O
it O
reached O
us O
. O

Everyone O
who O
was O
[ O
physically O
] O
able O
escaped B-TER
from O
Treblinka B-LOC
I O
and O
II O
. O

Engineer O
Galewski B-PER
escaped B-TER
with O
me O
. O

Unfortunately O
after O
a O
few O
kilometers O
, O
his O
nerves O
failed O
him O
, O
he O
took O
some O
poison O
from O
his O
pocket O
, O
swallowed O
it O
and O
died B-TER
immediately O
, O
right O
in O
front O
of O
my O
eyes O
. O

I O
escaped B-TER
into O
the O
forest O
with O
a O
group O
of O
several O
other O
prisoners B-TER
, O
and O
after O
two O
weeks O
of O
wandering O
, O
I O
made O
it O
to O
my O
family B-TER
, O
where O
I O
hid B-TER
. O

I O
was O
in O
the O
Opatów B-LOC
and O
Kielce B-LOC
regions O
the O
whole O
time O
, O
until O
those O
areas O
were O
liberated B-TER
by O
the O
Red B-ORG
Army I-ORG
. O

On O
January O
21 O
, O
1945 O
, O
I O
was O
in O
Praga B-LOC
, O
where O
I O
am O
now O
living O
. O

All O
the O
facts O
I O
have O
described O
are O
true O
. O

I O
read O
this O
document O
before O
signing O
it O
. O

Warsaw B-LOC
, O
March O
9 O
, O
1945 O
( O
- O
) O
Leon B-PER
Perelsztejn I-PER
Recorded O
by O
B. B-PER
Świderski I-PER
, O
M.A. O
