Statement O
written O
with O
Hanuš B-PER
Gibian I-PER
, O
born O
15 O
. O

8 O
. O

1902 O
in O
Prague B-LOC
, O
in O
the O
Nováky B-LOC
labor B-TER
camp I-TER
, O
Prijevica B-LOC
district O
, O
Slovakia B-LOC
, O
residing O
in O
Prague B-LOC
I. I-LOC
, O
Rybná B-LOC
8 O
, O
Czech B-TER
nationality O
, O
occupation O
bank O
clerk O
. O

From O
1941 O
to O
September O
1944 O
, O
I O
lived O
with O
my O
two O
- O
member O
family B-TER
( O
wife O
and O
son O
) O
in O
the O
Nováky B-LOC
camp B-TER
, O
Prijevica B-LOC
district O
, O
Slovakia B-LOC
. O

I O
worked B-TER
there O
in O
the O
construction O
administration O
. O

We O
were O
housed B-TER
in O
wooden O
buildings O
; O
families B-TER
lived B-TER
together O
, O
the O
unmarried O
separately O
. O

The O
food B-TER
was O
fair O
. O

At O
first O
, O
the O
camp B-TER
was O
supervised O
by O
Hlinka B-ORG
’s I-ORG
guards I-ORG
, O
who O
were O
extremely O
cruel O
. O

Later O
, O
Hlinka B-ORG
’s I-ORG
guards I-ORG
were O
replaced O
by O
Slovak B-LOC
policemen B-TER
. O

In O
September O
1944 O
, O
at O
the O
beginning O
of O
the O
Slovak B-LOC
uprising B-TER
, O
the O
camp B-TER
was O
abolished O
and O
the O
Jewish B-TER
inhabitants I-TER
of O
this O
camp B-TER
were O
allowed O
to O
move O
freely O
throughout O
the O
space O
occupied O
by O
the O
Slovak B-LOC
National B-ORG
Council I-ORG
. O

As O
a O
result O
of O
the O
gradual O
occupation O
of O
Slovakia B-LOC
by O
the O
German B-TER
army I-TER
, O
I O
escaped B-TER
together O
with O
my O
family B-TER
to O
the O
area O
around O
Banská B-LOC
Bystrica I-LOC
, O
where O
I O
worked O
in O
the O
state O
refinery O
in O
Dubová B-LOC
until O
October O
28th O
1944 O
. O

When O
the O
German B-TER
army I-TER
approached O
Banská B-LOC
Bystrica I-LOC
, O
we O
were O
forced O
to O
hide B-TER
in O
the O
Slovak B-LOC
mountains O
. O

After O
wandering O
aimlessly O
for O
three O
whole O
days O
, O
during O
which O
the O
Germans B-TER
twice O
shot O
at O
us O
, O
we O
were O
captured O
on O
1 O
. O

11 O
. O

1944 O
. O

German B-TER
SSmen B-TER
gathered O
all O
of O
us O
together O
in O
a O
meadow O
and O
asked O
us O
if O
we O
were O
Jews O
. O

Those O
who O
could O
provide O
papers O
proving O
they O
were O
Aryan B-TER
were O
released O
. O

The O
Jews O
were O
told O
to O
immediately O
hand O
over O
their O
watches O
, O
money O
, O
and O
all O
of O
the O
valuables O
that O
they O
had O
on O
them O
. O

The O
SSmen B-TER
told O
us O
that O
we O
would O
no O
longer O
need O
them O
. O

Then O
, O
the O
SS B-TER
leader O
ordered O
us O
to O
be O
transported O
and O
notified O
us O
that O
a O
patrol O
of O
2 O
soldiers B-TER
would O
accompany O
us O
, O
promising O
that O
nothing O
would O
happen O
to O
us O
. O

On O
our O
way O
down O
from O
the O
mountains O
, O
we O
were O
joined O
by O
4 O
more O
SSmen B-TER
, O
so O
there O
was O
a O
total O
of O
6 O
. O

They O
took O
us O
to O
a O
meadow O
where O
the O
SSmen B-TER
hung O
back O
and O
ordered O
us O
to O
walk O
toward O
Banská B-LOC
Bystrica I-LOC
and O
to O
stay O
together O
. O

After O
we O
had O
gone O
forward O
for O
about O
10 O
steps O
, O
they O
began O
to O
shoot O
us O
in O
the O
back O
. O

They O
fired O
until O
everyone O
( O
42 O
people O
) O
lay O
dead B-TER
or O
half O
- O
dead O
. O

They O
then O
examined O
each O
body O
and O
took O
whatever O
they O
liked O
, O
and O
murdered B-TER
anyone O
who O
was O
n’t O
dead B-TER
yet O
with O
a O
shot O
to O
the O
dead O
. O

I O
pretended O
to O
be O
dead B-TER
as O
well O
as O
a O
14 O
- O
year O
- O
old O
girl B-TER
who O
was O
covered O
by O
her O
father O
’s O
overcoat O
. O

By O
a O
miracle O
, O
she O
was O
saved O
. O

This O
happened O
on O
November O
1st O
, O
1944 O
, O
at O
13:00 O
in O
the O
gap O
between O
Kozí B-LOC
Chrbát I-LOC
and O
Prašiva B-LOC
in O
the O
Lower B-LOC
Tatra I-LOC
Mountains I-LOC
, O
near O
the O
village O
of O
Hiadel B-LOC
. O

Signature O
: O
Marta B-PER
Kratková I-PER
Hanuš B-PER
Gibian I-PER
Signatures O
of O
witnesses O
: O
Berta B-PER
Gerzonová I-PER
Jan B-PER
Müll I-PER
uncertain O
Robert B-PER
Weinberger I-PER
Karel B-PER
Liewerand I-PER
On O
behalf O
of O
the O
archive O
: O
Alex B-PER
. I-PER

Schmiedt I-PER
Documentation B-TER
campaign I-TER
19 O
. O

XI O
. O

1945 O
Zeev B-PER
Scheck I-PER
