Extract O
from O
the O
Statement O
of O
Dr O
Walter B-PER
Löbner I-PER
, O
born O
27.1.1903 O
In O
the O
Ellrich B-LOC
i I-LOC
m I-LOC
Harz I-LOC
camp B-TER
, O
the O
camp B-TER
commandant B-TER
SS B-TER
Oberscharführer I-TER
Brinkmann B-PER
forced O
a O
prisoner B-TER
who O
had O
been O
accused O
on O
cannibalism O
to O
eat B-TER
human O
body O
parts O
in O
front O
of O
witness O
, O
even O
having O
salt O
and O
pepper O
passed O
to O
him O
. O

On O
the O
same O
day O
, O
he O
had O
the O
prisoner B-TER
killed B-TER
. O

Kremmen B-LOC
, O
14.5.1945 O
Dokumentační B-TER
akce I-TER
26.VIII.1945 O
Zeev B-PER
Scheck I-PER
Transcript O
Kremmen B-LOC
, O
14.5.1945 O
I O
, O
Dr O
Walter B-PER
Löbner I-PER
, O
born O
27.01.1903 O
in O
Hermannshütte B-LOC
in O
Bohemia B-LOC
, O
a O
Czechoslovak B-LOC
citizen B-TER
, O
last O
living O
at O
Prague B-LOC
- O
Vinohrady B-LOC
, O
Fochova B-LOC
9 O
, O
was O
arrested B-TER
by O
the O
Prague B-ORG
Gestapo I-ORG
on O
18.04.1939 O
and O
imprisoned O
in O
several O
different O
concentration B-TER
camps I-TER
in O
Germany B-TER
( O
Sachsenhausen B-LOC
, O
Oranienburg B-LOC
, O
Auschwitz B-LOC
, O
Auschwitz B-LOC
3 I-LOC
, O
Gross B-LOC
Rosen I-LOC
, O
Dora B-LOC
, O
Ellrich B-LOC
i I-LOC
m I-LOC
Harz I-LOC
, O
Oranienburg B-LOC
) O
until O
I O
was O
able O
to O
escape B-TER
to O
freedom O
on O
21.04.1945 O
. O

At O
the O
moment O
, O
I O
am O
in O
Kremmen B-LOC
, O
because O
the O
garrison O
and O
population O
is O
without O
a O
doctor B-TER
, O
and O
I O
am O
employed O
as O
the O
head O
doctor B-TER
in O
a O
newly O
founded O
city O
hospital B-TER
. O

Until O
the O
loss O
of O
the O
Sudetenland B-LOC
and O
the O
occupation O
by O
the O
Germans B-TER
, O
I O
was O
a O
doctor B-TER
and O
surgeon O
in O
Marianské B-LOC
Lázně I-LOC
and O
the O
interim O
head O
of O
the O
hospital B-TER
there O
. O

I O
made O
no O
secret O
of O
my O
antifascist B-TER
opinions O
which O
, O
in O
April O
1939 O
, O
let O
my O
arrest B-TER
. O

The O
arrest B-TER
warrant O
stated O
the O
reason O
for O
my O
imprisonment O
as O
strong O
suspicion O
of O
high O
treason O
against O
the O
German O
people O
. O

During O
the O
six O
- O
year O
path O
of O
martyrdom O
and O
suffering O
, O
I O
had O
the O
opportunity O
to O
learn O
about O
the O
terrible O
, O
sadistic O
methods O
of O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
and O
the O
SS B-TER
, O
both O
first O
- O
hand O
and O
by O
observation O
. O

As O
I O
want O
to O
play O
my O
part O
in O
making O
sure O
that O
those O
responsible O
are O
punished O
, O
I O
want O
to O
make O
the O
names O
of O
several O
perpetrators O
that O
I O
know O
available O
to O
the O
commendable O
investigating O
authorities O
. O

1 O
. O

The O
Gestapo B-ORG
and O
SS B-TER
man I-TER
, O
Commissioner O
Wiggers B-PER
of O
the O
Prague B-ORG
Gestapo I-ORG
, O
who O
imprisoned O
me O
and O
sent O
me O
to O
the O
concentration B-TER
camp I-TER
without O
affording O
me O
– O
a O
Czech B-TER
citizen B-TER
– O
the O
right O
to O
a O
proper O
trial B-TER
. O

2 O
. O

The O
SS B-TER
man I-TER
and O
director O
of O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
prison B-TER
Pankrac B-LOC
in O
Prague B-LOC
, O
by O
the O
name O
of O
Zoppa B-PER
or O
something O
similar O
, O
who O
often O
terrorised O
the O
prisoners B-TER
personally O
with O
beatings O
. O

He O
broke O
two O
of O
my O
ribs O
on O
16.09.1939 O
by O
punching O
me O
. O

3 O
. O

The O
policeman B-TER
Max B-PER
Böhlke I-PER
– O
or O
something O
similar O
– O
from O
Leipzig B-LOC
who O
was O
a O
prison O
guard O
and O
burst O
my O
eardrum O
by O
punching O
me O
whilst O
I O
was O
in O
prison B-TER
in O
Prague B-LOC
, O
and O
as O
a O
result O
I O
got O
a O
terrible O
middle O
ear O
infection B-TER
, O
and O
lost O
my O
hearing O
. O

4 O
. O

In O
the O
concentration B-TER
camp I-TER
Sachsenhausen B-LOC
Oranienburg B-LOC
near O
Berlin B-LOC
, O
the O
following O
SS B-TER
men I-TER
who O
are O
known O
to O
me O
by O
name O
and O
whose O
unheard O
of O
brutality O
– O
both O
physical O
and O
mental O
– O
was O
an O
outrage O
to O
even O
the O
most O
primitive O
requirements O
of O
a O
prisoner B-TER
’s O
human O
rights O
: O
Oberscharführer B-TER
Bugdahle B-PER
, O
Fickert B-PER
, O
Van B-PER
Deezen I-PER
, O
Birke B-PER
, O
Kaiser B-PER
, O
Schubert B-PER
, O
Brumm B-PER
, O
Gustav B-PER
Sorge I-PER
, O
Sinke B-PER
, O
Camp B-TER
Commandant I-TER
Schwarzhuber B-PER
from O
Munich B-LOC
who O
was O
later O
the O
commandant B-TER
in O
Birkenau B-LOC
, O
Commandant B-TER
Sturmbannführer B-TER
Heydrich O
later O
Commandant B-TER
Heinkel B-ORG
- I-ORG
Oranienburg I-ORG
. O

They O
have O
, O
along O
with O
many O
others O
whose O
names O
I O
do O
n’t O
know O
, O
contributed O
to O
, O
or O
directly O
caused O
, O
the O
deaths B-TER
of O
thousands O
of O
innocent O
people B-TER
through O
beatings O
with O
their O
fists O
and O
sticks O
, O
through O
so O
- O
called O
sport O
and O
other O
torments O
, O
the O
withholding O
of O
food B-TER
and O
were O
also O
involved O
in O
the O
killing B-TER
of O
many O
Russian B-TER
prisoners B-TER
of I-TER
war I-TER
in O
the O
summer O
and O
autumn O
of O
1941 O
. O

5 O
. O

Sturmführer B-TER
Höss B-PER
( O
name O
unknown O
) O
in O
1940 O
the O
camp B-TER
commandant I-TER
in O
Sachsenhausen B-LOC
and O
later O
in O
Auschwitz B-LOC
, O
is O
the O
person O
responsible O
for O
the O
deportation B-TER
and O
killing B-TER
by O
gas B-TER
and O
starvation B-TER
of O
one O
and O
a O
half O
million O
Hungarian B-TER
, O
Romanian B-TER
, O
Slovakian B-TER
, O
Italian B-TER
and O
Greek B-TER
Jews O
. O

6 O
. O

For O
the O
killing B-TER
by O
starvation B-TER
, O
terror O
, O
epidemics O
, O
gas B-TER
, O
shooting B-TER
, O
beating O
, O
torture O
and O
similar O
of O
7 O
million O
Jews O
from O
the O
other O
countries O
of O
Europe O
and O
many O
hundreds O
of O
thousands O
of O
non O
- O
Jews O
in O
the O
camps B-TER
of O
Auschwitz B-LOC
and O
Birkenau B-LOC
, O
the O
following O
SS B-TER
men I-TER
are O
guilty O
: O
the O
camp B-TER
commandants I-TER
Auemier B-PER
, O
Schwarz B-PER
, O
Fritsch B-PER
, O
Hessler B-PER
, O
Baer B-PER
, O
Schwarzhuber B-PER
, O
Höss B-PER
. O

7 O
. O

In O
the O
women B-TER
’s I-TER
camp I-TER
, O
Auschwitz B-LOC
I I-LOC
Harmense B-LOC
, O
the O
female B-TER
SS B-TER
guard B-TER
Major O
Rendel B-PER
( O
name O
unknown O
) O
née O
Klein B-PER
was O
involved O
in O
the O
harassment O
and O
physical O
and O
mental O
abuse O
of O
the O
female B-TER
prisoners B-TER
and O
is O
to O
blame O
for O
the O
deaths B-TER
of O
many O
. O

8 O
. O

The O
same O
is O
true O
for O
the O
women B-TER
’s I-TER
concentration I-TER
camp I-TER
Auschwitz B-LOC
1 I-LOC
Budy B-LOC
and O
the O
female B-TER
SS B-TER
guard B-TER
Frau O
Hasse B-PER
from O
Görlitz B-LOC
, O
who O
was O
later O
the O
head O
of O
labour B-TER
in O
the O
women B-TER
’s I-TER
camp I-TER
Birkenau B-LOC
and O
took O
part O
in O
the O
selections B-TER
of O
women B-TER
who O
were O
no O
longer O
able O
to O
work B-TER
and O
so O
contributed O
to O
the O
deaths B-TER
of O
many O
women B-TER
. O

9 O
. O

The O
following O
so O
- O
called O
doctors B-TER
from O
the O
SS B-TER
made O
personal O
decisions O
about O
killing B-TER
hundreds O
of O
thousands O
of O
people B-TER
who O
were O
unable O
to O
work B-TER
but O
also O
completely O
healthy O
people B-TER
through O
the O
use O
of O
phenol O
injections O
into O
the O
heart O
, O
gas B-TER
, O
by O
being O
burnt O
alive O
, O
use O
in O
experimental B-TER
operations O
as O
medical O
guinea O
pigs O
, O
etc O
. O

Sturmbannführer B-TER
Dr O
Wirths B-PER
( O
spelling O
unknown O
) O
, O
Hauptsturmführer B-TER
Dr O
Mengele B-PER
, O
Hauptsturmführer B-TER
Dr O
Fischer B-PER
, O
Sturmführer B-TER
Dr O
Rode B-PER
, O
Sturmführer B-TER
Dr O
Klein B-PER
, O
Sturmführer B-TER
Dr O
König B-PER
, O
Dr O
Lucas B-PER
, O
Dr O
Thilo B-PER
. O

10 O
. O

The O
mutilation O
of O
living O
persons B-TER
through O
sterilisation B-TER
, O
castration O
and O
similar O
operations O
were O
carried O
out O
particularly O
by O
the O
Luftwaffe B-ORG
doctor B-TER
, O
Schumann B-PER
or O
a O
name O
similar O
to O
that O
. O

11 O
. O

In O
the O
so O
- O
called O
women B-TER
’s O
block O
of O
the O
men B-TER
’s O
camp B-TER
Auschwitz B-LOC
1 I-LOC
, O
thousands O
of O
healthy O
women B-TER
were O
mutilated O
by O
injections O
, O
exposure O
to O
radiation O
and O
operations O
and O
later O
violently O
murdered B-TER
, O
for O
which O
the O
nine O
or O
ten O
named O
doctors B-TER
are O
responsible O
. O

12 O
. O

Involved O
in O
the O
mass O
shootings O
in O
Block O
11 O
of O
the O
concentration B-TER
camp I-TER
Auschwitz B-LOC
were O
SS B-TER
Oberscharführer I-TER
Kleemann B-PER
– O
later O
the O
camp B-TER
commandant I-TER
in O
Janina O
and O
SS B-TER
Unterscharführer I-TER
Schmidt B-PER
( O
spelling O
unknown O
) O
from O
Saarbrücken B-LOC
. O

13 O
. O

Oberscharführer B-TER
Glaue B-PER
, O
camp B-TER
commandant I-TER
in O
Auschwitz B-LOC
1 I-LOC
Budy B-LOC
is O
responsible O
for O
the O
deaths B-TER
of O
many O
people B-TER
through O
physical O
stress O
and O
forcing O
them O
to O
work O
19 O
- O
hour O
work B-TER
days I-TER
without O
sufficient O
nutrition O
. O

14 O
. O

As O
the O
camp B-TER
Auschwitz B-LOC
, O
Birkenau B-LOC
was O
emptied O
in O
January O
1945 O
due O
to O
the O
advance O
of O
the O
victorious O
Red B-ORG
Army I-ORG
and O
the O
prisoners B-TER
were O
deported O
to O
Germany B-TER
, O
SS B-TER
Rottenführer I-TER
Niemeier B-PER
from O
Hannover B-LOC
shot B-TER
prisoners B-TER
in O
the O
neck O
and O
left O
their O
bodies O
where O
they O
fell O
on O
the O
18 O
- O
day O
march B-TER
from O
Auschwitz B-LOC
3 I-LOC
Janina O
to O
Gross B-LOC
Rosen I-LOC
in O
Silesia B-LOC
if O
they O
were O
no O
longer O
able O
to O
walk O
. O

15 O
. O

In O
the O
Ellrich B-LOC
camp B-TER
in O
Harz O
, O
the O
camp B-TER
commandant I-TER
, O
SS B-TER
Oberscharführer I-TER
Brinkmann B-PER
, O
forced O
a O
prisoner B-TER
who O
had O
been O
accused O
on O
cannibalism O
to O
eat B-TER
human O
body O
parts O
in O
front O
of O
witnesses O
, O
even O
having O
salt O
and O
pepper O
passed O
to O
him O
. O

On O
the O
same O
day O
, O
he O
had O
the O
prisoner B-TER
killed B-TER
. O

16 O
. O

As O
the O
Ellrich B-LOC
camp B-TER
in O
Harz O
was O
forced O
to O
Heikel B-ORG
- I-ORG
Oranienburg I-ORG
in O
1945 O
, O
the O
leader O
of O
the O
transport O
, O
Oberscharführer B-TER
Gaudeck B-PER
, O
was O
responsible O
for O
the O
death B-TER
of O
many O
hundreds O
of O
prisoners B-TER
due O
to O
insufficient O
distribution O
of O
food B-TER
. O

17.This O
is O
just O
a O
small O
excerpt O
of O
the O
horrific O
catalogue O
of O
guilt O
of O
Hitler B-PER
’s O
dogs O
of O
Hell O
and O
many O
names O
as O
I O
can O
remember O
. O

The O
number O
of O
the O
innocent O
dead B-TER
is O
without O
end O
, O
including O
my O
whole O
family B-TER
, O
my O
parents O
and O
siblings O
and O
I O
can O
be O
considered O
some O
kind O
of O
wonder O
of O
the O
world O
, O
that O
I O
managed O
to O
survive O
the O
past O
6 O
years O
of O
the O
most O
terrible O
mental O
, O
spiritual O
, O
physical O
and O
sexual O
distress O
, O
and O
, O
in O
the O
last O
hours O
– O
through O
a O
brave O
escape B-TER
over O
the O
wire O
– O
was O
able O
to O
avoid O
physical O
annihilation O
. O

To O
the O
public O
prosecutors O
, O
who O
might O
perhaps O
be O
helped O
by O
this O
indictment O
document O
, O
I O
would O
like O
to O
say O
one O
sentence O
, O
that O
I O
often O
recited O
in O
the O
shadow O
of O
the O
gas B-TER
chambers I-TER
in O
Auschwitz B-LOC
and O
Birkenau B-LOC
, O
as O
I O
wanted O
to O
collapse O
from O
anger O
, O
suffering O
and O
torment O
and O
only O
the O
thought O
of O
vengeance O
kept O
be O
going O
: O
Death O
is O
no O
punishment O
. O

Signature O
of O
the O
witness O
: O
Marta B-PER
Kratková I-PER
Berta B-PER
Gerzonová I-PER
Own O
signature O
: O
Dr. O
Walter B-PER
Löbner I-PER
For O
the O
Documentary B-TER
campaign I-TER
Zeev B-PER
Scheck I-PER
For O
the O
archive O
: O
Alex B-PER
Schmiedt I-PER
26.VIII.1945 O
