An O
informed O
source O
states O
on O
the O
basis O
of O
information O
assertedly O
just O
received O
from O
Hungary B-LOC
that O
the O
Kallay B-PER
Government B-TER
has O
prepared O
and O
shortly O
will O
propose O
a O
special O
war O
levy B-TER
on O
Jewish B-TER
property I-TER
along O
the O
lines O
of O
the O
taxes B-TER
of O
that O
nature O
recently O
established O
in O
Rumania B-LOC
and O
Bulgaria B-LOC
. O

[ O
... O
] O
The O
source O
adds O
that O
anti B-TER
- I-TER
Semitic I-TER
members O
of O
Kallay B-PER
’s I-PER
Government B-TER
declare O
Hungarian B-TER
Jews B-TER
should O
in O
their O
own O
interest O
practice O
more O
moderation O
and O
abandon O
their O
provocative O
attitude O
otherwise O
even O
severer O
measures O
will O
be O
applied O
to O
them O
in O
the O
near O
future O
. O

