It O
was O
a O
hot O
and O
humid O
July O
night O
. O

Already O
during O
the O
afternoon O
they O
’re O
had O
been O
a O
certain O
degree O
of O
unrest O
in O
the O
streets O
of O
Bratislava B-LOC
. O

The O
rumour O
was O
another O
transport O
. O

We O
were O
collected O
from O
my O
house B-TER
and O
on O
the O
next O
day O
were O
put O
into O
train B-TER
carriages I-TER
. O

In O
one O
carriage B-TER
, O
there O
are O
60 O
people O
, O
men B-TER
, O
women B-TER
, O
healthy O
and O
unhealthy B-TER
, O
whether O
young O
or O
old O
, O
everybody O
was O
put O
into O
the O
wagons B-TER
. O

1000 O
people O
were O
next O
to O
each O
other O
and O
the O
train B-TER
began O
to O
move O
. O

Heat O
and O
a O
bad O
, O
pestilent O
air O
made O
breathing O
difficult O
. O

We O
did O
n’t O
know O
where O
our O
journey O
was O
taking O
us O
. O

The O
carriages B-TER
were O
completely O
closed O
, O
no O
light O
came O
on O
, O
no O
air O
or O
water O
was O
available O
to O
us O
. O

Finally O
, O
after O
a O
two O
- O
day O
journey O
, O
tired O
and O
exhausted O
, O
we O
arrived O
on O
the O
25.7.1942 O
in O
an O
awful O
, O
empty O
field O
. O

The O
carriages B-TER
were O
opened O
by O
high O
- O
ranking O
members B-TER
of I-TER
the I-TER
SS I-TER
. O

We O
were O
told O
to O
get O
out O
. O

First O
, O
us O
women B-TER
had O
to O
get O
out O
of O
the O
carriages B-TER
, O
then O
the O
men B-TER
. O

We O
could O
hear O
the O
loud O
shouting O
of O
the O
SS B-TER
hordes I-TER
. O

Come O
on O
, O
come O
on O
, O
this O
is O
your O
final O
destination O
. O

And O
so O
, O
it O
was O
either O
obey O
or O
die O
; O
that O
was O
our O
welcome O
. O

Us O
women B-TER
were O
put O
to O
one O
side O
, O
of O
course O
only O
the O
young O
ones O
, O
maximum O
35 O
years O
old O
. O

The O
rest O
were O
thrown O
into O
vans O
like O
bags O
of O
flour O
, O
60 O
to O
80 O
per O
van O
. O

Before O
we O
were O
taken O
somewhere O
else O
, O
we O
saw O
the O
other O
vans O
leave O
. O

New O
vans O
were O
filled O
and O
driven O
away O
. O

Then O
was O
our O
turn O
: O
we O
were O
put O
in O
a O
line O
, O
counted O
, O
and O
made O
to O
march O
. O

A O
member B-TER
of I-TER
the I-TER
SS I-TER
, O
SS B-TER
- I-TER
Schütze I-TER
was O
our O
supervisor O
. O

With O
rifles O
and O
pistols O
, O
he O
showed O
us O
the O
way O
to O
our O
new O
site O
. O

On O
the O
way O
to O
the O
camp O
the O
supervisor O
shouted O
and O
so O
this O
is O
how O
you O
left O
Egypt O
, O
and O
here O
you O
will O
die O
anyway O
, O
those O
of O
us O
who O
heard O
this O
, O
broke O
out O
into O
a O
cold O
sweat O
. O

On O
the O
way O
, O
we O
met O
men B-TER
in O
striped O
uniforms O
, O
accompanied O
by O
SS B-TER
with O
carabiners O
in O
the O
hands O
. O

Some O
of O
them O
might O
have O
shouted O
to O
us O
whether O
we O
had O
any O
food B-TER
, O
but O
their O
fear O
of O
death B-TER
was O
too O
great O
. O

As O
we O
approached O
the O
camp B-TER
, O
we O
saw O
the O
large O
inscription O
Arbeit O
macht O
frei O
( O
Work B-TER
makes O
you O
free O
) O
, O
but O
still O
we O
did O
n’t O
know O
where O
we O
were O
being O
brought O
to O
. O

Columns O
of O
men B-TER
walking O
along O
the O
long O
, O
terrible O
streets O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

The O
tired O
and O
drawn O
faces O
of O
the O
men B-TER
solved O
for O
us O
that O
puzzle O
. O

In O
was O
a O
morning O
roll B-TER
call I-TER
in O
the O
women B-TER
’s I-TER
camp I-TER
as O
we O
arrived O
. O

Thousands O
of O
bald O
- O
headed O
people B-TER
with O
a O
Russian B-LOC
military O
uniforms O
turned O
to O
look O
at O
us O
as O
we O
entered O
. O

In O
that O
moment O
, O
we O
thought O
, O
that O
we O
were O
in O
a O
Russian B-LOC
prisoner B-TER
of I-TER
war I-TER
camp I-TER
. O

From O
the O
individual O
rows O
, O
I O
could O
hear O
muffled O
calls O
, O
I O
was O
recognised O
by O
several O
acquaintances O
from O
my O
own O
town O
. O

If O
you O
have O
anything O
with O
you O
, O
throw O
it O
away O
. O

A O
few O
people B-TER
from O
the O
rows O
of O
the O
roll B-TER
call I-TER
even O
put O
their O
hands O
out O
, O
in O
order O
to O
take O
some O
bread B-TER
or O
whatever O
from O
us O
, O
for O
the O
hunger B-TER
was O
eating O
away O
at O
them O
. O

It O
was O
a O
terrible O
sight O
. O

Immediately O
afterwards O
, O
all O
of O
the O
columns O
left O
the O
camp B-TER
to O
go O
to O
work B-TER
. O

We O
were O
led O
to O
a O
bathroom O
, O
undressed B-TER
, O
shaved O
. O

They O
called O
it O
delousing O
. O

We O
were O
given O
new O
clothes B-TER
. O

A O
linen B-TER
dress I-TER
and O
wooden O
shoes O
, O
that O
was O
all O
the O
clothes B-TER
I O
had O
, O
everything O
that O
I O
had O
on O
. O

We O
received O
a O
small O
flannel O
, O
that O
they O
called O
a O
hand O
towel O
, O
to O
share O
between O
three O
people B-TER
. O

93 O
freshly O
shaved O
, O
bathed O
, O
and O
newly O
dressed B-TER
, O
we O
were O
led O
to O
a O
muster O
point O
. O

SS B-TER
- I-TER
Hauptscharführer I-TER
Schwartz O
, O
the O
camp B-TER
leader I-TER
and O
commander B-TER
, O
reprimanded O
the O
newly O
arrived O
cohort O
. O

After O
registration B-TER
was O
carried O
out O
in O
the O
afternoon O
, O
we O
were O
allowed O
into O
the O
block B-TER
, O
which O
would O
now O
be O
our O
new O
home O
. O

The O
head O
female B-TER
supervisor I-TER
, O
Marie B-PER
Mandel I-PER
, O
also O
did O
n’t O
miss O
the O
opportunity O
, O
for O
us O
to O
be O
lined O
up O
again O
. O

It O
offered O
her O
amusing O
moments O
to O
insult O
us O
. O

Mistbiene O
( O
garbage O
bees O
) O
was O
her O
special O
term O
. O

That O
’s O
how O
we O
spent O
the O
first O
day O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

On O
the O
next O
day O
, O
we O
went O
to O
work B-TER
. O

Five O
hours O
we O
had O
to O
stand O
in O
roll B-TER
call I-TER
, O
until O
the O
supervisors B-TER
Gertrude B-PER
Weniger I-PER
, O
Brandl B-PER
, O
Erika B-PER
Clauss I-PER
, O
Marie B-PER
Hasse I-PER
, O
Berta B-PER
Franz I-PER
and O
others O
, O
agreed O
to O
pronounce O
roll B-TER
call I-TER
over O
and O
let O
us O
leave O
the O
rows O
. O

And O
so O
, O
every O
day O
was O
the O
same O
for O
us O
. O

On O
9.8.1942 O
, O
the O
women B-TER
’s I-TER
camp I-TER
in O
Auschwitz B-LOC
was O
moved O
to O
Birkenau B-LOC
. O

Here O
the O
plague O
have O
reached O
full O
bloom O
; O
illnesses B-TER
, O
hunger B-TER
, O
and O
abuse B-TER
were O
all O
part O
of O
the O
daily O
regime O
. O

In O
the O
blocks B-TER
there O
was O
no O
light O
, O
water O
was O
not O
to O
be O
found O
in O
the O
whole O
camp B-TER
, O
and O
the O
people B-TER
had O
to O
go O
to O
the O
toilet O
in O
the O
streets O
between O
the O
barracks O
. O

Hundreds O
of O
corpses B-TER
lay O
on O
the O
streets O
, O
without O
being O
cleared O
away O
. O

Transports B-TER
arrived O
hourly O
. O

Because O
there O
was O
no O
space O
, O
the O
old O
prisoners B-TER
were O
sent O
to O
the O
crematorium B-TER
. O

There O
was O
daily O
selections B-TER
, O
which O
the O
camp B-TER
leaders I-TER
( O
SS B-TER
- I-TER
Obersturmführer I-TER
Müller B-PER
und O
Frau O
Marie B-PER
Mandel I-PER
) O
carried O
out O
with O
the O
camp B-TER
doctor I-TER
Dr. O
Rohde O
( O
SS B-TER
- I-TER
Obersturmführer I-TER
) O
and O
ended O
with O
a O
balance O
of O
least O
400 O
to O
600 O
human O
lives B-TER
. O

On O
21.9.1942 O
, O
office O
workers O
were O
being O
looked O
for O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

Me O
and O
about O
nine O
of O
the O
female B-TER
prisoners I-TER
made O
themselves O
known O
. O

We O
were O
tested O
in O
the O
German O
language O
and O
sent O
over O
to O
the O
political B-TER
department I-TER
of O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

Here O
in O
the O
office O
, O
the O
motto O
was O
silence O
. O

At O
the O
beginning O
of O
our O
work O
there O
we O
were O
made O
aware O
, O
that O
if O
we O
said O
a O
word O
about O
the O
work O
done O
in O
the O
office O
of O
the O
camp B-TER
, O
then O
we O
would O
have O
to O
pay B-TER
for I-TER
this I-TER
with I-TER
our I-TER
lives I-TER
. O

This O
department B-TER
was O
actually O
nothing O
different O
than O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
. O

For O
example O
, O
the O
name O
of O
anybody O
who O
entered O
the O
camp B-TER
, O
normal O
cases O
of O
death B-TER
, O
those O
male B-TER
and O
female B-TER
prisoners I-TER
who O
were O
on O
a O
list O
for O
the O
crematorium B-TER
. O

Post O
that O
was O
meant O
for O
the O
individual O
prisoners B-TER
was O
registered O
and O
distributed O
. O

Investigations B-TER
of O
any O
sort O
, O
for O
example O
, O
interrogations B-TER
in O
court O
cases O
, O
tax O
, O
investigations O
by O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
, O
all O
carried O
out O
here O
and O
noted O
in O
the O
files O
. O

These O
investigations O
were O
carried O
out O
by O
individual O
SS B-TER
members I-TER
in O
the O
political B-TER
department I-TER
, O
which O
was O
under O
the O
jurisdiction O
of O
the O
camp B-TER
commandant I-TER
. O

The O
leading O
figures O
of O
the O
Kommandantur B-TER
where O
Höss B-PER
, O
Baer B-PER
and O
later O
Liebehenschel B-PER
, O
the O
leader O
of O
the O
political B-TER
department I-TER
was O
SS B-TER
- I-TER
Untersturmführer I-TER
Ernst B-PER
GRANNER I-PER
Head O
of O
the O
Political O
Department O
was O
Maximilian O
Grabner O
from O
Vienna O
. O

was O
from O
Vienna B-LOC
and O
his O
successor O
was O
SS B-TER
- I-TER
Untersturmführer I-TER
Schurz B-PER
, O
also O
from O
Vienna B-LOC
. O

The O
work B-TER
in O
this O
department B-TER
was O
divided O
amongst O
the O
SS B-TER
members I-TER
according O
to O
the O
circumstances O
. O

I O
worked B-TER
for O
a O
while O
in O
the O
registry O
, O
where O
all O
deaths B-TER
certified O
by O
a O
doctor B-TER
were O
recorded O
in O
the O
files O
. O

These O
files O
were O
then O
forwarded O
to O
the O
registry O
office O
for O
further O
processing O
, O
for O
a O
certificate O
to O
be O
produced O
and O
for O
family O
members O
to O
be O
informed O
, O
and O
forwarded O
to O
the O
Reich B-ORG
Security I-ORG
Headquarters I-ORG
in O
Berlin B-LOC
. O

Such O
notificaions O
were O
not O
sent O
to O
the O
family O
members O
of O
Jewish O
prisoners B-TER
. O

The O
head O
of O
this O
registry O
office O
was O
SS B-TER
- I-TER
Hauptscharführer I-TER
Karatensen B-PER
( O
from O
Stuttgart B-LOC
or O
Mannheim B-LOC
) O
. O

The O
terror O
of O
the O
camp B-TER
overall O
, O
was O
SS B-TER
- I-TER
Oberscharführer I-TER
Willy B-PER
Boger I-PER
, O
from O
Stuttgart B-LOC
, O
head O
of O
the O
escape B-TER
department O
. O

He O
butchered B-TER
in O
cold O
blood O
those O
prisoners B-TER
who O
had O
fled B-TER
and O
been O
caught O
when O
they O
tried O
to O
defend O
themselves O
with O
a O
lie O
, O
about O
why O
they O
are O
tried O
to O
escape B-TER
. O

It O
was O
common O
, O
such O
prisoners B-TER
were O
locked O
immediately O
in O
the O
bunker B-TER
, O
and O
after O
several O
days O
, O
on O
Boger B-PER
’s O
command O
, O
that O
they O
would O
be O
beaten O
to O
death B-TER
. O

Afterwards O
, O
the O
political B-TER
department I-TER
would O
receive O
the O
message O
, O
that O
the O
prisoner B-TER
in O
question O
had O
died B-TER
from O
some O
disease B-TER
or O
another O
. O

Usually O
, O
the O
cause O
of O
death B-TER
was O
given O
as O
a O
lung O
infection O
or O
a O
heart O
attack O
. O

We O
were O
well O
aware O
of O
what O
this O
meant O
, O
but O
we O
had O
to O
keep O
our O
countenance O
. O

We O
heard O
it O
from O
him O
often O
, O
that O
he O
would O
make O
us O
ready O
for O
a O
happy O
ascension B-TER
to I-TER
heaven I-TER
, O
if O
we O
said O
a O
word O
about O
it O
. O

It O
was O
peculiarity O
of O
his O
, O
that O
Boger B-PER
made O
sure O
that O
his O
staff B-TER
received O
better O
food B-TER
and O
clothing B-TER
than O
others O
. O

He O
did O
n’t O
ask O
his O
typists B-TER
to O
be O
involved O
in O
the O
so O
- O
called O
secret O
service O
, O
because O
he O
did O
n’t O
trust O
them O
. O

There O
were O
60 O
women B-TER
prisoners I-TER
in O
our O
commando O
. O

One O
day O
, O
it O
became O
clear O
that O
several O
of O
us O
have O
not O
been O
adhering O
to O
the O
regulations O
laid O
out O
for O
the O
camp B-TER
at O
the O
office O
. O

Namely O
, O
documents O
about O
certifications O
had O
been O
found O
in O
the O
corridor O
. O

Because O
none O
of O
us O
would O
say O
from O
whom O
they O
came O
, O
eight O
of O
the O
staff B-TER
in O
the O
office O
were O
fired O
and O
sent O
immediately O
back O
to O
Birkenau B-LOC
. O

This O
happened O
by O
order O
of O
the O
head O
of O
personnel O
, O
SS B-TER
- I-TER
Oberscharführer I-TER
Robert B-PER
Kirschner I-PER
Hermann O
Kirschner O
. O

In O
the O
first O
week O
of O
this O
hard O
labour B-TER
outside I-TER
, O
the O
eight O
female B-TER
prisoners I-TER
were O
ill B-TER
and O
brought O
to O
the O
Revier B-TER
. O

After O
they O
had O
recovered O
, O
one O
of O
the O
prisoners B-TER
managed O
to O
be O
assigned O
to O
an O
agricultural B-TER
commando O
. O

There O
she O
met O
a O
male B-TER
prisoner I-TER
, O
with O
whom O
she O
exchanged O
letters B-TER
for O
a O
long O
time O
. O

Personal O
discussions O
were O
completely O
forbidden O
at O
this O
time O
, O
and O
came O
with O
great O
personal O
danger O
. O

One O
day O
, O
one O
of O
the O
women B-TER
’s O
commandos O
was O
returning O
from O
work B-TER
. O

On O
the O
way O
, O
they O
met O
a O
men B-TER
’s O
commando O
. O

One O
of O
the O
female B-TER
prisoners I-TER
took O
the O
opportunity O
to O
give O
a O
passing O
male B-TER
prisoner I-TER
a O
letter B-TER
. O

This O
was O
noticed O
by O
a O
member B-TER
of I-TER
the I-TER
SS I-TER
and O
immediately O
reported O
to O
the O
political B-TER
department I-TER
. O

After O
a O
long O
interrogation B-TER
of O
the O
female O
prisoner O
, O
they O
were O
unable O
to O
find O
out O
, O
for O
which O
man B-TER
the O
letter B-TER
was O
intended O
. O

She O
was O
abused O
and O
locked O
in O
the O
prison B-TER
. O

And O
then O
suddenly O
, O
we O
received O
a O
notice O
of O
her O
death B-TER
, O
that O
the O
prisoner B-TER
had O
died B-TER
from O
lung O
infection O
whilst O
under O
camp O
arrest O
. O

The O
letter B-TER
was O
even O
by O
the O
camp B-TER
standards O
completely O
trivial O
, O
she O
wrote O
when O
will O
there O
be O
a O
time O
when O
we O
can O
say O
anything O
we O
want O
and O
nobody O
will O
stand O
in O
our O
way O
? O
. O

Such O
cases O
happened O
almost O
daily O
, O
first O
the O
prisoner B-TER
would O
be O
abused O
and O
then O
shot B-TER
, O
or O
even O
sent O
to O
the O
crematorium B-TER
alive O
. O

It O
sounds O
perhaps O
unbelievable O
, O
when O
I O
write O
down O
the O
individual O
things O
that O
happened O
during O
the O
months O
that O
I O
worked B-TER
in O
the O
office O
. O

We O
experienced O
some O
incredible O
things O
, O
for O
example O
: O
at O
the O
beginning O
of O
the O
month O
, O
always O
on O
a O
Thursday O
, O
purges O
were O
done O
in O
the O
camp O
prison B-TER
. O

With O
a O
degree O
of O
delight O
, O
the O
SS B-TER
members I-TER
of O
the O
individual O
departments O
from O
our O
political B-TER
department I-TER
went O
to O
the O
camp O
prison B-TER
and O
shot B-TER
the O
individual O
prisoner B-TER
s O
that O
they O
did O
not O
like O
. O

Naturally O
, O
they O
would O
drink O
afterwards O
and O
end O
the O
day O
with O
celebrations O
. O

SS B-TER
- I-TER
Rottenführer I-TER
Perry B-PER
Broad I-PER
from O
Berlin B-LOC
- I-LOC
Spandau I-LOC
, O
Jordanstrasse B-LOC
No O
. O

84 O
, O
Rottenführer B-TER
Kaufmann B-PER
from O
Ljubljana B-LOC
, O
Unterscharführer B-TER
Kristan B-PER
, O
Oscha B-TER
Kirschner B-PER
, O
Boger B-PER
, O
Kamphuis B-PER
. O

The O
addresses O
of O
some O
of O
them O
I O
ca O
n’t O
remember O
anymore O
. O

In O
1943 O
- O
06 O
, O
six O
male O
Polish B-LOC
prisoners B-TER
working O
in O
a O
surveying O
commando O
were O
able O
to O
escape B-TER
from O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

They O
were O
not O
recaptured O
. O

By O
way O
of O
reprisal O
, O
SS B-TER
- I-TER
Unterscharführer I-TER
Gerhard B-PER
Lachmann I-PER
aus O
Niederstreslitz B-LOC
9 O
chose O
nine O
Polish B-LOC
in O
intellectuals O
as O
prisoners B-TER
and O
on O
the O
30th O
August O
1943 O
, O
had O
them O
publicly O
hanged B-TER
in O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

Such O
cases O
were O
repeated O
often O
. O

And O
so O
, O
you O
were O
never O
sure O
whether O
you O
might O
be O
taken O
for O
reprisal O
, O
if O
you O
did O
n’t O
already O
fall O
under O
the O
selected O
prisoners B-TER
. O

SS B-TER
- I-TER
Oberscharführer I-TER
Lachmann B-PER
collaborated O
with O
the O
secret O
service O
within O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
. O

Prisoners B-TER
, O
particularly O
in O
the O
men B-TER
’s I-TER
camp I-TER
, O
smuggled B-TER
letters B-TER
and O
other O
things O
out O
of O
the O
camp B-TER
with O
the O
help O
of O
civilians O
. O

Lachmann B-PER
was O
a O
small O
, O
thin O
man O
and O
looked O
very O
pale O
, O
he O
would O
often O
put O
on O
the O
prisoner B-TER
clothing O
, O
go O
into O
the O
camp B-TER
and O
spend O
the O
night O
there O
, O
in O
order O
to O
hear O
from O
prisoners B-TER
who O
did O
n’t O
recognise O
him O
what O
was O
going O
on O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

After O
such O
undercover O
work O
, O
there O
are O
always O
many O
prisoners B-TER
who O
would O
be O
doomed O
to O
death B-TER
. O

SS B-TER
Uscha I-TER
Otto B-PER
Schmidt I-PER
issued O
death B-TER
sentences O
without O
substantial O
investigations B-TER
. O

As O
the O
second O
and O
neighbouring O
camp B-TER
of O
Auschwitz B-LOC
, O
Birkenau B-LOC
was O
known O
as O
Camp B-LOC
II I-LOC
. O

SS B-TER
- I-TER
Obersturmführer I-TER
Kramer B-PER
was O
the O
commandant B-TER
of O
this O
camp B-TER
. O

The O
head O
of O
the O
camp B-TER
was O
SS B-TER
- I-TER
Obersturmführer I-TER
Schwarzhuber B-PER
. O

They O
lead O
the O
selections B-TER
in O
the O
camp B-TER
, O
along O
with O
the O
camp B-TER
doctor I-TER
and O
together O
with O
the O
camp B-TER
supervisors I-TER
. O

In O
the O
years O
1942 O
to O
1945 O
, O
the O
camp B-TER
doctors I-TER
in O
Auschwitz B-LOC
were O
: O
Dr. O
Josef B-PER
Mengele I-PER
, O
Dr. O
Entress B-PER
, O
Dr. O
Rohde B-PER
, O
Dr. O
Wirths B-PER
, O
Dr. O
Thilo B-PER
, O
amongst O
others O
. O

These O
led O
in O
the O
most O
terrible O
and O
infamous O
way O
the O
selections B-TER
in O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

It O
is O
well O
known O
from O
several O
sources O
, O
that O
in O
Auschwitz B-LOC
there O
was O
a O
special O
experimentation B-TER
block I-TER
. O

This O
block O
was O
solely O
occupied O
by O
Greek B-LOC
, O
Polish B-LOC
, O
and O
Belgian B-LOC
female B-TER
Jews O
. O

The O
head B-TER
doctor I-TER
was O
Dr O
Wirths B-PER
. O

Based O
on O
different O
pieces O
of O
correspondence B-TER
in O
our O
office O
, O
it O
was O
clear O
that O
the O
block O
was O
supervised O
Prof O
Clauberg B-PER
in O
Königshütte B-LOC
near O
Kattowitz B-LOC
, O
who O
ran O
a O
sanatorium O
there O
. O

He O
wanted O
to O
develop O
a O
serum O
for O
fertilisation O
and O
sterilisation B-TER
, O
and O
in O
order O
to O
do O
so O
, O
experiments B-TER
were O
carried O
out O
on O
individual O
prisoners B-TER
who O
were O
accommodated O
in O
this O
block O
. O

In O
the O
crematorium B-TER
, O
the O
work B-TER
was O
solely O
carried O
out O
by O
Jews O
under O
the O
supervision O
of O
SS B-TER
members I-TER
, O
such O
as O
SS B-TER
- I-TER
Uscha I-TER
Seitz B-PER
, O
Georgen B-PER
, O
Erber B-PER
, O
Mokrus B-PER
, O
Schillinger B-PER
and O
others O
. O

Schillinger B-PER
was O
shot B-TER
by O
a O
female B-TER
prisoner I-TER
, O
who O
had O
only O
just O
arrived O
at O
the O
camp B-TER
, O
with O
his O
own O
pistol O
. O

The O
men B-TER
’s I-TER
camp I-TER
in O
Auschwitz B-LOC
was O
under O
the O
command B-TER
of O
SS B-TER
- I-TER
Obersturmführer I-TER
Max B-PER
Sell I-PER
, O
a O
master O
tailor O
from O
Berlin B-LOC
. O

He O
was O
a O
monster O
in O
human O
form O
. O

He O
could O
n’t O
stand O
either O
the O
smiling O
or O
the O
crying O
of O
a O
prisoner B-TER
. O

The O
abuse O
of O
prisoners B-TER
was O
a O
delight O
to O
him O
. O

Sell B-PER
found O
his O
equal O
in O
the O
form O
of O
SS B-TER
- I-TER
Obersturmführer I-TER
Rössler B-PER
. O

He O
was O
the O
head B-TER
of O
the O
women B-TER
’s I-TER
camp I-TER
. O

His O
subordinate O
, O
the O
female B-TER
guard I-TER
Drechsler B-PER
, O
carried O
out O
all O
of O
his O
commands O
and O
wishes O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
as O
quickly O
as O
possible O
. O

So O
, O
for O
example O
, O
searches O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
to O
find O
out O
whether O
a O
prisoner B-TER
has O
a O
piece B-TER
of I-TER
clothing I-TER
that O
the O
camp B-TER
leadership I-TER
considered O
excessive O
. O

Cooking O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
was O
one O
of O
the O
major O
crimes O
. O

This O
was O
punished O
with O
your O
hair O
being O
cut O
off O
, O
being O
put O
in O
the O
bunker B-TER
, O
denied B-TER
food I-TER
and O
even O
24 O
hours O
of O
standing O
. O

In O
the O
beginning O
, O
there O
was O
also O
a O
stake O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
, O
and O
30 O
to O
60 O
minutes O
at O
this O
stake O
were O
given O
as O
a O
punishment O
. O

In O
1943 O
, O
in O
July O
or O
thereabouts O
, O
this O
was O
abolished O
. O

A O
memo O
in O
the O
file O
about O
punishment O
at O
the O
stake O
was O
destroyed O
. O

As O
a O
result O
of O
this O
, O
we O
had O
to O
go O
and O
re O
- O
write O
thousands O
of O
files O
which O
contained O
such O
memos O
. O

Another O
toy O
that O
was O
used O
as O
a O
deterrent O
and O
to O
which O
prisoners B-TER
and O
civil O
workers O
both O
fell O
victim O
, O
was O
something O
that O
was O
known O
as O
the O
swing O
. O

It O
was O
a O
wooden O
contraption O
, O
to O
which O
iron O
bars O
were O
attached O
. O

The O
prisoner B-TER
that O
was O
to O
be O
the O
victim O
, O
was O
bound O
to O
the O
swing O
by O
their O
hands O
and O
feet O
and O
spun O
around O
. O

On O
both O
sides O
of O
the O
swing O
, O
SS B-TER
members I-TER
stood O
and O
would O
hit O
and O
kick O
and O
abuse O
the O
prisoner B-TER
as O
they O
were O
twisted O
. O

It O
often O
happened O
, O
that O
the O
victim O
remained O
unconscious O
. O

Blood O
stains O
and O
any O
other O
traces O
were O
often O
immediately O
cleaned O
away O
so O
that O
they O
would O
n’t O
be O
noticed O
by O
other O
prisoner B-TER
s O
when O
they O
entered O
the O
room O
for O
their O
interrogation B-TER
. O

One O
such O
swing O
was O
installed O
in O
the O
office O
– O
in O
the O
interrogation B-TER
room I-TER
– O
where O
I O
worked B-TER
. O

At O
such O
performances O
, O
I O
was O
observed O
to O
see O
what O
faces O
I O
made O
. O

Such O
things O
occurred O
almost O
daily O
. O

My O
nerves O
had O
reached O
the O
point O
that O
I O
’ve O
become O
quite O
mechanical O
, O
like O
a O
machine O
. O

Sleepless O
nights O
, O
illness B-TER
and O
tiredness O
were O
written O
large O
across O
my O
face O
. O

After O
several O
months O
, O
the O
SS B-TER
clerk O
Rottenführer B-TER
Perry B-PER
Broad I-PER
was O
transferred O
to O
another O
department O
and O
I O
was O
assigned O
to O
him O
again O
. O

Now O
it O
was O
a O
little O
bit O
easier O
. O

The O
abuses O
no O
longer O
took O
place O
right O
in O
front O
of O
my O
eyes O
. O

January O
1944 O
, O
I O
was O
once O
again O
in O
Birkenau B-LOC
, O
in O
the O
so O
- O
called O
gypsy B-TER
camp I-TER
. O

Here O
they O
were O
only O
German B-LOC
, O
Czech B-LOC
, O
and O
Polish B-LOC
gypsies B-TER
. O

At O
the O
beginning O
, O
there O
was O
roughly O
20,000 O
. O

Illness B-TER
and O
disease B-TER
in O
the O
camp B-TER
meant O
that O
after O
barely O
six O
months O
, O
the O
reduction O
by O
more O
than O
10,000 O
was O
noticeable O
. O

In O
spring O
1944 O
, O
the O
Hungarian B-LOC
Jews O
were O
brought O
to O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

Between O
15 O
and O
20,000 O
arrived O
daily O
. O

The O
crematorium B-TER
– O
there O
was O
four O
of O
them O
– O
could O
n’t O
keep O
up O
with O
the O
rapid O
burning O
of O
these O
victims O
and O
so O
between O
the O
third O
and O
fourth O
crematorium B-TER
, O
ditches O
were O
dug O
, O
and O
fires O
were O
set O
in O
them O
. O

The O
crematoria B-TER
were O
located O
in O
a O
wasteland O
, O
that O
was O
called O
the O
woods O
. O

Giant O
flames O
could O
be O
seen O
from O
far O
away O
. O

The O
smoke O
was O
such O
that O
for O
the O
whole O
of O
summer O
it O
was O
enough O
to O
almost O
suffocate O
. O

One O
morning O
, O
as O
I O
was O
on O
the O
way O
to O
work B-TER
, O
I O
noticed O
that O
there O
was O
a O
mass O
of O
people B-TER
gathered O
by O
our O
office O
block O
, O
which O
was O
located O
outside O
of O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

In O
that O
moment O
, O
I O
did O
n’t O
know O
what O
it O
meant O
. O

It O
was O
old O
people B-TER
, O
mothers B-TER
with O
children B-TER
in O
their O
arms O
. O

They O
were O
praying O
, O
because O
they O
had O
understood O
everything O
that O
stood O
before O
then O
. O

The O
crematorium B-TER
was O
only O
another O
hundred O
steps O
away O
. O

And O
soon O
it O
meant O
for O
the O
people B-TER
who O
are O
waiting O
, O
that O
it O
was O
their O
turn O
. O

After O
several O
minutes O
, O
from O
this O
mass O
of O
around O
300 O
people B-TER
, O
there O
was O
only O
clouds O
of O
smoke O
to O
be O
seen O
. O

This O
went O
on O
for O
the O
whole O
summer O
, O
even O
into O
late O
1944 O
of O
1944 O
, O
when O
in O
crematorium B-TER
three O
there O
was O
an O
uprising B-TER
and O
mass B-TER
escape I-TER
planned O
. O

It O
was O
a O
sunny O
evening O
in O
September O
, O
and O
we O
heard O
break O
a O
lot O
of O
noise O
coming O
from O
the O
camp B-TER
around O
midday O
. O

Crematorium B-TER
three O
have O
been O
set O
on O
fire O
. O

People B-TER
were O
sent O
back O
to O
the O
blocks O
ordered O
by O
the O
SS B-TER
and O
were O
not O
allowed O
to O
leave O
. O

After O
roughly O
an O
hour O
, O
the O
fire O
was O
brought O
under O
control O
. O

A O
report O
was O
written O
immediately O
by O
us O
in O
the O
office O
. O

I O
learnt O
that O
a O
mass B-TER
escape I-TER
had O
occurred O
. O

Namely O
, O
that O
all O
of O
the O
prisoners B-TER
who O
worked B-TER
in O
crematoria B-TER
2 O
and O
3 O
that O
escaped B-TER
. O

Before O
they O
blew O
up O
the O
crematorium B-TER
and O
escaped B-TER
, O
they O
had O
done O
a O
purge O
of O
the O
commando O
. O

As O
their O
leader O
– O
the O
so O
- O
called O
Capo B-TER
– O
the O
Jewish O
prisoners B-TER
had O
had O
an O
ethnic O
German O
prisoner B-TER
. O

He O
had O
spied O
on O
them O
for O
the O
SS B-TER
. O

In O
order O
to O
make O
sure O
that O
they O
were O
able O
to O
escape B-TER
and O
to O
blow O
up O
the O
crematoria B-TER
, O
they O
pushed O
him O
into O
the O
fire O
. O

Roughly O
two O
hours O
after O
the O
successful O
escape B-TER
, O
all O
of O
the O
prisoners B-TER
have O
been O
recaptured O
. O

SS B-TER
- I-TER
Oberscharführer I-TER
Erber B-PER
– I-PER
Heustek I-PER
, O
who O
had O
the O
Czech B-LOC
background O
, O
carried O
out O
a O
heroic O
act O
, O
in O
that O
, O
with O
the O
help O
of O
SS B-TER
- I-TER
Unterscharführer I-TER
Wurm O
und O
SS.-Uscha B-TER
Wunsch O
– O
both O
of O
whom O
came O
from O
Vienna B-LOC
– O
shot B-TER
and O
killed B-TER
279 O
prisoners B-TER
in O
front O
of O
crematorium B-TER
2 O
and O
450 O
prisoners B-TER
from O
crematorium B-TER
3 O
. O

We O
had O
a O
death B-TER
notice O
for O
over O
729 O
prisoners B-TER
who O
had O
been O
shot B-TER
trying O
to O
escape B-TER
. O

After O
about O
four O
weeks O
, O
by O
way O
of O
deterrence O
, O
a O
further O
100 O
prisoners B-TER
from O
the O
commando O
in O
crematorium B-TER
1 O
and O
4 O
were O
punished O
with O
death B-TER
. O

In O
connection O
with O
the O
crematorium B-TER
, O
four O
female B-TER
prisoners I-TER
, O
Polish B-LOC
Jews B-TER
, O
were O
hanged B-TER
on O
30.12.1944 O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
and O
all O
camp B-TER
inhabitants I-TER
had O
to O
be O
present O
for O
the O
carrying O
out O
of O
the O
death B-TER
sentence I-TER
. O

The O
prisoners B-TER
had O
been O
working B-TER
in O
the O
ammunition O
factory B-TER
UNION O
. O

From O
there O
, O
they O
brought O
explosives O
and O
had O
smuggled B-TER
them O
into O
the O
men B-TER
’s I-TER
camp I-TER
as O
well O
as O
the O
crematoria B-TER
. O

During O
summer O
1944 O
, O
prisoners B-TER
also O
escaped B-TER
from O
camp B-LOC
2 I-LOC
. O

There O
was O
a O
Belgian B-LOC
female B-TER
Jew O
and O
a O
Pole B-LOC
. O

After O
roughly O
14 O
days O
, O
they O
were O
found O
near O
to O
Auschwitz B-LOC
as O
they O
were O
trying O
to O
travel O
away O
, O
caught O
and O
locked O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
jail I-TER
. O

After O
a O
long O
interrogation B-TER
and O
harassment O
, O
the O
prisoners B-TER
were O
supposed O
to O
be O
hanged B-TER
. O

The O
female B-TER
prisoner I-TER
was O
brought O
to O
the O
roll B-TER
call I-TER
in O
the O
camp B-TER
and O
because O
she O
knew O
that O
this O
was O
the O
day O
that O
the O
death B-TER
sentence I-TER
would O
be O
carried O
out O
, O
she O
slit O
her O
wrists O
by O
the O
gate O
to O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

This O
was O
noticed O
by O
SS B-TER
- I-TER
Unterscharführer I-TER
Ritters B-PER
. O

He O
jumped O
at O
her O
, O
and O
took O
the O
razor O
that O
she O
had O
in O
her O
hand O
away O
from O
her O
. O

As O
the O
razorblade O
was O
taken O
away O
by O
the O
SS B-TER
man I-TER
, O
the O
prisoner B-TER
was O
able O
to O
deal O
him O
several O
blows O
to O
the O
face O
. O

And O
so O
, O
the O
abuse O
of O
the O
prisoner B-TER
began O
again O
anew O
. O

She O
was O
forced O
along O
the O
camp B-TER
streets O
and O
beaten O
. O

Every O
prisoner B-TER
of O
the O
Jewish O
nation O
had O
to O
be O
present O
. O

After O
an O
hour O
of O
this O
wrestling O
with O
death B-TER
, O
the O
prisoner B-TER
was O
half O
- O
conscious O
and O
thrown O
into O
a O
box O
with O
wheels O
attached O
and O
transferred O
to O
the O
crematorium B-TER
. O

The O
male B-TER
prisoner I-TER
was O
hanged B-TER
at O
the O
same O
time O
in O
the O
men B-TER
’s I-TER
camp I-TER
. O

The O
reason O
behind O
his O
sentence O
was O
because O
together O
with O
a O
Jewish O
femaleprisoner O
he O
attempted O
to O
escape O
from O
the O
camp O
. O

Such O
cases O
repeated O
themselves O
during O
my O
time O
at O
the O
camp B-TER
quite O
often O
. O

Prisoners B-TER
were O
escaping B-TER
almost O
daily O
from O
the O
men B-TER
’s I-TER
camp I-TER
, O
particularly O
Polish B-LOC
and O
Russian B-LOC
prisoners B-TER
. O

When O
they O
were O
recaptured O
, O
they O
were O
hanged B-TER
or O
shot B-TER
in O
front O
of O
all O
the O
camp B-TER
inmates B-TER
. O

If O
a O
prisoner B-TER
was O
shot B-TER
during O
their O
escape B-TER
, O
the O
corpse B-TER
would O
be O
tied O
in O
a O
sitting O
position O
to O
a O
chair O
and O
all O
of O
the O
camp B-TER
inmates I-TER
had O
to O
march O
past O
. O

This O
was O
used O
as O
a O
deterrent O
. O

After O
all O
of O
these O
experiences O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
, O
we O
all O
became O
more O
and O
more O
numb O
. O

Here O
it O
was O
either O
bend O
or O
break O
. O

Our O
facial O
expressions O
were O
n’t O
like O
those O
of O
people O
living O
in O
freedom O
. O

Hunger B-TER
, O
fear O
for O
your O
own O
life O
, O
this O
made O
us O
animals O
without O
feeling O
. O

Our O
many O
experiences O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
, O
such O
as O
the O
selections B-TER
and O
other O
things O
during O
my O
almost O
3 O
years O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
, O
made O
us O
hard O
. O

Often O
, O
I O
had O
the O
feeling O
that O
I O
would O
never O
experience O
the O
free O
world O
again O
. O

Particularly O
those O
of O
us O
in O
my O
commando O
did O
n’t O
think O
about O
ever O
being O
free O
again O
. O

Our O
supervisors B-TER
comforted O
us O
by O
saying O
that O
if O
Germany B-TER
was O
victorious O
, O
that O
we O
would O
still O
have O
to O
stay O
in O
the O
Reich B-TER
, O
but O
that O
will O
be O
no O
longer O
concentrated O
, O
but O
rather O
obliged O
to O
work B-TER
. O

If O
Germany B-TER
were O
to O
lose O
the O
war B-TER
, O
that O
will O
be O
the O
end B-TER
of O
us O
. O

We O
were O
no O
longer O
informed O
about O
the O
political O
events O
in O
the O
world O
, O
because O
we O
only O
had O
very O
few O
chances O
to O
listen O
to O
illegal O
radio O
stations O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

This O
was O
also O
punishable O
by O
death B-TER
. O

And O
there O
were O
many O
such O
victims O
. O

Particularly O
Czechs B-LOC
and O
the O
Polish B-LOC
fell O
victim O
to O
this O
. O

This O
kind O
of O
illegal O
activity O
developed O
amongst O
the O
prisoners B-TER
in O
the O
neighbouring O
camp B-TER
Jaworzno B-LOC
. O

In O
this O
coal O
mine O
a O
tunnel O
was O
being O
built O
. O

Over O
1500 O
Czech B-LOC
prisoners B-TER
were O
involved O
in O
this O
work B-TER
. O

As O
there O
were O
also O
experts O
amongst O
them O
, O
they O
built O
themselves O
a O
smaller O
tunnel O
alongside O
the O
main O
one O
, O
which O
was O
supposed O
to O
be O
used O
by O
the O
prisoners B-TER
to O
escape B-TER
. O

When O
the O
work B-TER
was O
finished O
, O
the O
prisoners B-TER
– O
this O
was O
roughly O
in O
September O
1943 O
- O
were O
going O
to O
all O
leave O
the O
camp B-TER
one O
night O
. O

The O
escape B-TER
was O
well O
- O
planned O
and O
well O
prepared O
. O

However O
, O
amongst O
these O
prisoners B-TER
there O
was O
a O
Pole B-LOC
who O
knew O
what O
the O
Czechs B-LOC
had O
planned O
. O

He O
pretended O
that O
he O
planned O
to O
escape B-TER
with O
them O
and O
was O
able O
to O
find O
out O
when O
they O
planned O
their O
escape B-TER
. O

He O
reported O
this O
to O
the O
political B-TER
department I-TER
, O
who O
were O
able O
to O
prevent O
the O
escape B-TER
with O
guard O
posts O
. O

At O
the O
end O
of O
October O
1943 O
, O
32 O
Czech B-LOC
people B-TER
were O
shot B-TER
after O
a O
long O
period O
of O
torment O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

The O
Polish B-LOC
man O
had O
, O
through O
this O
betrayal O
, O
gathered O
some O
attention O
in O
our O
department O
, O
especially O
with O
SS B-TER
- I-TER
Unterscharführer I-TER
Schürz O
and O
SS B-TER
- I-TER
Uscha I-TER
Lachmann O
. O

He O
carried O
out O
his O
work O
as O
an O
informant O
quite O
openly O
, O
and O
was O
a O
very O
feared O
man O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

None O
of O
the O
prisoners B-TER
dared O
to O
remove O
him O
from O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

It O
was O
shortly O
before O
Christmas O
, O
that O
the O
Polish B-LOC
prisoner B-TER
came O
to O
SS B-TER
- I-TER
Uscha I-TER
Lachmann O
, O
who O
at O
this O
time O
I O
was O
working B-TER
at O
the O
typist O
for O
, O
and O
demanded O
$ O
100 O
, O
so O
that O
he O
could O
catch O
prisoners B-TER
and O
civilians O
smuggling B-TER
. O

He O
gave O
the O
prisoner B-TER
the O
hundred O
dollars O
that O
he O
demanded O
. O

The O
prisoner B-TER
also O
asked O
that O
he O
be O
accompanied O
by O
SS B-TER
- I-TER
Rottenführer I-TER
Jarosewitsch O
, O
as O
the O
place O
of O
exchange O
was O
outside O
of O
the O
cordon O
. O

The O
prisoner B-TER
left O
our O
office O
and O
said O
that O
he O
would O
report O
back O
that O
afternoon O
before O
roll B-TER
call I-TER
with O
the O
results O
. O

The O
whole O
commando O
returned O
from O
work B-TER
to O
the O
camp B-TER
, O
but O
I O
had O
to O
wait O
in O
the O
office O
as O
the O
prisoner B-TER
and O
the O
SS B-TER
man I-TER
Jarosewitz B-PER
had O
not O
reported O
back O
. O

I O
was O
frightened O
. O

The O
message O
came O
, O
that O
the O
Polish B-LOC
prisoner B-TER
, O
together O
with O
the O
Jewish O
prisoner B-TER
, O
accompanied O
by O
Jarosewitz B-PER
had O
escaped B-TER
. O

Jarosewitz B-PER
had O
been O
murdered B-TER
by O
them O
behind O
the O
large O
fence O
of O
the O
camp B-TER
. O

Telegrams O
and O
wanted O
posters O
followed O
, O
regarding O
the O
two O
escaped B-TER
prisoners B-TER
. O

Nothing O
was O
said O
in O
front O
of O
me O
in O
the O
office O
, O
but O
I O
used O
to O
get O
the O
post O
, O
from O
which O
I O
was O
able O
to O
glean O
the O
important O
facts O
. O

From O
that O
day O
on O
, O
prisoners B-TER
were O
only O
allowed O
to O
leave O
the O
camp B-TER
with O
two O
SS B-TER
members I-TER
present O
. O

There O
are O
many O
other O
things O
that O
happened O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
and O
in O
the O
office O
that O
I O
do O
n’t O
feel O
I O
'm O
able O
to O
write O
down O
at O
the O
moment O
. O

On O
the O
13.1.1945 O
, O
the O
evacuation B-TER
of O
the O
camp B-TER
began O
. O

After O
eight O
days O
of O
wandering O
around O
without O
aim O
, O
we O
arrived O
half O
- O
frozen O
, O
hungry B-TER
and O
tired O
at O
Ravensbrück B-LOC
. O

Here O
we O
spent O
our O
time O
without O
food B-TER
, O
in O
a O
tent B-TER
– O
1500 O
prisoners B-TER
– O
for O
over O
three O
weeks O
. O

After O
that O
we O
were O
sent O
to O
the O
neighbouring O
camp B-TER
in O
Malchow B-LOC
in O
Mecklenburg B-LOC
. O

The O
Auschwitz B-LOC
SS B-TER
monsters I-TER
were O
now O
for O
us O
a O
forgotten O
chapter O
. O

Now O
we O
had O
a O
new O
one O
, O
camp B-TER
commandant I-TER
, O
Luise B-PER
Danz I-PER
. O

Opsáno O
dle O
originálu O
. O

Dáno O
dokumentační B-TER
akci I-TER
k O
dispozici O
od O
pí O
. O

Reginy B-PER
Lebensfeldové I-PER
- I-PER
Hofstädterové I-PER
, O
Bratislava B-LOC
. O

