Committee O
to O
Collect O
Material O
about O
the O
Destruction O
of O
Polish B-LOC
Jewry O
1939 O
Y. O
M. O
Sh O
. O

Wyszków B-LOC
Age O
: O
15 O
years O
; O
living O
with O
his O
parents B-TER
Testimony O
number O
3 O
( O
recorded O
on O
the O
15th O
of O
November O
, O
1939 O
) O
A O
lot O
of O
airplanes O
started O
to O
fly O
over O
our O
town O
after O
the O
1st O
of O
September O
1939 O
. O

The O
next O
day O
we O
saw O
refugees B-TER
from O
Ostrołęka B-LOC
and O
Przasnysz B-LOC
. O

They O
reported O
that O
cannons O
were O
shooting O
there O
already O
. O

The O
refugees B-TER
came O
by O
car O
, O
bus O
and O
horse O
and O
wagon O
; O
all O
of O
them O
were O
Jews O
. O

On O
Saturday O
evening O
, O
after O
the O
evening O
prayers O
, O
airplanes O
dropped O
bombs O
for O
the O
first O
time O
. O

They O
fell O
in O
the O
river O
Bug B-LOC
. O

On O
Sunday O
, O
the O
3rd O
of O
September O
in O
the O
morning O
, O
a O
German B-TER
airplane O
landed O
near O
our O
town O
, O
in O
a O
village O
, O
I O
believe O
it O
was O
Somianka B-LOC
Uncertain O
. O

. O

People O
were O
saying O
that O
the O
plane O
had O
been O
damaged O
near O
Warsaw B-LOC
. O

The O
pilots O
, O
there O
were O
three O
of O
them O
, O
disappeared O
, O
and O
the O
subsequent O
searches O
for O
them O
were O
unsuccessful O
. O

The O
same O
day O
, O
a O
few O
refugees B-TER
arrived O
from O
Pułtusk B-LOC
. O

Airplanes O
flew O
over O
our O
town O
, O
but O
they O
did O
not O
drop O
any O
bombs O
. O

On O
Monday O
, O
the O
4th O
of O
September O
, O
a O
multitude O
of O
refugees B-TER
came O
through O
our O
town O
, O
on O
foot O
or O
by O
horse O
and O
wagon O
, O
Jews O
with O
their O
bundles O
of O
bedclothes O
, O
peasants O
and O
landowners O
with O
cattle O
and O
wagons O
. O

There O
were O
so O
many O
people O
that O
the O
entire O
town O
was O
crowded O
. O

They O
came O
from O
Ciechanów B-LOC
, O
Pułtusk B-LOC
and O
other O
places O
. O

Only O
some O
of O
them O
stayed O
in O
Wyszków B-LOC
for O
the O
night O
, O
the O
majority O
set O
out O
directly O
for O
Warsaw B-LOC
. O

On O
Monday O
in O
the O
evening O
, O
airplanes O
flew O
over O
the O
town O
, O
and O
dropped O
bombs O
in O
the O
vicinity O
. O

The O
stream O
of O
refugees B-TER
continued O
to O
pour O
in O
and O
it O
was O
really O
difficult O
to O
make O
one O
’s O
way O
through O
, O
even O
at O
night O
. O

In O
some O
houses O
, O
influenced O
by O
the O
stream O
of O
refugees B-TER
, O
people O
started O
to O
pack O
their O
belongings O
. O

In O
my O
parents B-TER
’ O
house O
, O
we O
had O
not O
started O
to O
pack O
our O
things O
yet O
. O

We O
went O
to O
sleep O
and O
slept O
through O
the O
night O
undisturbed O
. O

On O
Tuesday O
, O
the O
5th O
of O
September O
, O
I O
was O
woke O
up O
by O
the O
explosions O
of O
bombs O
, O
thrown O
by O
German B-TER
airplanes O
. O

There O
was O
an O
explosion O
on O
the O
corner O
of O
Pułtuska B-LOC
Street I-LOC
and O
Stodolna B-LOC
Street I-LOC
: O
five O
Jews O
were O
killed B-TER
; O
a O
barn O
containing O
oats O
caught O
fire O
and O
burned O
down O
. O

A O
bomb O
fell O
on O
the O
threshold O
of O
my O
uncle B-TER
Hershl B-PER
Shults I-PER
’s O
house O
on O
Pułtuska B-LOC
Street I-LOC
, O
but O
did O
not O
explode O
. O

But O
it O
broke O
the O
doorposts O
and O
window O
frames O
, O
so O
we O
carried O
everything O
out O
of O
his O
house O
. O

Nobody O
from O
my O
uncle B-TER
’s O
family B-TER
was O
harmed O
, O
but O
the O
owner O
of O
the O
house O
, O
Antoni B-PER
Zyskowski I-PER
, O
was O
wounded O
. O

There O
were O
attempts O
to O
extinguish O
the O
burning O
barn O
next O
to O
the O
house O
, O
but O
without O
result O
, O
because O
the O
firefighters O
could O
not O
manage O
the O
pumps O
. O

The O
airplanes O
continued O
to O
fly O
and O
inspired O
terror O
in O
the O
population O
. O

The O
German B-TER
airplanes O
dropped O
bombs O
all O
day O
long O
. O

They O
destroyed O
Nadgórze B-LOC
and O
Świętojańska B-LOC
Streets I-LOC
. O

The O
airplanes O
probably O
came O
then O
because O
on O
the O
same O
day O
, O
troops O
had O
appeared O
in O
our O
town O
and O
an O
anti O
- O
aircraft O
cannon O
had O
been O
placed O
in O
the O
middle O
of O
P.O.W. B-LOC
Square I-LOC
Probably O
Polska O
Organizacja O
Wojskowa O
. O

. O

Around O
3 O
p.m. O
a O
house O
was O
hit O
by O
a O
bomb O
on O
the O
corner O
of O
P.O.W. B-LOC
Square I-LOC
and O
Piłsudski B-LOC
Street I-LOC
( O
Ostrów B-LOC
Street I-LOC
) O
. O

About O
50 O
persons O
were O
buried O
under O
the O
ruins O
. O

Among O
those O
who O
were O
killed B-TER
were O
the O
wife B-TER
of O
Leybl B-PER
Levin I-PER
( O
a O
coachman O
) O
and O
his O
three O
small O
children B-TER
. O

A O
certain O
number O
of O
people O
were O
successfully O
rescued O
. O

People O
hid B-TER
in O
cellars B-TER
, O
for O
fear O
of O
the O
airplanes O
. O

Other O
escaped B-TER
in O
the O
directions O
of O
Węgrów B-LOC
and O
Warsaw B-LOC
. O

Both O
Christians B-TER
and O
Jews O
were O
running B-TER
away I-TER
. O

There O
were O
no O
policemen B-TER
any O
more O
, O
apparently O
they O
disappeared O
the O
same O
day O
. O

The O
relationship O
between O
Christians B-TER
and O
Jews O
was O
very O
good O
. O

People O
were O
helping O
each O
other O
. O

Tuesday O
in O
the O
evening O
we O
did O
not O
get O
undressed B-TER
for O
the O
night O
. O

We O
discussed O
to O
where O
to O
escape B-TER
. O

We O
decided O
to O
run B-TER
to I-TER
the O
village O
of O
Sieczychy B-LOC
( O
18 O
km O
from O
Wyszków B-LOC
) O
, O
where O
some O
Germans B-TER
were O
living O
, O
our O
customers O
. O

We O
believed O
that O
nothing O
would O
happen O
in O
a O
place O
where O
Germans B-TER
were O
living O
. O

But O
on O
Wednesday O
we O
did O
not O
manage O
to O
escape B-TER
to O
Sieczychy B-LOC
, O
because O
in O
our O
family B-TER
there O
are O
small O
children B-TER
, O
six O
months O
old O
. O

So O
on O
Wednesday O
, O
the O
6th O
of O
September O
, O
we O
escaped B-TER
to O
Natalin B-LOC
, O
to O
the O
forest O
. O

We O
stayed O
in O
the O
forest O
the O
whole O
day O
, O
for O
fear O
of O
the O
airplanes O
. O

All O
day O
long O
, O
we O
had O
nothing O
to O
eat B-TER
or O
to O
drink O
. O

We O
were O
afraid O
to O
go O
out O
of O
the O
forest O
because O
next O
to O
it O
there O
was O
a O
railroad O
that O
was O
constantly O
being O
bombed O
by O
German B-TER
airplanes O
. O

In O
the O
evening O
, O
we O
decided O
to O
return O
to O
town O
. O

We O
arrived O
in O
town O
around O
12 O
or O
12:30 O
a.m. O
Some O
buildings O
were O
still O
burning O
. O

We O
saw O
flashes O
and O
heard O
cannonfire O
, O
a O
sign O
that O
the O
front O
was O
already O
near O
. O

We O
were O
told O
that O
except O
for O
the O
high O
school O
building O
, O
nothing O
else O
had O
been O
destroyed O
. O

On O
Thursday O
, O
the O
7th O
of O
September O
, O
the O
street O
was O
empty O
. O

Only O
the O
refugees B-TER
and O
Polish B-LOC
troops O
were O
hurrying O
through O
toward O
the O
bridge O
on O
the O
Bug B-LOC
. O

The O
German B-TER
airplanes O
continued O
to O
drop O
bombs O
. O

Around O
3 O
p.m. O
Szkolna B-LOC
and O
Chopin B-LOC
Streets I-LOC
Fryderyk O
started O
to O
burn O
. O

The O
fire O
lasted O
until O
the O
evening O
. O

We O
came O
out O
from O
our O
hiding B-TER
place I-TER
, O
because O
the O
fire O
was O
already O
threatening O
us O
. O

We O
tried O
everything O
to O
prevent O
the O
fire O
from O
progressing O
. O

The O
first O
row O
of O
houses O
on O
Wąska B-LOC
Street I-LOC
were O
rescued O
. O

The O
other O
houses O
, O
on O
Szkolna B-LOC
and O
Chopin B-LOC
Streets I-LOC
, O
burned O
down O
. O

On O
the O
same O
day O
, O
around O
3 O
p.m. O
, O
a O
bomb O
hit O
the O
butcher O
shops O
and O
destroyed O
a O
wall O
of O
Leybl B-PER
Przytycki I-PER
’s O
shop O
on O
Kościuszko B-LOC
street I-LOC
. O

There O
was O
soda O
- O
water O
, O
kvass O
and O
beer O
there O
. O

Shortly O
afterwards O
, O
the O
Polish B-LOC
soldiers B-TER
robbed O
the O
shop O
and O
drank O
everything O
up O
. O

Polish B-LOC
soldiers B-TER
were O
also O
in O
our O
courtyard O
, O
slipping O
along O
the O
walls O
, O
and O
shooting O
with O
their O
guns O
at O
German B-TER
airplanes O
. O

Therefore O
we O
were O
very O
scared O
that O
the O
Germans B-TER
would O
drop O
bombs O
on O
our O
house O
. O

At O
12 O
a.m. O
we O
consulted O
the O
Polish B-TER
officers O
about O
what O
to O
do O
. O

They O
advised O
us O
to O
escape B-TER
with O
the O
army B-TER
. O

They O
told O
us O
that O
on O
Friday O
morning O
both O
bridges O
would O
be O
blown O
up O
and O
afterwards O
it O
would O
be O
impossible O
to O
run B-TER
away I-TER
. O

But O
one O
of O
our O
acquaintances O
, O
a O
Jewish B-TER
soldier I-TER
from O
Wyszków B-LOC
, O
advised O
us O
to O
stay O
, O
because O
of O
our O
small O
children B-TER
. O

So O
we O
stayed O
. O

At O
night O
we O
cooked O
a O
meal B-TER
, O
because O
during O
the O
day O
it O
was O
impossible O
to O
do O
anything O
. O

We O
did O
not O
go O
to O
sleep O
. O

Throughout O
the O
whole O
night O
, O
Polish B-LOC
troops O
marched O
through O
, O
in O
such O
a O
dense O
throng O
that O
we O
could O
not O
make O
our O
way O
through O
them O
to O
get O
to O
the O
pump O
at O
the O
market B-LOC
square I-LOC
to O
get O
some O
water O
. O

On O
Friday O
, O
the O
8th O
of O
September O
, O
the O
German B-TER
airplanes O
continued O
to O
drop O
bombs O
. O

There O
were O
not O
many O
Polish B-LOC
troops O
left O
. O

Soldiers B-TER
drove O
through O
only O
rarely O
on O
the O
roads O
from O
Ostrów B-LOC
Mazowiecka I-LOC
and O
Pułtusk B-LOC
. O

There O
were O
no O
more O
civilian O
refugees B-TER
. O

No O
more O
bombs O
were O
fallings O
in O
town O
anymore O
. O

Only O
a O
few O
Polish B-LOC
soldiers B-TER
remained O
. O

The O
retreating O
army B-TER
blew O
up O
Elye B-PER
- I-PER
Meyer I-PER
Goldman I-PER
’s O
bakery O
; O
the O
population O
was O
told O
to O
take O
the O
flour O
, O
in O
order O
not O
to O
leave O
it O
to O
the O
Germans B-TER
. O

Mainly O
Jews O
were O
left O
in O
town O
, O
and O
they O
took O
the O
flour O
. O

The O
Poles B-LOC
had O
apparently O
already O
escaped B-TER
, O
because O
we O
did O
not O
see O
any O
. O

German B-TER
airplanes O
flew O
quite O
low O
, O
but O
they O
did O
not O
shoot O
. O

We O
did O
not O
run O
away O
from O
them O
, O
because O
we O
believed O
that O
after O
the O
Poles B-LOC
had O
left O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
would O
not O
shoot O
any O
more O
. O

Until O
4 O
p.m. O
it O
was O
calm O
. O

Around O
4 O
o’clock O
, O
the O
sound O
of O
violent O
shooting O
was O
heard O
. O

Apparently O
the O
bridges O
were O
being O
blown O
up O
. O

We O
crept O
into O
our O
homes O
. O

Around O
5 O
o’clock O
a O
small O
house O
on O
the O
corner O
of O
Wąska B-LOC
and O
Szkolna B-LOC
Streets I-LOC
caught O
fire O
. O

I O
and O
some O
other O
Jews O
ran O
over O
to O
help O
. O

But O
the O
German B-TER
artillery O
opened O
fire O
right O
then O
, O
so O
we O
dispersed O
and O
ran O
to O
hide B-TER
in O
the O
prayer B-TER
house I-TER
. O

The O
right O
side O
of O
the O
market B-LOC
square I-LOC
caught O
fire O
. O

All O
the O
people O
gathered O
in O
the O
courtyard O
of O
the O
prayer B-TER
house I-TER
and O
descended O
[ O
the O
stairs O
] O
to O
the O
ritual B-TER
bath I-TER
. O

It O
was O
impossible O
to O
enter O
the O
prayer B-TER
house I-TER
, O
because O
in O
the O
Talmud B-TER
- I-TER
Torah I-TER
classroom O
inside O
lay O
10 O
- O
15 O
corpses B-TER
, O
people O
who O
had O
perished B-TER
over O
the O
course O
of O
a O
couple O
of O
days O
, O
whom O
it O
had O
not O
yet O
been O
possible O
to O
bury B-TER
in O
the O
Jewish B-TER
cemetery I-TER
. O

There O
was O
an O
unbearable O
smell O
there O
. O

There O
was O
a O
loud O
lament O
in O
the O
prayer B-TER
house I-TER
– O
women B-TER
were O
crying O
, O
men B-TER
were O
saying O
the O
deathbed B-TER
confessional O
prayers B-TER
. O

The O
shooting O
lasted O
from O
5 O
p.m. O
until O
around O
2 O
a.m. O
A O
German B-TER
scout O
, O
alone O
on O
a O
horse O
, O
arrived O
in O
town O
and O
stopped O
on O
the O
corner O
of O
Kościuszko B-LOC
and O
Wąska B-LOC
Streets I-LOC
, O
by O
the O
police B-TER
station O
. O

That O
was O
around O
10 O
p.m. O
We O
looked O
out O
through O
a O
crack O
[ O
in O
the O
shutter O
] O
, O
and O
by O
the O
light O
of O
the O
conflagration O
we O
saw O
the O
German B-TER
. O

Around O
2 O
a.m. O
it O
became O
calmer O
and O
we O
ran O
, O
keeping O
close O
to O
the O
walls O
, O
to O
our O
house O
, O
which O
was O
still O
undamaged O
. O

In O
the O
middle O
of O
the O
night O
my O
father B-TER
made O
kiddush B-TER
the O
Sabbath O
blessing O
over O
wine O
, O
although O
it O
was O
dark O
; O
we O
ate O
a O
symbolic O
portion O
of O
food B-TER
and O
said O
the O
end O
- O
of- O
meal B-TER
blessing B-TER
. O

Shooting O
could O
still O
be O
heard O
in O
the O
distance O
. O

We O
did O
not O
undress B-TER
to O
sleep O
and O
could O
only O
doze O
during O
the O
night O
. O

At O
dawn O
, O
the O
artillery O
fire O
intensified O
and O
the O
town O
was O
burning O
on O
all O
sides O
. O

On O
Saturday O
the O
9th O
of O
September O
, O
around O
11 O
a.m. O
, O
we O
ran O
away O
from O
our O
small O
wooden O
house O
and O
hid B-TER
in O
a O
house O
made O
of O
bricks O
. O

On O
Saturday O
afternoon O
, O
when O
I O
was O
looking O
out O
through O
the O
courtyard O
, O
I O
spotted O
a O
Jew O
running O
. O

Three O
German B-TER
soldiers B-TER
ran O
after O
him O
aiming O
their O
guns O
. O

Shortly O
afterwards O
I O
heard O
shots O
– O
the O
Jew O
was O
apparently O
shot B-TER
to I-TER
death I-TER
. O

Buildings O
continued O
to O
catch O
fire O
. O

I O
saw O
a O
German B-TER
soldier B-TER
hanging O
around O
on O
the O
corner O
of O
Pułtuska B-LOC
and O
Ogrodowa B-LOC
Streets I-LOC
. O

Shortly O
afterwards O
a O
small O
house O
started O
to O
burn O
– O
apparently O
the O
German B-TER
had O
set O
fire O
to O
it O
. O

Through O
a O
shutter O
I O
saw O
a O
group O
of O
eight O
German B-TER
soldiers B-TER
use O
explosives O
on O
one O
of O
shop O
of O
Nielipowiczun B-PER
’s O
shops O
on O
Wąska B-LOC
Street I-LOC
, O
and O
the O
building O
caught O
fire O
right O
away O
. O

On O
Saturday O
afternoon O
the O
Germans B-TER
shot O
in O
through O
the O
windows O
into O
several O
houses O
on O
the O
market O
square O
. O

Afterwards O
they O
set O
fire O
to O
them O
. O

Some O
wounded O
Jews O
, O
shot O
by O
the O
Germans B-TER
, O
came O
to O
us O
in O
Marke O
’s O
Spelling O
uncertain O
. O

house O
on O
Wąska B-LOC
Street I-LOC
. O

I O
know O
that O
the O
Portowicz B-PER
Spelling O
uncertain O
. O

family B-TER
was O
wounded O
( O
the O
father B-TER
in O
the O
arm O
, O
the O
mother B-TER
in O
the O
leg O
and O
head O
, O
and O
the O
four O
- O
year O
- O
old O
child B-TER
in O
the O
leg O
) O
. O

When O
we O
saw O
that O
the O
houses O
across O
the O
street O
were O
burning O
, O
and O
that O
the O
houses O
next O
to O
us O
, O
ignited O
by O
the O
German B-TER
soldiers B-TER
, O
were O
also O
catching O
fire O
, O
we O
were O
afraid O
that O
our O
house O
would O
be O
also O
set O
on O
fire O
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
shot O
into O
our O
house O
too O
, O
through O
the O
window O
, O
but O
nobody O
was O
hit O
because O
we O
were O
lying O
on O
the O
floor O
. O

So O
we O
went O
out O
of O
the O
house O
( O
around O
11 O
a.m. O
) O
and O
we O
ran O
into O
a O
Polish B-LOC
house O
with O
a O
damaged O
roof O
. O

We O
ran O
into O
the O
ditch O
that O
encircled O
the O
bath O
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
shot O
after O
us O
, O
hit O
Tsirl B-PER
Holand I-PER
( O
60 O
years O
old O
) O
, O
and O
killed B-TER
her O
. O

Her O
son B-TER
– O
Fishl B-PER
Holand I-PER
– O
was O
wounded O
in O
the O
leg O
; O
a O
woman B-TER
– O
Shoshke B-PER
( O
60 O
years O
old O
) O
was O
killed B-TER
. O

There O
were O
other O
murder B-TER
victims B-TER
there O
, O
and O
the O
corpses B-TER
smelled O
bad O
, O
but O
because O
I O
was O
running O
, O
I O
could O
not O
recognize O
them O
. O

From O
the O
ditch O
we O
crossed O
over O
into O
the O
cellars O
, O
through O
the O
cellar O
windows O
in O
the O
bath O
. O

After O
a O
half O
- O
hour O
, O
the O
fire O
had O
already O
reached O
the O
bath O
. O

I O
went O
from O
the O
cellar O
to O
another O
small O
room O
, O
to O
check O
if O
the O
fire O
had O
already O
reached O
that O
far O
. O

When O
I O
came O
back O
, O
nobody O
was O
left O
in O
the O
cellar O
except O
for O
Moyshe B-PER
- I-PER
Zelik I-PER
Ostry I-PER
and O
his O
mother B-TER
; O
everyone O
else O
had O
run B-TER
away I-TER
. O

We O
remained O
in O
the O
cellar O
from O
Sunday O
the O
10th O
of O
September O
until O
Wednesday O
, O
the O
eve O
of O
the O
Rosh O
- O
Hashanah O
Jewish O
New O
Year O
. O

( O
the O
13th O
of O
September O
) O
. O

More O
people O
arrived O
on O
Sunday O
the O
10th O
in O
the O
daytime O
, O
and O
so O
we O
passed O
the O
time O
there O
until O
Wednesday O
. O

We O
were O
able O
to O
eat B-TER
because O
we O
happened O
to O
find O
a O
packet O
of O
old O
pastries B-TER
there O
, O
which O
someone O
had O
apparently O
lost O
on O
the O
run O
. O

At O
night O
we O
slipped O
out O
into O
the O
courtyard O
to O
get O
water O
from O
the O
pump O
. O

We O
relieved O
our O
physiological O
needs O
in O
one O
of O
the O
cellars O
, O
because O
we O
were O
afraid O
to O
go O
outside O
. O

On O
the O
same O
Sunday O
, O
a O
German B-TER
approached O
the O
cellar O
window O
. O

I O
was O
hiding B-TER
in O
another O
cellar B-TER
room I-TER
, O
in O
the O
bath B-TER
boiler I-TER
, O
and O
I O
heard O
gunshots O
. O

On O
Sunday O
at O
noon O
, O
more O
people O
arrived O
in O
the O
cellars O
, O
bringing O
with O
them O
a O
Jew O
whom O
they O
had O
found O
on O
the O
street O
, O
Binyomtshe B-PER
( O
70 O
years O
old O
) O
, O
wounded O
in O
the O
leg O
. O

They O
took O
him O
into O
the O
cellar O
and O
put O
him O
in O
a O
bed O
that O
was O
there O
– O
I O
do O
n’t O
know O
where O
it O
came O
from O
. O

The O
Jew O
died B-TER
on O
Tuesday O
the O
12th O
of O
September O
, O
without O
any O
[ O
medical B-TER
] O
help O
. O

The O
son B-TER
of O
Moyshe O
- O
Borekh O
the O
butcher O
also O
lay O
there O
, O
wounded O
in O
the O
belly O
. O

And O
opposite O
the O
bath O
, O
in O
a O
nearby O
orchard O
, O
lay O
a O
Jew O
from O
Pułtusk B-LOC
, O
wounded O
in O
the O
arm O
, O
as O
well O
as O
a O
seven B-TER
- I-TER
year I-TER
- I-TER
old I-TER
boy I-TER
with O
a O
piece O
of O
shoulder O
torn O
off O
; O
he O
bled O
a O
lot O
and O
smelled O
terrible O
, O
it O
was O
simply O
impossible O
to O
be O
near O
him O
. O

We O
learned O
from O
Simkhe B-PER
- I-PER
Yankev I-PER
Vengrov I-PER
, O
who O
looked O
like O
a O
German B-TER
and O
spoke O
German B-TER
, O
and O
who O
came O
to O
us O
in O
the O
cellar O
, O
that O
more O
than O
forty O
people O
were O
lying O
dead B-TER
in O
the O
brewery O
in O
Wyszków B-LOC
, O
shot B-TER
by O
the O
Germans B-TER
, O
among O
them O
Simkhe B-PER
Shnyek I-PER
Spelling O
uncertain O
, O
maybe O
Śnieg O
. O

and O
his O
wife B-TER
, O
Tuvye B-PER
Malovantshik I-PER
, O
Yisroel B-PER
- I-PER
Aron I-PER
Melamed I-PER
’s O
son B-TER
- I-TER
in I-TER
- I-TER
law I-TER
and O
others O
. O

On O
Wednesday O
the O
13th O
at O
6 O
a.m. O
, O
the O
butcher O
’s O
son B-TER
arrived O
from O
Jadów B-LOC
in O
order O
to O
bring O
the O
wounded O
man B-TER
to O
the O
hospital B-TER
there O
. O

A O
few O
of O
us O
laid O
the O
wounded O
man B-TER
on O
a O
broken O
mattress O
, O
carried O
him O
to O
the O
Bug B-LOC
, O
and O
crossed O
the O
river O
with O
him O
by O
boat O
. O

We O
did O
not O
see O
any O
Germans B-TER
on O
the O
way O
there O
. O

Everything O
[ O
we O
saw O
] O
on O
our O
way O
to O
the O
Bug B-LOC
with O
the O
wounded O
man B-TER
was O
destroyed O
. O

The O
prayer B-TER
house I-TER
– O
burned B-TER
down I-TER
. O

Not O
a O
single O
house O
remained O
– O
all O
had O
been O
burned O
down O
. O

Among O
us O
were O
members O
of O
the O
khevre B-ORG
- I-ORG
kedishe I-ORG
. O

On O
Monday O
the O
11th O
, O
at O
3 O
p.m. O
, O
Borekh B-PER
Stalik I-PER
Spelling O
uncertain O
, O
maybe O
Stolik O
. O

, O
Yenkl B-PER
Safirshteyn I-PER
, O
Moyshe B-PER
- I-PER
Zelig I-PER
Ostra I-PER
( O
although O
he O
was O
a O
cohen O
, O
he O
went O
with O
them O
anyway O
, O
because O
of O
the O
urgency O
of O
the O
commandment O
to O
bury B-TER
the O
dead B-TER
who O
have O
no O
one O
to O
bury B-TER
them O
) O
, O
Khaykl B-PER
Ulmer I-PER
( O
a O
Jew O
from O
Pułtusk B-LOC
, O
a O
carpenter O
) O
, O
and O
some O
others O
, O
went O
to O
give O
the O
dead B-TER
in O
the O
brewery O
a O
proper O
burial B-TER
. O

They O
let O
us O
know O
the O
names O
of O
those O
who O
had O
been O
shot B-TER
by O
the O
Germans B-TER
, O
more O
than O
forty O
names O
, O
among O
them O
Simkhe B-PER
Shnyek I-PER
, O
whom O
they O
barely O
recognized O
because O
pigs O
had O
eaten O
up O
his O
shoulder O
and O
hand O
. O

They O
had O
been O
killed B-TER
without O
reason O
, O
only O
because O
they O
were O
Jews O
. O

The O
burial B-TER
took O
a O
lot O
of O
time O
. O

The O
corpses B-TER
were O
buried B-TER
together O
in O
a O
trench O
, O
without O
shrouds O
, O
men B-TER
and O
women B-TER
separated O
by O
only O
a O
wooden O
board O
. O

The O
dead B-TER
in O
the O
prayer B-TER
house I-TER
had O
been O
burned O
up O
together O
with O
the O
prayer B-TER
house I-TER
. O

The O
smaller O
prayer B-TER
house I-TER
, O
as O
well O
as O
the O
prayer B-TER
house I-TER
of O
the O
Ger B-TER
Hasidim I-TER
, O
had O
also O
burned B-TER
down I-TER
. O

On O
Wednesday O
the O
13th O
of O
September O
, O
at O
7 O
a.m. O
, O
I O
crossed O
the O
Bug B-LOC
to O
Latoszek B-LOC
. O

In O
Latoszek B-LOC
I O
met O
Khaim B-PER
- I-PER
Yitskhok I-PER
Zabraniecki I-PER
and O
Henokh B-PER
Piekarz I-PER
( O
both O
of O
them O
from O
Wyszków B-LOC
) O
. O

They O
had O
been O
taken O
by O
the O
Germans B-TER
to O
a O
concentration B-TER
camp I-TER
near O
Pułtusk B-LOC
, O
together O
with O
Nosl B-PER
Later O
spelled O
Yosl O
. O

and O
Borekh B-PER
and O
Fayvl B-PER
Shoykhet I-PER
( O
all O
of O
them O
from O
Wyszków B-LOC
) O
. O

Piekarz B-PER
and O
Zabraniecki B-PER
told O
us O
that O
they O
had O
been O
beaten O
and O
tortured B-TER
in O
the O
camp B-TER
, O
like O
a O
lot O
of O
other O
Jews O
there O
, O
and O
they O
were O
not O
given O
anything B-TER
to I-TER
eat I-TER
. O

Yosl B-PER
and O
Borekh B-PER
Tsivyak I-PER
, O
and O
Fayvl B-PER
Shoykhet I-PER
, O
emaciated O
from O
hunger B-TER
, O
collapsed O
on O
the O
way O
and O
were O
not O
able O
to O
continue O
their O
escape B-TER
. O

Piekarz B-PER
and O
Zabraniecki B-PER
ran O
, O
drawing O
on O
their O
last O
shreds O
of O
strength O
, O
and O
arrived O
in O
Latoszek B-LOC
, O
whereas O
the O
former O
three O
remained O
behind O
. O

Their O
fate O
is O
unknown O
to O
those O
who O
told O
the O
story O
. O

They O
only O
heard O
shots O
when O
the O
other O
three O
fell O
. O

A O
road O
leads O
uphill O
from O
Latoszek B-LOC
to O
Jadów B-LOC
, O
bisected O
by O
an O
asphalt O
road O
that O
leads O
to O
Warsaw B-LOC
. O

On O
the O
asphalt O
road O
stood O
a O
German B-TER
patrol O
. O

As O
I O
was O
wearing O
a O
typical O
Jewish O
hat O
, O
I O
was O
afraid O
to O
pass O
near O
the O
Germans B-TER
. O

However O
, O
I O
continued O
to O
walk O
. O

A O
German B-TER
with O
a O
revolver O
approached O
me O
and O
spoke O
to O
me O
in O
German B-TER
. O

I O
did O
not O
understand O
what O
he O
said O
. O

He O
unbuttoned O
my O
coat B-TER
, O
asked O
if O
I O
had O
a O
gun O
, O
ordered O
me O
to O
show O
him O
my O
father B-TER
’s O
tallit B-TER
prayer O
shawl O
which O
I O
was O
carrying O
with O
me O
. O

Zum O
Gottesdienst O
For O
religious O
services O
. O

, O
I O
explained O
to O
him O
. O

He O
let O
me O
go O
, O
saying O
finally O
: O
Go O
, O
go O
, O
later O
it O
will O
be O
a O
slaughterhouse O
. O

Scared O
, O
I O
continued O
to O
walk O
. O

On O
the O
way O
we O
encountered O
German B-TER
soldiers B-TER
. O

They O
stopped O
us O
: O
Jude O
, O
where O
are O
you O
from O
? O
– O
From O
Wyszków O
, O
we O
answered O
. O

Yes O
, O
they O
answered O
the O
damned O
Jews O
were O
shooting O
at O
us O
in O
Wyszków O
. O

In O
Jadów B-LOC
I O
stayed O
with O
my O
acquaintances O
from O
Wednesday O
the O
13th O
of O
September O
until O
the O
1st O
of O
October O
( O
the O
first O
of O
the O
intermediary O
days O
of O
Sukkot O
) O
. O

The O
were O
no O
murders B-TER
in O
Jadów B-LOC
, O
but O
robberies O
occured O
, O
although O
a O
few O
Germans B-TER
did O
pay O
for O
products O
. O

Aside O
from O
that O
, O
Jews O
were O
severely O
beaten O
. O

On O
the O
first O
day O
of O
the O
Jewish O
New O
Year O
, O
the O
14th O
of O
September O
, O
young O
Jewish O
men B-TER
were O
taken O
away O
to O
perform O
forced B-TER
labour I-TER
. O

I O
was O
hiding B-TER
in O
a O
attic B-TER
. O

The O
prayer B-TER
house I-TER
was O
full O
of O
Jewish O
civilian O
captives O
, O
among O
them O
the O
rabbi B-TER
of O
Kołbiel B-LOC
. O

In O
the O
church O
there O
were O
Christian B-TER
captives O
. O

In O
the O
market O
square O
, O
there O
were O
Christian B-TER
captives O
, O
as O
well O
as O
some O
Jews O
. O

They O
stood O
outside O
in O
the O
rain O
and O
cold O
. O

The O
captives O
in O
the O
prayer B-TER
house I-TER
, O
who O
had O
been O
captured O
on O
the O
roads O
, O
were O
not O
allowed O
to O
go O
outside O
. O

They O
had O
to O
relieve O
themselves O
on O
the O
spot O
. O

They O
were O
not O
given O
food B-TER
, O
but O
the O
Jewish O
inhabitants O
of O
the O
town O
brought O
them O
something O
to O
eat B-TER
. O

There O
were O
rumors O
going O
around O
that O
the O
Red B-ORG
Army I-ORG
was O
on O
its O
way O
. O

On O
Tuesday O
, O
the O
19th O
of O
September O
, O
the O
captives O
began O
to O
be O
freed O
. O

By O
the O
24th O
- O
26th O
In O
the O
original O
: O
26 O
- O
64 O
. O

, O
all O
the O
captives O
were O
freed O
. O

The O
news O
of O
the O
arrival O
of O
the O
Bolsheviks O
provoked O
joy O
Unclear O
in O
the O
original O
. O

among O
the O
Jews O
. O

A O
kilo O
of O
dark O
bread B-TER
cost O
25 O
groschen O
, O
white O
bread B-TER
– O
30 O
groschen O
. O

Bread B-TER
was O
sold O
per O
kilo O
in O
the O
bakeries O
and O
there O
were O
queues O
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
threw O
Jews O
out O
of O
the O
queues O
even O
the O
queues O
to O
the O
Jewish O
bakeries O
. O

The O
Poles B-TER
had O
a O
bad O
attitude O
toward O
the O
Jews O
too O
, O
although O
I O
did O
not O
hear O
of O
Poles B-TER
who O
beat O
Jews O
. O

But O
they O
accepted O
the O
products O
that O
the O
Germans B-TER
stole O
on O
the O
Jewish O
New O
Year O
. O

Also O
, O
young O
Jewish O
girls B-TER
who O
appeared O
Polish B-TER
, O
accepted O
those O
products O
and O
then O
gave O
them O
back O
to O
the O
Jews O
from O
whom O
they O
had O
been O
stolen O
. O

They O
rescued O
what O
they O
could O
. O

On O
Rosh O
Hashanah O
The O
Jewish O
New O
Year O
. O

, O
we O
prayed B-TER
in O
the O
prayer B-TER
house I-TER
of O
the O
Radzymin O
Hasidim B-TER
, O
very O
quietly O
and O
without O
choirboys O
, O
so O
as O
not O
to O
be O
heard O
from O
outside O
. O

By O
chance O
, O
Germans B-TER
entered O
the O
courtyard O
at O
the O
end O
of O
the O
service B-TER
, O
and O
all O
the O
people O
in O
the O
prayer B-TER
house I-TER
ran O
away O
. O

No O
one O
blew O
the O
shofar B-TER
Ram O
’s O
horn O
blown O
on O
Rosh O
Hashanah O
. O

. O

On O
Yom O
Kippur O
, O
the O
German B-TER
soldiers B-TER
were O
already O
no O
longer O
there O
. O

People O
were O
saying O
that O
the O
German B-TER
commanders O
were O
already O
leaving O
. O

The O
Jews O
prayed B-TER
without O
choirboys O
, O
but O
less O
fearfully O
than O
on O
Rosh O
Hashanah O
. O

After O
the O
service B-TER
, O
the O
shofar B-TER
was O
blown O
, O
although O
the O
tekiyah B-TER
[ I-TER
gedolah I-TER
] I-TER
Long O
sound O
of O
the O
shofar O
blast O
blown O
to O
signal O
the O
close O
of O
Yom O
Kippur O
. O

was O
blown O
softly O
, O
under O
a O
tallit B-TER
. O

People O
built O
sukkahs B-TER
Booths O
for O
the O
holiday O
of O
Sukkot O
. O

, O
only O
in O
very O
hidden O
places O
that O
could O
not O
be O
seen O
from O
the O
outside O
. O

On O
Sukkot O
, O
people O
felt O
freer O
, O
because O
there O
were O
nearly O
no O
Germans B-TER
left O
in O
the O
area O
. O

On O
the O
second O
day O
of O
Sukkot O
, O
the O
29th O
of O
September O
, O
around O
2 O
p.m. O
, O
the O
German B-TER
commanders O
left O
. O

There O
were O
no O
more O
German B-TER
soldiers B-TER
. O

When O
they O
left O
, O
joy O
reigned O
among O
the O
Jews O
. O

People O
went O
out O
into O
the O
streets O
. O

We O
did O
not O
see O
any O
Poles B-TER
. O

We O
expected O
the O
arrival O
of O
the O
Russians B-ORG
, O
but O
they O
did O
not O
come O
. O

On O
Saturday O
, O
the O
30th O
of O
September O
, O
people O
started O
to O
say O
that O
the O
Germans B-TER
were O
going O
to O
come O
back O
. O

When O
I O
was O
in O
Jadów B-LOC
, O
I O
heard O
that O
in O
Wyszków B-LOC
Pinye B-PER
Krishtal I-PER
’s O
wife B-TER
and O
their O
two O
small O
children B-TER
, O
as O
well O
as O
Izraelski B-PER
and O
some O
others O
, O
had O
been O
shot B-TER
to I-TER
death I-TER
. O

From O
the O
Izraelski B-PER
family B-TER
, O
which O
had O
consisted O
of O
eleven O
persons O
, O
only O
two O
persons O
survived O
( O
a O
young O
man B-TER
and O
a O
girl B-TER
) O
. O

The O
aforementioned O
Pinye B-PER
Krishtal I-PER
had O
had O
three O
children B-TER
. O

Only O
a O
five O
- O
year O
- O
old O
boy B-TER
survived O
, O
and O
was O
hanging O
around O
hungry B-TER
, O
without O
supervision O
, O
amidst O
the O
ruins O
. O

The O
boy B-TER
was O
brought O
into O
Jadów B-LOC
and O
I O
saw O
him O
myself O
. O

His O
father B-TER
, O
Pinye B-PER
Krishtal I-PER
, O
was O
sent O
to O
a O
prison B-TER
camp B-TER
. O

Avrom B-PER
Rebeles I-PER
from O
Wyszków B-LOC
came O
with O
me O
to O
Jadów B-LOC
. O

He O
told O
me O
that O
in O
Kamieńczyk B-LOC
( O
on O
the O
Bug B-LOC
, O
near O
Wyszków B-LOC
) O
he O
and O
another O
Jew O
had O
been O
chased O
by O
men B-TER
on O
horseback O
. O

As O
they O
could O
not O
run O
very O
quickly O
, O
the O
horses O
ran O
them O
over O
. O

Also O
in O
Kamieńczyk B-LOC
, O
a O
house O
was O
burned O
down O
by O
the O
Germans B-TER
, O
burying B-TER
more O
than O
twenty O
people O
under O
the O
ruins O
. O

One O
of O
those O
who O
was O
burned B-TER
to I-TER
death I-TER
– O
Tuvye B-PER
Morgnshtern I-PER
( O
from O
Wyszków B-LOC
, O
65 O
years O
old O
, O
a O
mason O
) O
was O
buried B-TER
in O
the O
Jewish B-TER
cemetery I-TER
in O
Jadów B-LOC
. O

His O
bones O
were O
brought O
there O
in O
a O
small O
bag O
and O
buried B-TER
. O

On O
the O
way O
to O
Jadów B-LOC
I O
met O
Meir B-PER
Shtinski I-PER
from O
Wyszków B-LOC
, O
35 O
years O
old O
. O

He O
told O
me O
that O
he O
had O
been O
walking O
with O
a O
group O
of O
more O
than O
twenty O
people O
, O
when O
the O
Germans B-TER
stopped O
them O
for O
no O
reason O
, O
stood O
them O
up O
against O
a O
wall O
and O
shot O
them O
. O

He O
fell O
down O
among O
those O
who O
had O
been O
shot B-TER
and O
played O
dead B-TER
, O
and O
in O
this O
way O
he O
survived O
. O

On O
Sunday O
the O
1st O
of O
October O
( O
the O
second O
of O
the O
intermediary O
days O
of O
Sukkot O
) O
I O
left O
Jadów B-LOC
and O
set O
out O
for O
Ostrów B-LOC
Mazowiecka I-LOC
. O

From O
Jadów B-LOC
to O
Łochów B-LOC
the O
road O
was O
covered O
with O
spent O
ammunition O
. O

In O
Łochów B-LOC
, O
an O
munitions O
factory B-TER
was O
destroyed O
. O

An O
armoured O
train B-TER
lay O
flipped O
over O
. O

The O
road O
from O
Łochów B-LOC
to O
Ostrówek B-LOC
was O
damaged O
by O
bombs O
. O

In O
Ostrówek B-LOC
I O
rested O
for O
the O
night O
. O

On O
Monday O
the O
2nd O
of O
October O
I O
went O
by O
horse O
and O
wagon O
to O
Ostrów B-LOC
Mazowiecka I-LOC
. O

I O
passed O
through O
Brok B-LOC
, O
where O
forty O
- O
five O
Jews O
had O
been O
shot B-TER
by O
the O
Germans B-TER
. O

Houses O
were O
burned O
down O
, O
the O
forest O
had O
been O
badly O
damaged O
by O
artillery O
fires O
. O

That O
same O
day O
in O
the O
afternoon O
I O
arrived O
in O
Ostrów B-LOC
Mazowiecka I-LOC
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
were O
capturing O
people O
to O
perform O
forced B-TER
labour I-TER
. O

In O
the O
evening O
a O
decree O
came O
out O
: O
All O
refugees O
have O
to O
leave O
Ostrów O
by O
Tuesday O
the O
3rd O
of O
October O
. O

In O
Ostrów B-LOC
the O
Jews O
were O
forced O
to O
lick O
the O
urine O
of O
the O
German B-TER
soldiers B-TER
with O
their O
tongues O
. O

In O
the O
morning O
there O
was O
a O
commotion O
: O
all O
the O
Jews O
had O
to O
stand O
in O
front O
of O
their O
apartments O
at O
8 O
a.m. O
– O
no O
Jew O
was O
allowed O
to O
stay O
inside O
. O

Only O
Christians B-TER
. O

I O
did O
not O
wait O
until O
8 O
; O
at O
7 O
a.m. O
I O
set O
out O
, O
with O
a O
lot O
of O
other O
people O
, O
for O
Zambrów B-LOC
. O

The O
road O
was O
bad O
. O

It O
was O
raining O
. O

Eight O
kilometers O
past O
Ostrów B-LOC
– O
in O
Szumowo B-LOC
Unclear O
. O

we O
already O
encountered O
the O
Russians B-ORG
. O

We O
were O
let O
in O
without O
any O
difficulties O
. O

At O
last O
we O
rested O
. O

I O
was O
told O
that O
Christians B-TER
were O
stealing O
Jewish O
belongings O
that O
were O
hidden B-TER
in O
cellars B-TER
and O
that O
Jews O
were O
no O
longer O
being O
let O
into O
Jadów B-LOC
. O

A O
cobbler O
’s O
apprentice O
, O
Dovid O
Leyb O
’s O
son B-TER
, O
returned O
to O
Wyszków B-LOC
to O
get O
a O
pair O
of O
boots B-TER
. O

In O
Wyszków B-LOC
in O
the O
market O
square O
he O
was O
shot B-TER
by O
a O
German B-TER
soldier B-TER
. O

It O
is O
estimated O
that O
500 O
Jews O
were O
killed B-TER
in O
Wyszków B-LOC
. O

