Švenčionys B-LOC
( O
On O
the O
way O
from O
Vilna B-LOC
to O
Daugavpils B-LOC
[ O
Dinaburg B-LOC
] O
) O
September O
27 O
, O
1941 O
, O
they O
took O
all O
the O
Jews O
from O
the O
Švenčionys B-LOC
district I-LOC
: O
from O
the O
shtetls O
of O
Švenčionys B-LOC
, O
New O
Švenčionys B-LOC
, O
Adutiškis B-LOC
, O
Ceikiniai B-LOC
, O
Mielagėnai B-LOC
, O
Pabradė B-LOC
, O
Daugėliškis B-LOC
, O
Naujasis B-LOC
Daugėliškis I-LOC
, O
Ignalina B-LOC
, O
and O
the O
remainder O
from O
Kaltanėnai B-LOC
( O
the O
largest O
part O
had O
already O
been O
murdered B-TER
by O
Lithuanian B-TER
-bandits O
six O
weeks O
previously O
) O
, O
around O
( O
6,500 O
) O
six O
thousand O
five O
hundred O
altogether O
, O
they O
took O
them O
to O
Poligon O
which O
is O
two O
kilometers O
from O
the O
shtetl O
. O

Naturally O
, O
they O
did O
not O
tell O
them O
that O
they O
were O
being O
taken O
there O
to O
be O
murdered B-TER
but O
rather O
to O
work B-TER
. O

And O
indeed O
, O
on O
the O
second O
day O
they O
took O
them O
to O
work B-TER
in O
the O
shtetl O
. O

They O
even O
started O
repairing O
the O
barracks B-TER
in O
Poligon B-LOC
. O

At O
the O
same O
time O
, O
they O
started O
setting O
free O
Jews O
from O
the O
city O
of O
Švenčionys B-LOC
as O
useful O
Jews O
. O

This O
reinforced O
the O
hope O
among O
everyone O
that O
they O
would O
let O
them O
live O
, O
because O
each O
useful O
Jew O
, O
that O
is O
a O
shoemaker O
, O
a O
tailor O
, O
a O
doctor O
etc O
. O

, O
could O
also O
take O
his O
entire O
family B-TER
with O
him O
to O
Švenčionys B-LOC
, O
to O
the O
ghetto O
, O
which O
was O
already O
determined O
in O
advance O
. O

On O
October O
1 O
, O
the O
bandits O
selected B-TER
the O
strongest O
men B-TER
for O
work O
. O

They O
did O
not O
come O
back O
, O
but O
at O
the O
same O
time O
by O
the O
door O
they O
stopped O
letting O
out O
the O
Jews O
who O
were O
recognized O
as O
useful O
. O

At O
the O
same O
time O
they O
drove O
[ O
people B-TER
] O
to O
Poligon B-LOC
from O
New O
Švenčionys B-LOC
to O
dig O
graves B-TER
there O
in O
Poligon B-LOC
, O
the O
Jews O
already O
knew O
that O
they O
will O
be O
shot B-TER
but O
the O
Poligon O
was O
strongly O
guarded B-TER
by O
Lithuanian B-TER
bandits O
, O
who O
were O
brought O
in O
from O
the O
entire O
district O
. O

On O
October O
8 O
, O
all O
the O
Jews O
from O
the O
Švenčionys B-LOC
district I-LOC
had O
already O
been O
shot B-TER
. O

I O
learned O
from O
a O
bandit O
that O
the O
Rabbi B-TER
from O
Švenčionys B-LOC
was O
killed B-TER
in O
his O
prayer B-TER
shawl I-TER
. O

The O
Rabbi B-TER
from O
Ignalina B-LOC
, O
who O
was O
very O
ill B-TER
, O
the O
Rabbi B-PER
Moyshe I-PER
Aharon I-PER
Hayat I-PER
, O
they O
also O
forced O
him O
to O
the O
grave B-TER
. O

No O
one O
put O
up O
any O
resistance B-TER
, O
but O
one O
Borukh B-PER
Sholem I-PER
Gendtz I-PER
from O
Švenčionys B-LOC
did O
not O
go O
to O
the O
grave B-TER
and O
the O
bandits O
threw O
a O
grenade B-TER
at O
him O
. O

One O
Murasken B-PER
, O
a O
hairdresser O
, O
gave O
a O
short O
speech O
, O
saying O
that O
an O
evil O
end O
would O
come O
upon O
you O
bandits O
… O
and O
without O
letting O
him O
finish O
his O
speech O
they O
shot B-TER
him O
... O
( O
… O
. O

Švenčionys B-LOC
) O
They O
covered O
the O
graves B-TER
a O
bit O
with O
earth O
and O
left O
them O
almost O
open O
until O
the O
month O
of O
April O
, O
the O
blood O
of O
the O
martyrs O
forced O
its O
way O
through O
the O
white O
and O
yellow O
sand O
and O
in O
a O
few O
places O
the O
wolves O
, O
of O
which O
there O
are O
many O
in O
the O
district O
, O
ate O
a O
number O
of O
bodies B-TER
. O

At O
the O
end O
of O
April O
they O
brought O
Jewish O
workers B-TER
from O
the O
Vilna O
ghetto O
and O
they O
covered O
the O
graves B-TER
with O
( O
slaked O
lime O
) O
chalk B-TER
and I-TER
a I-TER
thick I-TER
layer I-TER
of I-TER
earth I-TER
and O
the O
place O
was O
fenced O
off O
. O

At O
first O
there O
were O
around O
sixty O
Jewish O
workers B-TER
who O
, O
after O
finishing O
their O
work B-TER
at O
Poligon O
, O
they O
were O
occupied O
with O
chopping O
wood O
and O
working B-TER
on O
the O
railway O
line O
. O

In O
a O
short O
time O
, O
around O
the O
end O
of O
May O
1942 O
, O
they O
brought O
new O
workers B-TER
from O
Švenčionys B-LOC
ghetto I-LOC
. O

There O
were O
already O
more O
than O
a O
hundred O
workers B-TER
laboring B-TER
there O
. O

This O
lasted O
until O
the O
end O
of O
March O
1943 O
. O

Then O
they O
sent O
them O
all O
to O
the O
ghetto B-LOC
of I-LOC
Švenčionys I-LOC
and O
they O
divided O
the O
entire O
ghetto B-TER
into O
two O
groups O
: O
in O
one O
group O
were O
those O
with O
friends O
or O
relatives O
in O
Vilna B-LOC
, O
they O
were O
sent O
to O
Vilna B-LOC
. O

The O
two O
groups O
were O
taken O
to O
… O
Kovno B-LOC
. O

And O
leaving O
Vilna B-LOC
they O
took O
them O
a O
few O
kilometers O
to O
Poligon O
and O
opened O
the O
wagons B-TER
. O

Then O
the O
people B-TER
straight O
away O
understood O
to O
where O
they O
had B-TER
been I-TER
taken I-TER
. O

They O
began O
shooting B-TER
with O
machine O
guns O
, O
all O
were O
murdered B-TER
, O
apart O
from O
a O
few O
who O
saved O
themselves O
in O
that O
moment O
. O

One O
of O
those O
who O
were O
saved O
was O
Dibinsky B-PER
from O
Ignalina B-LOC
( O
he O
was O
killed B-TER
at O
the O
end O
of O
1943 O
near O
Ignalina B-LOC
, O
a O
friend O
of O
his O
from O
Klaipeda B-LOC
, O
I O
do O
not O
know O
his O
name O
) O
. O

Munich B-LOC
9/12/1946 O
Yerachmiel B-PER
Kork I-PER
Born O
in O
Salakas B-LOC
, O
lived O
in O
Ignalina B-LOC
, O
Švenčionys B-LOC
district O
. O

