Committee O
to O
Collect O
Material O
about O
the O
Destruction O
of O
Polish B-TER
Jewry O
1939 O
Shloyme B-PER
Perkal I-PER
, O
24 O
years O
Currently O
in O
Vilnius B-LOC
, O
Sadowa B-LOC
street I-LOC
7 I-LOC
12th O
November O
, O
1939 O
Testimony O
10 O
The O
war B-TER
found O
me O
in O
Międzyrzec B-LOC
Podlaski I-LOC
. O

Before O
9th O
September O
the O
town O
had O
not O
been O
touched O
by O
aerial O
bombings B-TER
. O

The O
attitude O
of O
the O
local O
police O
toward O
the O
Jews O
changed O
considerably O
for O
the O
better O
. O

On O
the O
9th O
[ O
of O
September O
] O
there O
were O
two O
bombings B-TER
: O
a O
couple O
of O
times O
in O
the O
morning O
( O
but O
they O
missed O
the O
target O
) O
, O
and O
about O
4 O
p.m. O
in O
the O
vicinity O
( O
they O
set O
fire O
to O
villages O
on O
three O
sides O
of O
the O
town O
) O
. O

It O
was O
said O
that O
a O
peasant O
was O
killed B-TER
during O
the O
first O
attack O
, O
and O
that O
there O
were O
7 O
- O
8 O
civilian O
victims B-TER
( O
killed B-TER
or O
wounded O
) O
during O
the O
second O
, O
among O
them O
about O
three O
Jews O
. O

By O
then O
Międzyrzec B-LOC
had O
already O
been O
flooded O
with O
refugees B-TER
. O

On O
the O
9th O
, O
in O
spite O
of O
Shabbat O
, O
bakeries O
were O
working O
, O
and O
the O
authorities O
ordered O
to O
sell O
the O
bread B-TER
only O
to O
the O
refugees B-TER
, O
not O
to O
the O
local O
population O
. O

The O
refugees B-TER
continued O
to O
move O
on O
the O
road O
toward O
Biała B-LOC
Podlaska I-LOC
and O
Brest O
. O

Local O
inhabitants O
, O
afraid O
of O
bombings B-TER
, O
had O
started O
to O
leave O
the O
town O
already O
on O
the O
7th O
[ O
of O
September O
] O
. O

On O
7th O
, O
there O
was O
a O
terrible O
bombing B-TER
in O
Siedlce B-LOC
( O
the O
local O
starosta O
[ O
chief O
administrator O
] O
ordered O
the O
inhabitants O
to O
gather O
at O
a O
square O
– O
and O
the O
Germans B-TER
descended O
with O
their O
airplanes O
and O
threw O
bombs B-TER
on O
the O
crowd O
of O
civilians O
– O
a O
lot O
of O
victims O
) O
. O

Therefore O
, O
on O
the O
7th O
, O
to O
avoid O
a O
similar O
massacre O
, O
the O
starosta O
of O
Radzyń B-LOC
Podlaski I-LOC
ordered O
the O
population O
of O
Międzyrzec B-LOC
( O
apparently O
by O
phone O
) O
to O
leave O
the O
town O
and O
go O
to O
the O
surrounding O
forests O
. O

In O
the O
night O
from O
the O
7th O
to O
the O
8th O
the O
police B-TER
and O
the O
OPL O
[ O
Obrona O
Przeciwlotnicza O
, O
Anti B-TER
- I-TER
aircraft I-TER
defence O
] O
woke O
the O
inhabitants O
and O
so O
they O
went O
to O
the O
forests O
. O

The O
town O
was O
nearly O
deserted O
by O
3.30 O
a.m. O
On O
the O
8th O
in O
the O
evening O
, O
at O
about O
7 O
p.m. O
, O
the O
population O
returned O
to O
the O
town O
. O

On O
the O
10th O
[ O
of O
September O
] O
, O
at O
9 O
a.m. O
, O
I O
left O
Międzyrzec B-LOC
in O
the O
company O
of O
six O
comrades O
( O
Victor B-PER
Alter I-PER
, O
Bernard B-PER
Goldstein I-PER
Well O
known O
Bund O
activists O
in O
prewar O
Poland O
. O

and O
four O
young O
men B-TER
) O
, O
intending O
to O
go O
to O
Warsaw B-LOC
and O
to O
participate O
in O
the O
defence O
of O
the O
city O
. O

On O
the O
road O
the O
army B-TER
did O
not O
let O
us O
In O
this O
part O
of O
the O
testimony O
, O
there O
are O
no O
personal O
pronouns O
and O
no O
auxiliary O
verbs O
( O
probably O
in O
order O
to O
save O
time O
) O
, O
so O
it O
is O
not O
clear O
if O
it O
is O
the O
1st O
person O
( O
singular O
or O
plural O
) O
, O
or O
an O
impersonal O
form O
. O

to O
go O
to O
Warsaw B-LOC
. O

Therefore O
, O
we O
set O
out O
to O
Lublin B-LOC
– O
on O
foot O
, O
sometimes O
by O
a O
horse O
and O
wagon O
– O
and O
in O
this O
way O
we O
reached O
the O
city O
. O

The O
peasants O
on O
the O
road O
were O
friendly O
. O

One O
of O
them O
even O
gave O
us O
a O
lift O
on O
his O
wagon O
to O
the O
next O
town O
for O
free O
. O

We O
entered O
Lublin B-LOC
on O
the O
10th O
, O
Monday O
in O
the O
morning O
, O
after O
the O
city O
had O
already O
been O
severely O
bombed B-TER
. O

A O
lot O
of O
ruins O
. O

In O
Lublin B-LOC
special O
Jewish O
workers O
’ O
groups O
were O
created O
( O
the O
Polish B-LOC
militia B-TER
did O
not O
accepted O
any O
Jews O
) O
in O
order O
to O
clean O
up O
the O
ruins O
, O
help O
to O
extinguish O
fires O
and O
so O
on O
. O

They O
In O
this O
part O
of O
the O
testimony O
, O
there O
are O
no O
personal O
pronouns O
and O
no O
auxiliary O
verbs O
( O
probably O
in O
order O
to O
save O
time O
) O
, O
so O
it O
is O
not O
clear O
if O
it O
is O
the O
1st O
person O
( O
singular O
or O
plural O
) O
, O
or O
an O
impersonal O
form O
. O

worked O
hard O
. O

On O
the O
14th O
a O
single O
issue O
of O
the O
newspaper O
Lubliner B-LOC
shtime O
[ O
The O
Voice O
of O
Lublin B-LOC
] O
, O
the O
organ O
of O
the O
central O
committee O
of O
the O
Bund B-ORG
, O
was O
published O
. O

Victor B-PER
Alter I-PER
stayed O
in O
Lublin B-LOC
. O

He O
was O
appointed O
the O
Jewish O
press O
- O
officer O
by O
the O
city O
council O
and O
a O
member O
of O
its O
propaganda O
department O
. O

On O
the O
14th O
I O
[ O
set O
out O
] O
on O
foot O
toward O
Chełm B-LOC
with O
two O
comrades O
. O

Before O
we O
reached O
Chełm B-LOC
( O
on O
the O
15th O
) O
, O
about O
12 O
German B-TER
airplanes O
bombed B-TER
the O
road O
full O
of O
civilian O
refugees B-TER
, O
evacuated B-TER
policemen B-TER
and O
military B-TER
troops O
. O

They O
started O
to O
shoot O
when O
the O
troops O
had O
already O
passed O
, O
and O
aimed O
at O
civilians O
. O

On O
the O
road O
to O
Chełm B-LOC
we O
entered O
Piaski B-LOC
( O
on O
the O
14th O
) O
. O

In O
the O
town O
, O
perhaps O
two O
Jewish O
families B-TER
remained O
. O

The O
others O
had O
already O
run O
away O
. O

Among O
non O
- O
Jews O
also O
only O
few O
remained O
. O

In O
the O
evening O
airplanes O
arrived O
, O
flying O
very O
low O
, O
right O
over O
the O
roofs O
. O

They O
shot O
from O
machine O
guns O
( O
did O
not O
make O
any O
victims B-TER
) O
and O
set O
fire O
to O
a O
house O
outside O
of O
the O
town O
. O

Chełm B-LOC
was O
crowded O
with O
soldiers B-TER
. O

The O
town O
was O
constantly O
bombed B-TER
. O

A O
lot O
of O
ruins O
. O

I O
myself O
saw O
a O
military B-TER
hospital B-TER
being O
destroyed O
. O

In O
Chełm B-LOC
I O
went O
to O
the O
PKU O
[ O
Powiatowa O
Komenda O
Uzupełnień O
, O
District O
Recruiting O
Command O
] O
, O
as O
I O
wanted O
to O
join O
the O
army B-TER
. O

They O
told O
me O
to O
go O
to O
Kovel B-LOC
. O

So O
I O
went O
to O
Kovel B-LOC
. O

