Protocol O
No O
. O

114 O
11–1–1940 O
Dovid B-PER
M. I-PER
from O
Brok B-LOC
24 O
years O
old O
, O
j B-TER
ournalist B-TER
. O

Left O
Brok B-LOC
on O
September O
6 O
Now O
– O
Vilnius B-LOC
On O
Shabbat O
, O
September O
9 O
, O
Brok B-LOC
was O
set O
on O
fire O
by O
the O
Germans B-TER
. O

They O
poured O
gasoline O
and O
kerosene O
on O
the O
buildings O
and O
afterwards O
set O
them O
on O
fire O
. O

110 O
Jewish O
houses O
were O
burnt O
down O
. O

During O
the O
same O
day O
and O
night O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
shot B-TER
or I-TER
stabbed I-TER
to I-TER
death I-TER
38 O
Jews O
, O
among O
them O
: O
1 O
) O
Mikhalke B-PER
Finkelshteyn I-PER
, O
a O
lathe O
operator O
, O
fifty O
- O
odd O
years O
old O
; O
2 O
) O
Shmulke B-PER
Shmeltsinger I-PER
, O
a O
28 O
- O
year O
old O
bachelor O
; O
3 O
) O
Yidl B-PER
Levartovsky I-PER
, O
a O
butcher O
– O
in O
his O
thirties O
, O
together O
with O
4 O
) O
Moyshele B-PER
Pzsheshtshelenyets I-PER
, O
4 O
years O
old O
, O
his O
nephew B-TER
; O
5 O
) O
Berish B-PER
Yablkavsky I-PER
, O
a O
blacksmith O
, O
around O
60 O
years O
old O
; O
6 O
) O
Arke B-PER
- I-PER
Yosl I-PER
Langleyb I-PER
, O
a O
locksmith O
, O
in O
his O
sixties O
; O
7 O
) O
Mendl B-PER
Treblinsky I-PER
, O
a O
butcher O
, O
sixty O
- O
odd O
years O
old O
; O
8) O
Yitskhok B-PER
Kuperberg I-PER
, O
chairman O
of O
the O
Chevra B-ORG
Kadisha I-ORG
, O
in O
his O
nineties O
; O
9 O
) O
Itshe B-PER
- I-PER
Meyer I-PER
Sheyko I-PER
, O
a O
shopkeeper O
, O
around O
40 O
years O
old O
; O
10 O
) O
Yankev B-PER
- I-PER
Meyer I-PER
Rotbard I-PER
, O
dry O
goods O
store O
keeper O
, O
in O
his O
thirties O
; O
11 O
) O
Anshl B-PER
Pravidle I-PER
, O
a O
tailor O
, O
in O
his O
sixties O
; O
12 O
) O
Itshe B-PER
Shpaker I-PER
, O
an O
elderly O
sick B-TER
lady O
; O
13 O
) O
Hershl B-PER
Tshernovin I-PER
, O
a O
butcher O
, O
in O
his O
forties O
; O
14 O
) O
Yankl B-PER
Migdal I-PER
, O
a O
gravedigger O
and O
shoemaker O
, O
in O
his O
sixties O
; O
his O
son B-TER
15 O
) O
Henekh B-PER
, O
a O
lathe O
operator O
, O
in O
his O
forties O
; O
16 O
) O
Khaym B-PER
Shteynberg I-PER
, O
a O
tailor O
, O
in O
his O
seventies O
; O
17 O
) O
the O
wife B-TER
of O
Noyekh B-PER
Bureykes I-PER
, O
[ O
pregnant O
] O
in O
the O
eighth O
or O
ninth O
month O
, O
stabbed B-TER
to I-TER
death I-TER
when O
she O
was O
laying O
in O
bed O
; O
18 O
) O
Mendl B-PER
Yaspershteyn I-PER
, O
a O
rope O
maker O
, O
around O
80 O
years O
old O
; O
19 O
) O
the O
wife B-TER
of O
Alter B-PER
Eynbinder I-PER
( O
Finkelshteyn O
) O
, O
in O
her O
sixties O
; O
20 O
) O
Markl B-PER
Vaysbrot I-PER
, O
a O
kvass O
producer O
, O
approximately O
70 O
- O
odd O
years O
old O
. O

( O
He O
was O
walking O
on O
the O
street O
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
followed O
him O
in O
a O
car O
until O
they O
ran O
him O
over O
and O
killed B-TER
him O
. O

) O
21 O
) O
Meyer B-PER
, O
the O
son B-TER
of O
Shmulke B-PER
Pzsheshtshelenyets I-PER
, O
a O
butcher O
, O
around O
40 O
years O
old O
; O
22 O
) O
Zishe B-PER
Zshelenyets I-PER
, O
a O
baker O
, O
in O
his O
eighties O
; O
23 O
) O
Motl B-PER
Holand I-PER
, O
a O
merchant O
, O
in O
his O
fifties O
; O
24 O
) O
Hershl B-PER
Surek I-PER
, O
a O
butcher O
, O
in O
his O
forties O
; O
25 O
) O
Mates O
Mendzezshitski O
, O
a O
shoykhet O
[ O
ritual O
slaughterer O
of O
poultry O
] O
, O
fifty O
- O
odd O
years O
old O
; O
26 O
) O
Berish B-PER
Pivko I-PER
, O
a O
merchant O
, O
in O
his O
fifties O
; O
27 O
) O
Yisroel B-PER
- I-PER
Khaym I-PER
Nayman I-PER
, O
a O
shoykhet O
, O
around O
80 O
years O
old O
. O

The O
massacre B-TER
took O
place O
under O
the O
following O
circumstances O
: O
On O
Shabbat O
around O
3 O
, O
4 O
pm O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
ordered O
the O
whole O
population O
to O
gather O
in O
the O
church B-TER
. O

Whoever O
went O
on O
the O
street O
and O
they O
[ O
the O
Germans B-TER
] O
had O
the O
impression O
that O
this O
individual O
was O
not O
walking O
fast O
enough O
was O
shot B-TER
to I-TER
death I-TER
. O

A O
day O
later O
, O
at O
dawn O
, O
12 O
individuals O
were O
shot B-TER
whilst O
saying O
slikhes O
[ O
the O
morning O
prayers O
recited O
before O
or O
during O
the O
High O
Holidays O
] O
at O
Hershl B-PER
Surek I-PER
’s O
house O
. O

Six O
individuals O
were O
shot B-TER
on O
Sunday O
night O
when O
they O
were O
sleeping O
in O
their O
beds O
. O

Two O
individuals O
– O
Itshe B-PER
Shpaker I-PER
and O
Yankev B-PER
- I-PER
Meyer I-PER
Rotbard I-PER
– O
were O
burnt O
alive O
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
first O
stabbed B-TER
Rotbard B-PER
and O
then O
– O
barely O
breathing O
– O
they O
threw B-TER
him I-TER
into I-TER
the I-TER
fire I-TER
. O

The O
Jews O
, O
who O
they O
had O
gathered O
in O
the O
church B-TER
– O
around O
300 O
persons O
– O
, O
were O
escorted O
away O
by O
the O
Germans B-TER
outside O
the O
city O
to O
the O
peasant O
Kovaltshik B-PER
and O
there O
they O
were O
held O
for O
3 O
days O
under O
the O
constant O
threat O
of O
execution B-TER
. O

On O
the O
fourth O
day O
, O
they O
were O
all O
– O
children B-TER
at O
the O
age O
of O
14 O
and O
old O
men O
– O
taken O
into O
the O
barracks O
of O
the O
Ostrów B-LOC
( I-LOC
Mazowiecka I-LOC
) I-LOC
Concentration B-TER
Camp I-TER
. O

Many O
times O
during O
the O
night O
, O
they O
pointed O
at O
these O
Jews O
reflectors O
and O
machine O
guns O
. O

Before O
they O
executed B-TER
the O
announced O
shooting O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
issued O
the O
order O
that O
no O
one O
should O
dare O
to O
cry O
but O
that O
they O
have O
to O
be O
happy O
and O
laugh O
instead O
. O

They O
ordered O
them O
to O
sing O
songs O
. O

At O
the O
same O
time O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
took O
photographs B-TER
of O
the O
Jews O
. O

They O
did O
not O
shoot O
. O

The O
Jews O
were O
held O
without O
food B-TER
for O
three O
days O
and O
hungry B-TER
they O
were O
later O
led O
to O
work B-TER
repairing O
the O
highway O
. O

On O
different O
days O
, O
the O
Jews O
were O
finally O
released O
. O

On O
the O
eve O
of O
Sukkot O
, O
the O
remaining O
Jews O
from O
Brok B-LOC
were O
released O
. O

And O
they O
were O
chased O
across B-TER
the I-TER
border I-TER
to O
Zambrów B-LOC
( O
which O
was O
already O
on O
Soviet B-TER
territory O
) O
. O

Signature O
: O
Missing O
