The O
person O
in O
question O
has O
given O
us O
the O
following O
information O
: O
In O
1941 O
, O
I O
lived O
in O
Kőrösmező B-LOC
, O
my O
parents B-TER
owned O
land O
, O
and O
even O
two O
houses O
, O
I O
had O
three O
brothers O
and O
sisters O
. O

My O
father O
was O
taken O
into O
Poland O
The O
testimony O
is O
not O
precise O
. O

The O
survivor O
was O
taken O
to O
the O
occupied O
zone O
of O
the O
former O
Ukraine O
, O
later O
they O
also O
took O
me O
, O
my O
older O
brother O
, O
and O
my O
older O
sister O
. O

They O
left O
me O
on O
a O
cornfield O
, O
from O
where O
I O
managed O
to O
escape B-TER
and O
came O
back O
to O
Kőrösmező B-LOC
crossing O
the O
Dnyeszter B-LOC
. O

I O
went O
into O
hiding B-TER
for O
nine O
months O
on O
the O
attic O
. O

Once O
an O
Ukrainian B-TER
woman B-TER
noticed O
how O
much O
my O
sister O
cooked O
and O
baked O
and O
got O
suspicious O
. O

In O
the O
meantime O
my O
mother O
died B-TER
and O
as O
it O
started O
to O
be O
very O
dangerous O
staying O
on O
the O
attic O
we O
came O
to O
Budapest B-LOC
. O

As O
far O
as O
I O
know O
, O
it O
was O
a O
Hungarian B-TER
shoemaker O
who O
denounced B-TER
us O
claiming O
that O
someone O
was O
hiding B-TER
on O
the O
attic O
. O

Gendarmes B-TER
searched O
the O
house O
. O

Here O
, O
in O
Budapest B-LOC
the O
Jewish B-ORG
Supportive I-ORG
Office I-ORG
put O
me O
into O
an O
orphanage B-TER
where O
I O
stayed O
for O
two O
years O
, O
when O
I O
was O
summoned O
for O
labourservice B-TER
in O
June O
of O
1944 O
. O

I O
got O
to O
Budafok B-LOC
where O
they O
took B-TER
all O
my O
belongings O
, O
my O
watch O
, O
and O
my O
money O
. O

There O
was O
a O
Hungarian B-TER
warrant B-TER
officer I-TER
who O
beat O
us O
up O
terribly O
. O

He O
made O
the O
people O
from O
the O
orphanage B-TER
standing O
aside O
and O
he O
meant O
to O
send O
us O
home O
, O
but O
later O
changed O
his O
mind O
. O

From O
here O
we O
got O
to O
the O
brick O
factory O
of O
Budakalász B-LOC
and O
with O
the O
ghetto B-TER
for O
the O
people O
from O
the O
agglomeration O
of O
Pest B-LOC
we O
were O
entrained B-TER
74 O
of O
us O
in O
a O
car O
. O

We O
got O
water O
at O
departure O
and O
were O
escorted O
by O
Hungarian B-TER
gendarmes B-TER
till O
Kassa B-LOC
where O
the O
train B-TER
was O
handed O
over O
to O
Germans B-TER
, O
who O
gave O
no O
water O
but O
shot O
into O
to O
the O
freight O
cars O
all O
the O
time O
. O

The O
3rd O
of O
July O
, O
at O
10 O
am O
we O
arrived O
in O
Auschwitz B-LOC
, O
where O
prisoners B-TER
in O
striped O
clothes B-TER
were O
waiting O
for O
us O
. O

We O
had O
to O
leave O
our O
luggage O
in O
the O
cars O
, O
and O
to O
queue O
up O
men B-TER
and O
women B-TER
separately O
. O

I O
was O
selected B-TER
for O
the O
group O
for O
work B-TER
, O
and O
was O
taken O
into O
a O
baths O
where O
they O
cut O
my O
hair O
off O
and O
gave O
me O
striped O
clothes B-TER
. O

We O
were O
put O
into O
a O
barrack O
where O
they O
ordered O
us O
to O
present O
all O
our O
valuables O
because O
they O
claimed O
they O
had O
a O
machine O
that O
could O
see O
through O
us O
and O
if O
they O
found O
anything O
on O
you O
, O
you O
were O
going O
to O
be O
hanged B-TER
. O

We O
got O
into O
Camp B-LOC
A I-LOC
, O
where O
there O
were O
around O
600 O
people B-TER
in O
a O
block O
. O

I O
saw O
the O
crematorium B-TER
and O
often O
felt O
the O
smell O
of O
burnt O
bones O
but O
they O
told O
us O
they O
were O
burning O
old O
clothes B-TER
. O

Every O
day O
twice O
there O
was O
a O
roll B-TER
call I-TER
that O
lasted O
for O
hours O
; O
food B-TER
was O
scarce B-TER
. O

After O
a O
selection B-TER
I O
was O
sent O
to O
Buchenwald B-LOC
. O

The O
journey O
was O
around O
four O
days O
long O
, O
we O
were O
50 O
of O
us O
in O
a O
freight O
car O
, O
they O
gave O
us O
nothing O
to O
eat B-TER
although O
there O
was O
food B-TER
in O
the O
car O
but O
they O
kept O
it O
, O
so O
we O
had O
to O
starve B-TER
all O
the O
way O
. O

When O
we O
arrived O
we O
had O
a O
bath O
and O
received O
a O
loaf O
of O
bread B-TER
, I-TER
margarine I-TER
, O
jam B-TER
and O
sausage B-TER
. O

They O
put O
us O
up O
in O
the O
tent O
camp B-TER
which O
was O
a O
concentration B-TER
camp I-TER
, O
and O
they O
sent O
us O
from O
here O
to O
Remmsdorf B-LOC
for O
work B-TER
. O

The O
journey O
lasted O
again O
three O
days O
, O
we O
were O
50 O
of O
us O
again O
in O
a O
car O
and O
received O
two O
third O
of O
a O
loaf B-TER
, O
margarine B-TER
and O
jam B-TER
. O

The O
day O
after O
that O
we O
arrived O
, O
I O
was O
selected B-TER
for O
work B-TER
in O
a O
petrol O
company O
called O
Brabach B-ORG
where O
I O
worked B-TER
12 O
hours O
a O
day O
. O

The O
lager B-TER
lay O
approximately O
2 O
kilometres O
away O
from O
the O
plant O
. O

650 O
of O
us O
stayed O
in O
a O
barrack B-TER
, O
two O
in O
a O
bed O
. O

Hungarian B-TER
speaking O
SS B-TER
men I-TER
guarded O
us O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
, O
and O
often O
beat O
us O
up O
. O

If O
they O
simply O
did O
not O
like O
someone O
they O
made O
him O
get O
out O
of O
line O
and O
killed B-TER
him O
. O

I O
saw O
once O
that O
they O
killed B-TER
someone O
with O
a O
blow O
in O
the O
outlying O
kommando B-TER
. O

Every O
day O
in O
the O
winter O
there O
were O
40 O
- O
50 O
dead B-TER
bodies I-TER
, O
food B-TER
was O
scarce B-TER
and O
it O
was O
very O
cold O
. O

Death B-TER
found O
a O
fertile O
soil O
here O
. O

Before O
Christmas O
, O
Americans B-TER
bombed B-TER
the O
plant O
but O
lowered O
yellow O
lamps O
from O
the O
aircrafts O
to O
indicate O
the O
place O
of O
the O
lager B-TER
, O
as O
a O
result O
, O
no O
one O
got O
hurt O
. O

For O
a O
while O
I O
served O
a O
Capo B-TER
as O
his O
servant O
. O

Remmsdorf B-LOC
is O
next O
to O
Leipzig B-LOC
. O

Later O
, O
our O
lager B-TER
started O
to O
clear O
debris O
, O
that O
was O
what O
I O
did O
, O
too O
. O

We O
got O
food B-TER
in O
the O
houses O
but O
we O
also O
stole O
when O
we O
could O
not O
get O
hold O
of O
it O
otherwise O
. O

At O
the O
end O
of O
March O
, O
American B-TER
troops O
were O
only O
3 O
- O
4 O
kilometres O
away O
. O

That O
night O
at O
1 O
am O
they O
quickly O
entrained O
us O
and O
we O
started O
off O
in O
the O
direction O
of O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
. O

We O
came O
till O
Tarienburg O
by O
train B-TER
when O
low O
- O
flying O
airplanes O
bombed B-TER
two O
of O
our O
railway O
engines O
. O

We O
had O
350 O
sick B-TER
people B-TER
. O

Those O
who O
were O
not O
sick B-TER
tried O
to O
ran B-TER
away I-TER
; O
we O
went O
to O
the O
village O
, O
and O
by O
the O
time O
we O
came O
back O
we O
saw O
that O
dead B-TER
bodies O
were O
being O
carrying O
: O
three O
cars O
were O
full O
of O
dead B-TER
bodies O
. O

We O
asked O
what O
had O
happened O
and O
were O
informed O
that O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
had O
shot B-TER
those O
unfortunate O
. O

At O
this O
point O
we O
started O
walking B-TER
. O

Those O
who O
could O
not O
keep O
pace O
and O
sat O
down O
at O
the O
sides O
of O
the O
road O
were O
cruelly O
shot O
by O
the O
guards O
. O

When O
we O
started O
our O
journey O
we O
were O
in O
3,800 O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
, O
when O
we O
arrived O
to O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
, O
there O
were O
only O
800 O
of O
us O
alive O
, O
but O
around O
the O
half O
died B-TER
of O
typhus B-TER
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
. O

The O
9th O
of O
May O
, O
the O
Red B-ORG
Army I-ORG
liberated B-TER
us O
in O
the O
town O
. O

I O
stayed O
three O
weeks O
in O
Theresienstadt B-LOC
before O
we O
left O
for O
Prague B-LOC
already O
in O
a O
bigger O
group O
. O

In O
Prague B-LOC
I O
spent O
three O
weeks O
at O
the O
Red B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
, O
where O
we O
were O
disinfected O
and O
provided O
with O
everything O
good O
. O

I O
came O
home O
through O
Prague B-LOC
and O
Pozsony B-LOC
. O

My O
future O
plan O
: O
I O
return O
to O
the O
orphanage B-TER
. O

