The O
mass B-TER
massacre I-TER
of O
the O
Jews O
in O
Hrubieszów B-LOC
and O
Chełm B-LOC
Told O
by O
D. B-PER
Ravin I-PER
in O
: O
The O
Blood O
Cries O
for O
Vengeance O
! O
: O
What O
Victims O
tell O
about O
the O
Fascist B-TER
Atrocities O
in O
the O
Occupied B-TER
Poland B-LOC
, O
collected O
and O
assembled O
by O
L. B-PER
Kvitko I-PER
, O
Y. B-PER
Nusinov I-PER
, O
and O
Y. B-PER
Katsnelson I-PER
; O
Forword O
: O
Shakhne B-PER
Epshteyn I-PER
( O
Moscow B-LOC
: O
Der O
Emes O
, O
1941 O
) O
, O
46–52 O
The O
path O
of O
the O
Hitlerite B-TER
bandites O
over O
Polish B-TER
soil O
was O
drawn O
with O
streams O
of O
blood O
from O
the O
innocent O
civilian O
population O
. O

In O
the O
second O
week O
of O
their O
invasion O
into O
Warsaw B-LOC
, O
the O
Hitlerite B-TER
gangs O
had O
already O
ejected O
onto O
the O
streets O
residents O
of O
whole O
neighborhoods O
and O
did O
not O
permit O
anyone O
to O
take O
anything O
with O
them O
from O
their O
own O
belongings O
. O

In O
this O
vein O
, O
they O
issued O
a O
decree B-TER
, O
for O
instance O
, O
that O
residents O
of O
the O
whole O
Novolipky B-LOC
Street I-LOC
to I-LOC
the I-LOC
corner I-LOC
of I-LOC
Karmelitska I-LOC
are O
to O
move O
out O
within O
fifteen O
minutes O
and O
every O
person O
who O
they O
will O
meet O
there O
after O
those O
fifteen O
minutes O
will O
be O
shot B-TER
dead I-TER
. O

During O
the O
nights O
, O
special O
gangs O
used O
to O
command O
residents O
of O
single O
buildings O
to O
move O
out O
, O
beat O
the O
residents O
up O
terribly O
and O
took B-TER
everything I-TER
that I-TER
could I-TER
be I-TER
taken I-TER
. O

At O
the O
same O
time O
, O
they O
ridiculed O
the O
people O
in O
the O
most O
horrific O
and O
refined O
ways O
. O

– O
To O
whom O
do O
the O
things O
in O
the O
apartment O
belong O
? O
– O
the O
eldest O
of O
the O
gang O
would O
usually O
ask O
, O
who O
was O
in O
charge O
of O
the O
attack O
. O

– O
Ours O
– O
the O
residents O
would O
reply O
innocently O
. O

The O
bandits O
usually O
attacked O
everyone O
without O
exceptions O
– O
men B-TER
, O
children B-TER
and O
women B-TER
– O
and O
beat O
them O
up O
cruelly O
until O
it O
occurred O
to O
one O
of O
the O
victims B-TER
to O
say O
: O
Apologies O
, O
the O
things O
are O
not O
ours O
, O
they O
are O
yours O
. O

Those O
nighttime O
attacks O
became O
the O
terror O
of O
Warsaw B-LOC
. O

Especially O
horrible O
in O
inhumanity O
and O
open O
sadism O
was O
the O
evening O
hunt O
. O

At O
8 O
pm O
in O
the O
summer O
, O
not O
one O
civilian O
dared O
to O
be O
on O
the O
street O
anymore O
. O

The O
Hitlerite B-TER
cannibals O
used O
this O
situation O
to O
entertain O
themselves O
. O

They O
were O
usually O
walking O
on O
the O
streets O
drunk O
, O
tipsy O
, O
with O
guns O
in O
their O
hands O
, O
and O
if O
they O
noticed O
someone O
one O
minute O
after O
8 O
pm O
on O
the O
streets O
, O
possibly O
in O
front O
of O
the O
gate O
of O
his O
/ O
her O
home O
, O
they O
immediately O
aimed O
their O
guns O
at O
the O
person O
and O
shot B-TER
without O
any O
warning O
. O

In O
this O
way O
, O
the O
mother B-TER
of O
one O
of O
my O
acquaintances O
living O
in O
the O
first O
numbers O
of O
Muranov B-LOC
Street I-LOC
was O
shot B-TER
dead I-TER
, O
a O
elderly O
weak O
lady B-TER
who O
did O
not O
manage O
to O
run O
through O
the O
gate O
fast O
enough O
. O

The O
life O
of O
those O
people O
who O
were O
dragged O
to O
work O
by O
the O
Hitlerite B-TER
scoundrels O
turned O
completely O
chaotic O
. O

I O
put O
work O
in O
quotation O
marks O
because O
most O
of O
the O
time O
people O
were O
simply O
taken O
to O
be O
tortured B-TER
. O

In O
this O
way O
I O
witnessed O
the O
following O
case O
in O
the O
shtetele O
Miechów B-LOC
near O
Lublin B-LOC
, O
for O
instance O
, O
where O
I O
was O
caught O
by O
the O
Hitlerite B-TER
gangs O
for O
the O
first O
time O
during O
my O
wanderings O
across O
Poland B-TER
. O

As O
soon O
as O
the O
Hitlerites B-TER
invaded O
the O
shtetl B-LOC
, O
they O
first O
made O
a O
visit O
in O
the O
Jewish B-LOC
besmedresh B-LOC
Prayer O
and O
study O
house O
. O

and O
destroyed O
in O
a O
vandalic O
way O
everything O
that O
was O
there O
: O
they O
shattered O
the O
window O
panes O
, O
broke O
the O
walls O
into O
pieces O
, O
broke O
the O
clock O
, O
the O
mantle O
lamps O
, O
the O
cupboards O
and O
ripped O
all O
books O
and O
Torah O
scrolls O
apart O
. O

Afterwards O
, O
they O
rampaged O
through O
the O
city B-LOC
, O
beat O
up O
every O
young O
person O
they O
bumped O
into O
, O
and O
tore B-TER
off I-TER
the I-TER
beards I-TER
of O
the O
elder O
ones O
. O

Around O
three O
o’clock O
, O
they O
started O
going O
from O
house O
to O
house O
in O
order O
to O
summon O
people O
for O
work B-TER
. O

The O
taking O
for O
work B-TER
turned O
into O
a O
hunt O
by O
wild O
animals O
for O
a O
handful O
of O
innocent O
people O
. O

From O
all O
sides O
of O
the O
shtetl B-LOC
, O
the O
wild O
bandites O
came O
running O
with O
savage O
, O
inhumane O
howling O
, O
waving O
with O
thick O
sticks O
in O
their O
hands O
, O
and O
hunting O
people O
who O
in O
agony O
were O
running O
aimlessly O
back O
and O
forth O
. O

Finally O
, O
they O
rounded O
up O
a O
few O
hundred O
men B-TER
, O
old O
and O
young O
, O
almost O
completely O
undressed O
them O
, O
took B-TER
everything I-TER
what I-TER
they I-TER
owned I-TER
away I-TER
from I-TER
them I-TER
, O
and O
loaded O
them O
on O
trucks O
. O

All O
of O
this O
was O
, O
of O
course O
, O
accompanied O
by O
blows O
and O
vile O
insults O
. O

The O
most O
horrific O
part O
, O
however O
, O
started O
only O
at O
the O
work O
itself O
which O
consisted O
of O
pulling B-TER
in I-TER
heavy I-TER
trucks I-TER
into I-TER
a I-TER
deep I-TER
, I-TER
muddy I-TER
puddle I-TER
and I-TER
then I-TER
to I-TER
drag I-TER
it I-TER
out I-TER
again I-TER
, O
or O
it O
consisted O
of O
running B-TER
after I-TER
a I-TER
bicycle I-TER
which I-TER
was I-TER
going I-TER
as I-TER
fast I-TER
as I-TER
it I-TER
could I-TER
. O

The O
latter O
was O
mostly O
carried O
out O
during O
the O
breaks O
from O
work O
or O
after O
the O
work O
like O
an O
additional O
reward O
. O

Taken O
together O
, O
this O
whole O
system O
of O
work O
was O
called O
the O
education O
into O
people O
fit O
for O
work O
. O

The O
method B-TER
of O
this O
very O
education O
was O
as O
follows O
. O

The O
group O
, O
which O
was O
not O
capable O
to O
drag B-TER
out I-TER
the I-TER
truck I-TER
from I-TER
the I-TER
deep I-TER
puddle I-TER
very I-TER
fast I-TER
, O
had O
to O
immerse B-TER
itself I-TER
into I-TER
the I-TER
puddle I-TER
under I-TER
heavy I-TER
blows I-TER
and I-TER
to I-TER
drink I-TER
of I-TER
it I-TER
afterwards I-TER
. O

One O
thin O
, O
tortured B-TER
boy B-TER
from O
Puławy B-LOC
almost O
choked O
after O
such O
a O
puddle O
- O
bath O
and O
drink O
. O

It O
was O
terrible O
to O
watch O
how O
the O
boy B-TER
threw O
up O
mud O
and O
dirt O
. O

Hitlerite B-TER
animals O
stood O
around O
him O
and O
swelled O
up O
with O
delight O
: O
– O
He O
did O
it O
well O
, O
he O
did O
it O
properly O
! O
... O
Several O
Germans B-TER
with O
whips B-TER
ran I-TER
after I-TER
the I-TER
people I-TER
who I-TER
had I-TER
to I-TER
overtake I-TER
the I-TER
bicycle I-TER
and O
each O
one O
who O
lagged O
behind O
was O
carried O
to O
a O
side O
half O
dead O
. O

An O
elderly O
Jews O
of O
approximately O
sixty O
years O
of O
age O
was O
not O
able O
to O
run O
after O
[ O
the O
bicycle O
] O
at O
all O
and O
lagged O
behind O
. O

For O
this O
, O
he O
was O
beaten O
up O
horribly O
and O
remained O
lying O
on O
the O
floor O
. O

Later O
, O
he O
disappeared O
entirely O
and O
nobody O
dared O
to O
ask O
where O
he O
is O
. O

The O
Hitlerite B-TER
scoundrels O
reached O
the O
highest O
level O
of O
barbarity O
and O
lousiness O
with O
the O
so O
- O
called O
duel O
. O

They O
selected O
two O
victims B-TER
and O
commanded O
one O
of O
them O
to O
beat O
up O
the O
other O
. O

The O
one O
who O
beats O
and O
batters O
the O
other O
better O
will O
be O
released O
. O

Most O
of O
the O
time O
, O
the O
selected O
for O
this O
a O
Pole B-TER
and O
a O
Jew O
. O

Already O
in O
the O
first O
days O
of O
their O
occupation B-TER
of O
Poland B-LOC
, O
in O
the O
large O
forced B-LOC
labor I-LOC
camp I-LOC
close I-LOC
to I-LOC
Mińsk I-LOC
Mazowiecki I-LOC
, O
the O
bandites O
applied O
all O
of O
these O
methods B-TER
of I-TER
humiliation I-TER
of O
the O
local O
residents O
and O
of O
reducing O
them O
to O
the O
level O
of O
persecuted O
dogs O
. O

In O
this O
very O
camp B-LOC
near I-LOC
Mińsk I-LOC
Mazowiecki I-LOC
, O
a O
lot O
of O
people O
were O
shot B-TER
dead I-TER
for O
no O
reason O
, O
simply O
for O
entertainment O
and O
savage O
debauchery O
. O

So O
, O
for O
example O
, O
the O
brother B-TER
of O
the O
friend O
of O
mine O
called O
V.K. O
from O
Otwock B-LOC
was O
murdered B-TER
there O
together O
with O
a O
Polish B-TER
worker B-TER
simply O
because O
they O
dared O
without O
asking O
to O
take O
shelter O
under O
a O
roof O
during O
a O
rain O
. O

Generally O
, O
the O
murder B-TER
of O
the O
local O
population O
by O
the O
Hitlerite B-TER
cannibals O
became O
a O
daily O
phenomenon O
. O

The O
ease O
with O
with O
they O
did O
it O
was O
even O
more O
terrible O
and O
inhumane O
than O
the O
acts O
of O
murder B-TER
themselves I-TER
. O

With O
the O
very O
calmness O
with O
with O
one O
slaughters O
a O
little O
calf O
they O
massacred B-TER
two O
hundred O
people O
in O
Wawer B-LOC
, O
a O
shtetl B-LOC
south O
of O
Warsaw B-LOC
, O
simply O
because O
they O
had O
found O
the O
dead B-TER
body I-TER
of O
a O
German B-TER
soldier B-TER
near O
Wawer B-LOC
. O

Two O
hundred O
for O
one O
– O
this O
is O
what O
the O
brown O
bandits O
decided O
, O
and O
in O
bright O
daylight O
, O
they O
strolled O
from O
house O
to O
house O
of O
the O
Wawer B-LOC
residents O
, O
who O
did O
not O
suspect O
anything O
, O
took O
out O
several O
people O
, O
even O
mothers B-TER
breastfeeding O
their O
children B-TER
, O
and O
shot B-TER
all I-TER
of I-TER
them I-TER
dead I-TER
. O

The O
most O
brutal O
and O
savage O
of O
all O
was O
the O
relationship O
of O
the O
Hitlerite B-TER
murderers B-TER
to O
the O
Jewish O
population O
. O

No O
normal O
person O
could O
think O
of O
such O
savage B-TER
humiliations I-TER
and I-TER
pranks I-TER
as O
the O
ones O
the O
bandits O
came O
up O
with O
. O

I O
want O
to O
tell O
here O
of O
the O
mass B-TER
massacre I-TER
of O
the O
Jews O
in O
Hrubieszów B-LOC
. O

As O
I O
was O
told O
later O
on O
, O
many O
much O
more O
horrible O
massacres B-TER
took O
place O
after O
I O
had O
escaped B-TER
from O
Hitler B-PER
’s I-PER
hell O
. O

But O
the O
one O
I O
am O
going O
to O
talk O
about O
remains O
engraved O
into O
my O
memory O
with O
an O
especially O
sharp O
pain O
. O

Two O
cities O
were O
famous O
for O
their O
comparative O
calmness O
and O
security O
: O
Chełm B-LOC
and O
Hrubieszów B-LOC
. O

The O
local O
commanders O
– O
Jews O
said O
– O
are O
good O
people O
and O
stick O
up O
for O
the O
residents O
. O

When O
I O
was O
in O
Chełm B-LOC
on O
the O
eve O
of O
the O
terrible O
event O
, O
I O
really O
had O
the O
impression O
that O
I O
was O
in O
a O
city B-LOC
in O
which O
endless O
numbers O
of O
crazy O
, O
exasperated O
dogs O
ran O
around O
, O
but O
with O
bridles O
around O
their O
muzzles O
. O

With O
malice O
and O
fury O
, O
the O
Hitler B-ORG
Youth I-ORG
and O
Gestapo B-ORG
men I-ORG
jumped O
at O
each O
and O
every O
one O
– O
a O
push O
here O
, O
a O
curse O
there O
, O
but O
it O
did O
not O
go O
further O
. O

People O
were O
take O
to O
work O
according O
to O
a O
list O
. O

Many O
Jews O
from O
Chełm B-LOC
told O
me O
: O
it O
is O
indeed O
very O
miserable O
but O
we O
will O
persevere O
. O

Until O
this O
one O
Thursday O
evening O
when O
an O
order B-TER
was O
issued O
that O
tomorrow O
, O
on O
Friday O
in O
the O
morning O
, O
all O
men B-TER
of O
Jewish O
nationality O
between O
16 O
and O
60 O
of O
age O
shall O
gather O
in O
front O
of O
the O
city B-LOC
council I-LOC
. O

Who O
stays O
at O
home O
, O
will O
be O
shot B-TER
dead I-TER
. O

On O
the O
next O
day O
, O
up O
to O
twelve O
hundred O
people O
gathered O
on O
the O
town B-LOC
square I-LOC
. O

Around O
10 O
am O
, O
they O
were O
surrounded O
by O
large O
divisions O
of O
soldiers B-TER
and O
Gestapo B-ORG
men I-ORG
. O

They O
took O
the O
documents O
from O
everyone O
and O
tore O
them O
apart O
, O
and O
after O
that O
chased O
them O
to O
the O
road O
which O
leads O
to O
Hrubieszów B-LOC
. O

When O
after O
the O
first O
ten O
kilometers O
the O
elderly O
and O
weak O
started O
to O
lag O
behind O
, O
the O
Hitlerite B-TER
bandits O
shot B-TER
them O
. O

Seeing O
that O
, O
many O
of O
the O
crowd O
started O
to O
run O
ahead O
and O
a O
terrible O
panic O
broke O
out O
. O

And O
this O
is O
exactly O
what O
the O
Fascist B-TER
murderers O
were O
waiting O
for O
. O

Without O
pause O
, O
they O
shot B-TER
at O
the O
people O
in O
the O
back O
with O
a O
savage O
enjoyment O
forcing O
the O
whole O
crowd O
in O
this O
way O
to O
run O
. O

Sensing O
death B-TER
in O
their O
backs O
, O
the O
people O
tore O
off O
their O
clothes B-TER
, O
mustered O
their O
last O
strengths O
, O
and O
went O
insane O
out O
of O
fear O
. O

Many O
threw O
themselves O
into O
the O
brooks O
they O
encountered O
on O
their O
way O
. O

But O
not O
everyone O
managed O
to O
do O
that O
. O

From O
Chełm B-LOC
to O
Hrubieszów B-LOC
it O
is O
fifty O
kilometers O
and O
this O
savage O
, O
bloody O
hunt O
persisted O
throughout O
the O
whole O
way O
. O

Toward O
evening O
, O
half O
of O
the O
unfortunate O
arrived O
in O
Hrubieszów B-LOC
. O

There O
, O
all O
of O
them O
were O
locked O
in O
in O
a O
few O
barns O
and O
were O
prohibited O
to O
make O
any O
sound O
whatsoever O
. O

At O
the O
same O
time O
, O
when O
they O
chased O
the O
Jews O
from O
Chełm B-LOC
to O
Hrubieszów B-LOC
, O
the O
commander O
in O
Hrubieszów B-LOC
issued O
the O
same O
decree B-TER
that O
tomorrow O
, O
i.e. O
on O
Shabbat O
morning O
, O
all O
Jews O
– O
men B-TER
between O
16 O
and O
60 O
years O
– O
have O
to O
gather O
at O
the O
town B-LOC
square I-LOC
. O

In O
Hrubieszów B-LOC
, O
the O
whole O
crowd O
arrived O
dressed O
up O
for O
the O
Shabbat O
, O
and O
the O
rabbis B-TER
and O
ritual O
slaughterers O
in O
shtraymlekh B-TER
Traditional O
round O
fur O
hat O
. O

and O
their O
long O
coarse O
coats B-TER
. O

At O
that O
point O
, O
many O
could O
have O
still O
been O
saved O
because O
the O
Ukrainian B-TER
mayor O
of O
the O
city O
had O
whispered O
to O
the O
head O
of O
Jewish B-TER
community I-TER
that O
it O
looks O
bad O
for O
the O
Jews O
. O

But O
the O
respectable O
Jew O
, O
instead O
of O
communicating O
this O
to O
everyone O
, O
saved O
his O
own O
skin O
first O
and O
ran O
away O
. O

Only O
to O
those O
he O
bumped O
into O
on O
his O
way O
did O
he O
warn O
that O
they O
should O
run O
. O

In O
this O
way O
, O
a O
crowd O
of O
approximately O
six O
hundred O
men B-TER
gathered O
in O
Hrubieszów B-LOC
– O
a O
crowd O
which O
they O
started O
to O
chase O
to O
the O
Soviet B-TER
border B-TER
together O
with O
the O
Jews O
from O
Chełm B-LOC
. O

Up O
to O
its O
knee O
in O
mud O
, O
the O
crowd O
dragged O
itself O
onward O
and O
onward O
for O
a O
whole O
day O
with O
great O
difficulties O
and O
united O
in O
agony O
. O

For O
the O
night O
, O
they O
were O
all O
chased O
into O
a O
muddy O
gutter O
at O
the O
side O
which O
reached O
up O
to O
the O
neck O
. O

In O
the O
night O
, O
forty O
men B-TER
died B-TER
, O
froze B-TER
to I-TER
death I-TER
or O
drowned B-TER
, O
among O
them O
all O
of O
the O
functionaries O
of O
Jewish B-TER
communal I-TER
life I-TER
in O
Hrubieszów B-LOC
. O

On O
the O
next O
day O
, O
the O
bloody O
hunt O
started O
again O
even O
with O
more O
savagery O
and O
cruelty O
. O

Hundreds O
of O
people O
were O
shot B-TER
in O
a O
bandit O
- O
like O
way O
from O
behind O
, O
among O
them O
also O
my O
loyal O
friend O
, O
the O
lawyer B-TER
B. O
, O
and O
his O
father B-TER
- I-TER
in I-TER
- I-TER
law I-TER
, O
an O
elderly O
man B-TER
, O
whom O
he O
had O
to O
assist O
walking O
. O

The O
cannibals B-TER
were O
not O
satisfied O
with O
the O
shootings B-TER
on O
the O
way O
alone O
. O

Not O
far O
from O
the O
border B-TER
, O
in O
a O
grove O
, O
where O
they O
halted O
to O
rest O
a O
little O
, O
they O
played O
a O
little O
game O
simply O
for O
entertainment O
’s O
sake O
and O
shot B-TER
whomever O
they O
felt O
the O
urge O
to O
shoot B-TER
. O

They O
did O
the O
same O
thing O
right O
at O
the O
Soviet B-TER
border B-TER
. O

They O
divided O
the O
eight O
hundred O
remaining O
individuals O
into O
two O
groups O
and O
they O
turned O
to O
the O
dejected O
group O
with O
the O
most O
disgraceful O
, O
cynical O
calmness O
saying O
: O
– O
So O
, O
now O
for O
our O
goodbyes O
, O
demonstrate O
your O
courage O
and O
name O
eleven O
volunteers O
to O
be O
shot B-TER
. O

If O
not O
, O
we O
ourselves O
are O
going O
to O
select O
twice O
as O
many O
. O

In O
this O
way O
, O
the O
terrible O
massacre B-TER
of O
Jews O
from O
Chełm B-LOC
and O
Hrubieszów B-LOC
the O
took O
place O
. O

When O
the O
population O
of O
Hrubieszów B-LOC
learned O
about O
happened O
to O
their O
very O
own O
from O
the O
few O
that O
had O
managed O
to O
escape B-TER
– O
the O
women B-TER
, O
mothers B-TER
and O
children B-TER
– O
, O
the O
whole O
city O
broke O
out O
into O
a O
wild O
clamor O
. O

The O
good O
commander O
did O
prevent O
the O
women B-TER
and O
mothers B-TER
from O
crying O
in O
length O
. O

In O
order O
not O
to O
waste O
any O
time O
, O
he O
sent O
out O
people O
to O
collect O
the O
old O
taxes O
from O
Polish B-TER
times O
with O
all O
of O
his O
German B-TER
precision O
. O

