B. O
226 O
- O
English O
Translation O
Saturday O
morning O
31 O
December O
1938 O
was O
sent O
to O
Vienna B-LOC
as O
courier O
of O
the O
Nederl B-ORG
. I-ORG

Kinder I-ORG
Comité I-ORG
( I-ORG
Dutch I-ORG
Children I-ORG
’s I-ORG
Committee I-ORG
) I-ORG
. O

In O
accordance O
with O
my O
instructions O
I O
went O
to O
The B-ORG
Society I-ORG
of I-ORG
Friends I-ORG
, O
Singerstr B-LOC
. I-LOC

16 I-LOC
, O
for O
a O
meeting O
with O
Herr O
Lipopsky B-PER
, O
in O
charge O
of O
the O
department O
for O
kindertransports B-ORG
to O
England B-LOC
and O
the O
Netherlands B-LOC
, O
who O
was O
not O
available O
, O
however O
. O

Then O
I O
visited O
Herr O
Gildemeester B-PER
, O
for O
whom O
I O
had O
been O
given O
a O
message O
. O

He O
was O
not O
, O
however O
, O
inclined O
to O
discuss O
anything O
as O
he O
presumed O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
would O
hear O
everything O
and O
that O
could O
have O
unpleasant O
consequences O
for O
him O
. O

Herr O
G. B-PER
brought O
me O
to O
the O
Aktion B-ORG
- I-ORG
Gildemeester I-ORG
[ O
Nazi O
- O
run O
operation O
to O
evacuate O
Jews O
from O
Vienna O
] O
office O
, O
where O
I O
spent O
some O
hours O
and O
was O
told O
the O
following O
: O
It O
is O
as O
difficult O
for O
the O
emigration B-TER
offices O
to O
get O
Jews O
over O
the O
German B-ORG
border O
as O
it O
is O
to O
get O
admission O
for O
them O
to O
another O
country O
. O

Each O
Jew O
means O
money O
for O
the O
German B-ORG
government I-ORG
, O
how O
they O
get O
it O
and O
by O
what O
means O
is O
immaterial O
to O
them O
. O

Even O
when O
all O
papers O
are O
in O
order O
, O
ticket O
paid O
, O
etc O
. O

the O
emigrants B-TER
are O
sent O
back O
from O
the O
station O
and O
[ O
they O
] O
try O
to O
get O
more O
money O
out O
of O
them O
. O

Furthermore O
the O
head O
of O
the O
Gildemeester B-ORG
office I-ORG
, O
Herr O
Fasal B-PER
, O
had O
many O
complaints O
against O
the O
director O
of O
the O
Kultusgemeinde B-ORG
[ O
Jewish O
community O
] O
, O
Herr O
Löwenherz B-PER
, O
who O
according O
to O
him O
not O
only O
paid O
[ O
no O
] O
attention O
to O
the O
urgency O
of O
cases O
( O
in O
this O
case O
pure O
Jewish O
children B-TER
) O
but O
was O
very O
partial O
in O
his O
choice O
for O
the O
transports B-TER
e.g. O
Polish B-TER
Jews I-TER
and O
Zionists B-TER
enjoyed O
his O
favour O
. O

According O
to O
Herr O
Fasal B-PER
, O
that O
is O
also O
the O
reason O
for O
much O
disagreement O
between O
the O
Kultusgemeinde B-ORG
and O
the O
Gildemeester B-ORG
office I-ORG
, O
and O
cooperation O
is O
particularly O
bad O
. O

It O
is O
evident O
that O
children B-TER
who O
are O
in O
entirely O
bad O
circumstances O
and O
who O
have O
obtained O
permission O
from O
the O
Netherl B-LOC
. O

government O
to O
reside O
in O
Holland B-LOC
still O
do O
not O
come O
with O
the O
transport B-TER
although O
others O
are O
arbitrarily O
chosen O
in O
their O
place O
. O

This O
is O
laid O
down O
by O
the O
Kultusgemeinde B-ORG
. O

The O
Nederl B-ORG
. I-ORG

Comité I-ORG
is O
under O
the O
impression O
that O
these O
children O
have O
already O
been O
sent O
away O
and O
will O
do O
no O
more O
about O
them O
. O

Not O
cases O
in O
the O
greatest O
need O
, O
therefore O
, O
but O
favouritism O
. O

One O
of O
the O
difficulties O
at O
the O
moment O
concerns O
the O
emigration B-TER
of O
boys B-TER
of O
16 O
and O
17 O
years O
, O
as O
they O
are O
in O
continual O
danger O
of O
being O
sent O
to O
concentration B-TER
camps I-TER
, O
mainly O
if O
they O
are O
of O
large O
stature O
. O

One O
can O
guess O
what O
this O
indicates O
for O
these O
children B-TER
when O
one O
thinks O
that O
they O
undergo O
the O
same O
treatment O
as O
adult O
men B-TER
. O

On O
Sunday O
afternoon O
I O
went O
to O
the O
Swedish B-ORG
Mission I-ORG
and O
there O
heard O
about O
the O
possibilities O
of O
emigration B-TER
to O
Sweden B-LOC
. O

These O
are O
also O
not O
great O
. O

There O
are O
already O
many O
children B-TER
from O
Czechoslovakia B-LOC
there O
. O

7 O
January O
a O
transport B-TER
of O
100 O
Evangelical B-TER
children B-TER
left O
and O
during O
January O
the O
Kultusgemeinde B-ORG
organised O
a O
further O
transport B-ORG
of I-ORG
Jewish I-ORG
children I-ORG
to O
Sweden B-LOC
. O

One O
hundred O
families B-TER
have O
gone O
to O
Ecuador B-LOC
, O
who O
can O
find O
a O
life O
there O
. O

Thereafter O
I O
was O
at O
the O
Gildemeester B-ORG
office O
for O
some O
time O
again O
, O
where O
I O
was O
told O
about O
a O
great O
plan O
for O
emigration B-TER
to O
Abyssinia B-LOC
. O

The O
costs O
of O
it O
are O
100,000 O
pounds O
and O
would O
be O
carried O
out O
by O
England B-LOC
. O

Given O
Mussolini B-PER
’s O
attitude O
to O
the O
Jews O
and O
the O
climate O
there O
, O
many O
think O
this O
is O
an O
impractical O
plan O
, O
anyway O
unsuited O
to O
providing O
emigrants B-TER
with O
a O
permanent O
place O
to O
stay O
. O

Monday O
morning O
I O
found O
Herr O
Lipopsky B-PER
and O
he O
told O
me O
the O
following O
about O
the O
Gildemeester B-ORG
office O
: O
This O
office O
has O
asked O
the O
committees B-TER
of O
all O
countries O
to O
become O
officially O
recognised O
as O
an O
emigration B-TER
office O
. O

None O
of O
these O
committees B-TER
has O
complied O
with O
this O
and O
therefore O
the O
G. B-ORG
office O
is O
trying O
to O
achieve O
independence O
as O
far O
as O
possible O
. O

Favouritism O
plays O
a O
large O
part O
here O
too O
. O

On O
the O
first O
transport B-ORG
to O
Holland B-LOC
e.g. O
all O
20 O
children B-TER
were O
allocated O
by O
the O
G. B-ORG
office O
, O
children B-TER
of O
its O
own O
staff O
. O

Furthermore O
, O
they O
arbitrarily O
take O
everyone O
who O
turns O
up O
, O
whilst O
it O
is O
emphatically O
stated O
that O
the O
K. B-ORG
G. I-ORG
[ O
Kultusgemeinde B-ORG
] O
looks O
after O
Jews O
, O
The B-ORG
Society I-ORG
of I-ORG
Friends I-ORG
after O
Evangelicals B-TER
. O

Because O
of O
this O
the O
work O
is O
very O
thwarted O
, O
the O
children B-TER
have O
to O
report O
to O
different O
offices O
, O
and O
these O
meanwhile O
do O
not O
know O
from O
each O
other O
if O
the O
children B-TER
have O
gone O
with O
a O
transport B-TER
or O
not O
. O

The O
only O
thing O
that O
the O
G. B-ORG
office O
looks O
after O
for O
the O
K.G. B-ORG
and O
for O
the O
Soc B-ORG
. I-ORG

of I-ORG
Friends I-ORG
are O
the O
group O
permits O
with O
which O
the O
children B-TER
travel O
. O

The O
cooperation O
between O
the O
G. B-ORG
office O
and O
Herr O
L. B-PER
is O
thus O
limited O
too O
, O
and O
there O
is O
no O
talk O
of O
mutual O
working O
. O

In O
case O
of O
the O
greatest O
need O
they O
get O
in O
touch O
with O
each O
other O
. O

From O
Herr O
L. B-PER
I O
had O
the O
impression O
that O
Herr O
G. B-PER
himself O
is O
an O
entirely O
trustworthy O
person O
, O
but O
he O
is O
used O
as O
a O
tool O
by O
the O
staff O
of O
his O
office O
. O

Three O
weeks O
ago O
Herr O
G. B-PER
also O
went O
away O
as O
he O
had O
nothing O
more O
to O
say O
at O
the O
office O
and O
he O
was O
recalled O
again O
because O
his O
name O
and O
possible O
contacts O
were O
of O
great O
importance O
to O
the O
office O
. O

Some O
things O
were O
confiscated B-TER
from O
the O
till O
, O
though O
it O
is O
hoped O
to O
get O
these O
back O
again O
on O
15 O
January O
; O
according O
to O
Herr O
L. B-PER
this O
is O
not O
likely O
. O

The O
Gestapo B-ORG
had O
also O
been O
at O
the O
house O
of O
The B-ORG
Society I-ORG
of I-ORG
Friends I-ORG
and O
looked O
through O
all O
the O
books O
, O
which O
seemed O
not O
to O
indicate O
much O
, O
however O
, O
and O
they O
were O
left O
alone O
. O

It O
sometimes O
appears O
that O
the O
children B-TER
who O
have O
transport B-ORG
opportunities O
and O
are O
on O
Herr O
L. B-PER
’s O
list O
can O
not O
be O
found O
any O
more O
. O

This O
happens O
because O
the O
families B-TER
are O
often O
suddenly O
displaced O
from O
their O
house O
and O
then O
no O
longer O
have O
another O
fixed O
address O
. O

This O
explains O
sending O
other O
children B-TER
than O
those O
who O
are O
given O
to O
Herr O
L. B-PER
by O
the O
Nederl B-ORG
. I-ORG

Comité I-ORG
. O

Then O
Herr O
L. B-PER
went O
with O
me O
to O
the O
Swedish B-ORG
Mission I-ORG
to O
take O
lists O
of O
Evang B-TER
. I-TER

children B-TER
who O
could O
possibly O
emigrate B-TER
. O

In O
the O
waiting O
room O
there O
I O
saw O
various O
cases O
of O
frozen O
limbs O
as O
a O
result O
of O
spells O
in O
a O
concentration B-TER
camp I-TER
, O
incl O
. O

one O
young O
man B-TER
whose O
hands O
remained O
thick O
and O
blue O
. O

He O
had O
already O
been O
in O
Dachau B-LOC
twice O
and O
was O
in O
danger O
of O
being O
arrested B-TER
all O
the O
time O
. O

Further O
variously O
crippled O
men O
( O
frozen O
feet O
) O
and O
one O
man B-TER
with O
a O
totally O
bandaged O
head O
( O
frozen O
ears O
) O
. O

Many O
cases O
occur O
particularly O
as O
the O
men B-TER
are O
sometimes O
made O
to O
exercise O
day O
and O
night O
scantily O
clothed O
in O
a O
cotton O
jacket O
and O
trousers O
with O
a O
pair O
of O
shoes O
and O
bald O
shaven O
uncovered O
head O
. O

Whoever O
puts O
his O
hands O
in O
his O
pockets O
from O
the O
cold O
is O
struck O
with O
a O
club O
. O

Herr O
L. B-PER
told O
me O
afterwards O
that O
in O
a O
transport B-TER
to O
the O
camp B-TER
200 O
men B-TER
were O
loaded O
into O
a O
cattle B-TER
truck I-TER
and O
stood O
for O
5 O
days O
and O
nights O
without O
food B-TER
and I-TER
water I-TER
. O

Strong O
lights O
were O
brought O
onto O
the O
roof O
of O
this O
truck O
and O
the O
men B-TER
had O
to O
look O
into O
the O
light O
without O
a O
break O
. O

Whoever O
bent O
his O
head O
was O
beaten O
to O
attention O
again O
. O

The O
truck B-TER
was O
shot O
at O
if O
there O
was O
the O
slightest O
sound O
. O

The O
number O
reaching O
the O
camp B-TER
no O
longer O
alive O
is O
not O
small O
. O

On O
arrival O
there O
they O
have O
to O
exercise O
for O
hours O
. O

If O
they O
complain O
of O
thirst O
, O
coffee O
is O
thrown O
on O
the O
stone O
floor O
which O
they O
can O
lick O
up O
. O

In O
the O
race B-TER
crimes I-TER
section O
each O
man B-TER
gets O
5 O
kicks O
in O
the O
belly O
with O
a O
spiked O
shoe O
for O
each O
crime O
committed O
, O
many O
die O
here O
too O
. O

Another O
torture B-TER
is O
to O
tie O
round O
the O
men O
’s O
legs O
with O
a O
rope O
and O
in O
the O
room O
hoist O
them O
up O
to O
the O
ceiling O
with O
heads O
down O
, O
then O
the O
guards B-TER
undo O
the O
rope O
. O

Many O
are O
smashed O
to O
pieces O
on O
the O
stone O
floor O
. O

This O
is O
a O
bloodbath O
each O
time O
. O

Men B-TER
are O
laid O
on O
the O
floor O
in O
rows O
, O
they O
have O
to O
open O
their O
mouths O
wide O
and O
they O
urinate O
into O
their O
mouths O
. O

There O
are O
many O
indescribable O
variants O
of O
this O
policy O
. O

As O
regards O
small O
things O
there O
is O
punishment O
of O
20 O
lashes O
with O
a O
spiked O
stick O
, O
not O
administered O
by O
a O
single O
guard B-TER
but O
by O
20 O
different O
ones O
, O
so O
that O
each O
stroke O
is O
administered O
by O
a O
tireless O
arm O
. O

Each O
prisoner B-TER
must O
sign O
a O
paper O
where O
only O
one O
small O
square O
is O
left O
blank O
for O
the O
signature O
; O
the O
rest O
is O
covered O
up O
so O
that O
no O
one O
knows O
what O
he O
is O
signing O
. O

They O
must O
also O
sign O
a O
piece O
of O
paper O
which O
says O
that O
they O
were O
never O
mistreated O
, O
had O
always O
eaten B-TER
and I-TER
drunk I-TER
well O
, O
and O
they O
were O
forbidden O
to O
speak O
about O
their O
treatment O
in O
the O
concentration B-TER
camp I-TER
, O
on O
pain O
of O
death B-TER
. O

Machine O
guns O
are O
mounted O
at O
the O
four O
corners O
of O
the O
camp B-TER
; O
anyone O
who O
goes O
outside O
after O
sunset O
is O
shot O
down O
without O
further O
ado O
. O

Prisoners B-TER
may O
talk O
to O
each O
other O
for O
an O
hour O
a O
day O
; O
whoever O
says O
a O
word O
outside O
that O
time O
receives O
a O
number O
of O
blows O
. O

There O
is O
nothing O
to O
eat B-TER
, O
drinking B-TER
water I-TER
is O
inadequate O
and O
polluted O
. O

There O
is O
also O
no O
heating O
, O
while O
the O
shelter O
is O
totally O
inadequate O
. O

There O
are O
men O
returned O
from O
Dachau B-LOC
who O
lost O
30 O
pounds O
in O
one O
week O
. O

Fatalities O
are O
reported O
to O
the O
family B-TER
so O
they O
can O
come O
and O
fetch O
the O
urn O
; O
the O
body O
itself O
is O
never O
returned O
. O

There O
is O
also O
a O
concentration B-TER
camp I-TER
for O
women B-TER
guarded B-TER
by O
men O
. O

One O
can O
imagine O
what O
this O
indicates O
. O

It O
seems O
not O
to O
be O
rare O
for O
Jewish O
girls O
of O
12 O
- O
14 O
years O
to O
be O
assaulted O
by O
SS B-ORG
or O
SA B-ORG
men O
. O

The O
emigration B-TER
chances O
of O
these O
children B-TER
are O
naturally O
extremely O
small O
, O
because O
one O
must O
wait O
for O
the O
results O
of O
this O
outrage O
. O

A O
few O
cases O
have O
nevertheless O
been O
transported O
to O
England B-LOC
. O

All O
these O
stories O
were O
told O
to O
me O
by O
Herr O
Lipopsky B-PER
, O
himself O
a O
full O
- O
blooded O
Aryan O
. O

The O
general O
misery O
in O
Vienna B-LOC
is O
unbelievable O
. O

There O
are O
people O
who O
have O
not O
had O
a O
roof O
over O
their O
heads O
for O
weeks O
, O
walking O
from O
doorway O
to O
doorway O
, O
who O
dare O
not O
report O
for O
emigration B-TER
from O
fear O
of O
being O
arrested B-TER
. O

Others O
, O
who O
no O
longer O
possess O
a O
cent O
, O
can O
get O
food B-TER
at O
the O
K.G. B-ORG
to O
the O
value O
of O
15 O
Pf O
. O

[ O
Pfennig O
; O
pennies O
] O
per O
day O
. O

From O
a O
statistic O
of O
one O
of O
the O
Jewish B-TER
cemeteries I-TER
in O
Vienna B-LOC
it O
appears O
that O
in O
the O
first O
weeks O
after O
10 O
November O
130 O
dead O
per O
day O
had O
to O
be O
buried B-TER
. O

Many O
cemeteries B-TER
were O
set O
on O
fire O
and O
the O
bodies O
lay O
open O
above O
the O
ground O
until O
the O
Jews O
themselves O
covered O
them O
with O
straw O
. O

The O
number O
of O
Jews O
killed B-TER
on O
10 O
November O
and O
later O
can O
not O
be O
counted O
; O
they O
talk O
of O
hundreds O
. O

The O
Nederl B-LOC
. I-LOC

[ O
Dutch O
] O
government O
has O
provided O
green O
cards O
for O
adult O
Jews O
, O
with O
which O
they O
are O
permitted O
to O
cross O
over O
the O
Dutch B-LOC
border O
with O
a O
valid O
passport B-TER
. O

These O
cards O
are O
valid O
only O
three O
weeks O
. O

For O
those O
coming O
from O
Vienna B-LOC
, O
sometimes O
4 O
to O
5 O
days O
go O
by O
. O

As O
application O
for O
a O
pass B-TER
without O
the O
possibility O
of O
emigration B-TER
is O
pointless O
, O
and O
the O
minimum O
time O
required O
is O
three O
weeks O
, O
the O
cards O
expire O
before O
a O
pass B-TER
is O
obtained O
. O

Nor O
can O
these O
cards O
be O
extended O
. O

In O
these O
ways O
emigration B-TER
is O
made O
harder O
because O
a O
new O
application O
does O
not O
succeed O
. O

The O
cards O
should O
be O
valid O
for O
at O
least O
six O
weeks O
, O
as O
there O
is O
sometimes O
a O
delay O
through O
unpaid O
tax O
or O
fine O
. O

In O
relation O
to O
the O
various O
offices O
in O
Vienna B-LOC
one O
has O
the O
strong O
feeling O
that O
Austria B-LOC
is O
treated O
harshly O
by O
the O
Netherlands B-LOC
, O
as O
the O
number O
of O
Austrian B-LOC
children B-TER
in O
relation O
to O
the O
total O
number O
of O
emigrated B-TER
children B-TER
is O
particularly O
small O
, O
while O
the O
need O
in O
Austria B-LOC
is O
certainly O
no O
less O
. O

[ O
The O
Jews O
will O
not O
travel O
but O
perish O
. O

] O
© O
Wiener O
Library O
for O
the O
Study O
of O
the O
Holocaust O
& O
Genocide O
, O
London O
