Anzelm B-PER
Landesmann I-PER
Testimony O
( O
doc O
. O

301/905 O
) O
Typescript O
, O
1 O
page O
, O
210 O
x O
295 O
mm O
, O
Polish O
language O
Anzelm B-PER
Landesmann I-PER
. O

Twelve O
years O
old O
. O

He O
comes O
from O
Skałat B-LOC
. O

He O
has O
two O
brothers O
, O
one O
is O
a O
corporal O
in O
the O
Polish O
Army B-TER
and O
the O
other O
, O
17 O
years O
old O
, O
was O
baptized O
and O
stayed O
with O
the O
Ukrainians B-TER
in O
the O
vicinity O
of O
Skałat B-LOC
. O

Anzelm B-PER
, O
called O
Jaśko B-PER
by O
the O
Ukrainians B-TER
, O
arrived O
in O
Gliwice B-LOC
with O
the O
transport O
of O
repatriates B-TER
and O
was O
sent O
to O
the O
Children B-TER
’s O
Home O
in O
Chorzów B-LOC
. O

Janek B-PER
recounts O
: O
There O
were O
seven O
children B-TER
in O
our O
[ O
family O
] O
. O

I O
got O
up O
in O
the O
morning O
. O

The O
action B-TER
. O

I O
ran B-TER
away I-TER
this O
way O
, O
Mom O
that O
way O
, O
younger O
brother O
this O
way O
. O

When O
I O
was O
running B-TER
away I-TER
a O
German B-TER
shot O
after O
me O
, O
he O
wounded O
me O
in O
the O
head O
. O

I O
fell O
. O

They O
thought O
I O
was O
dead O
and O
everybody O
trampled O
on O
me O
, O
I O
did O
n’t O
even O
gasp O
and O
was O
just O
lying O
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
left O
, O
I O
got O
up O
and O
went O
to O
the O
hospital B-TER
where O
they O
bandaged O
my O
head O
. O

I O
returned O
home O
, O
parents O
were O
no O
more O
and O
I O
was O
with O
a O
farmer O
I O
knew O
. O

Then O
the O
Germans B-TER
came O
again O
, O
caught O
me O
[ O
and O
took O
me O
] O
to O
the O
synagogue B-TER
and O
[ O
loaded O
me O
] O
onto O
a O
truck O
and O
[ O
took O
me O
] O
to O
Tarnopol B-LOC
. O

From O
Tarnopol B-LOC
everyone O
was O
deported B-TER
to O
Bełżec B-LOC
. O

My O
sister O
escaped B-TER
from O
the O
truck O
and O
fell O
shot O
by O
a O
bullet O
. O

She O
ran B-TER
away I-TER
during O
the O
day O
, O
that O
’s O
why O
she O
did O
n’t O
make O
it O
, O
that O
’s O
why O
my O
brother O
and O
I O
escaped B-TER
in O
the O
evening O
. O

A O
German B-TER
fired O
, O
wounded O
my O
brother O
in O
the O
leg O
and O
myself O
in O
the O
face O
( O
Janek B-PER
was O
wounded O
twice O
, O
in O
the O
head O
and O
in O
the O
face O
) O
. O

But O
we O
did O
manage O
to O
escape B-TER
and O
we O
walked O
at O
night O
only O
. O

What O
to O
do O
… O
? O
We O
split O
, O
my O
brother O
went O
in O
one O
direction O
, O
I O
in O
the O
other O
. O

I O
went O
to O
the O
countryside O
and O
entered O
a O
house O
. O

There O
was O
only O
a O
Ukrainian B-TER
couple O
, O
I O
told O
them O
that O
I O
was O
from O
Drohobycz B-LOC
, O
that O
there O
is O
hunger B-TER
there O
and O
that O
I O
worked O
there O
. O

But O
I O
told O
them O
that O
I O
wanted O
to O
work O
here O
. O

They O
were O
glad O
that O
I O
would O
herd O
cows O
. O

I O
spoke O
good O
Ukrainian O
because O
at O
home O
I O
used O
to O
play O
with O
the O
neighbors O
’ O
children B-TER
. O

I O
knew O
how O
to O
pray O
in O
Polish O
and O
in O
Ukrainian O
. O

I O
worked O
for O
them O
, O
I O
forgot O
Yiddish O
but O
sometimes O
I O
wanted O
to O
say O
something O
in O
Yiddish O
to O
a O
horse O
in O
the O
stable O
but O
something O
would O
block O
my O
throat O
and O
would O
n’t O
let O
me O
. O

A O
village O
head O
came O
and O
asked O
for O
the O
names O
of O
my O
father O
and O
mother O
. O

I O
said O
: O
Michał O
and O
Natusia O
[ O
Nastusia O
] O
. O

I O
made O
up O
names O
for O
my O
grandpa O
and O
grandma O
. O

Once O
, O
I O
was O
herding O
cows O
and O
I O
heard O
someone O
singing O
, O
a O
familiar O
voice O
. O

Anzelm O
Landesmann O
used O
a O
Ukrainian O
word O
for O
‘ O
voice O
. O

’ O
I O
run O
to O
the O
road O
, O
I O
look O
, O
it O
’s O
my O
younger O
brother O
, O
I O
raised O
my O
hand O
, O
I O
weep O
, O
shout O
, O
he O
stopped O
, O
climbed O
down O
the O
cart O
, O
he O
wept O
too O
. O

Then O
he O
drove O
on O
and O
I O
never O
saw O
my O
brother O
again O
. O

I O
worked O
like O
this O
until O
the O
winter O
of O
1944 O
. O

Then O
the O
Soviets B-ORG
came O
and O
I O
thought O
there O
were O
no O
Jews O
left O
but O
I O
went O
to O
Skałat B-LOC
to O
see O
our O
house O
, O
I O
look O
and O
my O
uncle O
is O
walking O
down O
the O
street O
and O
he O
brought O
me O
to O
Gliwice B-LOC
. O

Record O
taken O
by O
Gliksztejn B-PER
Ida I-PER
. O

Bytom B-LOC
. O

