On O
20.10.1944 O
a O
labor B-TER
transport B-TER
was O
put O
together O
in O
Auschwitz B-LOC
in O
camp O
E. O
During O
the O
medical O
check O
- O
up O
, O
the O
examining O
SS B-TER
doctor B-TER
removed O
the O
following O
people O
due O
to O
physical O
weakness O
: O
Zeev B-PER
Scheck I-PER
, O
Egon B-PER
Haas I-PER
, O
and O
Bertl B-PER
Simonsohn I-PER
, O
because O
they O
looked O
very O
thin O
. O

They O
were O
assured O
that O
they O
would O
be O
sent O
as O
Stubendienst O
to O
the O
camp B-TER
for O
a O
short O
time O
so O
that O
they O
could O
get O
better O
and O
then O
be O
sent O
to O
work B-TER
. O

But O
they O
knew O
what O
was O
going O
on O
and O
Zeev B-PER
especially O
tried O
to O
get O
onto O
the O
transport B-TER
by O
showing O
his O
muscles O
and O
vowing O
that O
he O
was O
used O
to O
hard O
work O
, O
that O
he O
only O
appeared O
thin O
, O
but O
that O
he O
was O
completely O
healthy O
. O

Egon B-PER
Haas I-PER
and O
Bertl B-PER
Simonsohn I-PER
joined O
him O
. O

They O
were O
n’t O
successful O
, O
but O
were O
added O
to O
the O
transport B-TER
in O
the O
end O
only O
because O
some O
people O
were O
missing O
. O

It O
’s O
interesting O
that O
only O
4 O
people O
survived O
this O
transport B-TER
, O
and O
Zeev B-PER
and O
Bertl B-PER
are O
among O
them O
. O

Statement O
was O
accepted O
by O
: O
Signature O
of O
the O
witness O
: O
Marta B-PER
Kratková I-PER
Dr. B-PER
Nasch I-PER
On O
behalf O
of O
the O
documentary B-TER
campaign I-TER
: O
Zeev B-PER
Scheck I-PER
On O
behalf O
of O
the O
archive O
: O
Alex B-PER
. I-PER

Schmiedt I-PER
