Rozentsvayg B-PER
Leyb I-PER
, O
office O
worker O
Age O
: O
25 O
years O
, O
former O
address O
: O
Muranów B-LOC
8 I-LOC
Left O
Warsaw B-LOC
on O
the O
14th O
October O
1939 O
Testimony O
number O
4 O
The O
Jewish O
population O
was O
preparing O
for O
war B-TER
. O

Groups O
were O
formed O
, O
people O
worked O
in O
the O
trenches O
, O
all O
tasks O
and O
injunctions O
were O
accomplished O
zealously O
. O

On O
the O
night O
of O
6th O
September O
there O
was O
an O
alert O
, O
our O
whole O
area O
was O
mobilised O
to O
work B-TER
in O
the O
trenches O
on O
Bielany B-LOC
. O

At O
the O
gathering O
place O
anarchy O
reigned O
, O
there O
was O
no O
leader O
; O
several O
trams O
without O
conductors O
were O
parked O
there O
. O

When O
we O
got O
to O
Bielany B-LOC
, O
we O
were O
sent O
back O
– O
all O
of O
us O
, O
those O
who O
came O
with O
shovels O
or O
without O
. O

We O
heard O
loud O
shooting O
. O

People O
started O
to O
run O
in O
all O
directions O
. O

Thousands O
of O
people O
left O
Warsaw B-LOC
at O
that O
time O
, O
by O
the O
road O
to O
Minsk B-LOC
Mazowiecki I-LOC
or O
to O
Lublin B-LOC
. O

I O
met O
a O
policeman B-TER
that O
morning O
( O
on O
the O
7th O
[ O
of O
September O
] O
) O
. O

He O
said O
that O
they O
[= O
the O
police B-TER
] O
were O
retreating O
together O
with O
the O
army B-TER
by O
the O
road O
to O
Lublin B-LOC
and O
that O
the O
young O
people O
should O
also O
come O
with O
them O
. O

So O
I O
set O
off O
on O
the O
road O
to O
Lublin B-LOC
. O

On O
the O
road O
stretched O
masses O
of O
soldiers B-TER
and O
civilians O
. O

The O
whole O
road O
was O
crowded O
with O
people O
. O

The O
German B-TER
planes O
did O
not O
let O
them O
rest O
, O
but O
bombed O
constantly O
. O

People O
were O
constantly O
hiding O
, O
victims O
were O
lying O
on O
the O
road O
: O
soldiers B-TER
, O
civilians O
, O
horses O
. O

There O
was O
nothing O
to O
eat B-TER
. O

From O
the O
field O
we O
would O
grab O
carrots B-TER
, O
beetroot B-TER
, O
tomatoes B-TER
; O
it O
was O
also O
hard O
to O
find O
water O
, O
the O
wells O
were O
already O
empty O
. O

Near O
Ryki B-LOC
, O
troops O
were O
camped O
, O
with O
a O
high O
- O
ranking O
officer O
. O

He O
was O
sending O
the O
people O
back O
: O
an O
order O
from O
Starzyński B-PER
, O
we O
were O
to O
go O
back O
to O
defend O
Warsaw B-LOC
. O

He O
only O
let O
pass O
a O
certain O
category O
of O
conscripts O
. O

Therefore O
a O
lot O
of O
civilians O
returned O
, O
and O
so O
did O
I. O
On O
the O
way O
back O
there O
was O
heavy O
bombing O
, O
Kołbiel B-LOC
, O
Minsk B-LOC
Mazowiecki I-LOC
, O
Garwolin B-LOC
were O
burning O
. O

It O
was O
impossible O
to O
get O
through O
. O

We O
kept O
on O
going O
to O
Celestynów B-LOC
- O
Otwock B-LOC
. O

There O
we O
got O
a O
kilo O
of O
bread B-TER
. O

In O
Otwock B-LOC
only O
a O
few O
places O
suffered O
damages O
. O

From O
there O
we O
took O
the O
local O
train B-TER
to O
Wawer B-LOC
, O
where O
the O
planes O
were O
constantly O
overhead O
. O

Masses O
of O
people O
lay O
dead B-TER
or O
wounded O
, O
there O
was O
no O
place O
to O
hide O
. O

Wawer B-LOC
. O

We O
went O
into O
a O
house O
that O
was O
standing O
open O
, O
a O
small O
wooden O
house O
. O

There O
we O
stayed O
the O
whole O
day O
Sunday O
, O
10th O
September O
. O

In O
the O
evening O
, O
continued O
toward O
Warsaw B-LOC
. O

The O
dead B-TER
lay O
on O
the O
road O
, O
people O
and O
horses O
. O

There O
were O
lost O
helmets O
, O
articles O
of O
clothing B-TER
. O

All O
of O
Grochowska B-LOC
was O
burning O
, O
fallen O
telegraph O
poles O
, O
bomb O
craters O
. O

In O
Praga B-LOC
, O
cannon O
- O
fire O
, O
shrapnel O
, O
every O
few O
minutes O
we O
had O
to O
take O
shelter O
in O
a O
doorway O
. O

Praga B-LOC
was O
already O
unrecognizable O
, O
particularly O
around O
the O
Przem.[ienienia B-LOC
] I-LOC
Pańskiego I-LOC
hospital B-TER
, O
near O
the O
church O
, O
on O
the O
right O
, O
already O
we O
could O
not O
cross O
Kierbedź O
bridge O
, O
which O
was O
badly O
damaged O
. O

I O
reached O
Warsaw B-LOC
only O
in O
the O
evening O
. O

The O
Warsaw B-LOC
streets O
were O
empty O
, O
unrecognizable O
. O

On O
Nalewki- B-LOC
Franciszkańska I-LOC
they O
were O
grabbing O
Jews O
for O
work B-TER
details O
, O
for O
the O
trenches O
. O

In O
the O
Polish B-TER
districts O
, O
work B-TER
was O
voluntary O
, O
they O
picked O
up O
people O
in O
the O
streets O
only O
in O
the O
Jewish O
district O
, O
despite O
the O
fact O
that O
the O
Jewish O
professional O
or O
party O
organizations O
( O
Bundists B-ORG
, O
Skifists O
, O
even O
in O
uniform O
) O
, O
and O
Jews O
with O
[ O
traditional O
] O
Jewish O
hats O
, O
were O
going O
to O
work B-TER
in O
organized O
groups O
with O
shovels O
. O

At O
Senatorska B-LOC
Street I-LOC
29 I-LOC
, O
Luxenburg B-LOC
Gallery I-LOC
, O
there O
was O
a O
bureau O
to O
recruit O
volunteers O
, O
which O
was O
besieged O
by O
Jews O
. O

Some O
Poles B-TER
even O
expressed O
their O
displeasure O
that O
there O
were O
too O
many O
Jews O
. O

I O
myself O
worked B-TER
with O
a O
group O
of O
Jewish O
transport O
workers B-TER
, O
we O
sang O
revolutionary O
songs O
, O
no O
one O
could O
expect O
that O
in O
a O
few O
days O
all O
the O
work B-TER
would O
be O
for O
nothing O
. O

My O
neighborhood O
had O
suffered O
badly O
from O
the O
bombing O
. O

In O
my O
house O
, O
Muranowska B-LOC
6 I-LOC
- I-LOC
8 I-LOC
, O
the O
adjoining O
wall O
had O
completely O
collapsed O
, O
so O
we O
had O
to O
move O
out O
. O

We O
found O
a O
place O
at O
Prosta B-LOC
14 I-LOC
, O
in O
the O
high O
school O
. O

It O
had O
a O
shelter O
, O
where O
there O
were O
already O
refugees B-TER
from O
Żyrardów B-LOC
, O
Ząbki B-LOC
, O
Błonie B-LOC
and O
others O
. O

There O
were O
whole O
families B-TER
with O
children B-TER
. O

They O
had O
been O
given O
the O
cellars O
of O
the O
school O
. O

The O
bombings O
took O
place O
in O
the O
morning O
and O
evening O
, O
every O
day O
another O
district O
was O
hit O
. O

There O
was O
also O
a O
lot O
of O
shrapnel O
, O
as O
the O
Germans B-TER
got O
closer O
to O
Warsaw B-LOC
. O

The O
planes O
threw O
out O
appeals O
telling O
us O
to O
surrender O
. O

In O
the O
Jewish O
neighborhood O
, O
the O
hardest O
hit O
streets O
were O
Stawki B-LOC
, O
Niska B-LOC
, O
and O
parts O
of O
Miła B-LOC
. O

Also O
badly O
hit O
were O
Nalewki B-LOC
and O
Franciszkańska B-LOC
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
heavily O
bombed O
the O
churches O
on O
Leszno B-LOC
, O
Grzybów B-LOC
, O
Zbawiciela B-LOC
Square I-LOC
and O
others O
. O

The O
worst O
damage O
was O
in O
Wola B-LOC
, O
Mokotów B-LOC
and O
Marymont B-LOC
. O

The O
hardest O
hit O
of O
all O
were O
the O
houses O
with O
military B-TER
points O
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
entered O
Warsaw B-LOC
on O
2nd O
and O
3rd O
October O
. O

First O
they O
opened O
soup B-TER
kitchens I-TER
to O
feed O
the O
population O
, O
who O
rushed O
to O
the O
kitchens B-TER
. O

A O
crowd O
of O
50 O
000 O
gathered O
on O
Broni B-LOC
Square I-LOC
, O
standing O
in O
4 O
rows O
which O
extended O
the O
whole O
length O
of O
Bonifraterska B-LOC
. O

From O
4 O
tables O
with O
4 O
large O
vats O
, O
the O
Germans B-TER
distributed O
food B-TER
, O
and O
they O
filmed O
it O
all O
from O
a O
truck O
and O
played O
military B-TER
marches O
. O

Someone O
greeted O
the O
soldiers B-TER
in O
Polish O
. O

They O
made O
no O
distinction O
between O
non O
- O
Jews O
and O
Jews O
, O
even O
those O
wearing O
Hasidic O
dress B-TER
. O

But O
in O
the O
following O
days O
there O
began O
to O
be O
a O
difference O
between O
Jews O
and O
non O
- O
Jews O
. O

For O
clearing O
the O
rubble O
they O
rounded O
up O
only O
Jews O
in O
the O
Jewish O
quarters O
. O

In O
the O
Polish B-TER
quarters O
this O
was O
not O
done O
. O

By O
this O
time O
there O
was O
no O
water O
, O
no O
electricity O
; O
Jews O
had O
to O
go O
for O
water O
to O
the O
Vistula B-LOC
or O
to O
the O
wells O
, O
and O
already O
some O
Poles B-TER
were O
starting O
to O
say O
things O
like O
: O
Hitler B-PER
's O
here O
already O
, O
he O
'll O
soon O
be O
getting O
even O
with O
the O
Jews O
. O

By O
the O
Vistula B-LOC
, O
I O
once O
saw O
the O
following O
: O
A O
young O
Gentile O
grabbed O
a O
large O
pitcher O
of O
water O
that O
an O
elderly O
Jewish O
woman B-TER
was O
carrying O
and O
poured O
it O
all O
out O
. O

This O
was O
already O
quite O
a O
distance O
from O
the O
river O
. O

An O
older O
man B-TER
, O
also O
a O
Gentile O
, O
reacted O
like O
this O
: O
What O
kind O
of O
a O
person O
are O
you O
, O
to O
do O
this O
in O
such O
a O
time O
. O

What O
would O
you O
do O
if O
someone O
did O
that O
to O
you O
? O
Life O
was O
very O
hard O
. O

Bread B-TER
was O
impossible O
to O
find O
. O

Potatoes B-TER
cost O
3 O
złoty O
a O
kilo O
and O
were O
also O
hard O
to O
find O
. O

Brave O
young O
men B-TER
went O
out O
to O
the O
fields O
, O
dug O
up O
potatoes B-TER
and O
sold O
them O
. O

No O
transportation O
existed O
. O

I O
saw O
the O
following O
scene O
: O
A O
Gentile O
came O
up O
to O
a O
Jewish O
boy O
to O
buy O
cigarettes O
. O

He O
asked O
the O
price O
, O
then O
quickly O
called O
over O
a O
German B-TER
soldier B-TER
, O
who O
took O
all O
the O
cigarettes O
away O
from O
the O
boy O
and O
tossed O
them O
to O
the O
crowd O
. O

The O
Gentiles O
caught O
them O
. O

Another O
scene O
: O
a O
policeman B-TER
came O
up O
to O
woman O
selling O
herring B-TER
and O
asked O
the O
price O
. O

Then O
he O
took O
it O
all O
and O
gave O
it O
out O
to O
the O
crowd O
. O

The O
shops O
were O
completely O
closed O
. O

All O
commerce O
was O
in O
the O
streets O
. O

Before O
the O
Germans B-TER
arrived O
there O
was O
a O
lot O
of O
robbery O
: O
Polish B-TER
soldiers B-TER
would O
steal O
, O
as O
well O
as O
the O
criminals B-TER
who O
had O
been O
let O
out O
of O
jail B-TER
. O

There O
were O
whole O
gangs O
. O

We O
posted O
guards O
by O
the O
gates O
. O

Some O
firms O
, O
however O
, O
themselves O
distributed O
their O
goods O
to O
the O
population O
, O
just O
so O
it O
would O
n’t O
fall O
into O
the O
hands O
of O
the O
Germans B-TER
. O

Warsaw B-LOC
under O
the O
Germans B-TER
: O
Nowolipki B-LOC
from O
Zamenhof B-LOC
to O
Karmelicka B-LOC
was O
cleared O
of O
all O
Jews O
. O

Within O
the O
space O
of O
one O
or O
two O
hours O
all O
Jews O
had O
to O
leave O
their O
homes O
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
cleaned O
up O
the O
street O
, O
there O
was O
no O
passage O
off O
Nowolipki B-LOC
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
would O
grab O
Jews O
for O
work O
details O
and O
also O
make O
fun O
of O
them O
. O

I O
myself O
saw O
this O
scene O
: O
they O
asked O
an O
elderly O
Jew O
to O
clean O
the O
pavement O
with O
his O
beard O
. O

The O
Jew O
bent O
down O
and O
began O
wiping O
with O
his O
hands O
and O
they O
did O
n’t O
bother O
him O
any O
more O
. O

In O
many O
cases O
they O
forced O
people O
to O
work B-TER
but O
there O
were O
no O
shovels O
, O
no O
tools O
, O
and O
they O
had O
to O
work B-TER
with O
their O
bare O
hands O
. O

The O
Polish B-TER
population O
stood O
in O
line O
to O
get O
bread B-TER
, O
mainly O
in O
the O
Polish B-TER
neighborhoods O
. O

They O
would O
throw O
Jews O
off O
the O
line O
. O

If O
a O
Jew O
refused O
to O
leave O
they O
would O
call O
over O
a O
German B-TER
policeman B-TER
and O
point O
to O
him O
: O
Jude O
! O
Jude O
! O
and O
they O
would O
throw O
him O
out O
. O

Particularly O
good O
at O
these O
anti B-TER
- I-TER
Semitic I-TER
acts O
were O
the O
volunteer O
members O
of O
the O
Polish B-TER
militia B-TER
: O
One O
of O
these O
took O
hold O
of O
a O
Jew O
by O
his O
lapel O
and O
pulled O
him O
off O
the O
line O
. O

For O
Jews O
there O
's O
no O
bread O
! O
For O
some O
Gentiles O
a O
little O
business O
sprang O
up O
– O
to O
sell O
loaves O
of O
bread B-TER
to O
Jews O
at O
exorbitant O
prices O
. O

A O
new O
means O
of O
livelihood O
became O
available O
for O
Jews O
also O
during O
the O
water O
shortage O
: O
carrying O
water O
on O
pushcarts O
; O
there O
were O
also O
Jews O
who O
would O
stand O
in O
line O
( O
for O
a O
fee O
) O
. O

Until O
the O
Germans B-TER
entered O
Warsaw B-LOC
, O
a O
four O
- O
page O
edition O
of O
the O
Folkstsaytung B-TER
came O
out O
every O
day O
; O
once O
they O
were O
there O
, O
Yiddish O
newspapers O
were O
no O
longer O
available O
. O

There O
was O
only O
Kurier B-TER
Poranny I-TER
, O
Dziennik B-TER
Ludowy I-TER
, O
Kurier B-TER
Warszawski I-TER
, O
but O
they O
all O
carried O
exactly O
the O
same O
contents O
. O

There O
were O
2 O
appeals O
from O
Starzyński B-PER
to O
the O
population O
. O

12 O
guarantors O
were O
appointed O
, O
to O
be O
responsible O
for O
keeping O
the O
peace O
in O
the O
city O
. O

Among O
them O
were O
Szmul B-PER
Zygielbojm I-PER
( O
Artur O
) O
, O
Gepner B-PER
, O
Count B-PER
Lubomirski I-PER
, O
Zaremba B-PER
, O
etc O
. O

After O
a O
week O
and O
a O
half O
under O
the O
Germans B-TER
I O
decided O
to O
escape B-TER
; O
I O
expected O
that O
later O
things O
would O
become O
worse O
, O
that O
there O
would O
be O
special O
persecutions B-TER
for O
the O
younger O
generation O
. O

The O
city O
made O
a O
terrifying O
impression O
after O
the O
bombing O
. O

I O
left O
for O
Falenica B-LOC
in O
order O
to O
continue O
on O
from O
there O
. O

In O
Falenica B-LOC
the O
entire O
Handlowa B-LOC
Street I-LOC
had O
been O
burned O
. O

In O
Falenica B-LOC
the O
Germans B-TER
shot B-TER
a O
number O
of O
Jews O
, O
supposedly O
taking O
them O
to O
a O
prisoners B-TER
' O
camp B-TER
, O
but O
shooting B-TER
them O
on O
the O
way O
. O

As O
a O
former O
patient O
of O
the O
Medem B-LOC
Sanatorium I-LOC
, O
I O
wanted O
to O
have O
a O
look O
at O
the O
sanatorium B-TER
in O
Miedzeszyn B-LOC
. O

When O
I O
reached O
the O
sanatorium B-TER
I O
found O
no O
one O
there O
. O

So O
I O
went O
in O
to O
see O
the O
guardian O
Maksimenko B-PER
and O
he O
described O
to O
me O
in O
tears O
the O
plundering B-TER
of O
the O
sanatorium B-TER
: O
there O
were O
Polish B-TER
soldiers B-TER
in O
the O
sanatorium B-TER
and O
they O
robbed O
the O
place O
together O
with O
the O
civilian O
population O
. O

The O
soldiers B-TER
simply O
let O
the O
civilians O
in O
and O
whoever O
wanted O
to O
could O
steal O
whatever O
they O
wanted O
, O
and O
they O
took O
everything O
, O
beds O
, O
mattresses O
, O
everything O
. O

With O
tears O
, O
Maksimenko B-PER
explained O
: O
All O
he O
could O
do O
was O
to O
kill B-TER
himself I-TER
, O
for O
it O
was O
his O
responsibility O
and O
he O
was O
unable O
to O
prevent O
the O
destruction O
. O

As O
we O
entered O
the O
sanatorium B-TER
we O
were O
struck O
by O
a O
terrible O
smell O
. O

A O
great O
number O
of O
dead B-TER
horses O
were O
buried O
here O
. O

The O
sanatorium B-TER
buildings O
were O
standing O
but O
everything O
was O
in O
disorder O
, O
everything O
thrown O
about O
, O
the O
rooms O
empty O
, O
even O
the O
door O
handles O
had O
been O
stolen O
. O

In O
the O
kitchen O
the O
cooking O
pots O
had O
been O
taken O
. O

Maksimenko B-PER
said O
: O
I O
know O
where O
all O
these O
things O
are O
. O

If O
the O
directors O
of O
the O
sanatorium B-TER
would O
come O
we O
could O
get O
them O
back O
. O

When O
I O
came O
back O
a O
second O
time O
I O
found O
9 O
staff O
members O
, O
technical O
and O
medical B-TER
personnel I-TER
: O
they O
decided O
to O
set O
up O
a O
collective O
and O
began O
to O
put O
the O
sanatorium B-TER
in O
order O
. O

I O
found O
them O
working B-TER
with O
rakes O
and O
brooms O
. O

We O
prepared O
a O
lunch B-TER
together O
, O
not O
in O
the O
sanatorium B-TER
, O
but O
at O
the O
home O
of O
a O
friend O
who O
worked B-TER
in O
the O
sanatorium B-TER
and O
lived O
nearby O
. O

I O
never O
entered O
the O
sanatorium B-TER
again O
. O

The O
next O
day O
, O
the O
17 O
/ O
18th O
October O
, O
I O
continued O
on O
my O
way O
, O
through O
Minsk B-LOC
- I-LOC
Maz.[owiecki I-LOC
] I-LOC
, O
to O
the O
Bug B-LOC
River I-LOC
. O

In O
Minsk B-LOC
, O
for O
the O
first O
time O
I O
had O
some O
bread B-TER
. O

There O
were O
a O
lot O
of O
German B-TER
soldiers B-TER
. O

I O
also O
heard O
there O
was O
a O
prisoners B-TER
' O
camp B-TER
there O
, O
with O
many O
Jews O
, O
even O
civilians O
. O

The O
camp B-TER
was O
in O
the O
open O
air O
. O

From O
Minsk B-LOC
I O
left O
for O
Kaluszyn B-LOC
. O

Nothing O
was O
left O
of O
the O
entire O
town O
. O

All O
that O
remained O
was O
bits O
of O
walls O
sticking O
up O
, O
but O
the O
church O
was O
still O
there O
. O

Those O
who O
had O
hidden O
in O
the O
church O
survived O
. O

The O
Poles B-TER
saw O
this O
as O
a O
miracle O
. O

They O
estimated O
the O
number O
of O
dead B-TER
in O
Kaluszyn B-LOC
to O
be O
900 O
, O
most O
of O
them O
Jews O
. O

Everyone O
told O
me O
: O
They O
had O
never O
seen O
such O
destruction O
, O
a O
whole O
town O
wiped O
out O
! O
From O
Kaluszyn B-LOC
I O
went O
to O
Siedlce B-LOC
. O

While O
I O
was O
there O
they O
were O
rounding O
up O
Jews O
in O
the O
street O
for O
work B-TER
details O
. O

A O
large O
part O
of O
Siedlce B-LOC
was O
burned O
down O
. O

We O
were O
able O
to O
get O
bread B-TER
. O

The O
Jews O
complained O
that O
the O
Bolsheviks O
had O
retreated O
, O
for O
they O
had O
already O
been O
close O
to O
Siedlce B-LOC
. O

Then O
I O
headed O
for O
Mordy B-LOC
. O

There O
too O
they O
were O
taking O
Jews O
for O
labor B-TER
. O

I O
heard O
about O
Węgrów B-LOC
: O
they O
stabbed B-TER
the O
rabbi B-TER
with O
a O
knife O
. O

Many O
Jews O
were O
assembled O
in O
the O
synagogue B-TER
and O
the O
Germans B-TER
opened O
fire O
on O
the O
synagogue B-TER
. O

The O
Jews O
threw O
themselves O
on O
the O
ground O
and O
the O
Germans B-TER
kept O
them O
there O
all O
day O
under O
threat O
of O
being O
shot B-TER
. O

No O
one O
was O
killed B-TER
, O
only O
wounded O
. O

They O
also O
related O
: O
From O
those O
who O
reached O
the O
Bug O
the O
Germans B-TER
took O
everything O
: O
rings O
, O
furs O
, O
and O
distributed O
it O
all O
to O
the O
Christian O
population O
. O

From O
Mordy B-LOC
I O
went O
to O
the O
Bug O
, O
using O
back O
roads O
, O
then O
crossed O
the O
river O
with O
a O
small O
boat O
near O
Drohiczyn B-LOC
. O

At O
night O
, O
on O
the O
other O
side O
I O
met O
Soviet B-TER
soldiers B-TER
, O
who O
gave O
me O
dinner B-TER
and O
a O
place O
to O
sleep O
. O

All O
the O
sites O
that O
the O
Soviets B-TER
occupied O
after O
the O
Germans B-TER
were O
totally O
plundered B-TER
. O

