In O
adverting O
to O
reports O
from O
this O
Mission O
with O
respect O
to O
anti B-TER
- I-TER
Semitic I-TER
measures I-TER
in O
German B-TER
- I-TER
occupied I-TER
countries I-TER
, O
I O
have O
the O
honor O
to O
submit O
hereunder O
in O
summary O
form O
a O
description O
of O
measures B-TER
recently O
announced O
in O
the O
German B-TER
press B-TER
directed O
against O
the O
Jewish B-TER
population I-TER
of O
occupied B-TER
France B-LOC
, O
the O
Netherlands B-LOC
, O
Belgium B-LOC
and O
Northern O
France O
, O
Alsace B-LOC
, O
the O
General B-ORG
Government I-ORG
( O
of O
Poland B-LOC
) O
, O
and O
Slovakia B-LOC
. O

[ O
… O
] O
General B-ORG
Government I-ORG
( O
of O
Poland B-LOC
): O
In O
view O
of O
the O
heavy O
migration B-TER
of O
population B-TER
into O
the O
new O
Jewish B-TER
ghetto B-TER
in O
Warsaw B-LOC
, O
the O
period O
for O
the O
completion O
of O
voluntary O
establishment O
there O
by O
Jewish B-TER
families B-TER
from O
other O
quarters O
of O
the O
city O
has O
been O
extended O
through O
November O
15 O
. O

At O
the O
same O
time O
the O
limits O
of O
the O
ghetto B-TER
have O
been O
enlarged O
to O
take O
in O
certain O
additional O
blocks O
and O
it O
is O
feared O
that O
this O
enlargement O
may O
mean O
the O
moving B-TER
into I-TER
the O
ghetto B-TER
of O
Jews B-TER
not O
as O
yet O
resident O
in O
Warsaw B-LOC
. O

It O
has O
also O
been O
decided O
to O
force O
the O
transfer O
of O
Jewish B-TER
owned O
and O
operated O
industrial B-TER
plants I-TER
into O
the O
ghetto B-TER
and O
the O
removal O
from O
the O
ghetto B-TER
of O
many O
such O
enterprises O
carried O
on O
therein O
by O
non B-TER
- I-TER
Jews I-TER
. O

There O
are O
taking O
place O
conversations O
between O
the O
owners O
of O
such O
plants O
as O
to O
whether O
an O
exchange O
of O
ownership O
can O
not O
be O
effected O
in O
a O
manner O
acceptable O
to O
both O
the O
Jews B-TER
and O
non B-TER
- I-TER
Jews I-TER
. O

The O
authorities O
express O
the O
hope O
that O
this O
extension O
of O
the O
ghetto B-TER
idea O
to O
include O
industrial B-TER
enterprises I-TER
may O
be O
carried O
out O
without O
undue O
delay O
. O

Slovakia B-LOC
: O
A O
decree O
is O
reported O
to O
be O
under O
preparation O
by O
the O
Slovakian B-ORG
Government I-ORG
which O
will O
block O
Jewish B-TER
accounts B-TER
in I-TER
banking I-TER
establishments O
and O
will O
make O
obligatory O
the O
deposit O
of O
all O
securities O
belonging O
to O
Jewish B-TER
persons O
or O
enterprises B-TER
. O

Payments O
to O
Jews B-TER
will O
only O
be O
possible O
through O
such O
blocked B-TER
accounts I-TER
and O
Jews B-TER
will O
only O
be O
allowed O
to O
withdraw O
up O
to O
a O
maximum O
of O
5,000 O
crowns O
per O
week O
on O
the O
basis O
of O
a O
special O
and O
individual O
permit O
from O
their O
blocked B-TER
accounts I-TER
. O

The O
above O
developments O
indicate O
that O
German B-TER
anti B-TER
- I-TER
Semitic I-TER
measures I-TER
are O
rapidly O
being O
put O
into O
effect O
in O
the O
occupied B-TER
territories I-TER
. O

At O
the O
same O
time O
the O
German B-TER
press B-TER
publishes O
articles O
reporting O
somewhat O
similar O
measures B-TER
in O
Rumania B-LOC
, O
Jugoslavia B-LOC
, O
Bulgaria B-LOC
and O
unoccupied B-TER
France I-TER
. O

There O
appears O
, O
consequently O
, O
to O
be O
a O
definite O
program O
of O
carrying O
German B-TER
anti B-TER
- I-TER
Semitism I-TER
beyond O
the O
German B-TER
borders O
into O
such O
countries O
as O
come O
into O
the O
German B-TER
sphere I-TER
of I-TER
influence I-TER
. O

