The O
person O
in O
question O
has O
given O
us O
the O
following O
information O
: O
As O
a O
start O
, O
I O
have O
to O
comment O
that O
all O
actions O
, O
processes O
, O
and O
negotiations O
that O
regard O
either O
the O
times O
before O
Vadász O
Street O
or O
the O
emigration B-TER
, O
e.g. O
the O
letters B-TER
of I-TER
protection I-TER
, O
the O
protected B-TER
houses I-TER
, O
etc O
. O

were O
initiated O
and O
thought O
out O
by O
the O
Budapest B-LOC
office O
( O
the O
Palestine B-ORG
Office I-ORG
) O
of O
the O
Jewish B-ORG
Agency I-ORG
and O
by O
the O
Palestine B-LOC
Committee O
. O

The O
key O
and O
the O
condition O
of O
the O
success O
of O
these O
activities O
was O
the O
good O
rapport O
that O
existed O
between O
the O
Swiss B-ORG
Consulate I-ORG
( O
e.g. O
the O
consul B-PER
) O
and O
the O
Palestine B-ORG
Office I-ORG
. O

It O
was O
the O
Swiss B-ORG
Consulate I-ORG
, O
or O
more O
precisely O
, O
its O
special O
department O
called O
Delegation O
of O
Foreign O
Interests O
that O
represented O
the O
interests O
of O
both O
England B-ORG
and O
the O
US B-ORG
after O
they O
declared O
war B-TER
and O
also O
the O
case O
of O
emigration B-TER
to O
Palestine B-LOC
, O
that O
is O
, O
the O
interests O
of O
the O
people O
who O
wished O
to O
emigrate B-ORG
to O
Palestine B-LOC
. O

I O
have O
to O
add O
right O
away O
that O
as O
far O
as O
circumstances O
allowed O
the O
consulate B-ORG
, O
especially O
consul B-TER
Charles B-PER
Lutz I-PER
, O
did O
a O
great O
work O
representing O
these O
interests O
. O

The O
friendship O
that O
evolved O
through O
the O
permanent O
contact O
between O
consul B-TER
Lutz B-PER
and O
the O
head O
of O
the O
Palestine B-ORG
Office I-ORG
, O
Miklós B-PER
Krausz I-PER
was O
of O
great O
use O
both O
concerning O
these O
initiations O
and O
their O
successful O
execution O
. O

This O
friendship O
let O
its O
beneficial O
influence O
felt O
in O
all O
activities O
of O
Vadász B-LOC
Street I-LOC
. O

The O
establishing O
of O
the O
Vadász B-LOC
Street I-LOC
office O
was O
in O
particular O
the O
merit O
of O
Miklós B-PER
Krausz I-PER
, O
which O
he O
– O
as O
a O
Zionist B-TER
and O
the O
representative O
of O
Szochnut B-ORG
in O
Hungary B-LOC
- O
wanted O
to O
use O
for O
saving O
Zionist B-TER
youth O
and O
cháluc B-TER
figures O
, O
that O
is O
, O
people O
who O
were O
so O
important O
for O
the O
Jewish O
population O
and O
for O
Palestine B-LOC
. O

Around O
the O
end O
of O
May O
, O
1944 O
, O
it O
became O
obvious O
to O
all O
of O
us O
that O
the O
so O
- O
called O
Kasztner B-PER
-group O
would O
not O
leave O
the O
country O
soon O
, O
or O
if O
it O
set O
off O
its O
way O
would O
not O
go O
through O
Romania B-LOC
and O
the O
destination O
would O
not O
be O
Palestine B-LOC
. O

We O
also O
understood O
that O
this O
kind O
of O
action O
would O
not O
lead O
to O
the O
rescue O
of O
great O
masses O
of O
Jews O
from O
the O
clutch O
of O
Germans B-TER
and O
of O
the O
Arrow B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
. O

We O
had O
to O
find O
new O
ways O
for O
rescuing B-TER
Jewish O
people O
without O
delay O
. O

Deportations B-TER
in O
the O
country B-LOC
were O
already O
going O
on O
, O
and O
we O
already O
had O
testimonies O
regarding O
the O
dismay O
of O
Auschwitz B-LOC
, O
thanks O
to O
a O
few O
Polish B-TER
and O
Slovakian B-TER
chalucs B-TER
who O
had O
successfully O
escaped B-TER
. O

Therefore O
Krausz B-PER
’s I-PER
proposal O
regarding O
the O
awakening O
of O
the O
public O
opinion O
abroad O
as O
our O
most O
urgent O
duty O
was O
evident O
. O

He O
collected O
data O
concerning O
deportations B-TER
in O
Hungary B-LOC
with O
details O
of O
all O
the O
misery O
involved O
and O
attached O
to O
them O
to O
the O
testimonies B-ORG
regarding O
Auschwitz B-LOC
. O

He O
sent O
these O
documents O
to O
various O
Swiss B-ORG
Embassies I-ORG
and O
had O
them O
delivered O
to O
the O
US B-ORG
, O
to O
England B-ORG
and O
to O
the O
Pope B-PER
. O

He O
asked O
these O
governments B-TER
to O
put O
pressure O
on O
the O
Nazi B-TER
government B-TER
to O
stop O
this O
horror O
and O
to O
intervene O
in O
the O
interest O
of O
the O
emigration B-TER
of O
the O
Jews O
who O
remained O
still O
in O
Hungary B-LOC
. O

This O
was O
carried O
to O
abroad O
- O
thanks O
to O
consul B-TER
Lutz B-PER
– O
by O
a O
Swiss B-LOC
courier O
, O
and O
the O
results O
followed O
surprisingly O
fast O
. O

These O
data O
and O
testimonies O
got O
to O
Roosevelt B-PER
, O
Churchill B-PER
, O
and O
the O
Pope B-PER
as O
we O
learnt O
from O
Swiss B-LOC
journals B-TER
sent O
to O
us O
a O
few O
weeks O
later O
. O

( O
Some O
journals B-TER
published O
our O
material O
word O
by O
word O
, O
like O
the O
Neue B-TER
Züricher I-TER
Zeitung I-TER
on O
the O
deportation B-TER
from O
Nyíregyháza B-LOC
) O
. O

The O
three O
governments B-TER
commandingly O
intervened O
, O
and O
this O
reached O
the O
Hungarian B-LOC
government B-TER
June O
the O
17th O
. O

When O
in O
the O
following O
few O
weeks O
negotiations O
between O
the O
Swiss B-ORG
Embassy I-ORG
and O
the O
Hungarian B-LOC
government B-TER
still O
did O
not O
have O
any O
result O
this O
intervention O
was O
forcefully O
reasserted O
. O

( O
By O
the O
great O
bombings B-TER
of O
June O
and O
in O
particular O
of O
July O
. O

) O
The O
commanding O
ultimatum O
addressing O
the O
Hungarian B-LOC
government B-TER
was O
mediated O
by O
the O
Swiss B-ORG
government I-ORG
. O

Consul B-TER
Lutz B-PER
received O
a O
long O
dispatch O
in O
which O
his O
government B-TER
certified O
to O
have O
received O
our O
material O
and O
instructed O
him O
to O
personally O
deliver O
the O
aforementioned O
forceful O
letter O
of O
intervention O
from O
the O
part O
of O
the O
great O
political O
powers O
. O

Several O
of O
us O
were O
present O
when O
he O
asked O
for O
an O
urgent O
audience O
from O
the O
Ministry B-TER
of I-TER
Foreign I-TER
Affairs I-TER
on O
the O
phone O
. O

And O
when O
the O
deputy O
minister B-TER
asked O
something O
we O
could O
not O
hear O
he O
forcefully O
answered O
: O
No O
, O
Sir O
, O
exceptionally O
it O
regards O
not O
my O
government O
. O

I O
want O
to O
pass O
on O
information O
coming O
from O
the O
American O
government O
. O

Consul B-TER
Lutz B-PER
’s I-PER
intervention O
in O
the O
Ministry B-TER
of I-TER
Foreign I-TER
Affairs I-TER
did O
not O
meet O
considerable O
resistance O
. O

There O
were O
some O
people O
also O
there O
who O
could O
observe O
the O
state O
of O
affairs O
objectively O
and O
took O
forthcoming O
events O
into O
consideration O
. O

However O
, O
they O
emphasised O
that O
this O
case O
did O
not O
depend O
on O
the O
Hungarian B-LOC
government B-TER
but O
on O
the O
Germans B-TER
. O

But O
it O
appeared O
that O
similar O
actions O
had O
their O
effects O
also O
in O
Berlin B-LOC
. O

A O
few O
days O
later O
, O
a O
new O
dispatch O
came O
from O
Switzerland B-LOC
in O
which O
the O
Swiss B-ORG
government I-ORG
instructed O
Lutz B-PER
to O
get O
prepared O
for O
the O
negotiations O
and O
start O
preparing O
the O
emigration B-TER
since O
German B-ORG
Foreign I-ORG
Ministry I-ORG
in O
principle O
had O
given O
its O
consent O
. O

Already O
the O
day O
after O
the O
Hungarian B-LOC
government B-TER
invited O
consul O
Lutz B-PER
for O
an O
audience O
. O

Early O
in O
the O
morning O
a O
meeting O
started O
in O
the O
Ministry B-TER
of I-TER
the I-TER
Interior I-TER
which O
lasted O
until O
late O
afternoon O
, O
where O
only O
the O
head O
of O
the O
Palestine B-ORG
Office I-ORG
, O
Miklós B-PER
Krausz I-PER
was O
invited O
on O
behalf O
of O
the O
Jews O
. O

Almost O
all O
ministries B-TER
together O
and O
also O
the O
National B-ORG
Central I-ORG
Authority I-ORG
for I-ORG
Controlling I-ORG
Foreigners I-ORG
were O
represented O
on O
this O
meeting O
, O
where O
the O
German B-PER
ambassador I-PER
’s I-PER
deputy O
appeared O
as O
well O
. O

The O
infamous O
gendarme O
Lieutenant B-PER
Colonel I-PER
Ferenczy I-PER
was O
also O
invited O
, O
probably O
as O
a O
known O
expert O
of O
transports B-TER
. O

The O
representative O
of O
the O
foreign B-ORG
ministry I-ORG
officially O
confirmed O
that O
the O
German B-ORG
Ministry I-ORG
of I-ORG
Foreign I-ORG
Affairs I-ORG
had O
approved O
the O
emigration B-ORG
of O
those O
who O
had O
a O
certificate B-TER
. O

Further O
, O
he O
announced O
the O
decision O
of O
the O
Hungarian B-LOC
government B-TER
to O
halt O
deportations B-TER
and O
labour B-TER
service I-TER
conscriptions O
till O
the O
alia B-TER
was O
not O
concluded O
( O
till O
the O
31st O
of O
August O
) O
. O

Later O
, O
the O
number O
of O
emigrants B-TER
and O
details O
of O
their O
travel O
were O
discussed O
. O

The O
idea O
of O
protected O
houses O
- O
as O
places O
where O
the O
people O
who O
intended O
to O
alia B-TER
could O
be O
gathered O
- O
was O
first O
raised O
on O
this O
meeting O
. O

The O
story O
of O
Vadász O
- O
Street O
started O
here O
. O

We O
moved O
into O
the O
building O
in O
the O
middle O
of O
July O
. O

Collective O
passport O
and O
the O
Schutzpass O
that O
resulted O
from O
it O
were O
made O
here O
. O

Next O
to O
the O
60 O
- O
80,000 O
people B-TER
saved B-TER
by O
having O
a O
Schutzpass B-TER
, O
this O
place O
gave O
asylum O
to O
2,600 O
Jews O
, O
amongst O
them O
great O
masses O
of O
the O
Zionist B-TER
youth O
, O
who O
organised O
and O
led O
illegal O
and O
underground B-TER
actions O
. O

To O
be O
loyal O
to O
historical O
truth O
I O
also O
need O
to O
mention O
that O
among O
the O
protected O
people O
of O
Vadász O
Street O
there O
were O
quite O
a O
number O
of O
non O
- O
Jew O
leftists O
together O
with O
their O
numerous O
relatives B-TER
. O

An O
evening O
in O
December O
, O
I O
witnessed O
how O
three O
women B-TER
blue O
from O
the O
cold O
asked O
for O
asylum O
at O
least O
for O
a O
night O
at O
the O
gate O
claiming O
to O
have O
been O
relatives B-TER
of O
hunted O
leftists O
. O

As O
several O
people O
of O
the O
leftist O
fraction O
confirmed O
their O
identity O
they O
were O
let O
in O
and O
it O
was O
only O
natural O
that O
no O
one O
asked O
them O
later O
to O
leave O
. O

We O
should O
not O
be O
surprised O
therefore O
that O
the O
terrorist O
attempts O
on O
the O
banquet O
of O
the O
Arrow B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
in O
the O
city O
theatre O
were O
claimed O
to O
have O
originated O
from O
Vadász O
Street O
. O

This O
was O
followed O
by O
the O
gendarmes B-TER
’ I-TER
raid O
the O
4th O
of O
December O
at O
daybreak O
, O
which O
commenced O
with O
a O
long O
series O
of O
shots O
in O
the O
street O
, O
and O
men O
with O
the O
sickle B-TER
- I-TER
feather I-TER
appeared O
on O
the O
roofs O
. O

Luckily O
, O
the O
main O
entrance O
to O
the O
street O
was O
well O
barred O
so O
they O
could O
not O
get O
in O
. O

The O
head O
of O
the O
gendarmes B-TER
’ I-TER
squad O
started O
a O
long O
debate O
and O
negotiation O
with O
our O
leaders O
– O
in O
particular O
with O
Artúr B-PER
Weisz I-PER
. O

The O
commander B-TER
warned O
us O
that O
he O
would O
got O
the O
house O
searched O
by O
his O
own O
men O
unless O
we O
handed O
over O
the O
terrorists O
who O
attacked O
the O
City B-LOC
Theatre I-LOC
and O
all O
the O
available O
weapons O
. O

Although O
we O
did O
not O
know O
the O
men O
they O
wanted O
we O
did O
know O
about O
weapons O
. O

We O
started O
an O
endless O
number O
of O
telephone O
calls O
calling O
the O
Ministry B-TER
of I-TER
the I-TER
Interior I-TER
, O
the O
Ministry B-TER
of I-TER
Foreign I-TER
Affairs I-TER
, O
the O
city O
military B-TER
headquarters O
and O
other O
places O
. O

Finally O
, O
we O
achieved O
that O
around O
noon O
the O
gendarmes B-TER
temporarily O
left O
, O
but O
we O
could O
not O
foresee O
when O
we O
would O
meet O
them O
again O
. O

Although O
gendarmes B-TER
did O
not O
return O
it O
became O
obvious O
that O
we O
would O
not O
be O
spared O
trouble O
. O

A O
sign O
of O
this O
was O
the O
visit O
of O
two O
detectives O
from O
the O
so O
- O
called O
National O
Committee O
of O
for O
Calling O
to O
Account O
one O
morning O
in O
Vadász O
Street O
. O

Their O
visit O
regarded O
again O
forged B-TER
Schutzpasses B-TER
but O
they O
were O
also O
deeply O
interested O
in O
the O
huge O
mass O
of O
people O
accommodated O
in O
the O
building O
. O

They O
did O
not O
hide O
their O
opinion O
that O
the O
whole O
building O
of O
the O
Embassy B-ORG
was O
just O
a O
great O
hiding B-TER
place O
, O
and O
told O
us O
that O
they O
were O
going O
to O
give O
their O
report O
directly O
to O
the O
leading O
brother O
of O
the O
nation O
and O
we O
could O
hope O
for O
great O
clearing O
actions O
against O
us O
in O
the O
forthcoming O
days O
. O

At O
the O
same O
time O
our O
agents O
frequently O
reported O
that O
the O
Arrow B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
of O
the O
Garrison O
Albrecht O
was O
getting O
prepared O
for O
an O
action O
against O
Vadász O
Street O
. O

The O
first O
reports O
were O
quite O
fantastic O
. O

According O
to O
these O
the O
project O
was O
to O
lead O
us O
into O
the O
caves O
of O
Pálvölgy B-LOC
and O
then O
to O
kill B-TER
us O
with O
grenades O
. O

Later O
, O
we O
heard O
about O
only O
the O
killing O
. O

Hence O
, O
it O
was O
not O
a O
great O
surprise O
for O
our O
leaders O
when O
a O
squad O
of O
the O
Arrow B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
entered O
the O
building O
shooting O
around O
with O
their O
machineguns O
and O
throwing O
grenades O
the O
31st O
of O
December O
. O

This O
break B-TER
- I-TER
in I-TER
resulted O
in O
the O
death B-TER
of O
three O
and O
in O
17 O
injuries O
and O
it O
was O
a O
fortune O
that O
we O
could O
save O
the O
people O
drove O
out O
of O
the O
house O
to O
the O
street O
of O
being O
taken O
away O
using O
our O
rapports O
to O
the O
city O
military B-TER
headquarters O
and O
to O
the O
police B-TER
headquarters O
. O

This O
way O
we O
particularly O
upset O
the O
Arrow B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
squad O
and O
this O
led O
to O
the O
capture O
of O
Artúr B-PER
Weisz I-PER
, O
a O
heroic O
figure O
and O
comrade O
, O
the O
day O
after O
. O

After O
this O
event O
, O
the O
bandits O
of O
the O
Arrow B-ORG
Cross I-ORG
broke B-TER
in I-TER
regularly O
. O

It O
is O
hard O
to O
tell O
how O
we O
could O
have O
saved B-TER
the O
gathered O
mass O
if O
we O
had O
not O
been O
liberated B-TER
January O
the O
18th O
. O

