The O
persecution B-TER
of O
Jews B-TER
in O
Bulgaria B-LOC
The O
legation B-TER
has O
the O
honour O
of O
dispatching O
to O
the O
Royal B-ORG
Ministry I-ORG
a O
report O
received O
from O
the O
Consulate O
of O
Sofia B-LOC
, O
No O
. O

56 O
. O

of O
28 O
May O
1943 O
, O
on O
the O
above O
- O
quoted O
topic O
. O

With O
reference O
to O
previous O
reports O
, O
the O
Consulate O
hereby O
has O
the O
honour O
to O
report O
that O
according O
to O
a O
regulation O
of O
the O
Minister B-ORG
of I-ORG
the I-ORG
Interior I-ORG
, O
published O
in O
the O
current O
Press B-TER
on O
the O
25th O
of O
this O
month O
, O
all O
Jews B-TER
in O
Sofia B-LOC
must O
be O
moved B-TER
to O
the O
Province O
. O

As O
written O
in O
the O
Consulate O
's O
Report O
no O
. O

94 O
from O
1.9.1942 O
all O
unemployed O
Jews B-TER
were O
to O
leave B-TER
Sofia B-LOC
. O

However O
, O
since O
only O
a O
few O
Jews B-TER
have O
left O
Sofia B-LOC
, O
the O
Commission B-TER
on I-TER
Jewish I-TER
Affairs I-TER
is O
now O
carrying O
out O
an O
expulsion O
. O

Every O
Jewish B-TER
family B-TER
in O
Sofia O
is O
given O
a O
3 O
- O
day O
time O
limit O
to O
leave O
Sofia B-LOC
, O
during O
which O
the O
provincial O
town O
is O
announced O
to O
which O
they O
have O
to O
relocate O
. O

Those O
Jews B-TER
who O
do O
not O
comply O
with O
this O
regulation O
will O
be O
expelled B-TER
from O
the O
country O
immediately O
. O

About O
23,000 O
Jews B-TER
are O
affected O
by O
this O
Regulation O
. O

In O
Sofia B-LOC
, O
there O
are O
approx O
. O

25,000 O
Jews B-TER
, O
and O
only O
Jews B-TER
who O
are O
foreign B-TER
nationals O
, O
and O
Jews B-TER
who O
are O
civilized B-TER
mobilized I-TER
can O
still O
remain O
in O
Sofia B-LOC
. O

In O
old O
Bulgaria B-LOC
, O
there O
are O
approx O
. O

41,000 O
Jews B-TER
, O
including O
18,000 O
in O
the O
Province O
. O

About O
10,000 O
Jews B-TER
are O
mobilized O
, O
and O
the O
majority O
are O
employed B-TER
by O
road B-TER
construction I-TER
workers I-TER
. O

Erik B-PER
Andreas I-PER
Mathias I-PER
Biering I-PER
