Addressed O
to O
R. O
Ministry B-ORG
of I-ORG
Foreign I-ORG
Affairs I-ORG
, O
Rome B-LOC
R. O
Embassy O
of O
Italy O
, O
Berlin B-LOC
Prague B-LOC
, O
7th O
October O
1941 O
, O
Year O
XIX O
Re O
: O
Harsher O
measures B-TER
against O
Jews B-TER
in O
the O
Protectorate B-LOC
of I-LOC
Bohemia I-LOC
and I-LOC
Moravia I-LOC
. O

Following O
a O
decision O
by O
the O
Representative O
of O
the O
Reichsprotektor B-ORG
, O
further O
important O
measures O
against O
the O
Jews O
and O
their O
sympathizers O
have O
been O
taken O
and O
were O
made O
known O
by O
the O
Chief O
of O
the O
Security B-ORG
Police I-ORG
by O
means O
of O
a O
letter O
sent O
to O
the O
Protectorate O
’s O
Ministry O
of O
Interior O
. O

The O
attitude O
of O
the O
Jews B-TER
in I-TER
Prague I-TER
and O
in O
other O
towns O
of O
Bohemia O
and O
Moravia O
was O
judged O
to O
have O
been O
provocative O
immediately O
after O
the O
badge O
with O
the O
yellow B-TER
star I-TER
was O
introduced O
, O
before O
and O
after O
the O
recent O
developments O
in O
the O
local O
situation O
. O

It O
is O
true O
that O
they O
ostentatiously O
displayed O
their O
badge O
and O
walked O
in O
the O
streets O
in O
great O
numbers O
, O
giving O
the O
impression O
, O
as O
I O
have O
already O
reported O
, O
that O
they O
felt O
reciprocal O
support B-TER
with O
the O
local O
population O
. O

The O
letter O
of O
the O
Chief O
of O
the O
Security O
Police O
to O
the O
Ministry O
of O
Interior O
has O
not O
been O
published O
in O
full O
, O
but O
the O
main O
measures O
that O
have O
been O
decreed O
are O
reportedly O
the O
following O
: O
1 O
) O
All O
synagogues B-TER
and O
all O
Jewish O
prayer O
rooms O
are O
to O
be O
closed O
. O

2 O
) O
The O
compulsory O
wearing O
of O
the O
yellow O
star O
is O
to O
be O
extended O
to O
some O
categories B-TER
of I-TER
Jews I-TER
who O
are O
not O
required O
to O
wear O
it O
in O
the O
Reich O
. O

3 O
) O
All O
Jews O
are O
threatened O
with O
removal B-TER
from I-TER
the I-TER
towns I-TER
, O
presumably O
in O
order O
to O
collect O
them O
in O
concentration B-TER
or I-TER
labour I-TER
camps I-TER
. O

4 O
) O
Members O
of O
the O
State B-ORG
Police I-ORG
have O
been O
instructed O
to O
act O
against O
all O
those O
who O
in O
the O
street O
or O
in O
public O
establishments O
should O
with O
ostentatious O
friendliness O
associate O
with O
Jews O
wearing O
the O
star O
. O

I O
enclose O
the O
translation O
of O
the O
articles O
published O
in O
the O
local O
papers O
on O
this O
issue O
. O

Casto B-PER
Caruso I-PER
