I O
have O
the O
honor O
to O
present O
a O
summary O
of O
recent O
press B-TER
items O
relative O
to O
anti B-TER
- I-TER
Jewish I-TER
measures I-TER
in O
Rumania B-LOC
. O

Confiscation B-TER
of I-TER
property I-TER
and O
compulsory B-TER
labor I-TER
have O
apparently O
been O
the O
principal O
weapons O
employed O
in O
recent O
weeks O
against O
the O
Rumanian B-LOC
Jewry B-TER
, O
although O
additional O
forms O
of O
taxation O
have O
also O
been O
directed O
at O
this O
minority B-TER
. O

[ O
... O
] O
In O
connection O
with O
the O
announcement B-TER
by O
the O
Bulgarian B-ORG
Government I-ORG
that O
all O
Jews B-TER
within O
Sofia B-LOC
were O
to O
leave O
the O
city O
within O
a O
few O
days O
, O
PORUNCA B-ORG
VREMII I-ORG
of O
May O
27 O
suggested O
, O
in O
addition O
to O
heavily O
applauding O
the O
action O
of O
the O
Bulgarians B-TER
, O
that O
Ghettos B-TER
be O
established O
in O
every O
Axis B-TER
country O
, O
in O
order O
to O
suppress B-TER
communist B-TER
agitation I-TER
. O

