Mr. O
Foreign B-ORG
Minister I-ORG
I O
have O
the O
honour O
of O
forwarding O
the O
3 O
copies O
of O
the O
confidential O
report O
received O
from O
the O
Royal O
. O

Consul O
General O
in O
Prague B-LOC
. O

Dated O
the O
3 O
rd O
. O

concerning O
- O
the O
Conditions O
of O
the O
Protectorate B-LOC
of I-LOC
Bohemia I-LOC
and I-LOC
Moravia I-LOC
. O

I O
have O
the O
honour O
to O
remain O
with O
the O
highest O
consideration O
Dear O
Chamberlain O
Zahle B-PER
The O
situation O
has O
worsened O
considerably O
, O
since O
21 O
September O
of O
the O
same O
year O
, O
when O
I O
last O
reported O
about O
the O
conditions O
here O
. O

By O
the O
messages O
I O
have O
received O
I O
am O
under O
the O
impression O
that O
the O
State O
Protector O
and O
several O
of O
his O
officials O
sincerely O
wanted O
to O
establish O
a O
good O
relationship O
between O
Germans B-LOC
and O
Czechs B-LOC
. O

However O
, O
the O
party B-ORG
with O
the O
Sudeten B-LOC
German O
Secretary O
of O
State O
, O
Mr. O
Frank B-PER
at O
the O
helm O
have O
completely O
lacked O
the O
tact O
needed O
or O
they O
may O
have O
thought O
that O
with O
hardness O
one O
should O
suppress O
any O
resistance B-TER
from O
the O
Czechs B-LOC
. O

Now O
you O
can O
see O
a O
Germanization B-ORG
of O
the O
Protectorate B-LOC
in O
all O
areas O
. O

Many O
Czech O
estates O
, O
whose O
owners O
at O
the O
establishment O
of O
the O
Protectorate B-LOC
stayed O
abroad O
and O
did O
not O
return O
home O
, O
and O
estates O
which O
, O
at O
the O
demarcation O
, O
were O
located O
partly O
in O
the O
Protectorate B-LOC
and O
partly O
in O
the O
German B-LOC
Empire I-LOC
, O
are O
placed O
under O
German B-TER
administration I-TER
. O

It O
is O
expected O
, O
that O
similar O
extensions O
will O
take O
place O
in O
regard O
to O
German B-LOC
Colonization O
. O

Jewish B-TER
businesses I-TER
are O
mostly O
being B-TER
handed I-TER
over I-TER
to O
Germans O
. O

In O
Banks B-TER
and O
Industrial O
Enterprises O
, O
there O
is O
strong O
pressure O
from O
the O
German B-LOC
side O
for O
mergers O
and O
transactions O
, O
so O
that O
the O
main O
influence O
of O
the O
company O
in O
question O
can O
be O
transferred O
to O
rich O
German B-LOC
banks O
. O

Perhaps O
some O
of O
these O
transactions O
- O
as O
a O
bank O
director O
familiar O
with O
Czech O
transactions O
in O
the O
post O
- O
World O
Bank O
banking O
sector O
, O
has O
told O
me O
- O
are O
merely O
restitutions O
, O
but O
in O
my O
opinion O
, O
the O
German B-LOC
proceed O
with O
greater O
severity O
and O
consistency O
than O
the O
Czechs B-LOC
in O
this O
regard O
. O

Your O
honour O
Mr O
Chamberlain O
Herluf B-PER
Zahle I-PER
Royal O
envoy O
in O
Berlin B-LOC
Everywhere O
the O
German O
language O
is O
being O
preferred O
over O
the O
Czech O
language O
. O

Learning B-TER
institutions I-TER
and O
theatres B-TER
are O
taken O
over O
by O
the O
German B-LOC
Reich I-LOC
and O
Germans O
are O
hired O
in O
all O
institutions O
and O
administration O
offices O
. O

For O
example O
, O
an O
order O
has O
been O
imposed O
on O
the O
Tram O
conductors O
to O
call O
out O
the O
stations O
, O
first O
in O
German O
and O
then O
secondly O
in O
Czech O
, O
has O
caused O
unnecessary O
commotion B-TER
of O
the O
public O
. O

In O
Bohemia B-LOC
and I-LOC
Moravia I-LOC
, O
there O
were O
no O
food B-TER
shortages O
and O
before O
the O
war O
broke O
out O
, O
there O
were O
large O
supplies O
and O
industrial O
goods O
of O
great O
quality O
. O

In O
a O
short O
period O
of O
time O
, O
the O
stocks O
have O
been O
emptied O
and O
a O
rationing B-TER
system I-TER
has O
been O
introduced O
. O

The O
rationing O
is O
not O
yet O
as O
widespread O
as O
in O
the O
German B-LOC
Reich I-LOC
but O
it O
is O
just O
a O
matter O
of O
time O
before O
this O
happens O
and O
then O
there O
will O
be O
a O
Gleichschaltung B-TER
. O

In O
addition O
, O
Dualism O
in O
the O
Administration O
contributes O
to O
the O
fact O
that O
the O
demand O
for O
rationed O
consumer O
goods O
is O
hardly O
as O
well O
organized O
as O
in O
the O
German B-LOC
Empire I-LOC
. O

People O
often O
go O
to O
buy O
items O
, O
which O
according O
to O
the O
card O
system O
should O
be O
available O
just O
to O
find O
out O
that O
it O
is O
not O
. O

After O
the O
Munich B-TER
Decree I-TER
last O
year O
, O
the O
diminished O
territory O
of O
Czechoslovakia B-LOC
was O
established O
, O
and O
many O
Czechs B-LOC
believed B-TER
that O
with O
a O
little O
goodwill O
they O
could O
establish O
great O
relations O
with O
the O
German O
Empire O
. O

After O
the O
creation O
of O
the O
Protectorate B-LOC
, O
a O
few O
people O
still O
hoped O
this O
was O
possible O
but O
now O
you O
wo O
n’t O
find O
a O
single O
Czech O
person O
that O
does O
n’t O
feel O
resentment O
against O
Germany O
. O

I O
do O
n’t O
think O
that O
these O
feelings O
will O
cause O
any O
outbreaks O
as O
long O
as O
the O
German O
discipline O
stands O
firm O
. O

The O
people O
are O
not O
armed O
and O
they O
know O
that O
the O
German B-ORG
troops I-ORG
and O
the O
German B-TER
police I-TER
will O
suppress B-TER
any O
demonstration O
with O
extreme O
brutality O
. O

In O
the O
first O
period O
of O
the O
Protectorate B-LOC
there O
where O
arrests B-TER
among O
the O
supporters O
of O
Beneš B-PER
' I-PER
, O
undesired O
politicians O
, O
legionaries O
, O
and O
others O
. O

However O
, O
many O
of O
the O
arrested O
have O
since O
been O
released B-TER
and O
they O
believed O
that O
the O
main O
clash O
with O
Germans O
and O
people O
not O
well O
regarded O
by O
them O
had O
taken O
place O
. O

When O
the O
war O
broke O
out O
, O
Gestapo B-ORG
's I-ORG
activity O
increased O
and O
in O
addition O
to O
the O
before O
- O
mentioned O
, O
a O
large O
number O
of O
members O
of O
the O
Military O
were O
now O
also O
arrested O
, O
as O
well O
as O
people O
from O
the O
industries O
, O
clerics O
and O
many O
others O
. O

Ever O
since O
it O
looks O
like O
the O
arrests O
wo O
n’t O
stop O
and O
it O
is O
difficult O
to O
see O
a O
system O
in O
the O
actions O
of O
Gestapo B-ORG
, O
you O
might O
see O
this O
as O
taking O
hostages B-TER
. O

A O
former O
Czech O
politician B-TER
and O
diplomat B-TER
, O
which O
has O
been O
retired O
for O
several O
years O
, O
told O
me O
about O
some O
of O
the O
arrests O
. O

He O
told O
about O
how O
certain O
people O
on O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
's I-ORG
list O
of O
arrests O
had O
remained O
in O
Freedom O
– O
at O
least O
until O
now O
– O
just O
because O
they O
were O
not O
at O
home O
when O
the O
Gestapo B-ORG
came O
for O
them O
, O
so O
the O
police O
went O
on O
to O
the O
next O
one O
on O
the O
list O
. O

My O
informant O
told O
me O
that O
he O
changed O
his O
residence O
because O
he O
was O
afraid O
that O
he O
was O
going O
to O
be O
arrested O
. O

Many O
of O
the O
arrested O
people O
will O
be O
sent O
to O
the O
concentration B-LOC
camp I-LOC
Buchenwald I-LOC
in O
Germany B-LOC
. O

A O
reliable O
source O
told O
me O
that O
the O
internees O
are O
treated O
just O
as O
it O
is O
described O
in O
the O
newly O
published O
English O
white B-TER
paper I-TER
about O
German O
concentration B-TER
camps I-TER
. O

The O
prominent O
Jews B-TER
, O
the O
ones O
who O
lived O
there O
before O
the O
World O
War O
, O
are O
not O
as O
affected O
by O
the O
Jewish B-TER
persecutions I-TER
as O
others O
. O

I O
know O
of O
several O
examples O
of O
Jewish B-TER
Bank I-TER
Directors O
, O
although O
retired O
, O
that O
are O
working O
a O
couple O
of O
hours O
daily O
in O
the O
Bank O
to O
explain O
the O
conditions O
to O
the O
new O
Managers O
and O
live O
peacefully O
in O
their O
villas O
. O

However O
, O
they O
had O
to O
turn O
in O
their O
cars O
and O
radios O
. O

I O
have O
also O
heard O
of O
Jewish B-TER
lawyers I-TER
that O
work O
from O
home O
and O
then O
have O
their O
Aryan O
colleagues O
take O
the O
cases O
to O
court O
. O

Some O
Jewish B-TER
doctors I-TER
have O
been O
given O
temporary O
work O
in O
hospitals O
. O

Jews B-TER
who O
ca O
n’t O
prove O
a O
permanent O
residence O
in O
the O
Protectorate B-LOC
seem O
to O
be O
facing O
very O
bad O
times O
. O

They O
will O
probably O
all O
be O
transferred B-TER
to O
Poland B-LOC
, O
to O
the O
regions O
around O
Lemberg B-LOC
. O

From O
Mährisch B-LOC
Ostrau I-LOC
, O
many O
Hundreds O
of O
Jews B-TER
have O
already O
been O
sent O
to O
this O
area O
to O
do O
Labour B-TER
service I-TER
in O
preparation O
for O
the O
great O
relocation O
. O

Under O
the O
conditions O
described O
above O
, O
the O
former O
Czechoslovakia O
National O
Day O
, O
on O
October O
28 O
, O
was O
met O
with O
great O
anxiety O
. O

When O
it O
was O
reported O
that O
the O
Czechs B-LOC
wanted O
to O
grieve O
that O
day O
, O
the O
Germans O
had O
planned O
a O
mourning O
ceremony O
for O
the O
fallen O
people O
in O
Poland O
. O

The O
Czechs B-LOC
then O
canceled O
their O
plans O
, O
and O
the O
Czech O
national O
unity O
party O
ordered O
its O
members O
to O
stay O
indoors O
and O
keep O
calm O
. O

The O
Germans O
also O
distanced O
themselves O
from O
holding O
the O
mourning O
ceremony O
. O

Despite O
the O
fact O
that O
it O
was O
Labour B-TER
Day I-TER
, O
the O
traffic O
in O
the O
main O
streets O
was O
very O
busy O
. O

In O
spite O
of O
the O
prohibition B-TER
, O
many O
Czech O
people O
wore O
cockades O
with O
silk O
ribbons O
in O
the O
Czechoslovakia O
colours O
, O
and O
many O
male O
persons O
covered O
their O
heads O
with O
the O
same O
kind O
of O
cap O
of O
as O
the O
late O
President O
Masaryk B-PER
usually O
wore O
. O

All O
the O
Czech B-ORG
Police I-ORG
was O
stationed O
in O
the O
Main O
Streets O
and O
the O
German B-ORG
Police I-ORG
and O
S.S. B-ORG
-members O
had O
taken O
up O
positions O
as O
a O
reserve O
in O
side O
streets O
and O
passages O
. O

The O
tensions O
erupted O
into O
fights O
as O
large O
sections O
the O
S.A. B-ORG
-members O
passed O
through O
the O
main O
streets O
with O
music O
, O
and O
various O
clashes O
between O
the O
Czech O
people O
's O
groups O
and O
the O
police O
took O
place O
. O

In O
some O
streets O
, O
the O
Communists B-TER
demonstrated O
, O
and O
German O
police O
had O
to O
support O
the O
Czech O
police O
to O
get O
the O
streets O
cleared O
. O

During O
the O
clashes B-TER
, O
a O
couple O
of O
persons O
( O
allegedly O
a O
dozen O
people O
) O
were O
killed O
and O
some O
of O
them O
were O
injured O
. O

A O
couple O
of O
young O
people O
were O
arrested O
. O

However O
, O
in O
view O
of O
the O
population O
’s O
agitated O
state O
of O
mind O
, O
the O
events O
must O
be O
considered O
less O
serious O
than O
one O
might O
have O
expected O
. O

This O
was O
also O
stated O
to O
me O
by O
a O
German O
Official O
from O
the O
Chancellor B-PER
's I-PER
Office O
. O

However O
, O
we O
can O
not O
exclude O
that O
the O
incidents O
will O
give O
rise O
to O
new O
reprisals B-TER
against O
the O
Czechs B-LOC
, O
and O
the O
resentment O
against O
the O
Germans O
will O
then O
be O
further O
increased O
. O

Yours O
sincerely O
Your O
devoted O
( O
sign O
. O

) O
Leth B-PER
, I-PER
Eigil I-PER
. O

P.S. O
This O
Report O
was O
sent O
with O
a O
Swedish B-LOC
Courier O
to O
the O
Swedish O
Embassy O
in O
Berlin B-LOC
for O
its O
Further O
Action O
. O

