Testimony B-TER
taken O
by O
Efraim B-PER
Fishl I-PER
Mamet I-PER
Amarnikh B-PER
, I-PER
Rokhl I-PER
, O
born O
December O
7 O
, O
1926 O
in O
Międzyrzec B-LOC
, O
Poland B-LOC
, O
relates O
: O
On O
May O
25 O
, O
1943 O
, O
we O
were O
twenty O
people B-TER
, O
among O
them O
men B-TER
, O
women B-TER
, O
and O
three O
children B-TER
aged O
from O
four O
to O
fifteen O
years O
old O
, O
lying O
hidden B-TER
in O
our O
house O
in O
a O
bunker B-TER
. O

The O
Germans B-TER
discovered O
our O
hiding B-TER
place I-TER
, O
tore O
up O
the O
floor O
with O
iron O
bars O
, O
and O
managed O
to O
reach O
us O
: O
we O
tried O
to O
buy B-TER
our I-TER
lives I-TER
with O
money O
. O

We O
gave O
them O
gold O
and O
dollars O
to O
the O
value O
of O
200,000 O
Polish B-LOC
zlotys O
, O
they B-TER
took I-TER
the I-TER
money I-TER
and O
shot B-TER
a O
woman B-TER
and O
a O
man B-TER
on O
the O
spot O
. O

I O
fled O
together O
with O
another O
two O
girls B-TER
. O

The O
remaining O
fifteen O
were O
taken O
and O
deported B-TER
. O

We O
found O
an O
open O
bunker B-TER
and O
went O
in O
. O

From O
there O
observed O
the O
aktion B-TER
. O

This O
was O
the O
last O
aktion B-TER
in O
our O
city O
. O

There O
were O
then O
in O
total O
5,000 O
Jews O
therein O
. O

We O
saw O
how O
at O
first O
the O
SS B-ORG
[ O
men O
] O
took O
the O
children B-TER
from O
the O
women B-TER
by O
force O
and O
drove O
them O
to O
the O
cemetery B-TER
, O
where O
they O
shot B-TER
them O
. O

The O
remaining O
people B-TER
, O
men B-TER
and O
women B-TER
, O
remained O
in O
the O
Politzei O
Sqaure O
on O
Piekarsga B-LOC
Street I-LOC
. O

This O
was O
a O
large O
square O
in O
the O
middle O
of O
the O
city O
surrounded O
with O
walls O
; O
the O
Jewish B-TER
- I-TER
ghetto I-TER
police I-TER
was O
located O
there O
. O

In O
the O
square O
a O
selection B-TER
took O
place O
. O

Some O
women B-TER
and O
men B-TER
, O
around O
1,200 O
persons B-TER
, O
were O
shot B-TER
straight O
away O
, O
the O
rest O
were O
taken B-TER
away I-TER
to O
Treblinka B-LOC
and O
Majdanek B-LOC
. O

The O
aktion B-TER
continued O
in O
this O
way O
for O
three O
days O
. O

When O
the O
situation O
calmed O
, O
those O
in O
hiding B-TER
came O
out O
of O
their O
hiding B-TER
places I-TER
, O
among O
them O
also O
I O
and O
my O
mother B-TER
, O
who O
had O
hidden B-TER
in O
a O
different O
bunker B-TER
. O

Then O
, O
on O
May O
28 O
, O
we O
were O
caught O
by O
Germans B-TER
and O
Ukrainians B-TER
and O
deported B-TER
to O
Majdanek B-LOC
. O

We O
were O
transported B-TER
in O
closed B-TER
wagons I-TER
, O
up O
to O
150 O
people B-TER
in O
a O
wagon B-TER
. O

Arriving O
in O
Majdanek B-LOC
, O
a O
selection B-TER
took O
place O
. O

Old O
men B-TER
and O
women B-TER
went O
straight O
to O
the O
oven B-TER
, O
among O
them O
also O
my O
mother B-TER
. O

Children B-TER
also O
went O
directly O
with O
the O
elderly O
to O
the O
crematorium B-TER
. O

I O
was O
deemed O
to O
be O
among O
the O
healthy O
ones O
, O
who O
were O
taken O
for O
work B-TER
in O
Majdanek B-LOC
. O

The O
work B-TER
camp I-TER
was O
around O
250 O
meters O
from O
the O
place O
of O
the O
crematoria B-TER
and O
gas B-TER
ovens I-TER
. O

The O
daily O
schedule O
in O
the O
camp B-TER
was O
as O
follows O
: O
the O
roll B-TER
call I-TER
took O
place O
at O
3.30 O
AM O
. O

Many O
people B-TER
came O
out O
of O
the O
barracks B-TER
barefoot B-TER
and O
stood O
in O
the O
frost B-TER
and I-TER
snow I-TER
until O
6 O
Am O
. O

We O
would O
drag O
out O
the O
sick B-TER
to O
the O
roll B-TER
call I-TER
and O
lay O
them O
on O
blankets O
spread O
out O
on O
the O
floor O
. O

More O
than O
one O
of O
the O
sick B-TER
would O
beg O
for O
selection B-TER
so O
that O
he O
could O
go O
to O
the O
crematorium B-TER
, O
putting O
an O
end O
to O
his O
suffering O
. O

For O
breakfast B-TER
they O
would O
give O
us O
to O
drink O
a O
bit O
of O
chamomile B-TER
[ O
brew O
] O
and O
this O
was O
our O
nourishment B-TER
until O
midday O
. O

Twelve O
noon O
there O
was O
a O
watery B-TER
soup I-TER
. O

At O
6 O
PM O
was O
the O
night O
time O
roll B-TER
call I-TER
, O
at O
which O
we O
would O
stand O
on O
our O
feet O
after O
an O
entire O
day O
at O
work B-TER
, O
sometimes O
three O
hours O
, O
because O
punishment O
roll B-TER
calls I-TER
often O
took O
place O
and O
these O
lasted O
much O
longer O
due O
the O
beating B-TER
and O
killing B-TER
of O
the O
prisoners B-TER
, O
only O
then O
did O
we O
receive O
80 O
grams O
of O
bread B-TER
, O
ten O
grams O
of O
margarine B-TER
and O
black B-TER
coffee I-TER
. O

Our O
work B-TER
was O
hard O
physical O
labor B-TER
, O
hacking O
stones O
, O
dragging O
brick O
boards O
and O
other O
physical O
labor B-TER
. O

I O
was O
in O
Majdanek B-LOC
for O
six O
weeks O
. O

On O
July O
16 O
, O
1943 O
, O
we O
healthy O
women B-TER
and O
men B-TER
were O
transported B-TER
to O
Skarżysko B-LOC
- I-LOC
Kamienna I-LOC
near O
Radom B-LOC
in O
the O
Kielce B-LOC
Voivodship I-LOC
. O

There O
we O
worked B-TER
in O
an O
ammunition O
factory B-TER
which O
was O
called O
Shmutz O
’s O
factory B-TER
, O
number O
ALE O
84 O
. O

We O
worked B-TER
twelve O
hours O
per O
day O
from O
6 O
AM O
to O
6 O
PM O
. O

At O
4 O
AM O
a O
roll B-TER
call I-TER
took O
place O
, O
at O
night O
it O
would O
last O
until O
8 O
PM O
. O

A O
punishment O
roll B-TER
call I-TER
would O
last O
until O
9 O
or O
9.30 O
PM O
. O

The O
nourishment O
: O
80 O
grams O
of O
bread B-TER
. O

Midday O
: O
two O
watery B-TER
soups I-TER
with O
rotting B-TER
beats I-TER
, O
as O
well O
as O
10 O
grams O
of O
marmalade B-TER
. O

We O
made O
grenades O
and O
2 O
centimeter O
bullets O
. O

People B-TER
were O
often O
killed B-TER
by O
exploding O
material O
. O

Some O
became O
completely O
yellow O
due O
to O
the O
picric O
acid O
( O
such O
a O
material O
which O
is O
put O
into O
the O
grenades O
) O
. O

Selections B-TER
also O
took O
place O
. O

The O
weak O
would O
not O
be O
taken O
to O
crematoria B-TER
, O
since O
there O
were O
none O
, O
but O
would O
be O
shot B-TER
at O
the O
firing O
range O
. O

Out O
of O
540 O
people B-TER
, O
among O
them O
120 O
women B-TER
, O
40 O
men B-TER
remained O
alive O
and O
among O
the O
women B-TER
60 O
. O

As O
the O
Russian B-TER
front O
neared O
, O
after O
we O
have O
been O
there O
fourteen O
months O
, O
in O
September O
1944 O
, O
we O
were O
evacuated B-TER
to O
Leipzig B-LOC
together O
with O
the O
entire O
camp B-TER
. O

Also O
to O
an O
ammunition O
factory B-TER
, O
which O
was O
called O
SC O
ALE O
1 O
. O

There O
we O
worked B-TER
in O
somewhat O
better O
living B-TER
conditions I-TER
, O
however O
selections B-TER
took O
place O
from O
time O
to O
time O
, O
the O
weaker O
would O
be O
taken O
away O
and O
deported B-TER
, O
exactly O
to O
where O
I O
do O
not O
know O
. O

We O
were O
there O
for O
nine O
whole O
months O
. O

In O
April O
1945 O
, O
when O
the O
American B-TER
army I-TER
began O
to O
near O
Leipzig B-LOC
, O
they O
took O
us O
out O
of O
the O
barracks B-TER
at O
night O
and O
, O
together O
with O
the O
SS B-ORG
men O
, O
we O
started O
wandering B-TER
on O
foot O
over O
the O
fields O
and O
forests O
of O
Germany B-LOC
. O

There O
was O
already O
nowhere O
to O
evacuate B-TER
us O
to O
because O
the O
fire O
of O
war B-TER
had O
reached O
all O
corners O
of O
Germany B-LOC
, O
they O
dragged O
us O
around O
like O
this O
for O
three B-TER
weeks I-TER
. O

The O
250 O
grams O
of O
bread B-TER
for O
the O
journey O
, O
which O
they O
gave O
us O
when O
we O
left O
Leipzig B-LOC
, O
had O
already O
run O
out O
long O
ago O
, O
we O
would O
eat O
grass B-TER
and O
raw B-TER
potatoes I-TER
. O

When O
the O
Nazis O
noticed O
this O
, O
they O
would O
shoot B-TER
at O
us O
, O
and O
more O
than O
one O
person O
was O
killed B-TER
running O
to O
grab O
potatoes B-TER
or O
grass O
form O
a O
field O
. O

The O
SS B-ORG
would O
warn O
the O
surrounding B-TER
peasants I-TER
that O
they O
should O
beware O
of O
the O
stoylayz O
, O
meaning O
the O
thieves O
that O
they O
were O
driving O
onwards O
. O

They O
took O
from O
Leipzig B-LOC
12,000 O
persons B-TER
. O

Seeing O
that O
it O
was O
difficult O
to O
wander O
around O
with O
such O
a O
large O
group O
, O
they O
divided O
us O
into O
[ O
smaller O
] O
groups O
and O
each O
group O
wandered B-TER
in O
a O
different O
direction O
. O

The O
camp B-TER
commandant I-TER
would O
drive O
around O
from O
group O
to O
group O
in O
a O
taxi O
, O
holding O
a O
map O
in O
his O
hand O
, O
and O
wherever O
the O
Oberscharführer B-TER
would O
order O
, O
there O
they O
would O
take O
us O
. O

Usually O
these O
were O
places O
where O
the O
fire O
of O
war B-TER
was O
still O
a O
little O
way O
off O
. O

My O
group O
numbered O
4,000 O
women B-TER
, O
of O
which O
1,200 O
survived O
. O

Our O
group O
was O
mainly O
Jewish O
women B-TER
from O
Poland B-LOC
and O
Czechoslovakia B-LOC
. O

So O
we O
walked B-TER
on I-TER
foot I-TER
for O
600 O
kilometers O
. O

We O
went O
through O
all O
of O
Saxony B-LOC
, O
and O
together O
with O
the O
SS B-ORG
men I-ORG
hid B-TER
from O
the O
allied B-TER
armies I-TER
. O

When O
the O
SS B-ORG
men I-ORG
no O
longer O
had O
anywhere O
left O
to O
take O
us O
, O
they O
abandoned O
us O
under O
the O
open O
sky O
and O
the O
Russians B-TER
liberated B-TER
us O
on O
May O
7 O
, O
1945 O
( O
it O
was O
a O
Monday O
) O
in O
Großdorf B-LOC
near O
Apolda B-LOC
in O
Saxony B-LOC
. O

Rokhel B-PER
Amarnikh I-PER
